<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2334</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3605</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4870 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 415-419.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2334" type="letter">
        <head>2334. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1813-11-18">18 November
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Norwich<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 13
                        March<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4870 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 415-419.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-11-18">Nov. 18. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will not wonder that amid the engagements &amp; distractions of London, I could find no time to thank you for
                    your letter &amp; your Synonimes<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor&#8217;s <title>English Synonyms Discriminated</title>
                        (1813).</note> &#8211; or even to do more than look into the volume. I cast a wistful eye toward Norwich &#8211; you remember the Boys
                    objection to beginning the alphabet, because if he said A he must say B &amp; so on to C &amp; D. So it was with me. I could not
                    have taken that direction without making three or four visits on the way, &#8211; &amp; so long an absence had made me weary of new
                    faces, worn out with the continual stimulations of society &amp; sick for home. As soon as my presentation was over I slipt off my
                    masquerade suit &amp; hurried to the <ref target="places.html#BullandMouth">Bull &amp; Mouth</ref> to secure a place for the
                    following evening, &#8211; &amp; on Sunday last I had the happiness of finding all at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> as
                    well as I had left them three months before.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Laureateship without my knowledge was asked for me by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>,
                    &amp; given by the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, because he said he had heard that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S. had written well in <del>defence of the</del> support of the Spaniards. The <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Marquis of Hertford</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> meantime had taken council
                    together concerning the disposal of the vacant dignity upon the principle of <hi rend="ital">detur digniori</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Let it be given to the more worthy&#8217;.</note> &amp; fixing upon <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref> they wrote &amp; offered it to him. When the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> was informed of this, he was displeased &amp; said that his pleasure
                    ought to have been consulted; &#8211; he had given it to me &amp; I should have it. Upon this Croker of course interposed, observing
                    that he was upon friendly terms with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, that <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> &amp; I were friends &amp; that for the sake of all three the business must be allowed to rest where it was. A
                    letter soon came to me from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> telling me he had refused it, as not thinking it
                    becoming in him who held two lucrative <del>offices</del> professional situations, to accept of the only thing which seemd
                    exclusively to belong to a man of letters: &amp; he urged me to take the office, if as he had solicited, it should be proffered
                        me.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s letter of 1 September [1813] informed Southey that he had declined the
                        Poet Laureateship and instead recommended him to Croker. Scott also cautioned &#8216;I am uncertain if you will like it, for the
                        laurel has certainly been tarnished by some of its wearers, and as at present managed, its duties are inconvenient and
                        somewhat liable to ridicule&#8217;, H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of Walter Scott, 1787&#8211;1832</title>, 12, vols (London,
                        1932&#8211;1937), III, pp. 335&#8211;336. Scott held two legal offices: he was Sheriff-Depute of Selkirkshire (since 1799); and Principal
                        Clerk of the Court of Session (since 1806). These posts gave him a combined salary of &#163;1600 p.a. For Southey&#8217;s reply, see
                        Southey to Walter Scott, 5 November 1813, Letter 2323.</note> &#8211; It would raise <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> in your opinion if you saw the frank &amp; handsome manner in which he represented the office, considering it, as
                    a mark of honour, was more due to me than to himself. Upon this I wrote to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, expressing an unwillingness to write verses at stated times on stated subjects, &#8211; like a school boys exercise, but
                    saying that if on great public occasions it were understood that I should be at liberty to write, or to be silent, as the spirit
                    moved, &#8211; in that case the appointment would become a mark of honour, &amp; as such I should gladly accept it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Southey to John Wilson Croker, [4 September 1813], Letter 2298.</note> At the same time it
                    was not for me to propose terms <del>for</del> to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, but I left him to
                    judge <del>in what manner</del> how far such a reformation was practicable, &amp; in what manner it might be effected. He told me
                    that at some fitting opportunity he would suggest to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> that it would
                    be for his honour &amp; for mine to drop the regular odes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am however less solicitous about this than I was at first, &#8211; &amp; that for two reasons. First because the office
                    is of greater value than I <del>had at f</del> immediately perceived. It was raised for Ben Jonson<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of Southey&#8217;s predecessors as Poet Laureate, Ben Jonson (1572&#8211;1637; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate
                        1616&#8211;1637.</note> from 100 marks to 100 &#163;, &amp; a tierce of Spanish Canary Wine: a compensation of 26 &#163; has been established
                    for the wine, &amp; the various deductions reduce the whole net income to about 90 &#163;. But coming as a God-send I disposed of it
                    accordingly, &amp; by adding to it 12 &#163; a year, have converted it into a life-policy of &#163;3000. &#8211; It is paying a cheap price for
                    this legacy to write one or two odes in the year. And secondly, I am not averse to the task, considering the state of foreign
                    &amp; domestic affairs, my own views &amp; feelings, &amp; the tone which I feel myself able to support. In me, of all men, it
                    would have been cowardice to have refused the appointment, &#8211; &amp; if I were not to write as Laureate, it might seem<del>ed</del>
                    as if I shrunk from censure, or were ashamed of writing. But I take the laurel as a honour which is my due, &amp; as such
                        <del>&amp;</del> I will wear it. &#8211; You have here the whole history of a most unexpected occurrence in my life. &#8211; I am thinking
                    of the new years ode, &amp; think also of accompanying it with an Epistle to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> saying something of the office, of those who have held it heretofore, of myself, &amp; of the manner in which it
                    becomes me to address him &amp; <del>x</del> in which it is most fitting <del>for</del> that he should be addrest.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first poem as Laureate was the New Year&#8217;s ode <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>,
                        published, after much revision, in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814. It was not accompanied by an epistle to the Prince
                        Regent.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> is going on well. It is many years since I have enjoyed so much of his
                    company. <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> also is making way as he ought to do. I saw much of him, &#8211; &amp;
                    there are few men of whom I think so highly. We should <del>have</del> greatly have rejoiced if you could have joined us in
                    town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> is gone to France, anticipating before he went the censure which he was conscious
                    of deserving. &#8211; Mackintosh<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> On his return to Britain from India, where he had held a post
                        in the Bombay judiciary, in 1811, the writer and politician Sir James Mackintosh (1765&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>) had been
                        courted by Perceval and the Tories. He was elected to Parliament in 1813 as MP for Nairn and became a leading spokesman for
                        the Whigs. He had long planned a <title>History of England from the Earliest Times to the Final Establishment of the
                            Reformation</title> and this was published in 1830.</note> has brought back from India a diseased liver, &amp; a
                    reputation which I do not think he will be able to support either in Parliament, or in his <del>xx</del> intended historical
                    labours. I met him at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>, &amp; at Madam de Staels.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Louise Germaine de Sta&#235;l-Holstein (1766&#8211;1817), the writer and salonni&#232;re. She was much feted
                        during her 1813 visit to England.</note> The latter personage is the most remarkable, &amp; the most interesting of all my new
                    acquaintance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am returned to a world of occupations. My poem is going to press,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; so also is the concluding volume of Brazil,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two further volumes of the <title>History of Brazil</title> appeared, in 1817 and 1819,
                        respectively.</note> &#8211; &amp; the great work of the Spanish history<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is before me, &#8211; to say nothing of minor engagements. But
                    I am God be thanked in health &amp; spirits , &#8211; ready for all &amp; equal to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; It is needless to say how heartily I should rejoice to see you here whenever circumstances may allow you to
                    become my guest. &#8211; Times change, circumstances change &amp; the opinions of men change with them, &#8211; but affection &amp; esteem
                    &amp; gratitude where they are well founded are immutable. &#8211; Whenever you leave Norwich, give me one summer before you settle
                    elsewhere.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>