<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2087</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3358</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        392&#8211;395.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 265&#8211;267 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2087" type="letter">
        <head>2087. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1812-05-03">3 May 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        392&#8211;395<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 265&#8211;267 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-05-03">May 3. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Senhora</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaven knows how long it is since I have written to you; or rather it is known in Heaven if there be that Angel
                    there who according to Sterne serves in the capacity of Book Keeper,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Laurence Sterne
                        (1713&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy</title> (1759&#8211;1769), Book 6, Chapter 8: &#8216;&#8212; He
                        shall not die, by G&#8212;, cried my uncle Toby. &#8211; The ACCUSING SPIRIT which flew up to heaven&#8217;s chancery with the oath, blush&#8217;d as
                        he gave it in, &#8211; and the RECORDING ANGEL as he wrote it down, dropp&#8217;d a tear upon the word, and blotted it out for
                        ever&#8217;.</note> &#8211; otherwise I should presume it is likely to be known nowhere but at <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley</ref>, where the date of my last letter is perhaps in existence to rise up in judgment against me. Something I
                    should say concerning Frederick,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Barker&#8217;s brother, Frederick Barker (b. 1779).</note> &#8211; but what I can say except what you know already &#8211; that he is young &amp; unmarried, &#8211; the burden therefore
                    will be with less weight on him, &amp; better times may easily enable him to shake it off &amp; mount the hill of difficulty.
                    &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your story of the Forgers Fortress is an admirable one.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Not
                        identified.</note> I wish I could send you anything half as amusing in return, &#8211; but except riots at Carlisle,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> There was a protest in Carlisle on 4 April 1812 against the price of food. The army were called
                        out and one person was killed.</note> &amp; a contest between the colliers &amp; the pit owners with <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">L. Lonsdale</ref> &amp; Curwen at their head,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Lowther and John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Carlisle 1786&#8211;1790, 1791&#8211;1812, 1816&#8211;1820. They were
                        two of the largest mineowners in Cumbria.</note> with some little squabbling about the price of potatoes in our own market,
                    all goes on smoothly in the Land of Lakes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By the Almanac, &amp; the length of the days it is to be presumed that summer is near at hand, tho there be no
                    symptoms thereof in the fields or gardens. <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs. Wilson</ref> however has heard the Cuckoo this
                    morning. Senhora we used to look for you in the summer, &amp; tho several years have elapsed since we have ceased to expect you,
                    we have not ceased to let out an occasional sort of semi-grumble when we think of it. For as for seeing <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Ed</ref>. here, however much I could wish it it seems too great a risk to be
                    advised. If Buonaparte which God forbid! should live to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward&#8217;s</ref> years what
                    would he not give for a nurse like you to watch over him &amp; keep the Devil out of possession!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know I suppose that the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperial Colonel</ref> has married the widow
                    of a Creole.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Peachy married a widow, Mrs James Henry of Jamaica, in 1812.</note>
                    What kind of woman she may be I know not, but you will hardly suppose that I do not look on with any great pleasure to her arrival
                    at the Island.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Derwent Island, the summer home of the Peachys. The Southeys were extremely
                        fond of the first Mrs. Peachy (d. 1809) and named their third daughter Emma (1808&#8211;1809) after her.</note> I like the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperial</ref> well, &#8220;take him for all in all, we ne&#8217;er shall look upon his like
                        again,&#8221;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act I, scene 2, lines 186&#8211;187.</note> &#8211; especially Senhora when you remember the cymbals! But I should
                    not think him a likely sort of man for a woman to fall in love with, if it were only for that hand of his, the palm of which is
                    like a rhinoceros&#8217;s hide; &amp; the touch I should think must be as powerful an anti-philtre as that fountain in the forest of
                    Arden which produced so many cross-purposes between Angelica &amp; her suitors.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lodovico
                        Ariosto (1474&#8211;1533), <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1516). An important plot device is the Fountain of Disdain in the Forest
                        of Arden, which turns the love of Angelica and her suitors into hatred.</note> Now I can very well understand how the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperial</ref> got such a prize in the lottery as <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">that sweet woman</ref> whom we all loved so well &amp; in the same manner he might have had another prize, tho it would not
                    have been easy to have found such a one, but good women are by no means so rare as good husbands. There are but too many
                    interesting &amp; amiable women who would willingly accept any man as a husband, to whom there was no other objection than that he
                    was not the man they would have chosen. But this widow I have heard was in good circumstances, &#8211; has she married him for the love
                    of show &#8211; of making an appearance in the world; &#8211; or is she bon&#226; fide smitten with that persuasive tongue, &amp; worthy to be the
                    imperial consort? &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You need make no secret of my little Book.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Origin, Nature and Object of the New System of Education</title> (1812).</note> &#8211; I have no secrets of that kind.
                    It went into the world without a name, because an author, like a Prima Donna [has] a sort of dignity from appearing sometimes
                    incog. when in reality every body knows him. The book as I clearly foresaw, has been a day after the fair, &amp; it will be well
                    if the <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">bookseller</ref> does not find it a losing concern: however, I am very glad that there
                    it is, for it seems to me that no person can peruse it without perceiving that it sets the question [to] rest. &#8211; I am only ashamed
                    of the worthless company in which it seems to place me. John Bowles!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bowles
                        (1751&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer and fanatical anti-Jacobin who was entangled in long-running fraud allegations.</note>
                    Archdeacon Danbury,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Daubeny (1745&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Archdeacon of
                        Salisbury, 1804&#8211;1827. A particular foe of Nonconformists and defender of the rights of the Church of England.</note> &#8211; &amp;
                    the Rev. Dr. Hook, &#8211; a fellow whom I knew at school, who was known both then &amp; at College to be the epitome of everything that
                    is profligate.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Hook (1772?-1828; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman who was a Prebend
                        of Winchester Cathedral 1807&#8211;1825, rising to be Dean of Worcester 1825&#8211;1828; and minor novelist. His <title>Anquis in
                            Herba</title> (1802) was staunchly anti-Methodist and anti-Jacobin. At Westminster he had edited the magazine, <title>The
                            Trifler</title>.</note> Bigotry is the Devil, but a knave acting the Bigot &#8211; is butter upon Bacon, &#8211; the devil
                    hyper-devilized. This mans proper station would have been the green-room, &#8211; he has a brother who writes farces<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Theodore Edward Hook (1788&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), novelist, writer of farces and prankster.
                        He engineered the &#8216;Berners Street Hoax&#8217; against one Mrs. Tottenham in 1809 by sending out over 4000 letters in her name,
                        requesting everyone from the Lord Mayor of London to coal carts to appear at her house at a certain hour.</note> &amp; who was
                    the author of the great hoax upon the apothecary a few years ago, &#8211; he himself has just the proper sort of talent to write farces;
                    &#8211; instead of which he is Prebend of Winchester, a Chaplain to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince of
                        Wales</ref>! such a Chaplain as Ned Poins<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A thief and general rogue in <title>Henry
                            IV, Part One</title>.</note> would have made. Of course he is a strenuous supporter of the Church, &#8211; &amp; would be of any
                    church &#8211; in which he might be a Prebend.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. We are well save that <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Piggarel</ref> grumbles a little as you
                    may have known her do formerly, for a reason which it would not please her for me to hint at, tho I think it, like the Court of
                    Austria, a &#8216;blessed circumstance.&#8217;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isabel Southey was born in November 1812.
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 338 reported the Austrian Court&#8217;s announcement that
                        Empress Maria Louisa (1791&#8211;1847) was &#8216;in blessed circumstances of body&#8217; i.e. pregnant. Her child became Napoleon II
                        (1811&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; Make my respects to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward</ref> , &amp; let me have a
                    Shepistle as soon as you please. &#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent6"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent8"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>