<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1976</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3247</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS
                    42550.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1976" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1976" type="letter">
        <head>1976. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1811-11-02">2 November
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray/ Fleet Street/
                        London.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ 5 NO 5/ 1811<lb />Watermark: shield/ 1806<lb />Endorsement: 1811 Nov. 2.
                        Keswick/Q R N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 12/Southey R./Art. &lt;on&gt; Inquisition/Chalmers Poets/Bonapartes Poem/Pamp<hi rend="sup">t</hi> on Bell &amp; Lancaster/Life of Nelson<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS
                    42550<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-11-02">Nov. 2. 1811</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received your parcel duly, &amp; was exceedingly glad to see its contents. <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> has not been so fortunate, the copies of the Review<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Copies of the <title>Quarterly</title> requested via Southey to Murray; see Southey to John Murray, 23 October
                        1811, Letter 1971.</note> have not reached <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. How did you direct them?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This pamphlett<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of the New
                            System of Education</title> (1812), an expansion of his advocacy of Andrew Bell in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6
                        (August 1811), 264&#8211;304. It contained numerous attacks on Joseph Lancaster and on his defenders in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>.</note> will be a most triumphant thing. It will enable me to set the question of <del>the</del> invention
                    at rest; to explain to the public what the New School is, &#8211; which is not possible to learn from any of the Lancastrian writers, &#8211;
                    to do justice to <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>, who is one of the greatest benefactors of
                    mankind, &amp; who has been more villainously used than any man living, &amp; to strike the Edinburgh R. the heaviest &amp;
                    hardest blow which has ever been given them. Please to send me N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 21 of that Review,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The twenty-first number of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, which formed part of the eleventh volume of
                        the same. Southey wished to see <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11 (October 1807), 61&#8211;73, a positive review of Lancaster&#8217;s
                            <title>Outlines of a Plan for Educating Ten Thousand Poor Children, by establishing Schools in Country Towns and Villages;
                            and for Uniting Works of Industry with Useful Knowledge</title> (1806).</note> &amp; also that number which reviews <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> Portraiture of Quakerism,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Clarkson&#8217;s <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as taken from a View of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar Customs,
                            Religious Principles, Political and Civil Economy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title> (1806), reviewed in
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 10 (April 1807), 85&#8211;102. The article concluded: &#8216;Upon the whole, we are inclined to
                        believe the Quakers to be a tolerably honest, painstaking, and inoffensive set of Christians. Very stupid, dull, and obstinate
                        &#8230; in conversation; and tolerably lumpish and fatiguing in domestic society; active and methodical in their business, and
                        narrow minded and ill informed as to most other particulars: beneficent from habit and the discipline of the society; but cold
                        in their affections &#8230; childish and absurd in their religious scruples and peculiar usages &#8230; but exemplary, above all other
                        sects, for the decency of their lives, for their charitable indulgence &#8230; for their care of their poor, and for the liberal
                        participation they have afforded to their women in all the duties and honours of the society&#8217; (102).</note> &#8211; for it will be
                    useful to compare their character of the Quakers there given, with their present praises of the society,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Presumably the ridiculing of attack by Lancaster&#8217;s opponents on his Quakerism in <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 17 (November 1810), 68, 83 n. *; and <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 19 (November 1811), 26. Southey
                        cited the comments of November 1810 (68) not in a note but in the main text of his <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of
                            the New System of Education</title> (London, 1812), p. 155.</note> &#8211; matter for a wholesome note. I should be glad also of
                        <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancasters</ref> editions of 1808 &amp; 1811,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> An 1808 edition of Lancaster&#8217;s <title>Improvements in Education</title>; and probably <title>Report of J. Lancaster&#8217;s
                            Progress from the Year 1798</title> (1811).</note> &#8211; indeed any of his late publications. Colquhon&#8217;s Treatise on
                    Indigence, &amp; On the Education of the Poor.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>). His <title>A Treatise on Indigence</title> was first published in 1799; and his <title>A New and
                            Appropriate System of Education for the Labouring People</title> in 1806. Southey&#8217;s review of his <title>Propositions for
                            ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring
                            People</title> (1812), appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> The Bp. of
                    Londons Pastoral Letter with <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bells</ref> appendix,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Beilby Porteus (1731&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), bishop of London from 1791 to his death. A
                        supporter of Bell, evangelicals and the abolition of the slave trade. An appendix to his <title>A Letter to the Governors,
                            Legislatures and Proprietors of Plantations in the British West-India Islands</title> (1808) consisted of &#8216;a short sketch
                        of the new system of education for the poor; in a letter from the Rev. Dr. Bell&#8217;.</note> John Bowless late pamphlett upon the
                        controversy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bowles (1751&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), barrister, author and
                        anti-Jacobin. In 1811 he was involved in founding the National Society for the Education of the Poor. His <title>A Letter
                            Addressed to Samuel Whitbread, Esq. M.P., in consequnce of the Unqualified Approbation Expressed by Him &#8230; of Mr.
                            Lancaster&#8217;s System of Education</title> and its sequel, <title>Education of the Lower Orders, A Second Letter to Samuel
                            Whitbread &#8230; containing Observations on His Bill for the Establishment of Parochial Schools in South Britain</title> both
                        appeared in 1808.</note> &#8211; (<hi rend="ital">Non tali auxilio</hi>!)<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A contraction of
                        Virgil, <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 2, line 521, &#8216;non tali auxilio, nec defensoribus istis tempus eget&#8217;; &#8216;the times require
                        other aid and other defenders than those you bring&#8217;; a reference to Bowles&#8217; earlier involvement in the pursuit of English
                        Jacobins and to the sullying of his reputation in 1809 when he was accused of fraud.</note> Archdeacon Daubneys<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Daubney (1745&#8211;1827), Archdeacon of Sarum and author of <title>A Charge Delivered to the
                            Clergy of the Archdeaconry of Sarum, on the 26th, 27th, 28th and 29th of June 1810</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; &amp;
                    Whitbreads speech upon the Poor Laws.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The radical MP Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>). He took a close interest in poverty and the education of the poor; see for example, <title>Substance
                            of a Speech on the Poor Laws: Delivered in the House of Commons, on Thursday, February 19, 1807: with an Appendix by Mr.
                            Whitbread</title> (1807).</note> The terms which you propose for this pamphlett are perfectly liberal, &amp; I thank you
                    for them. I shall <del>dedica</del> address it in an Epistle Dedicatory to the Editor of the Ed. Review.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Epistle Dedicatory&#8217; to <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> was not included.</note>
                    This is already sketched out, &amp; when it is finished off will cut like a razor. In the body of the work I lay on the Beadles
                        Whip.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Henry the Sixth, Part II</title>, Act II, Scene 1, lines 136&#8211;155.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Respecting Nelson,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; of
                    course there will be no remarks on his former biographers. I shall always bear in mind the purpose &amp; use of the book, &#8211; that
                    it is to be the Midshipmans manual, &#8211; his moral &amp; intellectual compass. &#8211; For this reason I shall avoid all detail of the
                    dreadful scenes at Naples, &#8211; delivering my opinion, tho most intelligibly, in the gentlest terms, &amp; passing as rapidly as
                    possible over the whole disgraceful transaction.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nelson&#8217;s refusal to prevent the
                        execution of Neapolitan radicals in June&#8211;July 1799. Southey dealt with this matter briefly, but his views were plain, &#8216;a
                        faithful historian is called upon to pronounce a severe and unqualified condemnation of Nelson&#8217;s conduct&#8217;, <title>Life of
                            Nelson,</title> 2 vols (London, 1813), II, p. 51.</note> The History of Europe is the place where I shall soon be called upon to
                    enter at full into the story of Neapolitan politics.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey disliked the Bourbon
                        monarchy, which had been expelled from Naples by the French and had survived in Sicily because of British support. Its main
                        sins in his eyes were its reactionary nature and its unwillingness to wage war against the French; see <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422&#8211;437.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You shall have the Inquisition<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>The History of
                            the Inquisitions; including the Secret Transactions of those Horrific Tribunals</title> (1810); <title>Letter upon the
                            Mischievous Influence of the Spanish Inquisition as it actually exists in the Provinces under the Spanish Government.
                            Translated from El Espa&#241;ol, a periodical Spanish Journal published in London</title> (1811); <title>Narrativa da
                            Persegui&#231;&#227;o de Hippolyto Joseph Da Costa Pereira Furtado de Mendon&#231;a, Natural da Colonia do Sacramento, no Rio-da-Prata,
                            prezo e Processado em Lisboa pelo pretenso Crime de Fra-Ma&#231;on, ou Pedreiro Livre</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 313&#8211;357.</note> in about a week. Do not keep the first place for it, if you
                    &lt;have&gt; any thing else to begin with. I shall send you <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref> also, which
                    is nearly done,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Montgomery, <title>The West Indies, and other Poems</title> (1810)
                        and <title>The Wanderer in Switzerland, and other Poems</title> (1811), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly
                        Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 405&#8211;419.</note> &#8211; &amp; Chalmers<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander
                        Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810),
                        reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480&#8211;504, and <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12
                        (October 1814), 60&#8211;90.</note> I trust to conclude with. I perceive he inclines towards Methodism, &amp; of course writes very
                    uncharitably. What could possess the booksellers to pitch upon such a man as Editor General of the Poets! M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Whitbread &amp; his Committee might just as well have applied to me for a design for Drury Lane Theatre!<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Theatre Royal, Drury Lane had burnt down in 1809 and the new building was not opened until 10 October
                        1812. Whitbread headed the committee that raised funds for, and oversaw the rebuilding of, the theatre.</note> &#8211; I know as
                    much about architecture as he does about poetry. He does not even understand the names of his tools, as is evident by what he says
                    about Iambic &amp; Trochaic feet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had nearly forgotten one thing. Let me bespeak Lucien Buonapartes poem.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Lucien Bonaparte (1775&#8211;1840), <title>Charlemagne, ou l&#8217;Eglise D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1814).</note> I am better read in French Epics
                    than any body else sans doubt, &#8211; &amp; I can translate the specimens as well as any body else. But my reason for wishing it is
                    this. If the thing be bad I would say so in the most becoming terms, &#8211; at any rate I would fain speak of the author as he
                    deserves, &#8211; to my own certain knowledge. For I owe him something for the very liberal &amp; handsome manner in which he sent for
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> at Rome, &amp; advised him to get as soon as possible out of
                    his brothers<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Napoleon Bonaparte. Coleridge had fled Rome in 1806. He was worried the
                        French occupation of Naples in January 1806, would be followed by an invasion of Rome &#8211; a matter of real concern as he feared
                        Napoleon would punish him for his critical articles in the <title>Morning Post</title>. Lucien Bonaparte was living in
                        retirement in Rome at this time.</note> reach. It was done so liberally as with so much good sense as well as good feeling,
                    that it would wound me to see him treated with asperity when it was in my power to prevent it. Be assured I will not praise him
                    unjustly: all I desire to do is to <del>xxxx</del> censure the poem, if it requires censure, <del>in such terms as shall render
                        the censure</del> in the most decorous manner.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>