<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1890</idno><idno type="nines">rce3161</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text taken from William Knight,
                            Memorials of Coleorton, 2 vols (London,
                        1887).  Previously  published: William Knight, Memorials of
                            Coleorton, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 126–128.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1890" type="letter"><head>1890. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George
                        Beaumont</ref>, <date when="1811-03-28">28 March 1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text taken from William Knight,
                            <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London,
                        1887)<lb/>Previously published: William Knight, <title>Memorials of
                            Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 126–128.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-03-28">March 28, 1811</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir, </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The more necessary it becomes for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> to exert himself
                    in providing means for meeting the growing demands of his children, the more
                    incapable, by some strange and fatal infirmity, does he become of exertion.
                    Knowing his prodigious powers, and that there is no bodily disease which
                    incapacitates him, so that the mere effort of his own will would at any moment
                    render him all that his friends and family wish him to be, it is impossible not
                    to feel a hope that that effort will one day be made; yet this is hoping for an
                    intellectual and moral conversion, a new birth produced by an operation of
                    grace, of which there is no example to encourage us to hope for it.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> passed a few days
                    with me lately. The enclosure of <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>
                    is likely to put him in possession of the eastern side of Applethwaite
                        glen.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Beaumont had given
                        Wordsworth a plot of land at Applethwaite, a hamlet outside of Keswick, in
                        1803, so that he could be near Coleridge, then resident at Greta
                        Hall.</note> We walked up it together in the character of surveyors,
                    planning walks and plantations, and wishing it were but as easy to build houses
                    as castle. You must come to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> this
                    summer if you ever wish to see <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>
                    again in his majesty. The surface will soon be scored with enclosures, and stuck
                    over with larches. I cannot however but approve of the enclosure, and my
                    consolation is that if I live to go up the mountain twenty years hence, it will
                    be a comfort to rest in the shade upon the way.</p><p rend="indent1"> I expected to have been in London at this time, but business
                    which admits of no delay has grown under my hands, and it will be impossible for
                    me to leave this place before the first or second week in May, just when I
                    should be wishing to come back to it. My headquarters will not be in town, as
                    usual, but at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, where <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref> has lately
                    settled as rector. My goings on here are something like those of a horse in a
                    mill for labour and regularity – I may add too, for quietness and content. I
                    have made some little progress in a blank verse poem, of which Pelayo, the
                    restorer of Spain, is the hero;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        early version of what became <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814). Pelayo [Pelagius] (d. 737; reigned 718–737) was the founder of the
                        Kingdom of Asturias. He is credited with beginning the Christian reconquest
                        of the Iberian peninsula.</note> and I am planning another, which you will
                    think more original in conception when you hear that the scene lies in New
                    England, that the subject is that war which ensured the superiority of the
                    English settlers over the original inhabitants, and that the chief personage is
                    a primitive Quaker.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Oliver
                            Newman</title>, left incomplete at Southey’s death and published
                        posthumously.</note> His abominable costume would be less manageable in your
                    art than in mine.</p><p rend="indent1"> That sweet island<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Derwent Isle, in Derwentwater.</note> of <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Col. Peachy’s</ref>, I think, will be to
                    be sold. If you should think of visiting us this summer it might not improbably
                    be procured for the season. <ref target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Mrs.
                        Peachy</ref> was a great loss to us. I had a sincere regard for her, which
                    struck the deeper root because I always looked upon her as one who bore about in
                    her the seeds of a mortal malady. Having lost her, this lake will never again be
                    to me what it has been, and yet I have felt more pain in beholding her in her
                    most cheerful moments than when I heard the tidings of her death.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mrs. S.</ref> and
                    her sisters <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> and
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>. join me in respects
                    to Lady Beaumont. – Believe me, Sir George, very truly and respectfully
                    yours,</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>