<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2251</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3522</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 320&#8211;322 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2251" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2251" type="letter">
        <head>2251. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1813-04-24">24
                        April 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M.P./ Duke Street/ Westminster <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 320&#8211;322 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-04-24">April 24. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Booksellers when they share the profits, take the risk. That they themselves <del>xxx</del> wish to keep their
                    customary law<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bookseller&#8217;s practice of keeping half the copyright value of
                        publications they undertook at their own risk. See also Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 April 1812 (Letter
                        2078), [c. 13 April 1813] (Letter 2246), and 23 May 1813 (Letter 2263).</note> out of sight I can exemplify in a striking
                    case. <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Kirk Whites</ref> Remains<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807).</note> were published in this manner. When they came to a third or
                    fourth edition<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A third edition of the <title>Remains</title> appeared in 1808, a fourth in
                        1810.</note> (I forget which) &amp; it was apparent that the book had settled into a regular &amp; considerable sale, <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> White required of the booksellers (Vernor &amp; Hood<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London firm of Vernor &amp; Hood (fl. 1794&#8211;1811).</note>) two thirds of the profits. This produced a
                    letter from Hood<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The publisher Thomas Hood (1759&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>).</note> which
                    is a masterpiece in its kind. First he undertook to show that <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> did not
                    understand his own interests; for if he <del>had</del> were to have two thirds, they, the publishers, could then make such
                    deductions under various heads as would <del>make the net</del> &lt;render his&gt; receipts less than the half (thus impudently it
                    was stated); &amp; secondly he said that if the Remains belonged to the family, the Life<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        i.e. the biography of Henry Kirke White that was included in the <title>Remains</title>.</note> belonged to the publishers
                    they having paid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey 25&#163; for it. &#8211; This was if possible more impudent than the former assertion. The
                    fact was that a few months before when I was in town <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> had sent me 25&#163; with a
                    note saying that as the publishers had found the Remains so profitable they thought it proper to <hi rend="ital">present</hi> me
                    with that sum for the trouble I had taken in editing the work. &#8211; You may readily suppose what sort of a letter to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> this called forth from me;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter
                        to Longman has not survived.</note> &amp; in consequence I received, as I had required, a distinct acknowledgement of the real
                    &lt;nature of&gt; transaction. &#8211; In all this not a word was said of the <hi rend="ital">customary</hi> law. <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> yielded the point at the time, conceiving of course that it was always in his
                    power to take the whole property into his own disposal. But upon Vernor &amp; Hoods bankruptcy, their share <del>xx</del> was
                    sold, &amp; the affair is now in the Lawyers hands; &#8211; in what state <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref> can
                    inform you, if you have an opportunity of seeing him during the progress of the Committee.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        A government committee to enquire into existing copyright law was established in March 1813. Its findings led to legislation
                        in 1814. This extended copyright to an unconditional 28 years or the life of the author if longer. This was applied to new
                        publications and those already published by living authors. Posthumous works were also given a copyright period of 28
                        years.</note> &#8211; Should the business come to a trial I think that letter of Hoods ought to be produced. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> it was who first apprized me that such a Customary Law had been established,
                    &amp; that he had been employed to defend it against Townsend the traveller,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph
                        Townsend (1739&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), geologist, author of <title>A Journey Through Spain in the Years 1786 and 1787; with
                            Particular Attention to the Agriculture, Manufactures, Commerce, Population, Taxes, and Revenue of that Country</title>
                        (1791). He had entered into an agreement whereby his publishers took the risk of publication and shared any profits equally
                        with him. (The same terms Southey struck with Longman.) Townsend was shocked to discover that his publishers interpreted this
                       as giving them half the copyright of the book in perpetuity. He considered legal action, but was persuaded against it on the
                        grounds that he had no case; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 April 1812, Letter 2078.</note> who felt as
                    indignant at being entrapped by it as <del>any man who</del> every man <del>xxxx</del> must do who finds himself tricked out of a
                    part of his property.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your proposed clause will be a real benefit to the authors.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn had
                        spoken in the House of Commons on 11 March 1813 in favour of restricting number of copies of books given to copyright
                        libraries.</note> The copy right of Joan of Arc<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Joan of Arc</title>, first published in 1796; and <title>Poems</title> (1797) and (1799).</note> &amp; of my poems
                    would now have reverted to me if the Booksellers Custom did not declare otherwise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have the 4to edition of Maffeus.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Pietro Maffei (1536?-1603),
                            <title>Historiarum Libri XVI et Selectarum Epistolarum ex India Libri IV</title> (1588); no. 1657 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall have done with Annual Registers when the Edinburgh fails.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last on which Southey worked.</note> Its death will be owing
                    to the London booksellers, who being almost all concerned in the other two,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Annual Register</title> (founded 1758) was published by a congerie of booksellers, including Longman; the
                            <title>Asiatic Annual Register</title> (1799&#8211;1811) had captured the East India market.</note> by every possible means
                    impede its sale, so that where ten copies sell in Scotland, <del>not</del> &lt;scarcely&gt; one is sold in England. This is like
                        <del>x</del> what you rode upon in your theme, an insurmountable obstacle.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A joke
                        played on Wynn when he was a pupil at Westminster School. His theme &#8216;Pride is an insurmountable obstacle&#8217; had been corrected
                        by a waggish friend, possibly Southey, to &#8216;I ride an insurmountable obstacle&#8217;. Wynn then proceeded innocently to read the
                        corrected version out loud to the class, causing him much embarrassment.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> No man can think more mournfully than I do as to the prospect which the Spaniards have after they shall have
                    recovered their country, &#8211; &amp; till they have so done I <del>am</del> feel assured that they will continue the struggle, &#8211; even
                    if it were possible that Russia &amp; Germany could be once more put <hi rend="ital">hors de combat</hi>. &#8211; I cannot conceive that
                    the Queen&#8217;s party<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Maria Carolina (1752&#8211;1814; Queen Consort of Naples and Sicily
                        1768&#8211;1814). She had been the de facto ruler of the British-supported Bourbon Kingdom in Sicily until British pressure forced
                        her from power in 1812&#8211;1813.</note> can produce any <del>revolu</del> permanent revolution in Sicily, &#8211; for if there is any
                    one point in which all parties &amp; all authorities are agreed, it is in the abomination of the old system, &amp; the universal
                    wish of the people to be relieved from it. I shall look very anxiously for the next intelligence, for Sicily was the spot from
                    whence I hoped to have heard the trumpet sounded <del>to have</del> &lt;that should&gt; awaken<del>ed</del> Italy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the last vol: of the Asiatic Researches that strangest of all strange writers Wilford after a great deal of
                    pains to settle the exact place where the sea was churned to produce the Amreeta, fixes upon the Irish Channel, &amp; determines
                    that the Isle of Man was the mountain with which it was churned!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Wilford
                        (1761&#8211;1822), &#8216;An Essay on the Sacred Isles in the West, with other Essays connected with that work&#8217;, <title>Asiatic
                            Researches</title>, 11 (1812), 132. Southey owned a 12-volume edition of 1801&#8211;1811; no. 77 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I must send another inclosure to cover a letter from Coxe to Lord Auckland which has been sent me thro <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref>
            <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter from William
                            Coxe (1748&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), historian and Anglican clergyman; to William Eden, 1st Lord Auckland (1745&#8211;1814;
                                <title>DNB</title>). Coxe was writing <title>Memoirs of the Kings of Spain</title> (1813) and, in the course of a
                            distinguished career, Auckland had been British Ambassador to Spain 1787&#8211;1789. Coxe expressed his &#8216;warmest
                            acknowledgements&#8217; to Auckland for his help, <title>Memoirs of the Kings of Spain</title> (London, 1813), 3 vols, I, p.
                            xix.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>