<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2516</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3787</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 386&#8211;390.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2516" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2516" type="letter">
        <head>2516. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1814-12-15">15
                        December 1814</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 386&#8211;390.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-12-15">15 Dec. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must take the Old Ladys comfort in Shakespere respecting your daughter,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                    Wynn&#8217;s letter announced the birth of his fourth daughter, Emma (1814&#8211;1824).</note> &#8211; &#8216;tis a girl &#8211; promises boys hereafter&#8221;.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Henry VIII</title>, Act 5, scene 1, lines 165&#8211;166.</note> There is yet time before you, &amp; chance in your
                    favour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> After the enquiries which you have made it is very clear that no such person as <ref target="people.html#EvansGreeton">Greeton Evans</ref> is to be found; &#8211; the letter therefore must have been a trick, &amp;
                    never was a more witless one, for in what was the jest to end? The letter which I directed to the post office at Manchester was
                    not called for, &amp; came back to me in due course of time as having been unclaimed. The handwriting had certainly a female
                    appearance, &amp; the beginning of the letter had a turn of expression not much in character; &#8211; but in all the rest it was well
                    done, &amp; <del>had</del> &lt;bore&gt; a character of sincerity which shows at least <del>xx</del> some skill in the writer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had received a letter signed &#8216;Greeton Evans&#8217; asking for advice on pursuing a
                        literary career. For his reply, see Southey to Greeton Evans, 19 August 1814 (Letter 2470) and 20 August 1814 (Letter 2472).
                        He had asked Wynn to assist in ensuring Evans received his answer; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 19 August
                        1814, Letter 2471.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I trust you have received Roderick long ere this. According to the reports which reach me most persons are better
                    satisfied with it than I am myself. A small edition is gone to press, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>
                    apprehends that the quarto will be gone before this is ready.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second, duodecimo
                        edition of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> appeared in 1815.</note> But as for any thing like a great sale
                    &amp; a fashionable reputation, I never look for it, &amp; indeed am perfectly assured that no work of this character can possibly
                    attain it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> commendations are repeated to me from all quarters, &#8211; I regard them precisely as
                    I did his condemnation of Madoc; &#8211; the one opinion just serves to show the worthlessness of the other.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Byron&#8217;s satirical remarks on <title>Madoc</title> (1805) were contained in <title>English Bards and Scotch
                            Reviewers</title> (London, 1809), pp. 9&#8211;10. Byron&#8217;s opinion of <title>Roderick</title> was encapsulated in a letter to
                        Annabella Milbanke, 28 November 1814: &#8216;I think Southey&#8217;s Roderick as near perfection as poetry can be &#8211; which considering how
                        I dislike that school I wonder at &#8211; however so it is &#8211; if he had never written anything else he might safely stake his fame
                        upon the last of the Goths&#8217;, <title>Lord Byron&#8217;s Letters and Journals</title>, ed. Leslie A. Marchand, 13 vols (London,
                        1973&#8211;94), IV, p. 235.</note> For <del>tho</del> if one of these poems be bad, it is quite impossible that the other can be
                    good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will perhaps like to know what I am thinking of for my next essay. The New-England story for which the first
                    memoranda were made in January 1811 is now formed into something like a plan, sufficient to begin upon, if I had more time to
                    spare from more urgent employments. The chief personage is Oliver Newman, a son of Goffe the Regicide, &amp; godson of Old
                        Noll.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left incomplete at Southey&#8217;s death. In the poem, Newman was the
                        godson of Oliver Cromwell (1599&#8211;1658; <title>DNB</title>) and the son of William Goffe (d. 1679?; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Puritan, regicide and major general, who fled to New England in 1660 after he was excluded from the Act of Indemnity after the
                        Restoration.</note> He has <del>x</del> learnt the better parts of Quakerism from William Penn<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Penn (1644&#8211;1718; <title>DNB</title>), Quaker leader and founder of Pennsylvania.</note> &amp; acquired
                    a higher character from Milton,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and polemicist John Milton (1608&#8211;1674;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; at the age of about 25, after his mothers death, sails for America to seek his father.
                    On board the same ship there are Randolph, a man well known in the history of Massachusetts who was a keen hunter of the Regicides
                    in America,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The colonial administrator Edward Randolph (bap. 1632, d. 1703;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who, throughout his long and controversial career, was a tireless advocate of extending royal
                        authority in the American colonies. He first visited New England in 1676.</note> &amp; the wife &amp; daughter of a fine old
                    Cavalier, whom they are going to join in the country &lt;to&gt; which he having been totally neglected by Charles,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>), King of England, Scotland and Ireland,
                        1660&#8211;1685.</note> has retired. The mother dies upon the voyage &amp; leaves her daughter to Olivers protection, &#8211; &amp; the
                    poem will open with the funeral at sea. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Before the ship reaches Boston she is driven into Cape Cod, &#8211; where Oliver expends the greater part of his little
                    money in redeeming an Indian woman &amp; her <del>xxx</del> child from slavery, in order to restore her to her tribe. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Goffe married Whalleys daughter.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances (dates unknown), daughter of
                        Edward Whalley (d. 1674/5; <title>DNB</title>), parliamentarian Major-General and regicide. He fled to New England with Goffe
                        after the Restoration.</note> Leverett the Governor of Massachusetts<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Leverett
                        (1616&#8211;1679; <title>DNB</title>). Leading figure in Massachusetts, where he was Major-General 1663&#8211;1673 and Governor 1673&#8211;1679.
                        He had served in the Parliamentary army 1644&#8211;1648.</note> (an old Oliverian) had been attached to her before her marriage,
                    &amp; she to him. He is acquainted (<del>x</del> so he is believed to have been) with Goffes hiding place, &amp; Oliver brings a
                    letter to him. The scene that ensues <del>xx</del> explain the danger of N England from Philips War, then raging in its utmost
                        violence,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip&#8217;s War, or Metacom&#8217;s Rebellion, 1675&#8211;1676. An armed conflict
                        between English colonists and the native American inhabitants of New England.</note> &amp; the principles of Oliver, which
                    appear somewhat Quixotic. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His first business is to deliver Elizabeth to her father. Proceeding there with the Indian woman &amp; child they
                    find a wounded Mohawk lying among a party of his dead countrymen. By a piece of savage policy Philip<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Metacomet (c. 1639&#8211;1676), Sachem of the Wampanoag people. He used the name &#8216;Philip&#8217; in dealing with the
                        colonists in Massachusetts.</note> had waylaid &amp; murderd a party of these Indians &amp; left them <hi rend="ital">unscalped</hi> that it might be believed the English had killed them, &#8211; &amp; this being discovered by one who escaped with
                    life, was one main cause of his own destruction. By this Mohawk Oliver remains till he no longer requires assistance. He then
                    proceed to the womans tribe, who are in alliance with Philip, &amp; his most powerful ally.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A renegade who lives among the savages accuses Oliver of being a spy, insults him &amp; strikes him, which he bears
                    with Quaker patience. And here he learns of the apparition of his father at Hatfield; whither he sets out. On the way he falls in
                    with a party of the same tribe who are examining some booty which they have taken: they open a chest, &amp; find in it a dead
                    body, &#8211; which Oliver recognizes to be Whalleys, by the mutilated hand.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Whalley was
                        wounded in the hand at the Battle of Dunbar (1650).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Goffe in his long captivity has become a thorough fanatic, &amp; is not very well pleased with the quiet principles
                    of his son. &#8211; Randolph on the voyage had suspected who this son might be by his christian name, &amp; <del>had thus</del> by
                    watching him had obtained a clue to Goffe&#8217;s hiding place. Stanley the old Cavalier is sent to apprehend him, &amp; he finds father
                    &amp; son. Stanley however offers to let them go if Oliver will only declare that this person is not Goffe &#8211; which the Quaker will
                    not do, &amp; Randolph soon afterwards arriving identifies the Regicide.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On their way to the English settlement the Indians surprize them. Goffe &amp; Stanley escape, Randolph &amp; Oliver
                    are taken. On being brought to the encampment the latter is recognized &amp; welcomed, &amp; the former condemned to the stake.
                    Oliver obtains his life, they are then set at liberty &amp; depart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Goffe rallies some stragglers, makes head against the Indians &amp; takes some prisoners, whom they are about to
                    dispose of in the usual summary way, when Oliver appears, &amp; obtains the disposal of them. He goes with them to the encampment,
                    &amp; Elizabeth is brought in by the renegade. Scenes ensue in the course of which Oliver drops his non-resisting principles &amp;
                    cuts down the renegade with a tomahawk to the great delight of the Indians. The latter part of the story has not yet clearly
                    developed itself: this tribe makes peace thro Olivers influence, the Mohawk whom he saved comes at the head of his countrymen to
                    join the English, Philip is killed, Randolph promises secresy respecting the father, &amp; solicits a grant of lands for the son,
                    which Leverett gladly bestows for his services. &#8211; Stanley gives him his daughter, &amp; the story concludes with a wedding.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a rude outline, you will see however that it admits of some striking situations, &amp; a good deal of
                    historical &amp; descriptive ornament. I dare not write immediately after Roderick in blank verse, because I should be in danger
                    of repeating the same modes of expression. I incline therefore to the measure of Thalaba,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> &#8211; from which in the more dramatic parts I may pass into blank verse
                    without any dissonance from the general character of the poem.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not whether or not to introduce your old countryman Roger Williams,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Roger Williams (c. 1606&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>), religious controversialist, advocate of toleration and founder of
                        Providence, Rhode Island. He was a Londoner, though, rather than a Welshman.</note>
          <hi rend="ital">me judice</hi>
          <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In my judgement&#8217;.</note> the best of the Welshmen, who is
                    entitled to much of that praise which has been lavished upon W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Penn.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> Have you seen <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> poem?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Excursion</title> (1814).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>