<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2652</idno><idno type="nines">rce3923</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 425–426</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2652" type="letter"><head>2652. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1815-09-05">5
                        September 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [readdressed in another hand] To/ C W Williams
                        Wynn Esqr M.P./ <del>Wynnstay</del> &lt;Acton Park&gt;/ Wrexham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [illegible]<lb/>MS:
                        National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 425–426</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am on the eve of starting from home for a longer flight than I have for many years taken. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> carried his election, his four competitors successively withdrawing
                    from the contest,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey had been elected Senior Physician at the Middlesex
                        Hospital on 17 August 1815.</note> – he has married since to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">a woman</ref> whom I
                    remember a child in arms at Lisbon, – they are going to the continent for a months excursion, &amp; I have been tempted to join
                    their party. We go to Ostend &amp; Brussels, returning of course by Antwerp, – &amp; if the finances hold out we shall get as far
                    as Spa &amp; Aix la Chapelle. – into France I shall not go, – the state of affairs is too lowering, – if I had time &amp; money I
                    might perhaps see part of Holland, but travelling to me is doubly expensive inasmuch as I lose all that I should else have gained
                    in the time so employed. –</p><p rend="indent1"> On my return I purpose staying not more than a fortnight in town, &amp; taking you in my way home, if you should be
                    at Llangedwyn.</p><p rend="indent1"> I will try at an Inscription as soon as I can find out how to set about it. <hi rend="ital">Lapidary</hi>
                        inscriptions<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. an inscription that is engraved in stone.</note> I have never
                    written, &amp; know not how to write; never having been able to discover any principle upon which they are composed. But what can
                    be done in verse with the county of Denbigh &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnSirWatkinWilliams">Sir WWW!</ref><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A committee had been set up by
                        Wynn’s fellow Welshmen to commission a huge silver vase to commemorate the safe return from the Battle of Waterloo (18 July
                        1815) of Sir Watkin Williams Wynn. Southey was asked to write an inscription to be engraved on the
                        vase, but failed to do so; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 December 1815, Letter 2682.</note> – Your
                    resolutions may perhaps put something into my head.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had a bonfire on <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> for the battle of Waterloo &amp;c<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bonfire took place on 21 August 1815; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 22
                        August 1815 (Letter 2648) and Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 23 August 1815 (Letter 2649).</note> – follow the example on
                    Snowdon, &amp; you will have a feeling of sublimity which is certainly not to be obtained in a lower region. I wish you had been
                    with us. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> was there &amp; Boswell.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The barrister and literary scholar James Boswell (1778–1822; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You will see a long paper in the next Quarterly continuing the sketch of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellingtons</ref> life from the battle of Vittoria<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The allied defeat of the French at Vittoria, 21 June 1813, paved the way for eventual victory in the
                        Peninsular war.</note> to the present time.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been commissioned to write a
                        second review article on Wellington, capitalising on public interest following Waterloo. It comprised a review of:
                        Eustache-Auguste Carel (1788–1836), <title>Précis Historique de la Guerre d’Espagne et de Portugal, de 1808 à 1814</title>
                        (1815); Jean Sarrazin (1770–1848), <title>Histoire de la Guerre d’Espagne et de Portugal, de 1807 à 1814</title> (1814);
                            <title>General View of the Political State of France, and of the Government of Louis XVIII</title> (1815); <title>An
                            Answer to the Calumniators of Louis XVIII</title> (1815); <title>Official Accounts of the Battle of Waterloo</title>
                        (1815); Lieutenant-General W. A. Scott (dates unknown), <title>Battle of Waterloo</title> (1815), and appeared in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448–526.</note> I am to have 100£ for it, – these things are valued by
                    the <del>public</del> fashion for them, not by what they are intrinsically worth. This however has cost me more time than would
                    have sufficed for much better compositions. So it is, that I who heartily despise reviews &amp; have moreover a principled &amp;
                    moral dislike to them, am compelled to pass half my time in reviewing. Do not you however who have truly been my Maecenas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a patron in the mould of the wealthy, generous and enlightened patrician Gaius Clinius
                        Maecenas (70–8 BC).</note> &amp; support when I had <del>not</del> no other, quote upon me ‘<hi rend="ital">ut nemo quam sibi
                        sortem</hi> &amp;c<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A contraction of Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65–8 BC),
                            <title>Sermones</title>, Book 1, Sermo 1, line 1: ‘How comes it to pass, Maecenas, that no one lives content with his
                        condition’.</note> – for I am contented &amp; thankful in that state of life to which it has pleased God to appoint me.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here am I interrupted by news which would make a Welsh man swear. An importation of toasting-cheese from the county
                    of Durham (famous for that commodity) is just arrivd, – &amp; the mice have eaten half of it by the way.</p><p rend="indent1"> I cannot judge of what length your plinth will allow me, – tho of course the fewer lines the better. But you had
                    better tell me the extent of my tether. If you direct to 15 <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Queen Anne Street</ref>, I shall
                    find the letter on my arrival in town.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</signed><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1815-09-05">5 Sept. 1815.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>