<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2337</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3608</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Brotherton
                        Library, University of Leeds.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2337" type="letter">
        <head>2337. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1813-11-28">28 November 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry.<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmarks: E/ 1 DE 1/ 1813; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ DE 1/ 1813 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 169. 1813/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Decemb<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. 1814<lb />MS: Brotherton
                        Library, University of Leeds<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-11-28">Nov. 28. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Leave-taking is one of the evils of life, &amp; I do not therefore regret that we did not meet in London just to
                    say farewell. Here I am, recovered from three months of mental dissipation, &amp; from three hundred miles mail-coaching, &#8211; the
                    least fatiguing of the two: &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife</ref> &amp; children<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> all, thank God, in health, my books about me, my papers in
                    order, &amp; I myself in full enjoyment of health, happiness, &amp; uninterrupted leisure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I learnt at the Chamberlains Office that it is necessary to give you a letter of Attorney, because a receipt cannot
                    be transmitted from hence, but must be signed at the office. Will you therefore procure one empowering you to receive all monies
                    payable to me as Laureate, <del>&amp;</del>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert"> Henry</ref> will thro <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> transmit
                    it to me in a frank for signature, &amp; I will return it thro the same channel, &amp; apprize you at what time the salary will be
                    in course of payment. My appointment dates singularly enough from the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of August which is both the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince&#8217;s</ref> birth day &amp; my own, &#8211; the day after Pye&#8217;s death.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s predecessor as Poet Laureate, Henry James Pye (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), had died
                        on 11 August 1813.</note> With pensions one quarter is never paid till another is due, &amp; the Chamberlains office may
                    perhaps be somewhat longer in arrear. There will be fees to the amount of nearly &#163;20 to be deducted from the first quarter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> I have heard nothing since I saw you &#8211; but a letter
                    from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> was awaiting me, in which he says he had seen <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James B</ref> (the Printer, had spoken to him on the subject, &amp; was convinced that I
                    should find the treatment which I was so well entitled to expect. &#8211; I account for the delay in closing my account by the much
                    longer &amp; heavier ones which they have to settle. That I shall lose my share in the Register<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sum Southey had invested in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> (&#163;209) seems sufficiently
                    certain. What is due to me I expect to recover, &amp; am about to demand from them a bill payable to you in London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When the Laureateship was first mentioned to me I thought little of it, &amp; doubted whether I should accept it,
                    if it were placed at my acceptance. I think very differently now. As an honour it was given me, &amp; honourable I will make it.
                    &amp; I derive <del>a satisf</del> from the use to which it is applied a satisfaction greater than a much larger salary would have
                    given me if devoted to my own immediate use.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Ode<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first Laureate ode <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>,
                        published, after much revision, in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814.</note> will be finished in the course of the week,
                    &#8211; it is at once a Te Deum,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Thee, O God&#8217;, a Latin hymn of praise.</note> &amp; an
                    exhortation not to stop short in victory. I shall probably like it less than an Epistle to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> with which it is my intention to accompany it, concerning the office
                    &amp; myself.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ode was not accompanied by an epistle.</note> Could I but strike off a
                    beginning this would soon be written. I mean to do a good deal of volunteer duty, &amp; meditate among other things a series of
                    monumental inscriptions for the peninsular war.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Only 18 of the projected 30 inscriptions
                        were written.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I found some valuable letters from Spain on my return. One from D Pedro Maria Ric<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish aristocrat and politician Pedro Maria Ric y Monserrat, Baron de Valdeolivos (1776&#8211;1831).</note>
                    respecting Palafox &amp; Zaragoza<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Rebolledo de Palafox y Melzi (1780&#8211;1847), Spanish
                        general, who in 1808 and 1809 commanded the defending forces at the first and second sieges of Zaragosa.</note> which was
                    especially gratifying. He tells me that the Junta of Aragon have sent me a series of their journals<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A contribution to what became 24 volumes of Spanish <title>Gazetas</title>, 1808&#8211;1813, no. 3472 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; which I was very desirous of possessing. I am in high odour <del>among</del> in
                    Spain, &amp; shall obtain from thence every information which I know how to ask for. This is a great point. Perhaps no historical
                    work was ever undertaken under more favourable circumstances. &#8211; I have not seen you since the battle of Leipsic!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French were defeated by an allied army (composed of troops from Russia, Prussia, Austria and
                        Sweden) on 16&#8211;19 October 1813.</note> Ask M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Walpole<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sophia (d.
                        1829), widow of Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), envoy to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800.</note>
          <del>xxx</del> what she thinks &lt;now&gt; of my rose-coloured politics? My faith was that nothing founded upon evil could be
                    permanent, &#8211; &amp; that faith is now abundantly justified. We have now to look for the recovery of Italy,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> There was no decisive victory for the Austrians in Northern Italy and the French Army of Italy only
                        surrendered at the end of the war in April 1814.</note>
          <del>on</del> the capture of Davousts army,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The army commanded by the French Marshal
                        Louis-Nicolas d&#8217;Avout (1770&#8211;1823), which was besieged in Hamburg. It did not surrender until the end of the war in April
                        1814.</note> &amp; the submission of Denmark.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Denmark was increasingly isolated and
                        withdrew from the war under the terms of the Treaty of Kiel, 14 January 1814.</note> These we may expect, &amp; it would not
                    surprize me to hear that Buonaparte falls by the hands of the French. I think it likely that the Bourbons will be restored. I am
                    not sure that I wish for their restoration. <hi rend="ital">Pereat iste</hi>
          <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Let him die
                        himself&#8217;.</note> however, &#8211; let who will succeed him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am anxious to know what intelligence you have from Brazil concerning the ship.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I left directions concerning the Bust.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bust of Southey sculpted
                        earlier in 1813 by James Smith (1775&#8211;1815).</note> Two in a week are all that can be cast without injuring the mould, &#8211; &amp;
                    the &lt;artist&gt; has fifteen &amp; may probably have twenty to make. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> joins
                    me in kind remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> when you see him.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>