<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2313</idno><idno type="nines">rce3584</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 80-82. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2313" type="letter"><head>2313. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-10-16">16[–22] October
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland
                        <lb/>Postmark: BOC/ 22/ 1813<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 80-82. </note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1813-10-16">Saturday evening. Oct 16. 1813. </date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Streatham"> Streatham</ref>.</placeName></address></dateline><salute>My dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> My letter of yesterday by a provoking blunder of the servants was left for todays post, &amp; being sealed I could
                    not open it when yours, as I had hoped it would, arrived from <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Annes Street</ref>. – Make
                    yourself quite easy concerning money, – there will be plenty. My work here<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was
                        writing a pamphlet entitled <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George
                            Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813). This was a defence of Sir George
                        Barlow’s (1763–1846; <title>DNB</title>) conduct as Governor of Madras in 1807–1813, especially during the army mutiny of
                        1809. It was a direct reply to Charles Marsh (c. 1774–1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in
                            the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813).</note> is finished, &amp; as soon as I
                    receive the ‘remuneration’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Love’s Labours Lost</title>, Act III, scene 1, lines 136–137.</note> I shall send you a large supply. – The yearly
                    insurance for 1000£, at my age is £34 three times that will be £102. the Laureateship will not quite cover this, but the few
                    pounds which are deficient I shall willingly pay. There is no better mode of laying by money for a family. A policy for 5000£ was
                    paid the other day, &amp; the man had lived so long &amp; the society is so flourishing that his Executors received 9000£.</p><p rend="indent1"> Dear Edith you advise me still to make Ludlow in my way. My mind was made up to take the shortest road, for the
                    round would occasion at least a weeks delay. One day to Worcester, one day there, one day to Ludlow, not less than two there, –
                    then there is <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> expecting me, &amp; not willing to part with me when he gets me,
                    &amp; from him I should have to find my way thro vexatious delays, &amp; expensive routes to Chester &amp; Liverpool, whereas the
                    strait road saves money, saves <del>xxx</del> trouble, saves uncertainty, &amp; above all brings me home in three &amp; forty
                    hours. – If I promise <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brown</ref> to take you there in 1815 when I put
                    my great book to the press,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular
                            War</title> (1823–1832).</note> he will willingly forgive the disappointment now. In truth I am heartily homesick – &amp;
                    why should I be ashamed to confess it.</p><p>Thursday. 2 o clock. <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref>. </p><p rend="indent1"> Here I am, – engaged every day for a fortnight with only the exception of one. The delays about the Laureateship
                    are at last over. In order that every body might have a finger in the pye <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Marquis
                        Hertford</ref> chose to wait till <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> should please to write to him,
                    &amp; ask it for me. This was done yesterday, &amp; a note from <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> last night informed
                    me the appointment was made. I go to Court with <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, – which will be like seeing the
                    last scene of a pantomime, &amp; being on the stage myself. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> riggs
                    me in his Court-suit. The Levee will be held either immediately after the meeting of Parliament (which is fixed for the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. next Tuesday week) or perhaps before, – if there are any changes in administration. When it is over I shall
                    write a full true &amp; particular account to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Herbert</ref>, – as being not the
                    least curious passage in his fathers life. – On Wednesday next I go to the Insurance Office, – &amp; then (including my former
                    insurance), an improving legacy of 4000£ will be secured for the five who are come &amp; the nine who are to make up my lawful
                    number of children. – I should like to see whether you look vicious at reading this.</p><p rend="indent1"> We go to Woburn<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ancestral home of Herbert Hill’s patron, John Russell,
                        6th Duke of Bedford (1766–1839).</note> about the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. meaning to stay one clear day &amp; return the
                        <del>xxx</del> next. Then I shall remove my quarters to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>, &amp; my present
                    intention is to take my place in the mail for Tuesday the ninth of November so to reach home on this day three weeks, – after the
                    longest absence I ever <del>xxx</del> made, or ever again expect to make. But I have been profitably employed. My business at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> is compleated to the full satisfaction of the person concerned, &amp; I suppose
                    the ‘goodly guerdon’<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Faerie
                            Queene</title> (1590–1596), Book I, Canto VII, Stanza 15, line 2.</note> will not be delayed. As soon as it comes I shall
                    send you a large remittance. You need be under no uneasiness respecting money. Employments crowd upon me, &amp; every new
                    publication will be more profitable than the last.</p><p rend="indent1"> Friday. <ref target="people.html#MorganMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Morgan</ref> is better, &amp; I hope the
                    danger is not likely to return. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is gone to Bristol upon their
                    business, he went <del>Thur</del> Wednesday, &amp; is to return the end of the week. I had not seen him for ten days before, at
                    which he was unreasonable enough to wonder &amp; complain, when <del>x</del> if he had looked for me instead of expecting me to
                    look for him, he would have found that I was not in town, – &amp; when if he had reflected for a single minute he would have
                    perceived that, if in town, my very minutes must needs be numbered. He means to come down with me.</p><p rend="indent1"> We dined yesterday with <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, where <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> was introduced to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>. This
                    morning I am to breakfast with <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref>, – from <del>xx</del> Mark Lane I return in this
                    direction to Norton Street, for my second sitting for the bust – I sat for hours yesterday: it is not fatiguing, &amp; the process
                    being new to me was amusing. <del>He e</del> Smith<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Smith (1775–1815),
                        sculptor.</note> expects to succeed entirely, &amp; I believe my face is one of those which is better fitted for the sculptor
                    than the painter. We go to Champion Hill<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The home of the Gonne family, friends of Southey
                        since his first visit to Portugal in 1796.</note> to day where we shall meet M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Harrison.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> Tomorrow I dine with Stoddart,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        lawyer and writer Sir John Stoddard (1773–1856; <title>DNB</title>). In 1813 he was working as a leader-writer on <title>The
                            Times</title>.</note> Sunday we go to Richmond, return on Wednesday to dine with <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, Thursday with <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, Friday with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, Saturday with <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, Sunday with
                        <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>. – I am working at present upon documents which <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> has supplied me with.</p><p rend="indent1"> I found the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhoras</ref> letter on my return last night, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littletons</ref> card with it. If possible I shall call on him
                    today, – tomorrow at the latest. – See by what scraps I have written this scrawl, &amp; now I must set off for Mark Lane – nearly
                    an hours walk. So if at least it should be impossible to fill up the other side of the letter when I come back I will say God
                    bless you here.</p><closer><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>