<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1918</idno><idno type="nines">rce3189</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 13.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 219–221.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1918" type="letter"><head>1918. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1811-05-08">8 May
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ South
                        Parade/ Bath<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 13<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 219–221.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> I give you joy very sincerely.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had recently married <ref target="people.html#LandorJulia">Julia Thuillier</ref>.</note> No man can be thoroughly happy till he has a home, (– a
                    mere house is not one,) &amp; a family, whether it be his parents or his children, with whom he feels at rest, &amp; in his proper
                    place. To be at rest <del>oneself</del>, without either hope, wish, or desire beyond &lt;what&gt; the passing history of the human
                    race ought to inspire, is my summum bonum,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘highest good’.</note> &amp; this which by
                    Gods blessing I have enjoyed for many years, I never could have attained while unmarried. There is a passage in the Confessions of
                        S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Augustine the truth of which any man who has a heart neither of the pumpkin nor the pippin class will
                    recognize in the recollections of his own youth. “Nondum amabam, &amp; amare amabam; quærebam quid amarem, amans amare.”<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Augustine of Hippo (354–430), <title>Confessions</title>, Book 3, lines 2–4; ‘I loved
                        not yet, yet I loved to love … I sought what I might love, in love with loving’.</note> – The very Welshmen will become more
                    endurable if you take a wife to <ref target="places.html#Llanthony">Llanthony</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Early in July I shall be at Bath. One of the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">best hearted &amp; cleverest
                        women</ref> whom I have ever known, is there at present with <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward
                        Littleton</ref>, to whom she has been as a daughter for many years. She is a very old friend of ours, &amp; we must stay a few
                    days with her on <del>th</del> our progress thro the South. I hope you will be at Bath at that time, &amp; if not, – why you
                    cannot be very far out of the road from Bristol to Keswick, – <del>for</del> it is one advantage of having so long a <del>road
                        way</del> &lt;road&gt; to travel, that almost any part of England may be made in the way. I thought to have been at this time
                    on my journey, &amp; yet seem no nearer my departure than I was a month ago, so unmercifully does the business of 1809 grow under
                    my hands.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was investing more time and labour than he had anticipated in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register for 1809</title> (1811).</note> If it prove not a good volume, then will there have been
                    a great deal of precious time mis employed, &amp; a great deal of zealous labour thrown away.</p><p rend="indent1"> You shall hear <del>when I am in town that</del> soon after I reach town some tidings of Count Julian,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812). Southey was assisting Landor with attempts to have it staged at the Theatre
                        Royal, Covent Garden. In the event, nothing came of this plan.</note> – for I think it is needless that you should prepare a
                    more correct copy for Kembles<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The actor and theatrical manager John Philip Kemble
                        (1757–1823; <title>DNB</title>) of the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden.</note> perusal than that which I possess. It is best to
                    treat such men with something like haughtiness, – that is to make them understand no favour is solicited – &amp; that the
                    obligation is quite as much on their part as on ours. I will tell him that the copy is incorrect, – &amp; more than this, – that
                    if he chuses to bring it forth, there will be a readiness on the authors part to adapt it for representation in such way as he may
                    advise. If Kemble knows what is really excellent in dramatic composition (which <del>really</del> I doubt) – or if he knows what
                    suits his own powers, which he most likely does, he <del>will</del> &lt;ought to&gt; jump at this play, – &amp; the first hundred
                    lines, or any single scene <del>thro</del> of the whole will determine him at once. I do not expect him to understand its
                    excellence, – a man who can take as much pleasure in acting Zanga as King John cannot possibly have any real knowledge of
                        Shakespere.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The critique is of Kemble’s taking on ‘respectable’ Shakespearean roles
                        alongside leading parts in plays that Southey thought were ‘trash’. The vengeful Moor Zanga was the central character in
                        Edward Young (bap. 1683, d. 1765; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Revenge: A Tragedy</title> (1721). A version revised by
                        Kemble and with him in the lead role had been staged at the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden. Southey had seen and been disgusted
                        by the revival of 1801–1802; see Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 12 March 1811, Letter 1883.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> It <del>vex</del> vexed me that in your letter to Riquelme you should have spoken as you did of my poor friends the
                        Portugueze.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor’s <title>Three Letters to Don Francisco Riquelme</title> (1809);
                        which addressed ‘the Means of supplying an adequate Force of Calvalry’, and gave Landor’s opinions on the ‘Parties in England,
                        their Errors, and Designs’ and the conduct of the British forces in their attempts to take the Spanish ports of Ferrol
                        (August 1800), and Buenos Aires (1806–1807) and in signing the Convention of Cintra (1808). Landor was highly critical of the
                        conduct of the Portuguese. Francisco Riquelme (d. 1808) had commanded a division of the Spanish army of Galicia and had thus
                        been involved in fighting French forces in northern Spain in August–November 1808. He died on 10 November 1808 of wounds
                        received in action.</note> See how manfully they have acquitted themselves as soon as they had men at their head on whom they
                    could rely, &amp; a possibility appeared that their exertions might be successful. Surely all men are brave by nature, &amp; when
                    nations are cowardly the vice is wholly in the government. There will always be individual instances of cowardice; –
                        <del>but</del> whenever it happens it is a physical infirmity, – not always superable by moral exertion. But I maintain that
                        <del>we</del> as an animal man is naturally brave &amp; that the men of all countries will make good soldiers if only they are
                    well trained. Specific national qualities will still remain, – the Frenchman will march with most gaiety to the attack, the
                    Spaniard will endure the greatest privations, – the Russian will stand the most quietly to have his skull hammered in with the
                    butt end of a musket, &amp; the Englishman will behave best in the field. My life for it we shall beat Buonaparte out of the
                    Peninsula, &amp; it will be our own fault if we do not dictate <del>a px</del> under the walls of Paris a peace of which the first
                    article shall be that the French are never to have a ship of war. We must get them down, &amp; down we must keep them.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> writes me that he has 109 copies of Kehama in his warehouse, &amp; that he
                    hopes these will sell by the time a small edition is <del>xx</del> ready.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first (1810)
                        edition of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was in quarto. A second, duo-decimo edition was published in 1811.</note>
                    Accordingly I have written to <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> to reprint, but to take his leisure about
                    it, for there is no hurry. Madoc<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Madoc</title>, published in
                        1812.</note> also is just gone again to press. In the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Quarterly there is an article of mine upon
                        Methodism<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s review of <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the
                            Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November
                        1810), 480–514.</note> which if I had been in the church would have been worth a rich benefice, so completely has it delighted
                        <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>. Have you seen <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> criticism upon Kehama?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey’s appraisal of <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810), <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17 (February 1811), 429–465; which had attacked Southey’s ‘conceit
                        and bad taste, and … the perversity of his manifold affectations’ (429).</note> it is quite as original as the poem, &amp;
                    altogether matchless <del>f</del> for impertinence. </p><closer><salute rend="indent5"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent7"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-05-08">May 8. 1811.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>