<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2020</idno><idno type="nines">rce3291</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4869 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 369–373 [misdated 12 January
                        1812].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2020" type="letter"><head>2020. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1812-01-21">21 January
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Norwich<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 10
                        February<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4869<lb/> Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 369–373 [misdated 12 January
                        1812].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-01-21">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your last letter troubled both my sleep &amp; my waking thoughts, for tho I had heard of your losses I had no
                    notion of their extent.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor’s letter of 10 December 1811, J. W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        349–353, described how a series of failed investments by his father had annihilated ‘between three and four thousand pounds.
                        We cannot subsist, in our contracted shape, on the interest of what remains. The capital will last our joint lives; but I
                        shall be abandoned at once to solitarity and penury. To what can I look forwards but to a voluntary interment in the same
                        grave with my parents?’ (350–351). On receipt of Taylor’s letter, Southey immediately began to plan how to relieve his
                        distress; see Southey to Robert Gooch, 15 December 1811, Letter 1999.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> There is likely to be a place at the Museum vacated by the resignation of Douce. The thing I believe is not yet
                    known. The presentation is <del>in the</del> vested in <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">the Speaker</ref>, the AB. of Canterbury &amp; the Ld Chancellor.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Douce (1757–1834; <title>DNB</title>) had resigned as Keeper of Manuscripts at the
                        British Museum in April 1811. The post was in the gift of the Archbishop of Canterbury, The Speaker and the Lord Chancellor.
                        Southey had earlier refused to apply for the vacancy; see Southey to John Rickman, [c. November 1811], Letter 1991.</note>
                    Thro <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> I think the first may be secured, &amp; possibly I could get at the
                    second thro two channels, – but I am not without fear that your mortal heresies may stand in the way. However the trial may be
                    made. Tell me if such a situation would be conformable to your inclinations, – &amp; I will immediately set to work. That Douce
                    had the intention two months ago I know, &amp; the situation has been represented to me as worth 400 £ a year. But if he should
                    have changed his mind vacancies are not infrequently occurring, &amp; it is well to have an eye upon them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Cannot your literary employments be made more productive? The Monthly<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Monthly Review</title>, for which Taylor was a salaried reviewer 1793–1799. He started writing for the magazine
                        again in 1808.</note> when you were formerly connected with it paid better than the other Reviews, – it is now I believe much
                    behind the quarterly ones in this respect. Your political opinions square sufficiently with the Edinburghers,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, a Whig quarterly journal, founded in 1802.</note> – your
                    heresies would be inadmissable there, for their esoteric criticism is perfectly orthodox in its professions. But should you object
                    to assist the Quarterly in any of those <del>xx</del> topics which have no connection with party or sectarian feelings? I should
                    be sorry to see the weight of your talents thrown into <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jefferys</ref> scale.</p><p rend="indent1"> You once talked of arranging &amp; collecting your scattered writings; – make this your amusement, – &amp; while
                    the volumes are printing let your friends make out a list which will take off the whole impression without its passing thro a
                    booksellers hands. Your assent to this is all that would be needed, &amp; this, I think, you ought not to refuse. The task is one
                    which you owe to yourself, for unless you do this others will one day fasten upon your remains, &amp; pilfer &lt;the&gt;
                    reputation which you throw away. The manner ought not to be objectionable, – <del>it</del> leave that wholly to others, &amp; the
                    result will be that the whole of the booksellers profit will be saved, – amounting to more than a fourth of the gross product of
                    the whole impression.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor replied, 10 February 1812, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 373–375: ‘I
                        have anticipated your advice, and have already begun to collect and publish my writings’ (374). He began with <title>English
                            Synonyms Discriminated</title> (1813).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You have formerly talked of writing the history of the Hanse Towns.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        proposed work on the coastal cities and towns that formed part of the Northern European Hanseatic League, a trading monopoly
                        active between the thirteenth and seventeenth centuries. Taylor replied, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 375: ‘About the Hanse Towns I have
                        no present scheme’.</note> Should you seriously think of prosecuting this design, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has a volume which may be serviceable to you. It contains – Notitia Majorum, – Plurimas Lubecensium aliorum q
                    clarorum virorum, de Ecclesia, Republica et Literis egregie meritorum vitas, &amp;c comprehendens quam filiis impertit Jacobus a
                    Melle. Lipsiæ. 1707.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacob von Melle (1659–1743), Lutheran theologian, author and
                        polymath, who published widely on his native city, Lübeck. <title>Notitia Majorum, Plurimas Lubecensium aliorumque Clarorum
                            Virorum de Ecclesia, Republica et Literis Egregie Meritorum Vitas, ab aliquot Saeculis Repetitas et Documentis Authenticis
                            Illustratas, Comprehendens, quam Filiis Impertit Jacobus a Melle</title> (1707).</note> – Another work by the same Lubec
                    Pastor, entitled De Itineribus Lubecensium Sacris, seu de Religiosis &amp; votives eorum Peregrinationibus vulgo <hi rend="ital">Wallfarthen</hi> quas olim devotionis ergo ad Loca sacra susceperunt. – Lubecæ, 1711.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Jacob von Melle (1659–1743), <title>De Itineribus Lubecensium Sacris, seu de Religiosis &amp; Votives eorum Peregrinationibus
                            Vulgo ‘Wallfarthen’ quas olim Devotionis ergo ad Loca Sacra Susceperunt</title> (1711).</note> – Petri Vincentii de
                    Origine, Incrementis et Laudibus Lubecæ Elegia – &amp;c – 1755.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A 1755 edition of Peter
                        Vincent (1519–1581), <title>De Origine, Incrementis et Laudibus Lubecæ Elegia</title> (1552).</note> – and finally Historia
                    Lubecensis Recentior ab anno 1300, ad annum 1400<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacob von Melle (1659–1743),
                            <title>Historia Lubecensis Recentior ab anno 1300, ad annum 1400</title> (1679).</note> – by the aforsesaid Jacobus a
                        Melle<hi rend="ital">r</hi> as his name is here written Jenæ 1679. – The collection was made at Lubec for a Frenchman of great
                    book-learning at Lisbon, the Abbe Garnier,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles-Francois, Abbé Garnier (1722–1804),
                        had been chaplain to the French factory at Lisbon. He was a noted collector of books, manuscripts, coins and medals. Some of
                        his collection was auctioned in London on 10 June 1807.</note><del>&amp; xxxx</del> the four tracts form but a moderately sized volume, they must contain something to your purpose, &amp;
                    probably they are not easily to be found. Shall I send it you? I can take the opportunity of <del>x</del> a booksellers parcel to
                    London, &amp; direct it either to Richard Taylors<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The printer, naturalist and Unitarian,
                        Richard Taylor (1781–1858; <title>DNB</title>). Born in Norwich, he had moved to London in 1797 to serve his apprenticeship
                        and remained there. He was a fellow of the Linnean Society, Society of Antiquaries, Royal Astronomical Society, and the
                        Philological Society.</note> care or in any other way that you may appoint.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of all topics that of consolation is the most difficult to handle well. You ought to be a happy man, because you
                    have done your duty &amp; [MS torn] nothing wherewith to reproach yourself; – &amp; being a single one, &amp; likely from long
                    habits <del>xxx</del> to have remained so under any circumstances, no change of circumstances as respecting yourself ought to
                        <del>grieve</del> afflict you deeply. A single man may look with indifference upon all that <del>xxxx xxxxxxxx</del> does not
                    vitally affect him. But you are rich in friends, – rich in talents, rich in acquirements, rich in good works. And if I thought it
                    possible that you could ever feel a reasonable anxiety respecting the means of comfortable subsistence, while there are so many
                    men in the world who love you, &amp; are beholden to you, I should think far worse of human nature than my own experience teaches
                    me to do. – Were it needful, I would tell you &amp; press upon you, that a man who has ever been so ready to give, is bound in his
                    turn to receive.</p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor! Remember me I pray to your Mother;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sarah Taylor, nee Wright (1735/6–1812).</note> I fear your greatest grief is to know that she grieves for your
                    sake. But you have yet I trust long years of happiness before you.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>