<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1822</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3093</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the
                            Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 298&#8211;302.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1822" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1822" type="letter">
        <head>1822. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1810-11-03">3 November
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ William Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Feb 2<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS:
                        Huntington Library, HM 4866 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the
                            Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 298&#8211;302.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-11-03">Saturday. Nov. 3. 1810</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> On turning to your letter of Oct 31. 1808 I find that you thanked me for the Cid<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808). See J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 222.</note> &#8211; &#8220;in the name of the English people, in the
                    name of the Spanish people, &amp; in the name of Literature in general.&#8221; It adds &#8211; you proceed &#8211; to our domestic stock of books
                    another good &amp; lasting one. It will strengthen national sympathies, at present of high value to the liberties of mankind. It
                    augments the mass of recorded experience, critically &amp; benevolently commented. It is philosophic history in the form of
                    contemporary history, &amp; unites the interest of co&#339;val with the instruction of contemplated annalism. &#8211; You would however
                    quarrel with the theory of Mahommed<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Muhammad (c. 570&#8211;632), Prophet of Islam.</note> in the
                    Introduction, &amp; you say &#8220;it is not true that the Koran contains no maxims of morality &#8211; The command to record debts in the
                    second Sura, &amp; the general care for pecuniary probity, is one honourable instance &#8211; the inculcation of the eleemosynary
                    virtues is another.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the
                            Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 222&#8211;223. A response to Southey&#8217;s assertion: &#8216;There
                        is nothing in the Koran which affects the feelings, nothing which elevates the imagination, nothing which enlightens the
                        understanding, nothing which ameliorates the heart: it contains no beautiful narrative, no proverbs of wisdom or axioms of
                        morality&#8217;, <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (London, 1808), p. xviii.</note> &#8211; In a subsequent letter you wish that I had
                    seperated from the text of the Chronicle all that I disbelieved, &amp; that I had thrown it into notes or appendix.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor to Southey, 27 December 1808, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p. 234.</note> &#8211; But this I think would
                    have been relying too confidently on my own powers of discrimination, &amp; certainly setting a dangerous example: &#8211; nor does
                    their appear any necessity for it, as whenever any reason for doubting part of the story existed, it has uniformly been
                    stated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> wrote a poor reviewal of this book in the first Quarterly &#8211; &amp; expressed an
                    opinion that the capture of Valencia was a particularly suspicious fact.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had
                        reviewed <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 134&#8211;153. He
                        expressed his doubts about the Cid&#8217;s capture of Valencia (Ibid, 152).</note> He was not aware that there is no fact more fully
                    authenticated in history. &#8211; The Mocedades del Cid by Guillen de Castro is I believe the play from which Corneille formed his
                        tragedy.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guill&#233;n de Castro (1569&#8211;1631), <title>Las Mocedades del Cid</title> (written
                        1605&#8211;1615) did influence Pierre Corneille&#8217;s (1606&#8211;1684), <title>El Cid</title> (1636).</note>
          <del>xxxx</del> The most pertinent piece of information I can give you about it is that <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> means to publish a rhyme-translation of it, &#8211; he like Fox<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles
                        James Fox (1749&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>) was Lord Holland&#8217;s uncle.</note> carrying his love of rhyme into the drama. &amp; I
                    suspect (if they venture to say so) preferring Racine<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean Racine (1639&#8211;1699), French
                        playwright.</note> to Shakespeare. He probably means to enter a good deal into the bibliography of the Cid, for
                        <del>about</del> a few weeks ago I had a letter from him requesting me to collate my copy of the Romances del Cid with
                        his.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had written to Lord Holland on 6 October 1810, Letter 1812. Holland
                        published <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817), but
                        he did not complete a translation of any of the Spanish author&#8217;s plays.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I rejoice that you have an opportunity of giving this poor book a lift in the world,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In a letter of 29 October, Taylor mentioned that he planned to review the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        for the <title>Monthly Review</title>, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William
                            Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 295. The article, which drew attention to parallels with the
                        contemporary struggle for Iberian independence, appeared in <title>Monthly Review</title>, 64 (January 1811), 131&#8211;144.</note>
                    &amp; shall rejoice still more if you make it an opportunity of fighting the good fight for the Spaniards against that cowardly
                    &amp; calumnious spirit which the Edinburgh Review has been the principle means of diffusing. I have never for a moment despaired
                    of their cause, never had any other feeling than a full confidence in their final success, founded upon my knowledge of their
                    national character, as displayed in their whole history, &#8211; &amp; upon the strength of the moral nature of man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will receive Kehama<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> very shortly, &#8211; I have abstained from writing for the last six weeks in
                    expectation of telling you when to expect it. If it should not reach you in due time after it<del>s</del> is advertised, fail not
                    to let me know, that I may re-order it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Anti-Catholic opinions, would I was well aware, clash with your anti-church politics. I fear too that there are
                    some other points on which we do not thoroughly accord &#8211; but I am sure you are well pleased with the perfect freedom of this
                        Annal,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> &amp; its thorough consistency with the good old cause. I am
                    hard at work upon 1809. Indeed I am deeply concerned in this Register<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811).</note> &#8211; they pay me 400 &#163; a year for it, &amp; I have vested
                    209 &#163; of the first years payment in a twelfth share of the property, which will pay me 40 per cent. Thus I am at last well paid
                    for my labours. My books in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> hands may now be left to clear off arrears with
                    him, I have begun to discharge a debt contracted for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> to<ref target="people.html#MayJohn"> John May</ref>, &#8211; &amp; have a fair prospect, (life &amp; health permitting) of beginning in a
                    very few years to get above the world, &#8211; in the worldly meaning of the phrase.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a rod in pickle for <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> in the shape of a review of <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomerys</ref> poems,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Montgomery,
                            <title>The West Indies, and other Poems</title> (1810) and <title>The Wanderer in Switzerland, and other Poems</title>
                        (1811), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 405&#8211;419.</note> &amp; another for Sidney
                        Smith<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of and
                        leading contributors to the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. Southey&#8217;s strictures on Smith were included in his review of
                            <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title>
                        (1809), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514.</note> &amp; the Unitarian Barrister concerning the
                        Methodists.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on
                            the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4
                        (November 1810), 480&#8211;514. The author was James Sedgwick (1775&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), barrister and civil servant. Southey
                        was annoyed that many of his more cutting points were removed prior to publication; see Southey to Tom Southey, 5 December
                        1810, Letter 1836.</note> Of all the ignorant &amp; dishonest controversialists which I have ever met with, this Barrister is
                    the very worst. Such arguments against Methodism as he &amp; S Smith make use of, would persuade me into it, &#8211; if that were
                    possible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is in town, &amp; will probably visit Bury before he sets his face
                    Northward. If you talk to him about your theological theories you will find a man thoroughly versed in the subject, &#8211; bringing to
                    it all that can be brought from erudition &amp; meditation. I like Martin<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Martin
                        (1769&#8211;1850), formerly a Unitarian minister at Great Yarmouth, where Southey had met him in 1798, but by this time a Liverpool merchant, Secretary of the Royal Liverpool Institution and author of <title>Zetemata
                            dianoetika: or a View of the Intellectual Powers of Man</title> (1819), whom Taylor had proposed sending drafts of his
                        &#8216;original theory respecting the historic portion of the Gospels&#8217;, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 297.</note> but cannot think him as
                    deep as a well upon any subject. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Griffiths will remember that for ten years his Review has been my bitter &amp; even malicious enemy; &amp; how this
                    is to be got over I hardly know.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Edward Griffiths (1771/2&#8211;1828;
                        <title>DNB</title>), editor of the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 1803&#8211;1825. Taylor had asked to review the <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> for the <title>Monthly</title>, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 296. The review did not appear.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know nothing of the authorship in the second part of the Register.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810).</note> The criticism is indeed preciously absurd. I should as
                    soon think of being measured with Tom Thumb as &lt;with&gt; Thomas Campbell<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey,
                        Thomas Campbell (1777&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>) and Scott had been described as &#8216;the three most successful candidates for
                        poetical fame&#8217; in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 419.</note> &#8211; But as every dog will have his
                    day, so it seems may every puppy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> was with me last week. You are now almost the only <hi rend="ital">friend</hi>
                    whom I have never seen here. In the spring I go southward &amp; take <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> with me.
                    It is not impossible that we may visit <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, &amp; if so I shall find my way
                    once more to <ref target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>. Pray remember me to your Mother,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sarah Taylor, n&#233;e Wright (1735/1736&#8211;1812).</note> &#8211; the recollections of twelve years make me feel like an old
                    guest of the family &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent6"> R Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>