<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce591</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.582</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Brotherton Library, University of
                        Leeds .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        157-160; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        169-170 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="582" type="letter">
<head>582. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1801-05-23">23 May
                        1801</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>-/ Richmond/ Surry./ Single<lb/>Postmarks:
                        FOREIGN OFFICE/ JU 8/ 1801; [partial] 4o’Clock/ JU
                        8<lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 60/ 1801/
                        Robert Southey/ Lisbon 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> May/
                            rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        June/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        July<lb/>MS: Brotherton Library, University of
                        Leeds<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        157-160; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        169-170 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> A letter of mine, chiefly relating to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref>,
                    must assuredly have been lost. it matters little. at this
                    distance, all I could do was to express a full satisfaction
                    in what you &amp; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> have agreed.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">That <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry
                            Herbert Southey</ref> should train as a
                        doctor.</note> To <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> I
                    wrote some five or six weeks ago – recommending an unbiased
                    choice – rather wishing him to follow his <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncles</ref> plan,
                    than <del rend="strikethrough">recom</del> advising it. of
                    his private allowance – I could only promise him five pounds
                    quarterly – a sum which if good fortune enabled me I should
                    willingly double, but which you must be aware – knowing the
                    extent of my resources – to be the utmost that I can spare
                    from my own wants &amp; the demands upon me from other
                    quarters. some little – a possible ten pounds – may be
                    yearly hoped from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, who is ready to do all he can. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    will I know supply any deficiency. yet I think in
                    calculating from 30 to 40 pounds yearly as necessary,
                    circumstances have not been sufficiently considered. my own
                    personal expences have never reached even to the smaller
                    sum. I do not expend 15 pounds yearly in &lt;the whole of
                    my&gt; <hi rend="ital">dress</hi>. with all linen <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref>
                    would be supplied from home. it is however always better to
                    allow a young man too much than too little. I have felt the
                    latter evil myself. – The great expence of returning will
                    sink me for some time below the world. hitherto my resources
                    have always been kept equal with my expenditure, by obscure
                    &amp; unintermitted labour. from those means a residence
                    here has inevitably cut me off. my expences also have been
                    increased by travelling. I could indeed make my journeys
                    more than pay the&lt;ir&gt; own cost did I deem it advisable
                    to publish the materials which I have collected for a
                    miscellaneous volume relative to this country. from 60 to 80
                    pounds would doubtless be paid me for a first edition – but
                    from the time it would deduct from the greater work I should
                    think it a bad speculation in a pecuniary point of view –
                    &amp; in that point I must consider it. I have therefore no
                    literary pay to expect, (except from the success of Thalaba)
                    till a first volume of my History<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> be published – or ready for
                    publication. a labour for which one compleat year will be
                    little. meantime I can review – I can write rhymes to the
                    amount of 100£ – but this is improvident work – it is
                    spending the day in getting only enough for the dinner. Like
                    you good people in England I have corn enough in the ground
                    – but there is a famine till the harvest be ripe.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Portugueze news you know as regularly &amp;
                    correctly as it can be known. yet is M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Coppendale<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                        Coppendale (d. 1833), John May’s uncle and business
                        partner.</note> an infidel – incredulity saves him from
                    the fear-fever which infects everybody else. I believe at
                    all events – except a general peace speedily terminates the
                    calamities of Europe – that the port of Lisbon will be shut
                    against English vessels. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cyr<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Laurent de Gouvion
                        Saint-Cyr (1764-1830), French general.</note> is with
                    the Spaniards about Elvas – which is or will be
                        beseiged.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Spanish
                        forces had invaded Portugal on 20 May 1801 and besieged
                        the town of Elvas. It held out and did not
                        surrender.</note> we had a rumour of its capture which
                    is not believable. they are in great force &amp; have
                    refused to write any terms in the carte blanche which
                        Pinto<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Pinto
                        de Sousa Coutinho, Viscount of Balsemao (1735-1804),
                        Portuguese Secretary of State (prime minister)
                        1788-1801. He was dismissed on 6 January 1801, but
                        remained in the ministry as Foreign Secretary until 21
                        May 1801 and returned as Secretary of State in 1803. He
                        was the chief negotiator with Spain in the attempt to
                        prevent an invasion in 1801.</note> proffered. so far is
                    certain. When the moon shines upon the sea – the line of
                    moonlight always terminates in your own ship – so we view
                    all things chiefly with relation to self. I want <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to
                    England – &amp; verily &lt;believe&gt; him so rooted here
                    that he must be turned out or he never will move. for
                    ourselves – the sooner we are home the better. I am
                    enquiring for a vessel Bristol bound – if there be none we
                    shall return by Yescombe<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Bayntun Yescombe (1765-1803),
                        captain of the packet, <hi rend="ital">King George</hi>,
                        which sailed between Falmouth and Lisbon.</note> when
                    next he is here. but the difference of expence is to me of
                    heavy importance – it cannot be less than thirty guineas. We
                    have now lost most of our hill acquaintance – in <ref target="people.html#SetonBarbara">Miss Seton</ref>
                    particularly we have a daily &amp; hourly loss. Tis like the
                    end of the Pilgrims Progress<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bunyan (1621-1688;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Pilgrim’s
                            Progress</title> (1678).</note> – one by one our
                    friends go before us &amp; leave us at the side of the Great
                    Water that we all must cross!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am no ways weary of Portugal. it would be
                    the country of my choice residence certainly – its climate
                    so entirely suits me – &amp; its materials now afford me
                    such ample employment that I could beguile a more total
                    solitude than that in which we live. It is almost a solitude
                    – &amp; I look with a hunger &amp; thirst for the free &amp;
                    intimate society of my English friends – of those who can
                    look back with the same recollections – observe the present
                    with the same feelings, &amp; look on to futurity with the
                    same hopes.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My history<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> advances well. I have stewed down many
                    a folio into essential sauce. half the labour of a first
                    volume is done – that is the timbers are ready &amp; the
                    stones hewn tho little of the edifice appears above ground.
                    to the end of Fernandos<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernando I (1345-1383, King of Portugal
                        1367-1383).</note> reign the first sketch is done – the
                    second draught to that of Diniz<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Diniz (1261-1325, King of Portugal
                        1279-1325).</note> – the third &amp; decent copy is now
                    finishing the second Sancho.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sancho II (c. 1209-1248, King of Portugal
                        1223-1248).</note> my guides have been Faria<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel de Faria e Sousa
                        (1590-1649), <title>Epitome de las Historias
                            Portuguezas</title> (1628), no. 3743 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – Duarte
                        Galvao<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Duarte
                        Galvao (1446-1517) and Ruy de Pina (c. 1440-c. 1521),
                            <title>Chronica del D. Affonso Henriques Primero, D.
                            Sancho, I &amp; II, D. Affonso II &amp; III, e Dom
                            Diniz, Sexto Rey de Portugal</title> (1727-1729),
                        no. 3352 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> &amp; Ruy de Pina – Duarte Nunes.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Duarte Nunes de Liao
                        (d. 1608), <title>Chronica dos Reis de Portugal</title>
                        (1774), no. 3261 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> Mariana<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan de Mariana (1537-1624),
                            <title>Historia General de Espana</title> (1623),
                        no. 3580 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> – the Rainhas of Barbosa<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo Barbosa Machado
                        (1682-1772), <title>Catalogo Cronologico, Historico e
                            Genealogico e Critico das Rainhas de
                            Portugal</title> (1727), no. 3233 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – Zurita<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeronimo Zurita
                        (1512-1580), <title>Anales de la Corona de
                            Aragon</title> (1585-1610), no. 3811 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – step by step.
                    the Provas of the Genealogical History<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Caetano de Sousa
                        (1674-1759), <title>Historia Genealogica da Casa Real
                            Portugueza</title> (1735-1748), no. 3738 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library. The ‘Provas’ were
                        printed documents, published with the indices in six
                        volumes, 1739-1748.</note> have been indispensably
                    useful. the Monarquia Lusitana<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernardo de Brito (1569-1617),
                            <title>Monarquia Lusitano</title> (1690), no. 3320
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. The work was
                        continued by Antonio Brandao (1584-1637) and
                        others.</note> I have not yet been able to procure,
                    &amp; indeed the books already named, with the number of
                    others collaterally consulted were enough to carry on at
                    first.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I do not ask you to write –
                    there will I trust be no time to hear from you. – When three
                    months are elapsed from the time when you sent <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> the
                    ten pounds – have the goodness to send him five. I will do
                    all I can to prevent him from feeling any inconvenience for
                    money – even any unpleasant feeling – but these are my worst
                    times – I live at more cost here than at home – &amp; have
                    running expences in England also. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                    will I hope do well. he promises well.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> – We have yet no accounts of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> here tho two
                    packets have arrived since that that brought his name in the
                    list of the wounded.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">A British fleet had destroyed the Danish fleet at
                        Copenhagen on 2 April 1801. Tom Southey was a Lieutenant
                        on the <hi rend="ital">Beltona</hi> in this action and
                        listed as wounded, e.g. in <title>Bell’s Weekly
                            Messenger</title>, 19 April 1801.</note>
</p>
<lb/>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<lb/>
<postscript>
<p>Lisbon <date when="1801-05-23"> 23 May. 1801.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
