<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce402</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.393</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National
                        Library of Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 182–183.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="393" type="letter">
<head>393. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1799-03-30">30 March
                        1799</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W W Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M P –/ Chester
                        Circuit<lb/>Postmarks: BRISTOL/ MAR 30 99; AP/ 2/
                        99<lb/>Endorsement: March 30/ 99<lb/>MS: National
                        Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb/>Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 182–183.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> That a direct tax upon Income<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The budget of December 1798
                        had introduced income tax for the first time. It was
                        paid on a sliding scale on incomes from £60pa to £200pa
                        and at 10% on incomes over £200pa.</note> is the best
                    possible mode of taxation has long appeared to me probable.
                    in the present bill however I see great injustice &amp;
                    great absurdity. for instance − is it not absurd to make the
                    man with 185 £ a year pay <hi rend="ital">more than one
                        pound</hi> a year more than him who has 184? cast your
                    eye upon the latter part of the scale &amp; you will see the
                    same blunder at every jump. upon this scale 201 £ make a
                    less neat income than 199. are not these schoolboy blunders?
                    you talk of the deduction for children − it is too little –
                    the man who has 60 £ a year &amp; one child − is allowed
                    sixpence a year for it. the tax certainly falls very heavy
                    upon the rich, but the progression ceased too soon. ten per
                    cent is too much to take from 200. it is acting upon the
                    metaphor of Bishop Watson,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Watson (1737–1816;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Llandaff, <title>An
                            Address to the People of Great Britain</title>
                        (London, 1798), p. 4.</note> &lt;of&gt; which, I have
                    not charity enough to believe he could not himself see the
                    absurdity. you remember <ref target="people.html#WakefieldGilbert">Wakefields</ref>
                    reply – all parts of the building may sink together – &amp;
                    the gentlemen up stairs still have their comfortable
                    prospect – but where is the ground floor sunk to?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Gilbert Wakefield, <title>A
                            Reply to Some Parts of the Bishop of Landaff’s
                            Address to the People of Great Britain</title>
                        (London, 1798), p. 16.</note> – another fault is, a man
                    is allowed a deduction for children – good. suppose he has
                    ten for instance, he avoids half the tax. the father dies –
                    the brother has to maintain the nine children – &amp; he is
                    allowed nothing while they live in the house with him. is it
                    equitable to take the same proportion from one who supports
                    a housefull of relations – &amp; from a single unencumbered
                    person? these things strike me as strange oversights in the
                    framers of the bill, but all remediable.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The commercial objections to it are less
                    easily removed. in the country it must happen that many a
                    man has for his commissioner his principal creditor. every
                    body knows how much business depends upon credit. where is
                    the use of secresy in this case? the consequence is that to
                    keep up credit – they over-rate their income. the revenue
                    indeed profits by this – but it is grievous upon the
                    individual.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Direct taxation was one of Turgots<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The French economist and
                        statesman Anne-Robert-Jacques Turgot, Baron de Laune
                        (1727–1781).</note> favourite schemes. it is open &amp;
                    fair &amp; I should be glad to see all taxes commuted for
                    it. they should not however make people sign a lie that they
                    are <hi rend="ital">willing</hi> to pay the money to help
                    prosecute the war, in the next Dictionary the parliamentary
                    meaning must be affixed to the word.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I shall be in town as late as possible in the
                    term – on May day I believe, &amp; shall stay over the
                    vacation to keep the next. I expect to pass the greater part
                    of the time at Cambridge.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I was sorry to hear a bad account of the
                    Ancient Britons in Ireland<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Watkin Williams Wynn (1772–1840),
                        Wynn’s elder brother, had raised a home defence force in
                        North East Wales, the Ancient British Fencible Cavalry,
                        in 1794. The regiment served in Ireland in 1797–8 and
                        gained an unsavoury reputation for its role in
                        suppressing dissent and preparations for revolution. It
                        also took part in several battles against the Wexford
                        uprising in June 1798.</note> – from an Irishman, a
                    moderate man – a Unionist – &amp; one whom I could not but
                    credit. he did not say they had been bit by any of his
                    countrymen – &amp; yet accused them of all Irish enormities.
                    perhaps it is the soil of the country or the climate that is
                    in fault.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Pneumatic Institution<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pneumatic Institute,
                        Dowry Square, Bristol, founded by Thomas Beddoes.</note>
                    is just opened here. I am acquainted with <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">the young man</ref> who
                    manages it, &amp; just know chemistry enough to comprehend
                    his discoveries &amp; glimpse their consequences. he
                    possesses the most miraculous talents I ever met with or
                    heard of, &amp; will I think do more for medicine than any
                    person who has ever gone before him.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I long to see North Wales &amp; to become
                    familiar with its scenery. the first sketch of Madoc, for I
                    look upon as not much more, draws to its conclusion – &amp;
                    I may perhaps have the whole outline to show you in May. in
                    the first books I have spoken of Snowden &amp; Cader Idris –
                    &amp; that is all. careless &amp; hasty as I am thought in
                    my writings I would willingly go to Orleans to enable myself
                    to describe its situation – &amp; take the journey from
                    Aberffraw to Mathrafal – thence to Dinevor &amp; back to
                    Aberffraw for the same purpose.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I wish these March winds were over. by day I
                    feel nothing – a general relaxation – but at night every
                    sound startles me. it has hung on me a long while &amp; God
                    knows when I shall shake it off. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1799-03-30">Saturday. March 30. 99.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
