<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce497</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.488</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Bristol Reference Library, B20959.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 94–97 [in part]; Adolfo
                        Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                            1800-1801 and a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 62–64
                        [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="488" type="letter">
<head>488. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1800-02-09">9 February 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond Green/ Surry./ Single<lb/>Postmarks:
                        BRISTOL/ FEB 9 1800; 10 o Clock/ FE. 10/ 1800; B/ FEB 10/
                        1800<lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 48 1800/ Robert Southey/
                        Kingsdown 9. Feb/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 10 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/
                            ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 13 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
<lb/>MS: Bristol Reference Library, B20959<lb/>Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 94–97 [in part]; Adolfo
                        Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                            1800-1801 and a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 62–64
                        [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> It is so long since I have heard from you that I feel a degree of
                    uneasiness at your silence. but one great benefit of marriage is that it never
                    allows those intervals of vacancy which must occur in the best directed
                    solitude, &amp; which probably create the epistolary mania in very young
                    persons. this was my own case once. I wrote not from a fullness of matter to
                    communicate but from sheer emptiness – day after day – fools-cap sheets &amp;
                    close writing for three pages &amp; the top &amp; bottom of the fourth. more
                    knowledge &amp; the daily increasing consciousness of how much yet remains to be
                    learnt. more employments &amp; marriage have long since cured me. My pleasure
                    now consists in receiving letters, not in writing them. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> The state of my health is in some respects amended, in others
                    stationary. I had accustomed myself to low living, seldom eating except at
                    breakfast &amp; dinner &amp; then with an appetite no ways like my Portugal one;
                    &amp; when at home drinking only water. Since my removal here I have increased
                    the number of my meals, taken porter with my meat, &amp; wine after it.
                    certainly I feel stronger, – but the startings &amp; miserable feelings which
                    have so long distressed me at night still continued &amp; were only lessened by
                    ether, not removed. About a fortnight ago I breathed the oxyd of azote<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Nitrous oxide, or ‘laughing gas’.</note> –
                    the air whose strange effects you must have seen some account of in the
                        Reviews.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Beddoes’s and Davy’s
                        experiments with nitrous oxide and other gases were publicised in Thomas
                        Beddoes, <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the Medical Pneumatic
                            Institution</title> (1799) and Humphry Davy, <title>Researches, Chemical
                            and Philosophical, Chiefly Concerning Nitrous Oxide, or Dephlogisticated
                            Nitrous Air, and Its Respiration</title> (1800). Widely reviewed, these
                        accounts were also parodied in ‘The Pneumatic Revellers, An Eclogue’,
                            <title>Anti-Jacobin Review</title>, 6 (May 1800), 109–118.</note> I had
                    been fearful of it since my return to Bristol – but on making the experiment,
                    was surprized by its beneficial influence. I slept without <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> the disease which for months before had
                    invariably preceded sleep. after several nights it recurred again. I repeated
                    the dose. &amp; have taken it about once in three days since, &amp; the
                    complaint has been till now removed. to say the gas has been the cause would be
                    hasty – but I cannot help thinking so. The pain in my side still continues – its
                    intermittance seems to prove that there is no organic affection, &amp; this is
                    the opinion of all my medical friends. the spring is advancing – &amp; I hope
                    something from warmer &amp; less inconstant weather. certainly I will avoid the
                    next winter. the experience of two has satisfied me of the ill effect of that
                    season on my health. I have written to Lisbon, <del rend="strikethrough">xx
                        x</del> &amp; stated to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> my reason for thinking of removing somewhere abroad, &amp; the
                    sum I can raise for the consequent expence. my reasons also for not determining
                    immediately upon Lisbon, at the same time stating that if he thought that more
                    advisable, all circumstances considered, I would adopt that plan, &amp; employ
                    my time there by seriously beginning the History of the country.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s never-completed ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> a work which I could compleat in England, but for which
                    the materials &amp; the necessary topographical knowledge must be sought in
                    Portugal. his answer will <del rend="strikethrough">probably</del> determine me.
                    On the whole I am inclined to wish that his advice may favour this plan.
                    Occasional excursions of a fortnight or three weeks would afford novelty enough,
                    &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">enable</del> &lt;make&gt; me well acquainted
                    with the whole of the country. I know the language well enough to travel without
                    embarrassment, &amp; the subject of my studies would supply a constant interest
                    of employment. Less than two quarto volumes could not comprize the work. I
                    should suppose not less than three for the great Indian Episode would require
                    one to itself. the pecuniary profit of such a work might be estimated at not
                    much less than a thousand pounds. Gibbons six quartos<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737–1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Decline
                            and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776–1788).</note> acquired him
                    eight thousand. here is a great plan – &amp; the <del rend="strikethrough">ske</del> embryo skeletons of chapters on the religion &amp; manners &amp;
                    literature of the country are now [MS torn]ng before &lt;me.&gt; &amp; one half
                    filld sheet of paper by the next packet may [MS torn] them all!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I wait here for this letter to regulate by it my movements.
                    either to lose no time in getting into Germany that I may reach Trieste by
                    autumn; or to return to <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>, <del rend="strikethrough">which will not be</del> &amp; wait there a fit time for
                    my departure to Falmouth. in either case I shall see you – either when I visit
                    London, or when you visit Hampshire.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> In the course of a very few weeks I shall have the second
                        Anthology<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1800).</note> to send you. numerous contributions
                    have arrived, &amp; I shall not have written a single line myself with an
                    immediate view to the volume. [MS torn] Thalaba eight books are finished.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Will you exert yourself to assist the Chatterton
                        subscription?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Cottle’s
                            <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803).</note> I am
                    setting all my friends to work in this way, &amp; a little trouble will render
                    the sister &amp; her daughter<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Newton
                        (1749–1804) and her daughter.</note> comfortable for life. the volumes will
                    be fairly priced at 16 shillings. we have 177 names on our list, chiefly Bristol
                    &amp; Cumberland <del rend="strikethrough">nam</del> subscriptions. from
                    Hampshire I expect 20 or 30 more, a greater number from Norfolk. &amp; in London
                    I suppose the great subscription will be. the sale of 750 copies would produce
                        <del rend="strikethrough">about</del> between four &amp; five hundred
                    pounds. &amp;, the circumstances considered, this will be a smaller subscription
                    than ought to have been expected.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be remembered.
                        God bless you.</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown</ref>. Bristol.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1800-02-09">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 9. 1800.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
