<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce490</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.481</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="481" type="letter">
<head>481. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1800-01-27">[started before and continued
                        on] 27 January 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        To/ Lieutenant Thomas Southey./ Bellona./ Plymouth./
                        Single <lb/>Postmark: [partial] BRISTOL/ JAN/
                        1800<lb/>Endorsement: [date written in another hand at
                        beginning of letter]<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> A lucky sheet of paper which has been folded
                    up in my pocket-book since July last gives me the power of
                    writing to you – when otherwise lack of paper &amp; Sunday
                    must have delayed me. I am better than before I left
                    Hampshire, not so well as I since have been, &amp; my
                    determination is made to remove to a better climate – but
                    when or where I have not settled.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I met an acquaintance of yours here lately.
                        D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blake<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Malachi Blake (1771–1843), doctor and
                        prominent Unitarian in Taunton. He founded Taunton and
                        Somerset Hospital in 1809.</note> of Taunton who civilly
                    invited me there when I might happen to journey that way. he
                    is an old pupil of <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin</ref>
<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> – at
                    whose table I met him. Another Tauntoneer whom I have seen
                    is I believe unknown to you – D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Kinglake<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert
                        Kinglake (1765–1842; <title>DNB</title>), expert on
                        gout. His brother was William Kinglake (d. 1852), banker
                        and solicitor.</note> – Kinglakes brother. a man of
                    uncommon talents – indeed one of the ablest &amp; most
                    respectable whom I have ever met with. I have seen a good
                    deal of him.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your removal to the Bellona<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> was a 74-gun ship of the line, so more
                        likely to be used in engaging the French fleet and less
                        likely to pick up lucrative prizes than the smaller <hi rend="ital">Sylph</hi> on which Tom Southey had been
                        serving.</note> is I suppose more a matter of condolence
                    than of congratulation. no knocks – no money, – &amp; there
                    is little chance of a sea engagement. France is under able
                    rule, &amp; her expeditions will be well plannd &amp; her
                    exertions rightly directed. It is in Germany that the peace
                    will be made, by the cooperation of Prussia<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Germany was likely to be a
                        key area of conflict between France and Austria in 1800,
                        but Prussia had not joined the Second Coalition formed
                        against France in 1799 and was neutral.</note> – the
                    only government in Europe that acts wisely &amp;
                    respectably.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of late I have done little. Thalaba advances
                    – towards the end of the eighth book – but it must reach to
                    twelve – two more than my first plan.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey stuck to his revised
                        plan, and the Islamic romance <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) was composed of 12
                        books.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I know not wherefore you amuse yourself by
                    abusing <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> – if
                    on <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> account of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mothers</ref>
                    health – she never was better anywhere. it is only at Bath
                    &amp; Bristol that she suffers. if because <hi rend="ital">you</hi> do not like the country, we who live there do.
                    if the house be not fine enough – it is lucky that we are
                    contented with what we can afford. you damn <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> &amp; rejoice
                    that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                        Mother</ref> is at Bristol. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has
                    seen her at Bristol, &amp; can confirm what I tell you, that
                    at Bristol she is never well &amp; never happy. at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> she was well
                    &amp; chearful. here she is the slave of <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">her sisters</ref>
                    humours, &amp; lookd upon by her sisters friends as a sort
                    of dependant relation, whom they speak to if she opens the
                    door to them – not if they meet her in the street. believe
                    me the day on which she returns to <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>, will be a
                    happier one than she has known since she left it.</p>
<p>
<date when="1800-01-27">Monday</date>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The second volume of the Anthology<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1800).</note> is half done – you
                    have never yet received the first I believe – I carried it
                    all round Torbay in my knapsack in the hope of meeting with
                    you.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is
                    coming to pass a month at Bristol – chiefly on my account.
                    he often enquires for you. few men stand higher in my
                    judgement than <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                        Rickman</ref>. there will be much to interest him here
                    in the Pneumatic Institution,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pneumatic Institute, Dowry Square,
                        Bristol.</note> &amp; the conversation of <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref>. he has some
                    boat-improving plans <del rend="strikethrough">which</del>
                    upon which he wishes for an opportunity of talking with you.
                        <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>
                    head with all his apparent idleness is never unemployed.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> is
                    publishing his Alfred by subscription.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle,
                            <title>Alfred, An Epic Poem, in Twenty Four
                            Books</title> (1800) was not published by
                        subscription.</note> I could not offer to subscribe
                    myself because I knew he would of course give me a copy –
                    but by way of doing the same thing I subscribed in your
                    name. so by &amp; by, you must not scruple paying carriage
                    for a bulky quarto.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have in agitation some prose works. writing
                    for the paper<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                        had stopped writing regular poems for the <title>Morning
                            Post</title> in December 1799; see Robert Southey to
                        Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 15 December 1799, Letter
                        462.</note> I have given up from inability to bear the
                    irksomeness of periodical idea-hunting. a connected work
                    will not harrass me in this way – &amp; something I must do.
                    it is possible that before we return to <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> I may visit
                    London to make bargains with the booksellers – if indeed my
                    journey be delayed till the autumn.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is
                    much grown &amp; much improved. good company &amp;
                    instruction have not been wasted upon him. he will in the
                    course of another year be requiring an expence of education
                    which I am afraid we shall not find it easy to defray. I
                    shall not however fail to make my best exertions. if I can
                    get footing in the theatres the profits will be great.
                    travel where I will, the journal will pay [MS torn]
                    journey.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Direct <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown
                        Parade</ref>. Bristol. – I am so miserably tense with
                    wind – that government ought to engage me in the fleet – as
                    I could at any time give them a gale. my tripes are now
                    perfectly hurricanized. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>
                        love. God bless you.</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1800-01-27">Monday 27. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1800. </date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
