<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce532</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.523</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 65–68 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="523" type="letter">
<head>523. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1800-05-08">8–9 May 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: [in another hand] To/ Lieutenant
                        Thomas Southey./ HMS. Bellona./ Plymouth Dock./ or elsewhere./
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: LISBON<lb/>Endorsement: 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
<lb/>MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 65–68 [in part].</note>
</head>
<p> Lisbon. <date when="1800-05-08"> Thursday. May 8. 1800.</date>
</p>
<p>[Southey inserts a floor-plan of his residence in Lisbon]</p>
<p>This Tom is the plan of our house, the ground floor which belongs wholly to the
                    servants, is exactly the same, &amp; this is the plan of Portugueze building. 1
                    &amp; 5 are the bed rooms – for seperate beds are necessary in this climate. by
                    removing the folding doors 2 &amp; 3 are made into one room, in length 18 of <hi rend="ital">my</hi> feet, in breadth 6½ only. In the great room we dine
                    &amp; receive company. the house was built for two families &amp; there is a
                    kitchen on each floor. 1 was designed to serve that purpose &amp; the fire place
                    is marked in it. but it is a Portugueze fire&lt;place&gt; the hearth stone, 3
                    feet from the ground, so that the cook may stand at his work – for they know not
                    the use of grates: an earthern pan furnishes a Portugueze kitchen. in this they
                    stew every thing, or fry it in oil. Now for the ornamental part. our great room
                    has four doors, two windows &amp; two balconies. the walls are simply white
                    limed. do not however suspect us of too plain an appearance. around the top
                    &amp; the middle of the walls runs a broad board painted like marble veined with
                    blue. Each door<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> has a pilaster &lt;wood&gt;
                    framing of green veined marble, with the base streaked red. purple marbled tiles
                    go round the bottom. the cieling<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> is a floor of
                    wood, painted white &amp; edged with flesh colour. the windowshutters &amp;
                    balcony doors are green. the other doors have yellow pannels in mahogany
                    coloured frames. &lt;the window frames mahogany coloured&gt; our carpet is a
                    zigzag [Southey inserts sketch of the pattern] thunder &amp; lightning pattern
                    of all the rainbow colours. the balconies have also glass doors. the huge stone
                    which forms the standing place is rough as the paving by Northumberland house in
                    the Strand, &amp; enters some foot into the room, a notch is cut across it &amp;
                    a hole made thro, so that this serves as a sink to carry away what rain enters.
                    The locks &amp; latches are coarse beyond your conception. under every window
                    frame &lt;&amp; round it&gt; is a stone three inches broad, its surface rough
                    from the stone cutters chissel. the window frames are fastened with screws
                    broader than a halfcrown on their leads. the glass in every window is floored
                    with bricks.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The garret is one room over all so propped up with crooked sticks
                    that it would be difficult to lay a bed either length-breadth or athwart-ways.
                    this propping is a fine specimen of Portuguese building. the ends of the poles
                    are let into rude holes cut in the floor – &amp; some that were not long enough
                    for this, nor smooth enough to rest upon the ground, have another uncouth stick
                    stuck under them – as we steady a table in England on an uneven floor. there are
                    pigeon holes to admit light &amp; air like a church <del rend="strikethrough">tower</del> &lt;tower&gt; – windows no bigger than church-pigeon holes –
                    &amp; three large windows thus [Southey inserts illustration] so contrived that
                    if you open the shutters of the middle one, one of the sides must remain shut,
                    &amp; if you open the sides you fasten the middle. The roofing is like all other
                    houses here – the tiles are shaped thus [Southey inserts U shaped sketch], they
                    therefore lay on one row in that direction [Southey inserts illustration] –
                    &amp; then lest the rain should enter, cover it with a row reversed, [Southey
                    inserts illustration]. thus doubly loading the roof. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> The bedsteads instead of sacking have planks – a better thing as
                    it does not harbour vermin. the woods here are exceedingly beautiful, they come
                    from Brazil &amp; are many of them handsomer than mahogany. &lt;sets of
                    specimens are often sold made like little books, &amp; lettered each with its
                    name.&gt; The Portugueze perfume their houses by burning sugar or lavender –
                        <del rend="strikethrough">you frxx</del> a whiff of this incense often
                    surprizes me in the middle of a stink as I walk the streets.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The English when strangers here are so suspicious of the natives
                    as to be very rash in misinterpreting them. A young man whom I knew, fired at
                    the watch one night, when they accosted him. the ball passed thro the watchmans
                    hat. he was seized &amp; confined, &amp; it required interest &amp; money to
                    excuse him, for what was inexcusable. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> walking one night with a midshipman was stopt by persons
                    bearing a young man who had been run thro the body by a Lieutenant. they had
                    stopt him seeing his companions uniform, but knowing <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> suffered him to pass,
                    after telling the circumstance. The Lieutenant was drunk. the young man was a
                    gentleman who seeing him staggering about the streets, took him by the arm to
                    lead him home. the Englishman did not understand what he said, &amp; run him
                    thro.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> As yet we have not <del rend="strikethrough">done</del> received
                    all our visits of ceremony. we are going the first night we are at liberty, to
                    the Portugueze play. The court have shown a strange caprice about the opera.
                    they permitted them to have a few female singers, &amp; the proprietors of the
                    opera sent to Italy for more &amp; better ones. they came – no! they would not
                    license any more – the present <del rend="strikethrough">people</del> women
                    might act – but not the new comers. you must not expect me to give you any
                    reason for this inconsistency – tis the sheer whim of authority. but an odd
                    reason was assigned for permitting two who still act. one – because she is very
                    religious. The other <del rend="strikethrough">We x xx</del> because she is
                    Portugueze &amp; of a certain age.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> On Sunday a princess was christened.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Maria Francisca de Assis (1800–1834), fourth child
                        of John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826).</note> in the evening
                    the guns fired – a signal for all persons to illuminate. it was a pleasing sight
                    from our window, the town all starred – &amp; the moving lights of the shipping.
                    at ten a second discharge gave notice that we might put out our candles. But the
                    river seen by moonlight from hence is a far finer spectacle than art can make.
                    it lies like a plain of light under the heaven – the trees &amp; houses, now
                    forming a dark &amp; distinct foreground, &amp; now undistinguishable in shades,
                    as the moon moves on her way &lt;Almada stretching its black isthmus into the
                    waters, that shine like midnight snow.&gt;. we [MS torn] enough when it blows,
                    to see the rush of foam behind the boats. – A magnificent equipage passed our
                    window on Monday. it was a nobleman, either going to be married, or to court.
                    [MS obscured] carriage was drawn by four horses, each covered with a white
                    netting &amp; crested with white plumes. they were very restive – indeed but
                    half broke in. I had seen them breaking them in before, &amp; on these occasions
                    they always fill the carriage with servants to make it heavy – so that their
                    necks also run a chance of being broken in. it was like the pomp of romance. –
                    They bury in covered buildings that adjoin the church. the graves are built in
                    divisions – like a tanners pits. you may perhaps remember such at Bristol, at
                        S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">St
                        Pauls Church, Portland Square, Bristol; constructed between 1789 and
                        1794.</note> which I saw building. quick lime is thrown in with every body
                    which of course is soon consumed. still the bones accumulate, &amp; occasionally
                    these places are cleaned out. burying is every where miserably managed. that
                    superstition should once induce the desire to be interred in consecrated ground
                    was natural. the Church being Gods fort, the Devil would not come immediately
                    under its <hi rend="ital">bell</hi>-guns, the sound of a church bell being more
                    formidable to Beelzebub than cannon-balls to sailors. but now, when that folly
                    is extinct, that the dead should all be huddled together in <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> nar[MS obscured] places, of which all the
                    soil is human matter, where they must taint the a[MS obscured] must be disturbed
                    – in all probability are half rotten – this is a beastly adherence to custom
                    which disgraces an enlightened country. – They have a singular mode of fishing
                    at Costa, a sort of wigwam village in the sands south of the bar. the gang of
                    fishermen to each net is about fifty all paid &amp; fed by the Captain
                    regularly, not according to their success. half hold one end of a rope – the
                    other is carried off in the boat. the rope is about half a mile in leng[MS
                    obscured by binding] the net in the middle. a high surf breaks on the shore. the
                    men there thrust off the boat, themselves breast deep &amp; stooping under every
                    wave that meets them. the others row round to shore, &amp; then they all haul
                    in. – this place is about nine miles only from Lisbon, yet criminals run away
                    there &amp; are safe. sometimes a Magistrate goes down, but they always know
                    that he is coming &amp; away to the woods for the day. it is common to go there
                    from town &amp; dine upon the sands. the people are civil &amp; inoffensive,
                    indeed generally so over Portugal except among the boatmen, who have enough
                    intercourse with foreigners to catch all their vices.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Lord Somerville<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                        Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>),
                        agriculturist and distant relative of Southey.</note> went by the last
                    packet. I did not see him – he would have called one evening but <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> knowing him pressed for
                    time beg[MS obscured by binding] him to waive the ceremony. I have been very
                    industrious &amp; continue so. rise early, &amp; never waste a minute – if I am
                    at home without visitors – from book to book – &amp; change is more relief than
                    idleness. the American Minister<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Loughton Smith (1758–1812), resident Minister of the USA in Lisbon
                        1798–1801.</note> called on me after supper on Tuesday. this was somewhat
                    familiar – &amp; I apprehend was meant as civility. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. God bless you.</p>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent1"> R.S.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1800-05-09">Friday. May 9. 1800.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
