<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce849</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.840</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        239-242 [in part; dated October 1803].Dating note:
                        Dated from internal evidence relating to Coleridge’s
                        return (15 September 1803) and the ascent of
                        Skiddaw.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="840" type="letter">
<head>840. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1803-09-18">[18 September
                        1803]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers./ 4. Orchard Street/ Bristol<lb/>Stamped:
                        [illegible]<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        239-242 [in part; dated October 1803].<lb/>Dating note:
                        Dated from internal evidence relating to Coleridge’s
                        return (15 September 1803) and the ascent of
                        Skiddaw.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="left">
<date when="1803-09-18">Sunday night.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I should more speedily have replied to your
                    enquiry about the receipt for preserving berberries – but
                    that in fact the receipt is so nothing at all that if
                        Betty<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Danvers’s
                        servant; her first name and dates are unknown.</note>
                    have proceeded according to the common analogy of the noble
                    art of preservation she cannot have failed. it is simply
                    boiling them with their own weight of sugar – The books
                    which you sent per coach have not yet arrived – in truth it
                    was the most William-Reid-sort of a thing<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Reid (dates
                        unknown), a Bristol insurance broker and acquaintance of
                        Southey’s; presumably a by-word for extravagance in
                        Southey’s circle.</note> you ever did to send a parcel
                    upon such a journey by coach. it will cost God knows
                    what.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Since my last I have taken very vigorous
                    exercise &amp; am the better for it. one morning round the
                    lake – a ten or twelve mile walk, only disagreable as being
                    solitary. yesterday with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> to the top of Skiddaw – the work of
                    four &amp; a half hours – that is there &amp; back but the
                    descent is mere play. up-hill a mans wind would fail him tho
                    his lungs were as capacious as a church organs, &amp; the
                    legs ache tho the calves were full grown bulls. the panorama
                    from the summit is very grand – not indeed equal to what I
                    had seen from Monchique<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Mountain in Portugal that Southey had
                        visited in April 1801.</note> neither in height nor in
                    its whole beauty, but in some certain features certainly of
                    unequalled interest, the Lake Keswick &amp; Basenthwaite
                    lying below us, &amp; seeming each to fill its vale, for the
                    shores are merged in the mountain &amp; quite lost as you
                    look down, whereas the water lying all in light is seen in
                    its full extent. The summit is covered with loose stones
                    split by the frosts &amp; thus gradually are they reduced to
                    a very rich soil &amp; washed <del>to the</del> down to the
                    glens, so that like old women Skiddaw must grow shorter. for
                    some little distance below, nothing but moss grows – for it
                    is bitter bleak there next door to heaven. – To day I have
                    been tracking the river Greeta, which instead of Great A
                    ought to have been called Great S. but its name hath a good
                    &amp; most apt meaning – the loud lamenter. it is a lovely
                    stream. I have often forded such among the mountains of
                    Algarve, &amp; lingered to look at them with <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> &lt;a&gt; hungry eye, if
                    I may so express myself <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>
                    with a feeling that it was the only time I was ever to
                    behold the scene before me, so beautiful. that feeling has
                    often risen in me when gazing upon the permanent things of
                    Nature which I was beholding but for a time. God knows I
                    often looked upon my poor child with the same melancholy, as
                    tho to impress more deeply in remembrance a face whose
                    beauties were certainly to change – &amp; perhaps to pass
                    away. – How glad shall I be<del>x</del> to shew you these
                    things &amp; to make you confess that if He who tempers the
                    wind to the shorn lamb, should brace me up to the climate –
                    this is the best place for my sojourn. We had indeed a
                    gloomy &amp; comfortless parting. your comfort had been more
                    deeply rooted up than mine – &amp; yet the axe cut deep at
                    mine.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> continues
                    as you would expect – silently &amp; deeply affected. I have
                    not yet been able to get her out of the house tho our
                    weather has been uncommonly fine – &amp; without exercise
                    the tonics which she takes under Doctor Southey will be of
                    little avail. last night indeed we<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> went to see a set of strollers play She Stoops
                    to Conquer.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver
                        Goldsmith (1728-1774; <title>DNB</title>), <title>She
                            Stoops to Conquer</title> (1773).</note> nothing
                    could be worse &amp; that you know was the mirth we desired
                    – but it made me melancholy to see such a set of wretches
                    collected together, one of them an old man I am sure little
                    short of fourscore lean &amp; lanthorn-jawed, &amp; so ripe
                    for the grave that his face was as striking a memento mori
                    as ever glared in gold letters under the skulls &amp; thigh
                    bones of a tomb-stone.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref>
                    grows up as miraculous a boy as ever K Pharoahs
                        daughter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Pharaoh’s daughter found the infant Moses and brought
                        him up as her son; see <title>Exodus</title> 2:
                        10.</note> found his namesake to be – I am perfectly
                    astonished at him &amp; his father has the same sentiment of
                    wonder, &amp; the same forefeeling that it is a prodigious
                    &amp; unnatural intellect – &amp; that he will not live to
                    be a man. there is more Danvers in the old womans saying –
                    he is too clever to live, than appears to a common observer.
                    diseases which ultimately destroy, in their early stages
                    quicken &amp; kindle the intellect like opium. it seems as
                    if Death looked out the most promising plants in this great
                    nursery to plant them in a better soil. – the Boys great
                    delight is to get <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his
                        father</ref> to talk metaphysics to him – few men
                    understand him so perfectly. &amp; then his own incidental
                    sayings are quite wonderful. the pity is, said he one day to
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his
                        father</ref>, who was expressing some wonder that he was
                    not so pleased as he expected with riding in a wheel barrow
                    – the pity is that <hi rend="ital">I’se</hi> always thinking
                    of my thoughts. – The Child’s imagination is equally
                    surprizing. he invents the wildest tales you ever heard – a
                    history of the Kings of England who are to be. how do you
                    know that this is to come to pass <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>
                    – why you know it must be something or it could not be in my
                    head – &amp; so because it had not been did <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref>
                    conclude it must be &amp; away he prophecies of his King
                    Thomas the third. then he has a tale of a monstrous beast
                    calld the Rabzezekallaton. whose skeleton is on the outside
                    of his flesh – &amp; he goes on with the oddest &amp; most
                    original inventions till he sometimes actually terrifies
                    himself &amp; says I’se afraid of my own thoughts. It may
                    seem like superstition but I have a feeling that such an
                    intellect can never reach maturity – the springs are of too
                    exquisite workmanship to last long.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will see by the inclosed bill of
                        Savarys<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Harris
                        and Savarys bank in Narrow Wine St, Bristol.</note> what
                    a foul trick I play in overlooking it – or rather mistaking
                    it for London paper. – I expect daily my account for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. as I
                    have this bill to send back the better way [MS obscured] be
                    as soon as that account comes to send you a draft for 20£ –
                    that will be better than having a London bill sent back to
                    me to exchange. – I miss my wine merchant, &amp; if there be
                    any vessels that go from Bristol to Whitehaven should be
                    very glad to pay water carriage for the sake of getting good
                    wine, for to me it is a very essential of life. Do enquire –
                    it would be quite worth while to have down six dozen – for I
                    pay dearer &amp; drink far worse. – God bless you I miss you
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> &amp;
                        Cupid<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Danvers’s
                        dog.</note> &amp; my Books, &amp; sometimes James<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac James (b. 1759)
                        was the son of Samuel James (1716-1773), Baptist
                        minister at Hitchin. He came to Bristol in 1773 as a
                        student at the Baptist Academy. He kept a shop as a
                        bookseller, teadealer (and sometimes undertaker) first
                        in North Street and then in Wine Street. He was a member
                        of the Baptist meeting at Broadmead and served as
                        classical tutor at the Baptist Academy in Bristol from
                        1796 to 1825. During the late 1790s and early 1800s,
                        James collaborated with Joseph Cottle in selling
                        numerous works, mostly by dissenters. Among James’s own
                        works were <title>Providence Displayed: or, The
                            Remarkable Adventures of Alexander Selkirk</title>
                        (1800). He also tried his hand at poetry, including
                            <title>The Pilgrim’s Progress. The First Part:
                            Rendered into Familiar Verse</title> (1815), as well
                        as a polemical work, <title>An Essay on the Sign of the
                            Prophet Jonah</title> (1802). An associate of the
                        members of the Baptist Missionary Society Committee,
                        James was well placed to supply the <title>Periodical
                            Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> (1800-1817). These were published as
                        a periodical beginning in 1793, but then as bound
                        volumes beginning in 1800. Southey reviewed
                            <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title> (1800-1801), in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803),
                        207-218.</note> the Bookseller. Would to God that was
                    all that I missed! but that Gods will is best has been at
                    all times present to my heart &amp; reason.</p>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent1"> R S.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
