<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce328</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.319</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 165–166.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="319" type="letter">
<head>319. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1798-05-27">[27–]28 May
                        1798</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ G.
                        C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ London/ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        YARMOUTH<lb/>Postmark: E/ MA/ 29/ 98<lb/>Endorsement: 28 May 1798<lb/>MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 165–166.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1798-05-27">Sunday.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Well Grosvenor – &amp; how is it? am I to congratulate or to
                    console? there is fortunately so much to be said on either alternative, that
                    were a man to write a declamation he might toss up to determine on which side he
                    should declaim. however Grosvenor God prosper you in this &amp; every other wish
                    of your heart. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> You have expected to hear from me before this - I have visited
                    little – walked little – in fact have scarcely done anything but talk to <del rend="strikethrough">B</del>
<ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge"> George Burnett</ref> – now laid up in
                    the lying in chair with a venerable sciatica – &amp; written letters – aye
                    Grosvenor but they were to my wife, &amp; so you will not complain. I bathed
                    once, but it gave for some seconds such acute pain all round my loins or veins
                    that I feel half discouraged from incurring the risk of such another morsus
                        diaboli.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as
                        ‘devil’s bite’.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Time however has past tolerably well here – &amp; if there had
                    not &lt;been&gt; a magnetic point fixed elsewhere perpetually attracting my
                    wishes, I should have said very happily, in the first place I have no law books
                    here. God be praised there is not one in <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> library, in the next I had two days conversation with <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, a man whose whole
                    character &amp; conduct has very much interested me. I go to visit him on
                    Wednesday &amp; remain till the Tuesday following – so directez vous to me at
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Taylors. Surrey Street. Norwich. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> This morning I have been clearing off my epistolary debts – tis
                    now half past twelve – we dine at half past one – &amp; I have previously to
                    pulchrify. –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> these occupations however would not however have made me halt in
                    my letter till Monday morning, had not two flaming young Ladies<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> entered, the one of whom is
                    laying close siege to the citadel of <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">the
                        Bishops</ref> affections, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">bom</del>
                    attacking his heart thro his palate bombards him during his confinement with
                    blamonge (you may spell the word better if you can.) She has desired him to
                    preach upon this text – it is not good for man to be alone.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Genesis</title> 2: 18.</note> the folly
                    &amp; pertness &amp; forwardness that would have disgusted if given in &lt;a&gt;
                    large dose, amused me for half an hour. I was disposed to Democratize &amp; so
                    laughed with them &amp; at them.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am now in almost momently expectation of the vehicle in which I
                    leave <ref target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref>. I could write you a
                    good traveller like letter &amp; describe to you the particularities of the
                    place, as how the cows have no horns (by the by a great improvement –) &amp; of
                    the <ref target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref> arch-architecture, which
                    consists in forming it of two whale jaw bones; the triumphal arch of a Greenland
                    trader. &amp; I could write you a descriptive letter, for however unpromising
                        <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> the first view of a flat country may be,
                    it has yet its peculiar &amp; characteristic beauties. I am not disposed to
                    repeat what I have said elsewhere – &amp; what is but uninteresting in prose. As
                    for the society here, it was a remark of <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">Mary Wollstonecraft</ref> that the
                    inhabitants of a sea port were less cultivated than the inland dwellers, &amp;
                        <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> like most of that Womans remarks it was a
                    wise &amp; a true one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of
                        sentiments in Mary Wollstonecraft, <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in
                            Sweden, Norway, and Denmark</title> (London, 1796), esp. pp.
                        134–138.</note> they send their boys to sea – ergo their young men being
                    amphibious, rise but little above other animals of that genus. sedition there is
                    in plenty in the circle to which I have been introduced. I have found also two
                    very interesting young men, <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref> &amp; a cidevant Unitarian minister, now a Theist, by name
                    Martin, a man of gentle manners &amp; unassuming ability.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Martin (dates unknown) had resigned from
                        his post in 1797 due to a theological dispute with some of his congregation;
                        see <title>A Letter to the Society of Protestant Dissenters, at the Old
                            Meeting, Yarmouth, from Thomas Martin, On His Resignation of the Office
                            of Minister Among Them</title> (1797). His replacement was <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref>.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Grosvenor God bless you, write to me &amp; believe here as every
                    where &amp; now as always</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1798-05-28">Monday 28 May.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Yarmouth"> Yarmouth</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
