<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce678</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.669</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British
                        Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="669" type="letter">
<head>669. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1802-04-12">12 April
                        1802</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers/ Kingsdown/ Bristol./ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        [illegible]<lb/>Postmark: BAP/ 12/ 1802<lb/>MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I was yesterday much shocked by the news of
                    poor <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas’s</ref> death. his silence had <del rend="strikethrough">made me</del> surprized me, for I
                    had been long in daily expectation of money from him to have
                    paid off the Bristol debts. poor fellow he left London in an
                    ill state of health, &amp; brought on a fever by attending a
                    cause at Hereford. his poor wife<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Bowyer Thomas had married a
                        cousin in 1800. Her name and dates, and those of her
                        father, are unknown.</note> has lost both husband &amp;
                    father within ten days.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> This unhappy circumstance will much derange
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> affairs, of which <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref>
                    was sole manager. I know not when it will be possible to get
                    the money which he had in his hands, of which fifty pounds
                    were to have gone directly for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>
                    Hospital fee at Norwich – &amp; fifty I had written for to
                    remit to you, designing to have borrowed a part till my own
                    salary became due. I can manage for my self – but am sorry
                    that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                        mothers</ref> bills must longer remain unpaid.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We were at Cheshunt four days in the last
                    week – &amp; were both greatly benefitted by fresh air,
                    &amp; the sight of something green. I have resolved to leave
                    London early in May, heartily glad to escape from it – but
                    you may pity me when I shall take an affectionate farewell
                    of my books. my consolation is the joy that there will be in
                    welcoming the new cargo. Still a removal disjoints my plans
                    &amp; disorders the whole march of associated ideas. I am
                    hard at work, surrounded by documents – folios &amp;
                    quartos, one open upon another collating, comparing, picking
                    hemp out of all &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del>
                    twisting it into one cord.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> are
                    at work upon Chatterton.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Joseph Cottle’s planned
                        subscription edition of <title>The Works of Thomas
                            Chatterton</title>, eventually published in
                        1803.</note> they appear to have little or nothing to do
                    as yet. <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>
                    would have done better to have remained in Bristol with the
                    whole business if <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref> had been disposed to move – that is if he
                    had had any rational inclination for employment. his life
                    cannot be very comfortable here – in a court in Fleet Street
                    – too lame to walk abroad. – a cupboard in his room holds
                    his books &amp; bread &amp; cheese – I should pity his way
                    of life were it not that he has always lived in a slovenly
                    swine way.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel
                        Biggs had moved his business to Crane Court, London, in
                        1800-1801. Joseph Cottle, who remained his business
                        partner, seems to have been staying with Biggs in London
                        in order to complete the Chatterton edition. Cottle was
                        lame, so the description of a ‘slovenly swine way’ of
                        life applies to him, not Biggs.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have received of Maddison<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mr Maddison (first name and
                        dates unknown), lottery office-keeper in London.</note>
                    £2 – 3<hi rend="sup">s</hi> –6<hi rend="sup"> d</hi> – the
                    eighth part of an eighteen pounds prize. &amp; I am sorry to
                    say that when Bish<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Bish (fl. 1790-1826), a well-known lottery
                        office-keeper at 4 Cornhill, London.</note> pays me the
                    like sum, your Lottery receipts for this year will be over –
                    the new quarter being drawn a blank. next year I wish you
                    better luck, &amp; a more fortunate agent. you have had
                    eight shares, &amp; among them four prizes – &amp; yet the
                    balance is an ugly one.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Johnson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Johnson (1738-1808;
                            <title>DNB</title>), bookseller and
                        publisher.</note> has hardly sold any of the
                        sermons.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Sermons, By the Late Rev. David Jardine, of
                            Bath. Published from the Original Manuscripts, by
                            the Rev. John Prior Estlin</title> (1798).</note>
                    there are nine copies in his warehouse – &amp; only eleven –
                    or 13 (I forget which) were sent. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp;
                    Rees have sold all. they desire <ref target="people.html#JardineMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Jardine</ref> will send up twenty five copies; &amp;
                    they will do what they can with them. the fact is <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp;
                    Rees have advertised them generally at the end of other
                    books – whereas Johnson (himself an excellent man) publishes
                    few books &amp; cares for none.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> This morning I have received a letter from
                    Lisbon. I like <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> letters there is so much about books in
                    them, but about every thing else he is a most unsatisfactory
                    correspondent. not a word about his own plans, whether he
                    stays or returns to England. the death of poor <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref>
                    will perhaps be one reason for his coming here – it will
                    else be very troublesome to arrange matters by letter with a
                    new agent.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> It was not quite friendly in <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> to pass
                    thro London to Bristol without shaking me by the hand. I
                    should willingly, now the <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Montgomeryshire
                        Member</ref> is from town, have written by him, &amp; it
                    would have been convenient to me if he could have convoyed
                    down some half a dozen volumes, which might have gone
                    carriage free with him. What are his plans now? does he
                    purpose returning to Edinburgh – to graduate in a
                    profession, wherein he has no probability of ever obtaining
                        practise?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Burnett
                        was studying medicine in Edinburgh.</note> poor fellow –
                    I have seldom known a man whom it was so impossible to
                    serve.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Tyler</ref> has replied to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> in
                    an impertinent letter which he has enclosed to me. I know
                    not whether her wickedness or folly predominates. the Devil
                    take her! –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Let me soon hear from you. you are my only
                    regular correspondent, &amp; your letters we look for as
                    things customary &amp; necessary. I wish we could hear of
                    any situation for your brother. how is <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Danvers</ref>. this is the worst time of the year<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> for those who are not in
                    robust health. I myself feel the frequent alterations of [MS
                    obscured]ther summer &amp; winter, &amp; hail &amp; sunshine
                    in the same day.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has a
                    delightful house here.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">As Secretary to The Speaker, Rickman had
                        an official residence in the corner of Palace Yard,
                        Westminster, and adjoining The Speaker’s own
                        house.</note> my books from <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> are to be sent
                    to him &amp; there I trust they may rest – till I myself get
                    an abiding place. I am truly &amp; sorely weary of wandering
                    – of a vagabond life that allows no local attachments – no
                    cat &amp; dog society – &amp; deprives me of half the
                    comforts of domestic life. <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Corry</ref> pays me 400
                    a year to run about after him – I would <del rend="strikethrough">let him</del> take half to stay in
                    one place.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love.
                    remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref>.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> God bless you –</salute>
<salute rend="indent3"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed>
<lb/>
<date when="1802-04-12">Monday 12. April. 1802.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Strand">35. Strand</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
