<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce681</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.672</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="672" type="letter">
<head>672. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Charles
                        Biddlecombe</ref>, <date when="1802-04-22">22 April [1802]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Charles Biddlecombe
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Burton/ near/ Ringwood/ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        449 Strand<lb/>Postmark: [illegible]<lb/>Watermark: E &amp; P/ 1801<lb/>MS:
                        Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I was surprized to learn at the Hotel that you were gone – &amp;
                    am vexed to have seen you so little during your stay.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Since your departure I have received letters from <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> at
                    Paris. interesting inasmuch as they differ from the common newspaper accounts,
                    &amp; are the observations of an observing man. he says that the public
                    conversation is free, worthy of a free people, &amp; that at the coffee houses
                    the measures of government are discussed acutely &amp; severely but without
                    ill-will or acrimony. The temper of the people disposes them to peace. Order is
                    worth more than Liberty. – In changing governments we do not change men. – New
                    Constitutions are periodical publications – &amp; each costs something. These
                    &amp; like proverbial maxims are the favourite texts in Paris. My friend<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> says that the French are less officious in
                    politeness than formerly. that manners &amp; morals of a more English character
                    are fashionable. that young men talk of the “Religion of our fathers” as if they
                    meant to learn the Catechism. that the tide in fact is setting in to those
                    opinions of morality, religion &amp; politics which pervade the works of
                        Burke.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The conservative politician
                        and writer Edmund Burke (1729/30-1797; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am sorry &amp; ashamed to think of the trouble you will have in
                    clearing off our things – &amp; would apologize if I knew how to find a fitting
                    apology for what is unavoidable. the prints will travel safely if wrapt in the
                    linen, &amp; so laid in the large chest. a half-workd hearthrug of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> industry will also go in that
                    chest. there is a small mahogany machine which <del rend="strikethrough">you</del> would perhaps puzzle you to know its use – it is for making
                    fringe. that we must not lose – it may come in the chest or trunk if there be
                    one. every thing else to be sold except linen &amp; silver things. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Jenkins<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably a neighbour of Southey’s during his residence at
                            <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>, Hampshire.</note> said
                    she would at any time give a guinea for the kitchen grate which we bought of
                    her, together with the boiler. there was a silver pepper box – but it was
                    carelessly left loose. It will certainly be adviseable to have all the things
                    cleaned up before they are sold – they will sell to much greater advantage. All
                    the books may be directed to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court. New Palace Yard. the
                    chest (which must be quite full) &amp; trunk if there be one must go to Bristol,
                    directed to <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Fricker</ref> 29. <ref target="places.html#StokesCroft">Stokes Croft</ref>.
                    We have some spirits there, which will well pay the expence of their removal to
                    Bristol. Some few things such as would rust chiefly were left with the next door
                    neighbour.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I believe I have left nothing unsaid upon this business.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Morning Post of yesterday promised to give some news to day
                    which they thought the most interesting that had appeared in that paper for
                    twenty years. We were all full of wonder &amp; expectation. Lo! the newspaper
                    came &amp; announced – that the sale of the Morning Post now exceeded that of
                    every other newspaper. very impudent – &amp; I suppose very true.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Have you seen a periodical work called the Beauties of England
                    &amp; Wales?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Britton (1771-1857;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Edward Wedlake Brayley (1773-1854;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Beauties of England and Wales</title>
                        (1801-1815).</note> it is really a beautiful work – the prints are in the
                    very best stile. two volumes are published at 20 shillings each – that is the
                    large paper with which only good impressions can be had – the whole will be ten
                    or twelve. your Christ-Church will doubtless one day come in so too should High
                    Cliff before it be farther dilapidated.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> There is War in the City. the Sheriffs &amp; the Mayor. he did
                    not give them tickets nor their Chaplain – &amp; they declare that they are
                    obliged to resent what is an insult to the established Religion &amp; the
                    established Orders of Society.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">There was
                        a royal visit to the City of London on 3 April 1802. The Lord Mayor, Sir
                        John Eamer (1750-1823), did not allocate places at the Lord Mayor’s table to
                        the two Sheriffs, Sir William Rawlins (d. 1838) and Robert Cox (dates
                        unknown) and their chaplains, so they boycotted the ceremony. The incident
                        provoked a number of satirical prints, including ‘The City combat, or the desperate
                        attack at the English baron, an Easter tale’ (1802) and ‘A peep in the City
                        – or, spoil’d children’ (1802).</note> it is infinitely ridiculous &amp;
                    will &amp; must – occasion satire.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Do you think of visiting Paris? curiosity will probably lead you
                    where it is leading every body. I should think of it myself if I had leisure
                    enough &amp; was rich enough. that not being the case I do not allow my
                    curiosity to be very strong, &amp; persuade myself with some truth that nothing
                    on the banks of the Seine can equal the shores of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; Killarney.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Remember me to your mother – &amp; to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Colman.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably a
                        neighbour of Southey’s during his time at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>, Hampshire.</note> your little<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey has omitted ‘girl’; Biddlecombe’s daughter (first
                        name unknown) had been born in March 1799. His wife, Catherine (née Lacy),
                        had died on 24 March 1799 (see the <title>Oracle</title>, 2 April 1799) from
                        complications resulting from the birth.</note> is not old enough for an
                    acquaintance. I trust she continues well.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> Yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<lb/>
<postscript>
<p>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Strand">35 Strand</ref>. </placeName>
<date when="1802-04-22">22 April.</date>
</p>
<p>Direct under cover to</p>
<p rend="indent1"> R<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Honble</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Isaac Corry</ref>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="places.html#DukeSt">Duke Street</ref>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Westminster</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
