<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce396</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.387</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Huntington Library,
                        HM 4820 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of
                            the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2
                        vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 261–264 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="387" type="letter">
<head>387. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref>, <date when="1799-03-12">12 March 1799</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/
                        Norwich/ Single<lb/>Postmarks: BRISTOL/ MAR 12 99; B/ MR/ 13/
                        99<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 25<lb/>MS: Huntington Library,
                        HM 4820 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of
                            the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 261–264 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has mistaken my complaint,
                    &amp; you have mistaken my disposition. at one time I was apprehensive of some
                    local complaint of the heart, but there is no danger of its growing too hard,
                    &amp; the affection is merely nervous. the only consequence which there is any
                    reason to dread, is that it may totally unfit me for the confinement of London
                    &amp; a Lawyer’s office. I shall make the attempt, somewhat heartlessly, &amp;
                    discouraged by the prognostics of my medical adviser.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Thomas
                            Beddoes</ref>, whom Southey did consult in 1799.</note> if my health
                    suffers I will abandon it at once – at the age of 25 there is little leisure for
                    waiting – the world will be again before me – <del rend="strikethrough">or if xx
                        following xxxx xxxxxxxx legs xxxxxx xxx xxxxxxxx xxxx xxxxxxxxx
                        Burnett</del> – &amp; the prospect sufficiently comfortable. I have no wants
                    &amp; few wishes. literary exertion is almost as necessary to me now as meat
                    &amp; drink, &amp; with an undivided attention I could do much. – Once indeed I
                    had a mimosa-sensibility, but it has long been rooted out. five years ago I
                    counteracted Rousseau by dieting upon <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> &amp; Epictetus.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Stoic philosopher Epictetus (c. AD 60–after100), whom Southey had read to
                        counteract the influence of Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712–1778).</note> they
                    did me some good, but Time has done more. I have a dislike to all strong emotion
                    &amp; avoid whatever would excite it. a book like Werter<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann von Goethe (1749–1832), <title>Die Leiden des Jungen
                            Werther</title> (1774).</note> gives me now unmingled pain. in my own
                    writings you may observe that I rather dwell upon what affects than what
                    agitates.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will by this I suppose have received my volume.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of <title>Poems</title>
                        (1799). The first volume was a third edition of the collection first printed
                        in 1797.</note> when another edition of the first is printed you shall have
                    an answerable copy.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I should much like more reliques of Rowley<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770:
                        <title>DNB</title>) ascribed his medieval-style poems to Thomas Rowley, a
                        fictional fifteenth-century monk.</note> – were it not that the language
                    would preclude them, like the other reliques, from ever becoming popular. a
                    ballad or two – some fragments of a Romance – &amp; more books of the English
                        Metamorphoses<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Chatterton’s
                        incomplete ‘Englysh Metamorphosis: Bie T. Rowleie’ (1769).</note> might make
                    an amusing volume. these are tempting subjects. eight years ago I thought of
                    continuing the Metamorphoses – &amp; soon after actually planned six books to
                    compleat the Faery Queen, &amp; wrote three Cantos.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Spenser’s (1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>)’ unfinished
                            <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590–1596).</note> the Cantos I burnt
                    – but the plans I believe still exist. I should like to see your play.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor’s play,
                            <title>Wortigerne</title> (1801), in the style of Thomas Chatterton’s
                        Rowley forgeries.</note> somebody should do for the Hindoo Gods what D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers, has done for Odin.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Frank Sayers (1763–1817; <title>DNB</title>), whose
                            <title>Dramatic Sketches of the Ancient Northern Mythology</title>
                        (1790) included poems about Odin, chief of the Norse gods. Sayers was a
                        close friend of Taylor’s and a significant early influence on
                        Southey.</note> we know enough of them now for a poetical system.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> A man of Lynn,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The port
                        of Kings Lynn, Norfolk.</note> who once wrote to ask me when I should
                    publish Madoc, has published a volume of verses himself lately – George Goodwin
                    is his name.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">George Goodwin (dates
                        unknown), <title>Rising Castle, With Other Poems</title> (1798). This
                        appears to have been Goodwin’s only book, although he contributed two new
                        poems, ‘Omar at the Tomb of Azza’ and ‘Fragments’, to <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1800), pp. 219–222, 281–283.</note> in
                    reviewing his book I was amused at cautioning him against imitating a living
                        writer.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Critical
                            Review</title>, 25 (March 1799), 314–318.</note> I will copy below a
                    burlesque imitation, surely allowable, as being of myself. the
                        Anti-Jacobines<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The editors of and
                        contributors to the <title>Anti-Jacobin Review</title>, who had lampooned
                        Southey, Coleridge and other members of their circle.</note> seem to be
                    ashamed of their own verses of late. they must have known as little of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; me when
                    they talkd of our “splay-foot madrigals of love”<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">An attack on Southey, <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor
                        Coleridge</ref>, <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref>
                        and <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref>, in ‘The
                        Anarchists. – An Ode’, in <title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine</title>, 1
                        (September 1798), 366.</note> as they did of the “<ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">Taylors</ref> the brothers of Norwich” –
                    correspondents to the Monthly Magazine.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine</title>, 1 (August 1798),
                        201.</note> even party spirit will not support that precious review here.
                    there was one man violent enough to take it <del rend="strikethrough">ln</del>
                    in instead of the Monthly Review – but even he<del rend="strikethrough">r</del>
                    could not endure its stupid malignity &amp; returned to his old one, in spite of
                    the principles.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You have heard of the Metallic Tractors.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The quack remedy Perkins Patent Tractors, created by Elisha
                        Perkins (1741–1799). Drawing on experiments conducted by Luigi Galvani
                        (1737–1798), Perkins theorized that redirecting the body’s natural
                        electricity could draw out pain and disease. He developed brass and iron
                        rods of about 4 inches in length, with one flat side and one round side with
                        one blunt end and one pointed end. The practitioner held the rods in his
                        hand and rested the point of the rods on the skin. Then he stroked or drew
                        the tractors over the unhealthy area of the body to attract and draw out
                        affliction; see Benjamin Douglas Perkins (1774–1810), <title>The Influence
                            of Metallic Tractors on the Human Body</title> (1798). The subject of
                        much controversy, Perkinism was attacked by James Gillray (1757–1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in his satirical print ‘Metallic Tractors’
                        (1801).</note> a surgeon here has practised at the Infirmary with two pieces
                    of wood coloured like them, &amp; actually in several instances cured paralysed
                        limbs!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The experiments carried out
                        at the Bristol Infirmary (probably by a Mr Smith and his colleagues) and
                        various Bristolian medical establishments to expose the quack medicine
                        behind Perkinism are described in John Haygarth (1740–1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Imagination, As a Cause and as a Cure of
                            Disorders of the Body; Exemplified by Fictitious Tractors, and
                            Epidemical Convulsions</title> (Bath, 1800), pp. 6–14.</note> one of the
                    patients declared he felt more pain from them than when five pieces of bone were
                    extracted from his leg. the patients are astonished at the effect of the
                    Tractors &amp; the Surgeons at the effect of faith. I grow daily more sceptical
                    &amp; shall soon disbelieve nothing. this fact authenticates to me many of the
                    Saint &amp; relic miracles. my inclination credits the existence of apparitions
                    – &amp; for the reality of witchcraft I have in spite of system, certain doughty
                    arguments, not easily confuted.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> had time
                    to spare &amp; were advanced enough in medical knowledge here would be a fine
                    opportunity for him. the Pneumatic Institution<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pneumatic Institute, Dowry Square, Bristol, was devoted
                        to using gases to treat illness. Its early findings were publicised in
                        Thomas Beddoes, <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the Medical
                            Pneumatic Institution</title> (1799).</note> opens tomorrow, &amp; it
                    will be part of their plan to receive students in medicine, without a premium.
                    the mischief is that studies here, which would probably be of more importance
                    than all the University lectures in Europe, could not assist him in graduating.
                    I hope much from pneumatic medicine, but if the first trials should prove
                    unsuccesful <del rend="strikethrough">I will xxxxxxxxx xxx</del> an outcry will
                    be raisd against it. they will also find a difficulty in getting patients. even
                    in hopeless disorders people are not fond of having experiments tried upon them.
                        <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref>, the young man who has the
                    management of the institution, possesses most extraordinary talents. <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> speaks of him with
                    unbounded praise, &amp; he appears to deserve it.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your poetry. What is the <hi rend="ital">Burnie</hi>-Bee?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor’s ‘To the
                        Burnie Bee’ in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1799), p. 64
                        was given the note ‘A provincial name of the beetle <hi rend="ital">coccinella</hi>, or lady-bird.’ This information was conveyed in a
                        letter from Taylor to Southey, 25 March 1799 (J.W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p. 268).</note> is it not
                    &lt;the Humble Bee, or&gt; what we call the Dumbledõre, a word whose descriptive
                    droning deserves a place in song? the Lines of the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    century I suppose you altered from Beaumont &amp; Fletcher for the sake of the
                        parody<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor’s ‘Lines Written in
                        the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century’, <title>Annual Anthology</title>
                        (Bristol, 1799), pp. 205–206, were an adaptation of John Fletcher’s
                        (1579–1625; <title>DNB</title>) ‘Hence, all you vain delights’ from
                            <title>The Nice Valour</title> (1647). Southey had wrongly assumed that Fletcher’s
                        collaborator, Francis Beaumont (1584–1616; <title>DNB</title>), was a
                        co-author. Taylor, who had seen the song transcribed on the blank leaf of an old
                        astrological almanac, had himself incorrectly assumed it was by Philip Massinger (1583–1640;
                            <title>DNB</title>); see Taylor to Southey, 25 March 1799, J.W. Robberds
                        (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor
                            of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p. 268. Taylor followed
                        his adaptation with a parody of the song’s sentiments, ‘Parodied in the
                            18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century’, <title>Annual Anthology</title>
                        (Bristol, 1799), pp. 206–207.</note> – the Almanach goes to the Press next
                        week.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1799).</note> I expect no communications out of the
                    circle of my own acquaintance for the first volume – but I hope the first volume
                    will be popular enough to bring in cart-loads for the second. I have begun an
                    Eclogue between The Devil &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Anthony,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">St Anthony of Egypt (252–356), whose legend
                        included his temptation by the devil. The Eclogue was sent to Taylor on 18
                        March 1799 (Letter 391).</note> for which my Saint book<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Southey’s copy of the <title>Acta
                            Sanctorum</title>.</note> furnished me with the hint. there are mines of
                    poetry in the Popish Legends. my Kalendar<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unrealised plan for a sequence based on the
                        calendar.</note> will be rich in them.</p>
<p rend="indent4"> Inscription – under an Oak<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Published anonymously in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 27
                        February 1799.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent6"> ____</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3"> Here Traveller pause awhile: this ancient oak</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Will parasol thee if the Sun ride high,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Or should the sudden shower be falling fast</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Here mayest thou rest umbrellaed. all around</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Is good &amp; lovely. hard by yonder wall</l>
<l rend="indent3"> The kennel stands; the horse flesh hanging near</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Perchance with scent unsavoury may offend</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Thy delicate nostrils, but remember thou,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> How sweet a perfume to the hound it yields,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And sure its useful odours will regale</l>
<l rend="indent3"> More gratefully thy philosophic nose,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Than what the unprofitable violet</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Wastes on the wandering wind. nor wilt thou want</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Such music as benevolence will love,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> For from these fruitful boughs the acorns fall</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Abundant, &amp; the swine that grub around,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Shaking with restless pleasure their brief tails</l>
<l rend="indent3"> That like the tendrils of the vine curl up,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Will grunt their greedy joy. dost thou not love</l>
<l rend="indent3"> The sounds that speak enjoyment? oh if not – </l>
<l rend="indent3"> If thou wouldst rather with inhuman ear</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Hark to the warblings of some wretched bird</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Bereft of freedom, sure thine heart is dead</l>
<l rend="indent3"> To each good feeling, &amp; thy spirit void</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Of all that softens or ennobles man.</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent6"> ________</p>
<p> We are growling at the Income Bill<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Income tax was introduced for the first time in December 1798 at a rate of
                        10% on incomes over £200 pa.</note> here, &amp; wondering what will be the
                    next measure. perhaps a tenth of capital. the people are <del rend="strikethrough">ready</del> willing to submit to anything. Edward the
                    Confessor returned a tax to the people because he saw the Devil dancing upon the
                    money raised by it.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">The actions of
                        Edward the Confessor (1003/5–1066; reigned 1043–1066; <title>DNB</title>)
                        are recounted in Southey’s ‘The Tax Repealed; Or, An Historical Ballad of
                        King Edward the Confessor’, published anonymously in the <title>Morning
                            Post</title>, 10 April 1799.</note> I wish he would make his appearance
                    in the Treasury now!</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you – </salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p rend="right">
<date when="1799-03-12">Tuesday. March 12. 99.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
