<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3404</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4675</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3404. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey,
						17 December 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3404" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3404.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.107.
						ALS; 4p.  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3404" type="letter">
        <head>3404. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>,
						<date when="1819-12-17">17 December 1819</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London.<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark:
						E/ 20 DEC 20/ 1819<lb /> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb /> Endorsement: 36 &#8211; 3 / 31 &#8211; 12 / 25
						&#8211; 4 / 10 &#8211; 9 /___/ 103 &#8211; 8/ 415 &#8211; 14 / ___ / 519 &#8211; 2<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.107.
						ALS; 4p. <lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the first place I hope you received a haunch of venison which I sent your Lordship some time
					ago, dividing with you half a doe from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly, I have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>. But
					before <del>xxx</del> we take Counsels opinion, <del>xx</del> it must be ascertained <del>xx</del> whether I am
					heir at law.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cannon Southey&#8217;s (d. 1768) fantastically complex will gave
						Southey some hope of inheriting property at Fitzhead after the death of his third cousin, and John Cannon
						Southey&#8217;s heir, John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>). An heir at law was
						entitled to receive the real property of someone who died intestate. Southey did stand in this relation to John
						Cannon Southey, but it did not help his claim on the Fitzhead property.</note> And I &lt;have&gt; now written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> putting the question in such precise terms, that we shall
					see whether there be any doubt about it. Your pedigree is right, as far as it goes, but it remains to be seen
					whether the common ancestor to whom we <del>xxx</del> go back, had not other children besides the father of Cannon
					S. &amp; our G. Grandfather, &amp; whether there may not be descendants of an elder branch than the said G.G.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cannon Southey&#8217;s father was John Southey (1666&#8211;1728) and his grandfather
						was William Southey (dates unknown), who was the common ancestor of John Cannon Southey and the poet Robert
						Southey (he was, as Southey said, the father of Southey&#8217;s great-grandfather, Robert Southey (1670&#8211;1726)).</note>
					The world swarms with Southeys. I have seen three in the newspapers within this fortnight. I expect to hear of one
					in an Old Bailey list, &#8211; or at a Radical Meeting &#8211; the name is so common. And unless our G. Grandfather was the
					next brother to the father of the Cannon, &#8211; some of these sons of guns may have a prior claim to mine. After all
					the claim may be worth nothing. For that Lord Somerville did all he could to cut off the right of the heir at law,
					is quite certain: &amp; the only chance I have is that he may have been mistaken, &amp; done what he was not
					legally enabled to do, &#8211; that is, &#8211; whether I am not entitled to a suit in Chancery, as a cheap &amp; agreable
					amusement for the rest of my life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thirdly. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt</ref> assures me that about 600 &#163;
					recovered at law by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Tom Southey</ref> in pursuance of a suit
					instituted by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John</ref>, for the plate &amp; furniture of Fitzhead,
					was by Lord Erskines decree vested in the 3 per cents.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Erskine, 1st
						Baron Erskine (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>). As Lord Chancellor 1806&#8211;1807 he had delivered a judgment in the
						Court of Chancery, on 28 March 1807, in the case of Southey <title>v</title>. Lord Somerville, one of many legal
						actions arising from the will of John Cannon Southey. Lord Erskine had decided that the money raised from the sale
						of the furniture and plate from the Fitzhead estate should be invested, and that Thomas Southey should receive the
						interest from that money. It was not clear what would happen after his death.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Tom S.</ref> to have the interest during his life, &amp; then the money to
					be claimed by those to whom it might belong, for Lord Erskine is <hi rend="ital">said</hi> to have <hi rend="ital">said</hi> that he did not know who it belonged to. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt</ref>
					can hardly be mistaken in the main fact: &amp; if that money be in the funds as she says, it must belong to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southeys</ref> heirs at law, one third to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">our fathers</ref> children in equal parts, one third to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt Mary</ref>, &amp; the other to the representatives of her sister,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A puzzling statement: Southey should have been aware that Mary Southey&#8217;s only
						sister, Betty (b. 1746), had died in infancy.</note> if there be any, as I believe there are. <del>Surely</del>
					The main point can be ascertained by enquiry at the Bank, I should think, &#8211; or by ascertaining what the decision
					was, which must have been made in 1806 &#8211; or &#8211; 7. Neither your share or mine are of much consequence, but to all the
					rest of the parties it would be no inconsiderable God-send, &amp; therefore I would bestir myself in the business.
					Will you read this to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> &amp; ask him how to go to
					work.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the last two or three weeks I have felt nothing of my infirmity,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was suffering from a rectal prolapse; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 3 October 1819,
						Letter 3356.</note> &#8211; this is passing from entailed estates, to <del>xxx</del> diseases in tail. Perhaps the
					season has braced me, &#8211; tho I hardly know how it gets at me, <del>hearth</del> the hearth being as much my habitat
					as it is that of a cricket or a salamander: However I am surprized at the change.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am reviewing Marlboroughs Life for the next number,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke of Marlborough, with his Original Correspondence;
							Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other Authentic Sources. Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and
							Military Plans</title> (1818&#8211;1819) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (May 1820), 1&#8211;73.</note> &amp;
					must make a push to get a second article inserted, that I &amp; the Constable may once more get cheek by jowl.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;To outrun the Constable&#8217; was a phrase that described getting into debt. Southey
						wished to at least break even by being &#8216;cheek by jowl&#8217; with the Constable.</note> I don&#8217;t like outrunning that
					fellow. &#8211; What a pity that he should be such a limping, lazy, tortoise paced wretch, when I have the legs &amp; the
					leanness &amp; the disposition of a grey hound!</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Upon re-perusing <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref> letter I perceive
					that what he says refers wholly to the Fitzhead property. And therefore I apprehend that he has only an extract
					from the will, &#8211; not the whole of it. The point of most importance is to know how the rest of the property was
					devised, &#8211; whether <del>xxx xxx</del> upon the death of John Southey Somerville without issue, <del>it does
						not</del> it goes to his heirs, or to the heirs of the testator. There is no doubt that the testator did not
					intend it to go out of his own family into a strangers, but he had a clumsy way of expressing his meaning. What a
					pity that this Cannon should have proved but a Blunderbuss!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been amused with the squibs upon Martin Bree in the Guardian.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Bree (1771&#8211;1842), formerly of Braithwaite Lodge near Keswick, changed his name to Stapylton
						in 1817 to inherit the estates of his uncle, Sir Martin Stapylton (1751&#8211;1817), 8th Baronet, of Myton. He had
						previously been known as a quack doctor, especially in the treatment of venereal disease, and had engaged in some
						unsuccessful mining ventures in the Keswick area. He was lampooned in the first issue of the new conservative
						Sunday paper, the <title>Guardian</title>, 12 December 1819.</note> Here is another for you &#8211; Martin&#8217;s Motto &#8211; <hi rend="ital">Tam Mercurio quam Marte</hi>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;made for wisdom as much as war&#8217;;
						an inversion of the motto of the poet George Gascoigne (c. 1535&#8211;1577; <title>DNB</title>). Southey here jokes that
						Bree has added &#8216;wisdom&#8217; to the existing Stapylton reputation for valour, exhibited previously in the Crusades and
						the Hundred Years War.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-12-17">17 Dec. 1819</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>