<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3346</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4617</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3346. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford, 28 August 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3346" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3346.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3346" type="letter">
        <head>3346. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford</ref>, <date when="1819-08-28">28 August 1819</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] Aberdeen Twenty Ninth August/ &#8212; 1819/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/
						Exchequer/ Westminster/ Fm/ JRickman<lb /> Postmarks: ABERDEEN/ 29 AUG 1819/ 528-E; AUG/ W 30 N/ 1819<lb /> MS:
						Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline> Aberdeen. <date when="1819-08-28">28 Aug. 1819</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear
						G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here I am 250 miles from home, &amp; in no very comfortable state. One of the tumours on my head
					which I offered to the knife in London but was advised to let alone has suppurated. This process did not begin till
					we had left Edinburgh. When I reached Perth I called upon Edward Collins<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Collins (c. 1777&#8211;1841), Captain in the 21st Light Dragoons, was the brother of Charles Collins, Southey&#8217;s
						old schoolfriend. Southey missed seeing him, as Edward Collins had travelled south to deal with matters arising
						from the death of his father, William Collins (c. 1751&#8211;1819), naval engineer and inventor, on 23 April 1819 at his
						home in Maize Hill, Greenwich.</note> &amp; showed it to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wood,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Wood (d. 1825) of Keithick, Perthshire; he was the uncle of Edward Collins&#8217;s wife, Margaret
						Collins, n&#233;e Wood (d. 1852).</note> ready to return home immediately if he should advise me so to do, or submit to
					an operation. He assured me there <del>would be</del> &lt;was&gt; no occasion for either, that it seemed likely to
					discharge itself, &amp; that I had nothing to do but dress it with a little simple ointment. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> accordingly acted as my surgeon till we reached this place
					yesterday. He &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">R.</ref> left me with the Ladies &amp;
						children<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah
							Rickman</ref>; her two youngest children, William Charles Rickman (1812&#8211;1886) and Frances Rickman (dates unknown,
						she married Richard Brindley Hone (1805&#8211;1881), Vicar of Halesowen 1836&#8211;1881, in 1836); and their companion, Emma
						Pigott. It is difficult to be sure of Miss Pigott&#8217;s identity, but she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown),
						younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d. 1822) of Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. Fitz-Hall was only five
						miles from Susannah Rickman&#8217;s home at Harting. Emma Pigott married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen
						Hill, Berkshire.</note> while they went to inspect some works to the Westward, &amp; I went to the nearest
					Apothecarys to have the tumour dressed. A decent man with an honest face<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> officiated, but withal told me then in the morning his brother, who was of the medical
					profession, would be there. And the said brother this morning wanted to enlarge the orifice &amp; tells me that it
					may probably inflame &lt;talked of communicating with the dura mater &amp; so forth&gt;. I proposed to set off homeward,
					&#8211; but he said this was not necessary, &#8211; &amp; on the whole I concluded that he wanted to keep me under his hands,
					&amp; finding that if I was to be laid up my resolution was that it should be in my own house, &#8211; he changed his
					note, &amp; said I might as well proceed. I do not like the man because he manifestly endeavoured to deceive me,
					saying that the contents of the tumour could not suppurate, because they were without vitality &#8211; when they are
					suppurating. So too he says there can be no healing till a wound is made by art, &amp; tho I suspect it is doing
					injustice to Nature who has made one for herself, &amp; if I reason justly would be likely when the obnoxious
					matter was got rid off to set about healing <del>xxx</del> it without the assistance of an Aberdeen
					Laboratory-keeper, &#8211; <del>xxxxx</del> (you must know that Apothecary in Scotland signifies an Oil &amp; Colour
						Man.)<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An &#8216;oil and colourman&#8217; was a retailer of household goods, which might
						include quack remedies, but usually extended from soap and candles to ironmongery, chalk and pickles.</note> &#8211; On
					the whole therefore I am inclined to pursue my journey, thinking that easy stages (we travel with the same horses
					&amp; therefore cannot exceed 35 miles <del>xxx</del> a day) are less likely to produce harm than two days &amp;
					nights of mail coaching.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But it is not easy to make up my mind, &amp; come to any decision under these circumstances. You
					know how little I am in the habit of complaining. I said nothing of this matter to any person of the party, till we
					reached Taymouth, &amp; then perceiving that it had broke, I desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> who slept in the room with me by accident that night, to look at
					it. No one else has heard of it yet &#8211; merely because we thought it best not to give them any uncomfortable feelings
					about me, &#8211; my hair is long enough to cover the lint, so that it has not been observed. But I begin to think that
					they ought to be told &amp; consulted, &#8211; &amp; that it is not fair to proceed with them, with such a chance of
					being laid up on the way. &#8211; In short I am perplexed &amp; uneasy, &amp; heartily wish I were either at home, or in
					London. At present I have no pain, &amp; endure no other inconvenience than that I cannot lie on my right side nor
					clean my hair properly as I use to do. It will be a week before we reach Inverness, &#8211; there I can either obtain
					advice if needful, or get into the stage for Edinburgh, &#8211; but after all the proper course will be to enquire who is
					the best surgeon here, &amp; consult him at once, &amp; act upon his opinion, &#8211; that is as to advancing or
					returning, &#8211; for as for <del>lay</del> lying by at an Inn, that I will never do <del>xxxxx xxx</del> &lt;unless&gt; it
					becomes inevitable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent0"> &#189; past 2.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been to a chirurgeon with a head twice as big as the Laboratory-Mans, &amp; of course,
					with twice as much brains therein.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Rather worryingly, George Kerr
						(1771&#8211;1826) had claimed in his <title>Observations on the Harveian Doctrine of the Circulation of the
							Blood</title> (1816) that the body&#8217;s arteries only contained air, not blood.</note> What he says agrees with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Woods opinion &amp; with my own notions &#8211; So I proceed, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> will doctor or rather chirurgize me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My course thus far has been from Edinburgh to Linlithgow, Sterling, Callander, Loch Kattern, Loch
					Earn Head, Killin, Taymouth, Dunkeld, Perth Dundee &amp; so along the coast to this city. E. Collins was not arrivd
					from England, but was expected every hour. I had not heard of his fathers death. I saw his good little wife &amp;
						D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wood, &#8211; they were very <del>xxx</del> kind to me &#8211; &amp; I
					was sorry that I had only an hour to pass with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not well possible for two men to be more opposite in their pursuits than I &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref>, &#8211; &amp; yet it is not possible for two men to take to
					one another more cordially. He is of a kind, frank, chearful, generous nature, &#8211; &amp; seems to take as much
					interest in looking <del>the</del> after the vile <del>xxx</del> sore upon my pericranium, as in inspecting any of
					his own stupendous works.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If there be any money forthcoming for me at the Exchequer, you may send it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. I cannot tell you where to direct to me, we have such a zig-zag
					course before us, &#8211; &amp; it will probably be nearly four weeks before I get home. But I will write a few lines
					from Inverness as you will be desirous to know how my volcano is going on. We shall be there I believe about Friday
					next</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>