<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3083</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4354</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3083. Robert Southey to Andrew Bell, 27 February 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3083" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3083.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>West Sussex Record Office, Mitford 2328, no. 27.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3083" type="letter">
        <head>3083. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BellAndrew">Andrew Bell</ref>, <date when="1818-02-27">27 February 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Dr Bell/
                  &amp;c &amp;c &amp; &#8211;<lb /> MS: West Sussex Record Office, Mitford 2328, no. 27.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-02-27">27 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
                  1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The best thing I can have to tell you concerning myself would be that
               we were all going on as we were when you left us: &#8211; this however I cannot say of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref>, whose health has
               been much worse than in any former winter, &amp; who is manifestly much changed in
               consequence. For the rest of us, young &amp; old, our lives have only been
               diversified by occasional varieties of cold, cough, chillblains, &amp; toothache, &#8211;
               with interludes of tooth drawing. &#8211; We had <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> with us for two or three weeks, &amp; our sister <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEliza">Eliza</ref> during the Christmas holy days. Since that
               time I see neither man woman or child, except <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>, who now &amp; then dines with me, &amp; sometimes walks up
               for an hour in the evening. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> is
               in <ref type="m" target="places.html#RosthwaitePlace">Borrodale</ref>, full of cares, her own
               &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FletcherSarah">Miss Fletchers</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Barker&#8217;s finances were seriously stretched by the house
                  she was building at Rosthwaite, Borrowdale. Sarah Fletcher was a friend of Mary
                  Barker&#8217;s and had recently closed the girls&#8217; boarding school she ran in Ambleside;
                  she was attempting to reach agreement with her creditors.</note> &#8211; &amp; full of
               trouble, for the death of one of her brothers within a few weeks after he had arrived
               in Canada, &#8211; father of the little boy whom I believe you saw.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick Barker (b. 1779) had emigrated to Canada after a
                  number of business failures. The name of his son is unknown.</note> &#8211; A lucky
               chance has turned up for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Dawes">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dawes</ref> has placed him as
               tutor to some little boys near Ulverstone under very pleasant circumstances; &#8211; &amp;
               there he may continue for two years, if means for removing hom to college should not
               be forthcoming during that time.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent
                  Coleridge had gone to live with the Hopwood family, well-connected Lancashire
                  landowners, at Summerhill, near Ulverston 1817&#8211;1819. Robert Gregge Hopwood
                  (1773&#8211;1854) had married in 1805 Cecilia Elizabeth Byng (1770&#8211;1854), daughter of
                  John Byng, 5th Viscount Torrington (1743&#8211;1813). She was a first cousin of
                  Georgiana Byng (1768&#8211;1801), first wife of Lord John Russell, later the 6th Duke of
                  Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). Lady Russell had lived in Lisbon for two
                  years for her health and was known to Herbert Hill. Derwent Coleridge was tutor to
                  the Hopwoods&#8217; sons: Edward (1807&#8211;1891); Frank (1810&#8211;1890); and Hervey (1811&#8211;1881).
                  He continued in this post until December 1819, later becoming an
                  undergraduate at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And where my dear Sir are you, &#8211; &amp; what have you done with your
               amanuensis &amp; historiographer, who has the sin of curiosity upon him so strongly,
               that he <del>could</del> never {ought to} reproach his grandmother Eve? M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Calvert<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert,
                  n&#233;e Mitchinson (dates unknown), wife of William Calvert. She was the daughter of
                  John Mitchinson (dates unknown), a Quaker conveyancer in Carlisle.</note> heard of
               you at Carlisle, so I conclude you are gone Northward, &#8211; &amp; perhaps we may hope to
               see you when you come southward again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For myself, &#8211; as the old Thessalian &amp; his horse were once
               regarded as one centaur,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Lapiths, a
                  legendary tribe of Thessaly, were described by Ancient Greek writers as the
                  inventors of horseback riding and the relatives of the half-human, half-horse
                  centaurs. Thus the theory arose that the idea of centaurs derived from early
                  reports of men on horseback.</note> so might I &amp; my chair almost be considered
               as one substance: &#8211; there <del>th</del> I am when the breakfast bell rings in the
               morning, &amp; when the supper bell summons me at night. I have been busy upon a long
               paper concerning those measures of reform which may be carried into effect in every
               parish merely by a proper <del>enforcement</del> use of existing power, &amp; a
               proper enforcement of existing laws.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;On the Means of Improving the People&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79&#8211;118.</note> This was half printed for the
               Quarterly &amp; then laid aside for a paper of more immediate bearing upon the Poor
                  Laws,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman and Southey&#8217;s &#8216;On the Poor
                     Laws&#8217;,<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308.</note> &#8211;
               &amp; for this latter after all it was not found convenient to wait. I have also made
               good progress with the Life of Wesley,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism
                     </title>(1820).</note> &#8211; indeed it is <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> fault
               that it is not in the press at this time; &#8211; in the course of this book I look far
               &amp; wide, both at home &amp; abroad &#8211; &amp; am very well satisfied with the
               arrangement of its miscellaneous materials. But my main employment has been the
               history of Brazil, which is now drawing fast towards its termination.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810&#8211;1819).</note> This book I verily believe to be the most laborious of its
               kind in any modern language since the great works of Joam de Barros &amp;
                  Herrera:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The most famous Portuguese and
                  Spanish historians of their nations&#8217; imperial conquests: Joao de Barros
                  (1496&#8211;1570), <title>Decadas da Asia</title> (1552&#8211;1615); and Antonio de Herrera y
                  Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625), <title>Historia General de las Indias Occidentales o de
                     los Hechos de los Castellanos en las Islas y Tierra Firme del Mar
                     Oceano</title> (1601&#8211;1615). </note> &#8211; but it is not in this country, &amp;
               hardly in this age that its value will be appreciated. It satisfies myself, &amp; the
               half-dozen persons whom I was desirous of satisfying, &#8211; &amp; with this I am
               contented. &#8211; I wait for a French work upon Buonapartes system of education in his
               Lyceums before the introductory chapter upon the Peninsular War can be
                  compleated.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray had sent Southey the
                  first two volumes of Jean Baptist Germain Fabry (1770&#8211;1821), <title>Le Ge&#769;nie de
                     la Re&#769;volution Conside&#769;re&#769; dans l&#8217;Education ou Me&#769;moires pour Servir a
                     l&#8217;Histoire de l&#8217;Instruction Publique, Depuis 1789 jusqu&#8217;a&#768; Nos Jours</title>
                  (1817&#8211;1818). Southey awaited the third volume. See <title>History of the
                     Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 40&#8211;43, for Southey&#8217;s
                  account of how the Lyceums played a key role in Napoleon Bonaparte&#8217;s (1769&#8211;1821;
                  Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815) domestic and foreign policy by training up
                  &#8216;the youth of France to become men after his own heart&#8217; (p. 40).</note> Delay here
               is useful; &#8211; fresh documents are published meantime, both in France &amp; in England,
               &#8211; &amp; others from private sources come to my hands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing in the way of public matters interests me so much as the
               revolution about the North pole, &amp; the breaking up of the ice.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Reports of events in the Arctic were widespread
                  in British newspapers, e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817,
                  which noted the retreat of the ice sheets around Greenland.</note> During [MS
               missing] <del>whole</del> month of May I repeatedly said to my fellow travellers that
               nothing but immense masses of floating ice could account for those cold winds from
               the South &amp; S West, which made us shiver with cold in Champagne &amp; Burgundy,
               &amp; prevented the vines from putting out a single leaf, when they ought to have
               been in flower. Barrow in his very interesting paper in this last number<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>). His
                  article on Lieutenant Edward Chappell (1792&#8211;1861), <title>Narrative of a Voyage to
                     Hudson&#8217;s Bay, in His Majesty&#8217;s Ship Rosamond, Containing Some Account of the
                     North-Eastern Coast of America, and of the Tribes Inhabiting that Remote
                     Region</title> (1817), was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18
                  (October 1817), 199&#8211;223.</note> has not noticed a fact which seems to indicate the
               cause of this great alteration. For the last two years the fish have forsaken the
               coast of Kamtschatka, to the great distress of the Bears, who had begun in
               consequence a civil war among themselves, &amp; another <del>xxxx</del> with the
               Russian-Kamtschatkans which may be called more than civil, the bipeds being the
               greater bears of the two. This I think strengthens the supposition that earthquakes
               &amp; volcanos have caused the disruption of the ice, &#8211; the combustibles which used
               to explode in Iceland have probably broken out nearer the pole, &#8211; &amp; marine
               volcanoes <del>have at</del> wherever they exist drive away the fish, destroying of
               course all within the sphere of their action, &amp; infecting the water to a
               prodigious distance.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">British newspapers
                  had carried a number of extracts from Hamburg papers, e.g. <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 8 December 1817. One of the extracts reported that in the
                  Kamchatka peninsula &#8216;in the course of last winter an incredible number of bears
                  have left the woods, frequently entered the houses of the Kamtschdales; in many
                  places have attacked and devoured the inhabitants; nay traces have even been found
                  of their having killed and devoured each other; at the end of the winter many
                  bears were found who had perished of hunger. In several settlements they have
                  killed from two to three hundred bears, the oldest Kamtschadales do not remember
                  ever to have seen so many bears so savage and blood-thirsty. The cause of this
                  savageness and of their hunger is, that for these two years past there has been an
                  entire want of fish in the Kamschatka sea, and fish, as is well known, are the
                  chief food of the bears, which being usually so abundant in those waters, they
                  easily contrive to catch. A couple of shocks of an earthquake have been lately
                  felt in the Peninsula.&#8217; </note> &#8211; These speculations interest me as much as a
               continental war, or a Spafields mob,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  Spa Fields Riots of 2 December 1816. A crowd of about 20,000 had assembled at Spa
                  Fields, Islington to hear the radical speaker, Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835;
                     <title>DNB</title>). A small group of revolutionaries broke away and attempted
                  to storm the Tower of London, looting a gun shop on the way. They were dispersed
                  by troops at the Royal Exchange.</note> &amp; a great deal more than the
               preparations for a Westmorland election.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  general election was imminent, though the House of Commons was not dissolved until
                  10 June 1818. It was already clear, though, that there would be a contest in
                  Westmorland, which was dominated by the Lowther family, who were supporters of the
                  government &#8211; the two sitting MPs were the brothers Henry Lowther (1790&#8211;1867), MP
                  for Westmorland 1812&#8211;1867 and William, Viscount Lowther (1787&#8211;1872), later 2nd
                  Earl of Lonsdale and MP for Cockermouth 1808&#8211;1813, MP for Westmorland 1813&#8211;1831
                  and 1832&#8211;1841. So complete was the Lowthers&#8217; dominance that the last contested
                  election in Westmorland had been in 1774. However, in January 1818, a committee of
                  Whigs and smaller landowners had brought forward Henry Brougham to challenge the
                  Lowthers &#8211; Brougham&#8217;s family home was Brougham Hall near Penrith and he could
                  plausibly be presented as a local candidate.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All here desire their kindest remembrances.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> most truly &amp; affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>