<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2874</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4145</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2874. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 December 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2874" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2874.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2874" type="letter">
        <head>2874. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-12-07">7 December 1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 11 DE 11/ 1816<lb /> Endorsements: 7 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816; 7 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> It seems a long while since I <del>have</del> received a letter from your worship, &amp; tho the newspapers for some
               days have been abundantly interesting, still there has been some disappointment when the dispatches arrived without any communication
               from you. On Tuesday I finished the sketch of Wesleys Life for the Correspondent,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1817 a new
                  journal was launched, published by Longmans and edited by John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), who had in 1816 been
                  dismissed from the editorship of the <title>Times</title> for the intemperate Toryism of his articles. It was entitled <title>The Correspondent; Consisting of Letters, Moral, Political, and Literary, between Eminent Writers in France and England; and designed by presenting to each Nation a Faithful Picture of the Other, to Enlighten both to their True Interests, promote a Mutual Good Understanding between them, and render Peace the Source of a Common Prosperity</title>. Southey contributed a sketch of the life
                  of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) to the first two numbers (1 (1817), 26&#8211;48; and 2 (1817), 157&#8211;176). However, the
                     <title>Correspondent</title> lasted only one further number. Stoddart became the editor of a new ministry-supported paper,
                     <title>The New Times</title> (1817&#8211;1828).</note> (a foolish title, &amp; a more foolish form, which will be as formal, as
               senseless &amp; as tiresome as Dinarzades morning addresses to her sister Scheherezade)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Correspondent</title> took the form of articles by British writers addressed to French writers, and by the French
                  writers addressed to their British counterparts. In the <title>Arabian Nights Entertainment</title> (1706) the stories of
                  Scheherezade are followed by the brief and dull responses of her sister Dinarzade.</note> &#8211; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> has not yet written his letter of {the} tomorrow <del>a fortn</del> which was a
               fortnight ago,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 29 November 1816 (Letter 2868), in
                  which he revealed that Murray had responded to his complaints about under-payment for articles contributed to the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title> and promised to write again.</note>
          <hi rend="ital">tant mieux</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;So much the better&#8217;.</note> I shall leave him in the lurch
               till I have done other work of more import, that, to wit, upon which you set me going, <del>&amp; which</del> For the present the title
               is Observations upon the Moral &amp; Political State of England.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been asked to edit
                  a pro-government journal, but declined. Instead he proposed to write a pamphlet, or book, with this title. This project was not
                  realised and instead Southey wrote on &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 225&#8211;278, and the
                  &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552.</note> I have made some
               way in the first chapter, of which the object is to show that the war was popular as well as necessary, in confutation of the Common
               Hall Resolution<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">On 27 April 1815, as war with France was about to be renewed, a meeting of the
                  Mayor, Aldermen and Liverymen of the several Companies of the City of London in Common Hall assembled at the Guildhall, London,
                  resolved that &#8216;the Livery of London have ever been, and now are, ready to support the honour, the character, and the interests of
                  the British Empire, and to resist every act of aggression; but, seeing all the consequences of the late war, looking at the
                  depressed state of the country, the burthens and privations of the people, the financial difficulties, the uncertainty and hazards
                  of war, seeing likewise that France has disclaimed all intention of interfering in the concerns of other nations, that she has
                  declared her determination to adhere to the Treaty of Paris, that she has made pacific overtures to the different Allied Powers, has
                  already abolished the Slave Trade, and given other indications of returning to principles of equity and moderation; and holding, as
                  we do, all wars to be unjust, unless the injury sustained is clearly defined, and redress by negociation cannot be obtained; and
                  more particularly holding in abhorrence all attempts to dictate to, or interfere with, other nations in their internal concerns, we
                  cannot but protest against the renewal of hostilities, as neither founded in justice nor necessity.&#8217;</note> &amp; such other great
               authorities, <del>that</del> {asserting} it was carried on against the <del>opinion</del> wishes of the nation: &#8211; &amp; here I am about
               to draw a portrait of Buonaparte<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French,
                  1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> as the Perfect Emperor of the English Reformers. The next assertion of the Lord Mayor,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Matthew Wood (1768&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Mayor of the City of London 1815&#8211;1817, MP for the
                  City of London 1817&#8211;1843. A Whig, and inveterate opponent of the government.</note> Orator Hunt,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), veteran radical and speaker at the Spa Fields meeting on 2
                  December 1816.</note> Jack Cade<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jack Cade (c. 1420&#8211;1450; <title>DNB</title>) led a popular
                  rebellion in Kent 1450.</note> &amp; C<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. being that the War is the cause of the present distress the second
               chapter is intended to <del>take</del> examine that question in all its bearings, &amp; the third to their pleasant proposition that
               Parliamentary Reform is the remedy for all, &#8211; in threshing this chaff the flail will fly about the ears of the save-all politicians.
               When I shall have fully exposed the ignorance, folly &amp; falsehood of the Reformers I shall then endeavour to form an estimate of the
               general state of public opinion, &amp; <del>show</del> {to} trace progress of disaffection, &#8211; the dry rot which is spreading in all
               directions. I shall point out as clearly as I can the real evils in society, &amp; endeavour as far as I am able to give confidence
               &amp; hope to <del>good</del> the well-intentioned, &amp; direct their exertions into the best course. &#8211; <hi rend="ital">Ni
                  fallor</hi>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;Unless I mistake&#8217;.</note> the book must attract notice, &#8211; indeed it will be
               abused into notoriety. &#8211; If you have the Ed. Review<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Edinburgh Review</title>
                  (1802&#8211;1929), the leading Whig journal.</note> you <del>xx</del> might assist me by looking out such passages <del>xxxx</del> as are
               peculiarly mischievous. &#8211; My plan will fill a moderately-sized volume.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These riots<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A large pro-reform public meeting was held at Spa Fields, London,
                  on 2 December 1816, addressed by Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt. Some of the crowd, breaking away from the meeting and moving to attack the
                  Tower of London and Bank of England, looted a gun shop and were confronted by troops at the Royal Exchange.</note> give Government
               an opportunity which it would be madness to neglect. They must not despise the danger because this <del>was</del> scheme was absurd
               &amp; impracticable. &#8211; They may well be alarmed at discovering how many sailors were in the mob, &#8211; &amp; they should ask themselves
               what would become of them if the opinions which are almost universal among journeymen, mechanics &amp;c should get ground <del>in</del>
               among the soldiers. And this they will do unless the licentiousness of the press be checked. I cannot distrust my own judgement upon
               this matter, because all who know me, know how long I have distinctly perceived the danger, &#8211; witness the first paper upon the Poor in
               which tho <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> cut out the strongest paragraphs, so much was said, that had
               it been acted upon, <del>no such</del> the disease would not have attained its present height.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. Southey blamed the manufacturing system for the physical and moral
                  degeneracy of the urban poor, argued for an improved system of parochial education, for suppression of the radical press, for
                  cultivation of wastelands and for the employment of the unemployed on public works.</note> &#8211; I shall preach boldly <del>upon the
                  population</del> in direct contradiction to <del>other</del> {the maxim} which has obtained <del>xxxx great xxxx vogue</del> credit,
               that the power of the populace has increased, is increasing, &amp; ought to be diminished.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                  inversion of the famous Whig resolution moved in the House of Commons on 6 April 1780 that &#8216;the influence of the Crown has
                  increased, is increasing, and ought to be diminished&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; Oh &#8211; when you find yourself in the Strand, send me a case of sauces from Burgess&#8217;s<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The firm of John Burgess and Son, sauce manufacturers, was established by John Burgess (dates unknown), a farmer from
                  Hampshire, at 101 Strand, London, by 1774.</note> &#8211; per waggon &#8211; I think they cost 24/<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Remember me to all at home &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-12-07">7 Dec. 1816.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>