<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3224</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4495</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3224. Robert Southey to William Wilberforce, 24 December 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3224" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3224.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg
                  Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3224" type="letter">
        <head>3224. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>,<date when="1818-12-26"> 24 December 1818</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: Pri Southey ans/ wer
                  to mine on/ Characters of/
                  &#951;&#966;&#945;&#957;&#947;&#949;&#955;&#953;&#967;&#945;&#955; /
                  &#967;&#955;&#949;&#961;&#947;&#953; [&#8216;Evangelical clergy&#8217;] <lb /> MS: Berg
                  Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p. <lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot but feel myself greatly honoured by receiving from you such
               a letter as your last upon such a subject. The want of zeal in the Clergy has been
               one of the many causes which has produced the present deplorable state of morals
               among the peasantry &amp; the populace. You may have perceived that I have often
               adverted to this, &amp; if I have not gone as far as you could have wished, &#8211; <del>xx
                  xx</del> I have gone to the length of my tether. Less effect would have been
               produced if more had been said, even if more would have been permitted thro that
               channel; where what I would say is often suppressed or mutilated, &#8211; &amp; not always
               judiciously. &#8211; But in the Life of Wesley<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>
                  (1820).</note> I am under no controul of this kind, &amp; tho I shall lay myself
               open in it to the charge of superstition &amp; weakness of mind, yet the book will be
               so free from any sectarian spirit, or bigotry of any kind, that it will have its
               weight. And here I shall distinctly <del>state</del> point out among the good effects
               of <hi rend="ital">Methodism</hi>, the spirit which it has excited in the
               Establishment, &amp; endeavour to show both directly &amp; by implication (which is
               sometimes the surest, &amp; safest way) how desirable it is that that spirit should
               be cherished, &amp; that the Church Establishment should condescend to take from <hi rend="ital">Methodism</hi> what there is really good in its practices &amp;
               detail. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of the Clergymen whom you mention M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cunningham
               of Harrow<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John William Cunningham
                  (1780&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), evangelical Vicar of Harrow from 1811 until his
                  death and an associate of Wilberforce. He was also a writer, whose <title>Velvet
                     Cushion</title> (1814) was a great success.</note> is the only one I ever
               heard. I have indeed seen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stewart of Percy Chapel,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The evangelical Anglican clergyman James Haldane
                  Stewart (1778&#8211;1854) was the Minister at Percy Chapel, London 1812&#8211;1828.
                  Wilberforce attended Percy Chapel when he was in London. </note> who was here on
               his bridal excursion, with his brother in law Robert Owen of Lanark.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), the
                  humanitarian industrialist, who provided improved living conditions for the
                  workers at his mills at New Lanark, Scotland 1799&#8211;1825. Stewart married Mary Dale
                  (b. 1787), a daughter of David Dale (1739&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), the merchant
                  and founder of New Lanark, in Glasgow on 20 August 1816. Owen was married to one
                  of Mary&#8217;s sisters, Ann Carolina Dale (1778&#8211;1831).</note> What he may be in the
               pulpit I know not, &#8211; but he seemed to be a very poor creature out of it. With regard
               to doctrines oh how much it is to be wished that men would not presumptuously attempt
               to search into the inscrutable, &amp; to define what the scriptures have left
               indefinite! I do not think they have much influence upon the lives of men, &#8211; as far
               as my observation goes indeed, less than I should theoretically have expected: but
               the evils which they occasion by exciting angry &amp; uncharitable feelings &amp;
               schisms &amp; factions where the spirit in which these originate cannot have its full
               scope so as to bring forth persecution {&amp; civil war} &#8211; are serious indeed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I was a young man I was proud, presumptuous &amp; positive. My
               views were clear because they were confined, &#8211; I saw only the single point before me
               on which my attention was fixed. I had no misgivings, &amp; was so conscious
                  <del>that</del> my intentions were right that it never occurred to me even as a
               possibility that my opinions might be wrong. <del>This was for want of an
                  adviser</del> As men grow older they become less dogmatical &amp; more tolerant. I
               have learnt to believe some things, &amp; to doubt concerning others which I once
               totally disbelieved, (<del>xxx</del> preternatural appearances or impressions,
                  <del>xxx</del> the agency of the invisible world, &amp; the existence of an Evil
               Principle) &amp; my belief in the great truths of Revelation has ripened into an
               habitual feeling I should still scruple at subscription,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Subscription to the Thirty-Nine Articles of the Church of
                  England, as set out in its <title>Book of Common Prayer</title> (1662). It was
                  necessary for all Anglican clergymen to assent to these beliefs and, because he
                  could not do this, Southey had declined the career in the church that his uncle,
                  Herbert Hill, had planned for him.</note> &#8211; but not from the same cause. My
               objection would be, not that I held an opposite opinion to this article or that, but
               that I am unable to form an opinion upon such subjects; they seem to me to be beyond
               the scope &amp; sphere of human knowledge, &amp; <del>xxx</del> fitter (as
                  Milton<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674;
                     <title>DNB</title>) <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667), Book 2, features a
                  theological debate between the fallen angels in hell.</note> represents them) to
               be {the} speculations of fallen Angels, than to be digested into formulas of faith.
               Just as with regard to our own immortality it suffices for us to know that we are
                  <del>xxx</del> created <del>in the image of our Makers eternity</del> to be
               immortal, &#8211; to be the image of our Makers eternity, &#8211; without understanding the mode
               of our future existence, &#8211; so I wish that our fathers had been contented to leave
               other points in the same reverential obscurity. <del>In proportion as</del> {I know}
               the Evangelical Clergy only by report, &amp; know how little report is to be trusted,
               but as far as I know them I am led to distrust their judgement while I admire their
               zeal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You were surprized at seeing Huntingtons Works<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Huntington (1745&#8211;1813;
                  <title>DNB</title>), a coalheaver turned Calvinist preacher, who believed he
                  would, on Judgement Day, be revealed as a prophet. Huntington became a popular,
                  rich and controversial preacher. Southey reviewed his life and writings in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462&#8211;510.</note> upon my
               table. I have lately looked thro twenty volumes of the <title>Gospel Magazine</title>
               (from 1796 to 1816),<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Gospel
                     Magazine</title> (1766&#8211;present). An evangelical magazine, mainly aimed at
                  Anglicans.</note> &amp; should scarcely have believed that such opinions were
               entertained by any body of people in the country if I had not raked in this rubbish.
               The writers <del>were</del> {are} mostly Hutchinsonians;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Followers of John Hutchinson (1674&#8211;1737; <title>DNB</title>),
                  who claimed the Bible contained a complete explanation of the universe and that
                  therefore the Newtonian system was false as it was not based on Biblical
                  sources.</note> &amp; all Antinomians<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The idea that Christians who are predestined to salvation are free from
                  moral laws, as they are saved by God&#8217;s grace and not their actions. Antinomians
                  tended to believe that Christ only died for those who would be saved, not for all
                  human beings.</note> &#8211; they dispute <del>for</del> the propriety of praying for
                  <hi rend="ital">all</hi> men, or of inviting <hi rend="ital">all</hi> into the way
               of salvation, they have an essay on the Blessings of Predestination, &amp; they
               notice it as &#8220;worthy of remark that the words moral &amp; morality never occur
               throughout the whole Bible.&#8221; They give you credit for good intentions, but set you
               down for a Baxterian.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A follower of
                  Richard Baxter (1615&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan divine and religious
                  controversialist who was deeply hostile to antinomianism and whose theology
                  insisted Christians must obey moral laws. He attempted to find a middle way
                  between those who believed all souls were predestined to salvation or damnation
                  from before the beginning of the world, and those who believed in the agency of
                  free will in determining a soul&#8217;s fate.</note> They say that Wesley<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was reading about theology because he was
                  researching the career of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) towards his
                  biography, <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820). Wesley&#8217;s theology owed much to the beliefs of the
                  Dutch theologian, Jacobus Arminius (1560&#8211;1609), especially the idea that Christ
                  died for all humanity, but it was up to each individual to decide, with the help
                  of God&#8217;s grace, whether to accept or reject salvation.</note> was as weak as he
               was vicious, &amp; call him a forger &amp; a blasphemer. This life, they maintain, is
                  <hi rend="ital">not</hi> a state of probation. And as for Arminianism it is the
               direct road to everlasting perdition. &#8211; If the doctrines of these men were to
               influence their practice their morality would be like that of the Jesuits.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The idea associated with the Jesuit order
                  that even sinful actions are permissible if they attain a good object.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps I have not expressed myself plainly concerning the
               Evangelical Clergy. &#8211; Do they not dwell rather upon the dark parts of the Epistles,
               than in the light &amp; sunshine of the Gospels?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">St Paul&#8217;s Letters (or Epistles), such as <title>Romans</title>
                  8: 29, were often used to justify the idea of predestination, while those who
                  favoured the concept of free will tended to look to the four Gospels, for
                  instance, <title>Matthew</title> 11: 28&#8211;30.</note> Do they not sometimes
               exaggerate the doctrine of Original Sin?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The concept that, following Adam&#8217;s disobedience to God in the Garden of Eden
                     (<title>Genesis</title> 3), all human beings are born in sin, have a natural
                  tendency to wrong-doing and can only be saved by God&#8217;s grace.</note> Do they not
               exclude Turk, Jew &amp; Gentile from salvation <del>xxx</del> &amp; thus, whether
               Predestinarians or not, reprobate at once the larger part of the human race? &#8211; I
               cannot but believe that God will deal mercifully with all his creatures: &#8211; that they
               who seek him with sincerity under any dispensation will find him; &amp; that there
               may be a state of farther probation after death, for those who, by the fatal
               circumstances in which they were placed here, have lived &amp; died in darkness.
                  <del>Will you think me</del> Perhaps the <del>for</del> Reformers were led astray
               in more points than one by their just indignation against the corruptions of Popery.
               Would they not otherwise have admitted that less than an eternity of torments would
               suffice {as punishment} for certain sins, &amp; that grossly as the <del>do</del>
               hypothesis of a Purgatory<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The doctrine
                  held in the Catholic Church that souls after death may undergo a period of
                  purification before attaining Heaven. It was rejected by most Protestants.</note>
               had been abused, it is in itself neither absurd, nor contradictory to scripture? &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think it is S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Evremont who records the saying
               of a Dutch General that &#8216;when men have taken out of Christianity all that they have
               put into it, &#8211; all men will be Christians.&#8217;<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles de Marguetel de Saint-Denis, Seigneur de
                  Saint<title>-</title>&#201;vremond (1613&#8211;1703), reporting a remark of the German
                  General, Paul Wurtz (1612&#8211;1676). The remark is quoted in <title>The Works of
                     Monsieur de St. Evremond</title>, 3 vols (London, 1714), II, p. 168; no. 1016
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Tho this is too strongly
               expressed, there is some truth in it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have procured &amp; read Baxters narrative of his Life &amp;
                  Times.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Baxter,
                     <title>Narrative of His Life and Times</title> (1696), no. 239 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Baxter was a key figure in the failed negotiations
                  at Savoy House in 1661 to include Presbyterians in the Church of England after the
                  Restoration of the Monarchy.</note>
          <del>He</del> The history of his own mental progress is in the highest degree
               interesting, &amp; unquestionably he appears to have been a most conscientious &amp;
               exemplary man. But the book rather lessens <del>my</del> than raises my respect for
               the Nonconformists; &#8211; so many of their objections to the liturgy were puerile &amp;
               captious, that (setting all other considerations aside) it is no wonder than no
               attention was paid to those which really had some weight. &#8211; They were abominably
               used, &#8211; but they seem to have entirely forgotten the use which they themselves made
               of power when they possessed it. Baxter lays much of their sufferings to Clarendons
                  account.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of
                  Clarendon (1609&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>). As the chief minister in 1660&#8211;1667 of
                  Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>), King of England 1660&#8211;1685;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Clarendon&#8217;s name was given to the &#8216;Clarendon Code&#8217; of laws
                  passed 1661&#8211;1665, which were designed, after the years of Puritan ascendancy
                  during the Commonwealth, to re&#8211;establish the supremacy of the Church of England
                  and restrict Protestant dissent.</note> Now Clarendon appears to me the perfect
                  <del>xx</del> ideal of an English statesman.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the course of a fortnight there will be an opportunity of sending
               up <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref>
                  translation<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster had proposed to
                  further the anti-slavery cause in Brazil by translating Clarkson&#8217;s <title>History
                     of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African
                     Slave&#8211;Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808) into Portuguese.</note> by
               John Wordsworth.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Captain John
                  Wordsworth (1754&#8211;1819), Wordsworth&#8217;s older cousin.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> most truly &amp; respectfully yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-12-26">26 Dec. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>