<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3170</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4441</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3170. Robert Southey to John Murray, 21 July 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3170" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3170.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Scotland,
                  MS 42551. ALS; 4p.  .  Previously  published: Samuel Smiles, A Publisher and His Friends. Memoir and Correspondence of the
                     Late John Murray, with an Account of the Origin and Progress of the House, 1768&#8211;1843, 2 vols (London, 1891), II, pp.
                  42&#8211;43.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3170" type="letter">
        <head>3170. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1818-07-21">21 July 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 24 JY 24/ 1818 <lb /> Watermark: R E &amp; S BATH 1814<lb /> MS: National Library of Scotland,
                  MS 42551. ALS; 4p. <lb /> Previously published: Samuel Smiles, <title>A Publisher and His Friends. Memoir and Correspondence of the
                     Late John Murray, with an Account of the Origin and Progress of the House, 1768&#8211;1843</title>, 2 vols (London, 1891), II, pp.
                  42&#8211;43.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made good way in a letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> in consequence
               of a false &amp; slanderous attack which he made upon me from the hustings, &#8211; with the amiable intention I believe of setting my
               neighbours upon stoning me, &#8211; this being the fashion with the rabble of his party.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">On 30 June
                  1818, Brougham, campaigning for the parliamentary seat of Westmorland against the candidates favoured by Wordsworth&#8217;s patron, the
                  Earl of Lonsdale, was reported to have attacked Southey and Wordsworth from the hustings. Southey did not finish his response, which
                  he termed his &#8216;Tender Epistle&#8217;, but parts of it saw print, without mention of Brougham&#8217;s name, in a postscript to the second edition
                  of <title>Carmen Triumphale </title>(London, 1821), pp. 45&#8211;53.</note> As I was not present to give him the lie in the face of the
               multitude, (as assuredly I would have done) I have given him such a castigation as such a thorough-paced scoundrel deserves, &#8211; a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">WilliamSmithiad</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Letter
                     to William Smith, Esq., M. P.</title> (1817).</note> But I should hardly have taken this trouble for mere personal motives if I
               had not hoped to do some good by a full &amp; compleat exposure of his system of slander. For this purpose in the body of the letter I
               want to give in order a clear, succinct &amp; strong statement of all the calumnies in the H of Commons of which he has been convicted,
               &#8211; with the documents in the Appendix (between ourselves this is a suggestion of <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Crokers</ref>). &#8211; Send me therefore the Debates of the last Parliament &#8211; from the time <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> came in for Winchelsea &#8211; I forget whether in 1814 &#8211; 15 or 16.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham was MP for Winchelsea 1815&#8211;1830.</note> The first part I shall very shortly send you thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> hands &amp; you will let <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> print it. By the bye this printer has requested me to speak a good word for him to
               you, &#8211; &amp; if in the plenitude of your power you could sometimes employ him, &#8211; you would confer a favour upon me by serving a very
               deserving man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffery</ref> &amp; the ER.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Edinburgh Review</title> (1802&#8211;1929), the main Whig quarterly journal.</note> Come in for some tremendous blows in this
               letter. &#8211; I expect also to have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> to append to it,
               addressed to myself. He was included in the attack.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You can have no conception of the <hi rend="ital">devilish</hi> spirit which <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> has raised &amp; left behind him in Westmorland. It has <del>xxx xxx</del>
               shocked many of his own party.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You want some German in the Review &#8211; &amp; I can help you to some. Here is a neighbour of mine perfectly competent to
               give you an able &amp; philosophical criticism upon Schillers works, if you will send the collected edition to <ref type="m" target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">Thomas de Quincey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref>
          <ref type="m" target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> near <ref type="m" target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">De Quincey did not review the works of Johann Christoph Friedrich von Schiller (1759&#8211;1805) for the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I have been talking to him this day upon the subject. He is a man of singular acuteness
               &amp; ability.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Evelyns Memoirs<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Memoirs, Illustrative of the Life and
                     Writings of John Evelyn</title> appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> (1818), 19 (April 1818), 1&#8211;54. He did not write
                  an article on the reign of Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; King of England 1660&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>).</note> would assist in furnishing
               materials for an Essay of great pith &amp; moment upon the reign of Charles 2. &amp; the spirit of that age. &#8211; But my next paper must
               be the New Churches &amp; the Catacombs, &#8211; easily &amp; naturally connected.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of
                  Haydon, <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title>
                  (1818) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;591. His review &#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217; appeared
                  in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a book upon Nonconformity lying for me at your house, &#8211; written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Conder</ref> the bookseller,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Josiah Conder, <title>On
                     Protestant Nonconformity</title> (1818).</note> &#8211; let it come in the next parcel &#8211; I shall have occasion to touch upon it in my
               life of Wesley.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism
                  </title>(1820).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What if I were to make a life of Marlbrough for the Review from <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoxeWilliam">Coxes</ref> book?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke of
                     Marlborough, with his Original Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other Authentic Sources.
                     Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818-1819) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (May
                  1820), 1&#8211;73.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-07-21">21. July 1818</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I shall not fail in the Copyright question<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on the &#8216;Inquiry
                     into the Copyright Act&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;213, responding to the Report of the House of
                     Commons Select Committee that investigated the Copyright Act (1814) in 1818.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>