<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2976</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4247</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2976. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 13 April 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2976" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2976.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 259&#8211;261 [in
                  part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2976" type="letter">
        <head>2976. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1817-04-13">13 April 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Norton/ near/
                  Warrington<lb /> Endorsement: 19 April<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 259&#8211;261 [in
                  part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I would take reproof from you as a dog does blows from his master; &#8211; which same dog if he were struck by a stranger
               would make his teeth meet in the calf of his leg. The first proof of my Letter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Letter
                     to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817).</note> arrived this evening. I shall not return it till the conclusion arrives,
               &amp; till I hear whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> object to any expression which it contains, &#8211; the proofs would have {been}
               sent to you also if there had been time. The strongest passage in it stands thus. After quoting a sentence from the Register about
               looking backward at evening for the sun because there it had been seen &amp; worshipped at its uprise &#8220;I on the contrary altered my
               position as the world went round. For so doing <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Mr W S.</ref> is said to have insulted
               me with the appellation of Renegado, &amp; if it be indeed true that the foul aspersion past his lips, I brand him for it on the
               forehead with the name of Slanderer. Salve the mark as you will sir, it is uneffaceable. You must bear it with you to your Grave, &amp;
               the remembrance of it will outlast your Epitaph.&#8221;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq.,
                     M.P.</title> (London, 1817), p. 28. Southey&#8217;s quotation was from his own words in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 23.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> repeated this
               passage to a brother of Lockhart the Member,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Lockhart (1763&#8211;1852), retired banker and
                  mathematician, who lived near Windermere; his younger brother was John Ingram Lockhart (1766&#8211;1835), MP for Oxford 1807&#8211;1818,
                  1820&#8211;1830.</note> who replied that he knew <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith</ref> well
               &amp; that a duel must be the consequence. &#8211; The thought had not entered into my head otherwise than as a vindictive feeling; &#8211; but
               then I took care to <del>xxxx</del> {write} in a subsequent part as follows &#8220;Such <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Mr
                  WS.</ref> are the opinions of the man whom you have traduced. Had you read his works you could not have mistaken them. <del>X</del>
               &amp; I am willing to believe that if you had done this &amp; found your opinions for yourself instead of taking those of wretches
                  (<ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</ref> to
               wit) who are libellers by trade, &amp; live by sedition &amp; slander you would neither have been so far forgetful of your
               parliamentary character, nor of the decencies which <del>are</del> {is} due from man to man &amp; in such a place &amp; in such a
               manner to have attacked one who had given you no provocation. How Sir did you expect that the affair would end? Did you take the step
               in full knowledge that the man whom you were injuring knew his duty towards God &amp; man too well to violate upon any provocation the
               laws of both? or did you suppose that he would demand what the world is pleased to call satisfaction? &amp; <del>xxxx xxxxx</del>
               Perhaps Sir you would have waived your privilege, aimed at the life of him whose reputation you had attempted to stain &amp; exposed
               your own in a quarrel wherein you knew yourself to be wilfully &amp; wantonly the aggressor. I shall not put you to the trial. Your
               estates &amp; your distillery would remain for your family, &amp; the bells of Norwich would ring as merrily <del>for</del> {at} your
               successors election as they had done at yours. My place in the world would not be so easily filled, even if I were actuated by no
               higher ends <del>xxx</del> considerations.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>
                  (London, 1817), pp. 42&#8211;43. In the published version the whole passage following &#8216;How Sir did you expect ..&#8217; was omitted.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot tell what you may think of this, &#8211; but there are no other passages concerning which I feel any doubt of your
               acquiescence in their fitness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you not see that the charge of my speaking acrimoniously against persons for thinking as I once thought is
               ridiculously false? Against whom are the strong expressions used, to which you refer in the Q R and the Registers. Against the rank
               Buonapartists, <del>when I</del> with whom I had never any more resemblance than I have with the worshippers of the Devil in Africa;
               and against those who, without actually favouring him as Whitbread<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey regularly denounced
                  the radical MP, Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), for his opposition to the war in Spain, e.g. <title>Edinburgh
                     Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 303 and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813),
                  295&#8211;296.</note> did, nevertheless thought it hopeless to make our stand against him on that ground where we had every possible
               advantage? And for the Jacobin writers of the day, &#8211; in what have I ever resembled them? Did I ever address myself to the base and
               malignant feelings of the rabble? &amp; season falsehood &amp; sedition with slander &amp; impiety? &#8211; It is perfectly {true} that I
               thought the party who uniformly predicted our failure in Spain to be ignorant,*<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">* The paper in
                  the QR is directed against the E Review, whose words are quoted to justify the epithets. [Southey&#8217;s note.] [Editor&#8217;s note: Possibly
                  a reference to Southey&#8217;s article, &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title> 16 (October 1816), 241, where Southey
                  quoted the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> 14 (April 1809), 262 on the unreasonableness of Spanish dislike of the French occupying
                  forces in 1808&#8211;1813.]</note> &amp; pusillanimous, &amp; presumptuous, &#8211; surely surely their own words which are given in the
               Register prove them to have been so. Can you have forgotten in 1809&#8211;10 how those persons who thought with me that there was reasonable
               ground for hope &amp; perseverance were insulted as idiots, &amp; laughed <del>xxx</del> to scorn. For my own part I never doubted of
               success, &amp; proud I am that the reasons upon which my confidence was founded were recorded at the time. Had you been in power you
               would have thought otherwise {than as you did} because you would have known more of the state of Europe. Arms were sent from this
               country to Prussia as early as the autumn of 1811. &#8211; Believe me the terms in which I have spoken of the peace-party are milk &amp;
               water compared to what I have seen among the papers with which I have been intrusted. But enough of this. -</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you saw me now you would not think otherwise of my temper under affliction<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  reference to the death of Southey&#8217;s son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, on 17 April 1816.</note>
               than you did in the summer. I have never in the slightest degree yielded to grief, &#8211; but my spirits have not recovered nor do I think
               they ever will recover their elasticity. The world is no longer the same to me, &#8211; you cannot conceive the change in my occupations
               &amp; enjoyments, &#8211; no person who had not seen what my way of life was <hi rend="ital">can</hi> conceive how they were linked with his
               life. But be assured that I look habitually for comfort where it is to be found.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I shall be in town on the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref>&#8217;s, and leave it on the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> of May.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-04-13">13 April 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>