<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">7. Overview of the Rydal Journals
                </title>
                
                
                <!-- DW will be the author for the "reading texts" because she is a historical figure, change role to "primary" -->
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Nick Mason</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Nick Mason</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.RJ-1-overview</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">7. Overview of the Rydal Journals
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.RJ-1-overview"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">Lake District</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">landscape</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">mapping</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">travel</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">walking</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">women writers</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-01-27</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
            <head>7. Overview of the <title level="m">Rydal Journals</title><lb/>
                <hi rend="small">Nicholas Mason</hi></head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Nicholas mason</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Brigham Young University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dorothy&#8217;s Forgotten Diaries</hi><lb/>
                Despite Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s having long ago joined the pantheon of English diarists,
                her most sustained effort in the genre, the fifteen compact notebooks from 1824&#8211;35
                generally identified as the <title level="m">Rydal Journals</title> (<title level="m">RJ</title>), 
                remains largely unpublished and virtually unknown outside specialized academic circles. While
                several of the more striking passages from these journals have been referenced in the occasional
                biography or scholarly article, only one short segment&#8212;a three-week stretch chronicling her
                1828 trip to the Isle of Man&#8212;has appeared in its entirety.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">William Knight published the first two weeks of DW&#8217;s Isle of Man tour in his 1889 <title level="m">Life of William
                     Wordsworth</title> and later reprinted these excerpts in his 1897 edition of DW&#8217;s journals (Knight, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, 3:140&#8211;49; 
                     <hi rend="italic">KJ</hi>, 2:277&#8211;82). Two generations later, Ernest De Sélincourt included the entire tour in vol. 2 of <title level="m">DWJ</title>.
                     </note>
                Accordingly, this concluding section of <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Lake 
                District</title> marks an important first step toward rectifying this problem, as it
                features complete transcriptions of the first and last volumes (Notebooks 1 and 15)
                of what proved to be the last great endeavor of Dorothy’s writing career.
            </p>
                
            <p>Paradoxically, one of Dorothy&#8217;s foremost champions, the early twentieth-century
                Oxford don Ernest De Sélincourt, is perhaps most culpable for consigning the
                <title level="m">RJ</title> to obscurity. For in both his landmark study of her life
                (1933) and his two-volume edition of her journals (1941), De Sélincourt categorically
                dismissed the <title level="m">RJ</title> as &#8220;eleven shabby little notebooks,&#8221;
                calling them &#8220;wholly capricious&#8221; in design and displaying &#8220;little of
                the character of the Alfoxden or Grasmere Journals.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Eight years after disparaging the <title level="m">RJ</title> in his 1933 biography, De
                     Sélincourt recycled many of his remarks verbatim in the introduction to <title level="m">DWJ</title> (<title level="m">DWB</title>,
                     368; <title level="m">DWJ</title>, 1: xviii&#8211;xix). A half-century later, his erroneous description of the
                     <title level="m">RJ</title> notebooks&#8212;which are, in fact, fifteen in number and remarkably well preserved&#8212;received
                     new life when, without citing their obvious source, Gittings and Manton described DW&#8217;s later diaries as &#8220;eleven worn
                     and shabby notebooks&#8221; (242).</note>
                To justify how, in a collection putatively featuring all of Dorothy&#8217;s journals, he
                included just a tiny fraction of the <title level="m">RJ</title>, he somewhat feebly
                asserted that the Isle of Man tour is &#8220;the only portion written in consecutive
                style, as a journal rather than a mere diary.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">DWJ</title>, 1:xix.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>While assertions like these have undoubtedly suppressed interest in the 
                <title level="m">RJ</title>, numerous researchers and enthusiasts have nonetheless
                made pilgrimages to Grasmere to study the original notebooks at the Wordsworth
                Trust. In the 1970s Carl Ketcham transcribed roughly 20% of the
                <title level="m">RJ</title> and then summarized his findings in a
                lengthy article published in <title level="m">The Wordsworth Circle</title>
                in 1978.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Ketcham, <title level="a">Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Journals.</title> Ketcham&#8217;s partial transcription, which his
                     family donated to the Wordsworth Trust upon his passing in 1991, proved immensely helpful during the early stages of this project, when we were
                     still learning to decipher DW&#8217;s handwriting.</note>
                Where he, like many Wordsworthians of his generation, turned to Dorothy&#8217;s
                journals primarily for insights into the life and works of her famous brother,
                subsequent scholars have firmly reinstalled Dorothy at the center of the
                <title level="m">RJ</title> narrative. In an important 2015 article on
                <title level="a">Dorothy Wordsworth and Old Age,</title> for instance, Pamela Woof
                offered what was at the time the most thorough engagement with these later notebooks
                since Ketcham&#8217;s essay. And, in 2021, a pair of writers based three radically
                different books on the <title level="m">RJ</title>: a historical novel on Dorothy&#8217;s
                final years (Kathleen Winter&#8217;s <title level="m">Undersong</title>), a poetry 
                collection on themes of ageing and illness (Polly Atkin&#8217;s <title level="m">Much 
                with Body</title>), and an alternative biography incorporating perspectives from
                disability studies (Atkin&#8217;s <title level="m">Recovering Dorothy</title>).
            </p>
                
            <p>That, in order to write about the journals, each of these researchers had to
                independently copy out those portions that pertained to their interests underscores
                the need for a reliable and readily accessible transcription of all fifteen volumes
                of the <title level="m">RJ</title>. While such an undertaking is beyond the scope of
                this edition, we are excited to make available for the first time fully annotated
                and contextualized transcriptions of Notebooks 1 and 15. These bookend volumes of
                the <title level="m">RJ</title> cover dramatically different life stages, the one a
                period of robust health and the other of increasing infirmity. Yet they share both a
                setting (Rydal Mount and its environs) and an abiding emphasis on Dorothy’s love for
                the people and landscapes of her native region.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">While, as the name implies, nine volumes of the <title level="m">RJ</title> (Notebooks 1, 5&#8211;7, and 11&#8211;15)
                    are set in and around Rydal, the remaining six chronicle extended trips DW made in the late 1820s to the Midlands (Notebooks 2&#8211;4), Halifax (parts of
                    Notebooks 6 and 10), the Isle of Man (Notebook 8 and part of Notebook 9), and Leicestershire (much of Notebook 10).</note>
                Notebook 1 spans December 1824 through December 1825, capturing the daily routines of
                an unusually vibrant 53-year-old who clearly relished a new phase with fewer domestic
                responsibilities, relative financial security, and a large circle of friends within
                walking distance of home. Notebook 15, by contrast, chronicles a comparatively
                dispiriting six-month period of late 1834 and early 1835, when, having survived
                several recent brushes with death, Dorothy found her experience narrowed to her
                memories and what she could see or hear from her upstairs bedroom at Rydal Mount.
            </p>
                
            <p><hi rend="bold">The Text of the <title level="m">Rydal Journals</title></hi><lb/>
                The typical <title level="m">RJ </title>entry consists of three or four succinct,
                allusive, and fragmentary descriptions written in the slapdash hand that Dorothy 
                often called &#8220;my scrawl.&#8221; While full of compelling observations and
                vibrant descriptions, the <title level="m">RJ</title> are considerably more prone
                than the <title level="m">GJ</title> to lapsing into bare-bones accounts of the
                weather, the day&#8217;s events, and the health of Dorothy&#8217;s housemates.
                This &#8220;sparser&#8221; style of the later journals has prompted Lucy Newlyn to
                conjecture that their &#8220;main purpose was to serve as a rudimentary mnemonic
                device&#8221; or perhaps as a &#8220;mood-diary.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Newlyn, 271&#8211;72.</note>
                For his part, Ketcham discerns a subtle artistry in Dorothy&#8217;s &#8220;customary
                brevity,&#8221; remarking that the finest entries in the <title level="m">RJ</title>
                combine &#8220;a vivid, staccato
                impressionism with the awareness of underlying unity.&#8220;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Ketcham, &#8220;Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Journals,&#8221; 4. Woof has also repeatedly referenced the
                    &#8220;staccato&#8221; style of DW&#8217;s entries (<hi rend="italic">GJ</hi>, ix; <title level="a">Dorothy Wordsworth and Old
                    Age,</title> 157).</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>In keeping with her former practice, Dorothy typically composed several entries in
                one sitting rather than writing in her journal every night, and she continued to
                have no compunctions about using the same notebook as a journal, commonplace book,
                and expense ledger.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">For the mixed uses of DW&#8217;s earlier notebooks, see Woof, &#8220;Dorothy
                    Wordsworth&#8217;s Grasmere Journals,&#8221; 173&#8211;74. For the degree to which this was common practice during this era,
                    see Bellanca, <title level="m">Daybooks of Discovery</title>, 11&#8211;14.</note>
                Yet, whereas the <title level="m">GJ</title> was explicitly written for her brother
                William and a few close friends and relations, the <title level="m">RJ</title> seem
                to have been intended solely for Dorothy&#8217;s own benefit. Alternations and emendations
                in these journals consistently appear in the same shade of ink and quality of pen as the
                original entry, suggesting that Dorothy almost invariably corrected her prose as she
                wrote rather than in some later round of dedicated revision. In consequence, this
                section varies from other parts of this edition in only noting those textual
                variants or irregularities that might offer fresh perspectives into Dorothy’s
                writing process. Above all, our priority has been to provide clean and accurate
                transcriptions that faithfully preserve Dorothy’s final wording, spelling, and
                punctuation.
            </p>
                
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER"/>
                    <figDesc><hi rend="bold">Figure 1:</hi> Page from Notebook 15 (covering 8&#8211;12 November 1834) showing the quality
                     of handwriting and types of revisions typically found in the <title level="m">RJ</title>.
                    </figDesc>
                </figure>
                
            <p>After countless passes through the original manuscripts, we have become sufficiently
                familiar with Dorothy&#8217;s handwriting, diction, and orthography to now be able to
                offer confident transcriptions of over 95% of the text. Where our transcription
                remains tentative, we enclose the elusive word or phrase in editorial brackets and
                add a question mark (e.g., [night?]). If unable or unwilling to hazard a tentative
                transcription, we use an empty set of editorial brackets ([ ]) to mark each
                illegible word. Dorothy&#8217;s idiosyncratic punctuation poses a different set of
                challenges, as she routinely omits apostrophes in possessives (e.g., &#8220;Marys
                book&#8221;), treats line breaks as a substitute for end punctuation, and does little to
                distinguish her short dashes from her commas and periods. While careful to retain
                her punctuation, we have provided clarifying punctuation marks, always placing them
                inside editorial brackets (e.g., Mary[&#8217;]s book), as needed.
            </p>
                
            <p>Since even a clean transcription of the
                <title level="m">RJ</title> can be opaque without some knowledge of the people,
                places, and events being described, we preface both notebooks with a
                brief introduction and an extensive biographical index covering individuals who
                appear most frequently therein. And within the text of the journals, we supply
                scores of hypertext annotations in hopes of helping readers have an even more
                engaging experience with Dorothy&#8217;s remarkable accounts of life in Rydal 
                in the 1820s and 1830s.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
