<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Untitled Document</title>
                <author>Nicholas Mason</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-12-16T23:50:00</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>no publication statement available</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><name>Lavender Earnest</name><date>2022-12-31T18:53:00</date></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="color(#000000)bold">Introduction to Notebook 15 of the
                    </hi><hi rend="color(#000000)bold italic">Rydal Journals</hi></p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="color(#000000)bold">(DCMS 118.5, </hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)bold">4 October 1834—19 April 1835, 4 November
                1835)</hi></p>
            <p>When, in October 1834, Dorothy Wordsworth began what would prove the last volume of
                her <hi rend="italic">Rydal Journals </hi>(<hi rend="italic">RJ</hi>), she already
                seemed on borrowed time, having repeatedly been on deathwatch since falling
                seriously ill in April 1829. Her survival was, in part, a testament to the devoted
                care of her <hi rend="color(#000000)">physician, Thomas Carr, and </hi>her family,
                including her brother William, whose daily routine in 1833 included reading to her,
                massaging her swollen feet, and, weather permitting, wheeling her into the garden
                (fig. 1).<note xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1">
                    <hi rend="italic">Barker</hi>, 646–48.</note> While Dorothy’s condition was no
                longer critical during the six-month span (October 1834–April 1835) at the center of
                Notebook 15, she remained largely confined to her upstairs bedroom at Rydal Mount. </p>
            <p rend="center"><figure><graphic
                        url="Pictures/100000000000025800000175EBA236DE4C97F926.jpg"/>A picture
                    containing text, book Description automatically generated</figure></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: </hi>John Harden, <hi rend="italic">Dorothy Wordsworth in a
                    Wheelchair</hi> (pen and ink on paper, 25 August 1842). The artist, a longtime
                friend and neighbor of the Wordsworths, wrote beneath this sketch, “Recollection of
                Jessie’s &amp; my visit R[yda]l M[oun]t &amp; interview with poor Miss W—.” The
                Jessie who accompanied him was not his wife (who had died in 1837) but his youngest
                daughter. (Courtesy: Lakeland Arts/Bridgeman Education)</p>
            <p>The prevailing norm for interpreting—or, perhaps more accurately, disregarding—the
                two decades between the close of the <hi rend="italic">RJ </hi>in 1835 and Dorothy’s
                death in 1855 was established by Ernest De Sélincourt in 1933, when he asserted that
                “the last twenty years of posthumous life . . . only belong to the biography of
                Dorothy Wordsworth in so far as they reveal in fitful gleams something of what she
                once had been.”<note xml:id="ftn2" place="foot" n="2">
                    <hi rend="italic">DWB</hi>, 394.</note> While subsequent biographers have
                devoted more space to diagnosing Dorothy’s medical condition—variously speculating
                that suffered from gallstones, arteriosclerosis, “pre-senile dementia of a type
                similar to Alzheimer’s disease,” or “depressive pseudo-dementia, a condition in
                which severe depression mimics the symptoms of dementia”<note xml:id="ftn3"
                    place="foot" n="3"> Newlyn, 275; Gittings, 271, 282–83; Wilson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ballad of Dorothy Wordsworth</hi>, 281.</note>—they have
                largely followed De Sélincourt’s lead in taking the period covered by Notebook 15 as
                a harrowing transition into Dorothy’s “posthumous life.” With growing sensitivity in
                literary studies toward ageing and disability, however, this pattern might be
                changing. Polly Atkin’s recent book <hi rend="italic">Recovering Dorothy</hi>
                (2021), in particular, offers an overdue corrective to the longstanding impulse to
                dismiss her final decades. Noting how “Dorothy Wordsworth’s biographers have had a
                peculiar predilection for killing her long before her death,” Atkin sets out “to
                shine a light into the darkness and restore the rest of Dorothy’s narrative.” Quite
                simply, she insists, Dorothy “did not die, emotionally or otherwise, until 1855. She
                did not vanish. She was not undone. She may have changed, as we all do, in sickness
                and in health, but she was still Dorothy.”<note xml:id="ftn4" place="foot" n="4">
                    Atkin, <hi rend="italic">Recovering Dorothy</hi>, 6, 8.</note></p>
            <p>Of course, there is no disputing that Dorothy’s health was never again as robust
                after she was stricken with cholera or some other disease in early 1829; and, if
                read in isolation, Notebook 15 might be taken as proof of her gradual physical and
                mental decline. Shaky handwriting, ink spills, crossings-out, and basic errors
                proliferate as the volume draws to a close, and signs of what seems an increasingly
                circumscribed and dreary existence appear at every turn. On the “dull, dark &amp;
                cold” tenth day of February 1835, for instance, Dorothy writes, “My limbs unusually
                weak. With difficulty I went to window &amp; back.” A month later, on 15 March, she
                laments, “<hi rend="color(#000000)">The greatest evil attending my present
                    disordered state is that I can read or work little or none.” For every simple
                    pleasure, such as her “companion Robin,” the bird who </hi>frequents her
                windowsill throughout the autumn of 1834, there seems a counterbalancing threat,
                like the new cat at Rydal Mount that leaves Dorothy in terror about the bird’s
                safety.</p>
            <p>Seemingly further support for a narrative of steady decline comes in Dorothy’s
                concluding entry of 4 November 1835. Since having last written in her journal on 19
                April, she had grown too “dreadfully weak and languid” to write, and her mental
                health had further plummeted after the shock of Sara Hutchinson’s sudden passing on
                23 June.<note xml:id="ftn5" place="foot" n="5">
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 6:51, 78.</note> Yet, resolved to return to her
                decade-long habit of recording her daily activities, she “[took] up the pen once
                again.” The pathos of the final entry that follows emanates, in part, from its
                inaccuracies—she gives the year as 1815 (not 1835) and seems to have been confused
                about her nephew John’s recent whereabouts—and also from its ending with the double
                negative “Dora not unwell,” as if asserting that to be “not unwell” is all one might
                reasonably hope for in this life (see fig. 2). The most heartbreaking aspect of this
                entry, however, is its isolation on the journal’s last page, as, after having
                mustered the strength to resume her journal, Dorothy could eke out but a single
                entry before needing to set it aside for good.</p>
            <p rend="center"><figure><graphic
                        url="Pictures/1000000000000174000002519E07191C60695105.jpg"/>Text, letter
                    Description automatically generated</figure></p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Figure 2: </hi>The final entry in Notebook 15
                (Courtesy: Wordsworth Trust)</p>
            <p>Writing in his own journal two months later, Dorothy’s friend Henry Crabb Robinson
                would attest to the severity of her physical decline. Two years had passed since
                Robinson’s last visit to Rydal, and he was obviously rattled to find on 2 January
                1836 that, even in what was said to be “her best state,” Dorothy paid little heed to
                his presence and “went on repeating without intermission fragments of poetry—her
                brother’s, Cowper’s, Dr. Watts’s—then repeating the Doxology, and the most
                melancholy act of all, carried away by the association of ideas, repeating the Amen
                in a loud tone and mocking a clerk accompanied by loud laughter.”<note xml:id="ftn6"
                    place="foot" n="6"> Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Henry Crabb Robinson on
                        Books</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>2:477.</note> Were one to stop reading
                there, this might seem unimpeachable proof of her ongoing deterioration; but
                continuing just a few pages further, we find Robinson rejoicing on 31 January at
                having found her “much calmer and reasonable.” Dorothy “sang some of her brother’s
                poems,” he reports, and “she evidently knew me, and was not irrational in anything
                she said.”<note xml:id="ftn7" place="foot" n="7"> Robinson, <hi rend="italic">Henry
                        Crabb Robinson on Books</hi>, 2:487.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That this was not merely a momentary rebound is suggested by a remarkably lucid and
                witty letter that Dorothy sent Christopher Wordsworth Jr. a few weeks after
                Robinson’s visit. Playfully greeting her 28-year-old nephew as a “public Orator”
                often summoned “to speak in the presence of Kings, Princes and Bishops,” she
                explains she is writing because Christopher’s “uncle, the Poet of the Lakes, has
                been deputed” to speak at the groundbreaking for a new seminary, but “alas! the poet
                is no Orator and he knows not what to say on this important occasion.” Rushing to
                her brother’s aid, she merrily entreats her nephew, as “the first Orator of the
                Nation,” to “make a speech for [William] which I will answer for it he will
                pronounce verbatim.” Dorothy concludes by announcing her intention “to see you all
                at Cambridge in summer,” sanguinely reporting, “I have got through a mighty
                struggle, and thank God am now as well as ever I was in my life except that I have
                not recovered the use of my legs. My Arms have been active enough as the torn caps
                of my nurses and the heavy blows I have given their heads and faces will
                    testify.”<note xml:id="ftn8" place="foot" n="8">
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 6:188–89.</note></p>
            <p>Clearly, then, as Pamela Woof has written, “even in these final years there was more
                than imbecility to Dorothy Wordsworth; there are glimpses of what De Quincey calls
                her ‘very originality’ . . . in the later letters, verses and journals.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn9" place="foot" n="9"> Woof, “Dorothy Wordsworth and Old Age,”
                    175.</note> Recognizing as much offers an important check upon any temptation to
                reduce the whole of Notebook 15 to a tale of her physical and mental slide. It
                invites us to balance Dorothy’s recurring complaints over the deaths of several dear
                friends, her own debilitating maladies, and dispiriting political news from
                Westminster with other moments when she exudes her trademark optimism and zest for
                life. The series of entries she wrote as 1834 rolled over into 1835, for instance,
                are among the most affecting and exuberant in the whole of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >RJ</hi>. In her entry for 30 December, she describes how “<hi
                    rend="color(#000000)">W</hi><hi rend="sup color(#000000)">m</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> came to me rejoiced to hear thickly pattering rain after
                    so long a pause – I could not but feel a touch of sympathy with him in
                    remembrance of many a moist tramp; but sh[oul]d have been better pleased with
                    bright moon &amp; stars, &amp; our late splendid evenings &amp; mornings.” Two
                    days later, after noting the “</hi>Lovely sun-rise &amp; set,” she rhapsodizes,
                “Never surely in the 63 years that I have lived can there have been such brilliant
                New-years &amp; Christmas days.” And, in the same elevated strain, she writes on 2
                January, “Another year begun! and what a brilliant sun-rise<hi rend="color(#000000)"
                    > –</hi> Oh! that men’s hearts could be <hi rend="underline">softened</hi>!<hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> –</hi> then elevated by the goodness &amp; beauty of all
                that is done for &amp; spread before us!” </p>
            <p>Elsewhere, Notebook 15 paints a portrait of long days and nights in a sickroom,
                where, when well enough, Dorothy read newspapers and religious books, made rugs for
                friends, and welcomed visits from well-wishers. While the entries at the start of
                this volume show her reading voraciously, her stamina had waned by February 1835 to
                the point that she had become reliant on her goddaughter (and regular companion)
                Ebba Hutchinson reading to her aloud. Wary, no doubt, of the addiction that had
                plagued her friends Coleridge and De Quincey, Dorothy took to assiduously logging
                each time she opened a new bottle of laudanum, and—in what should prove a remarkable
                trove for historians of medicine—she details treatments including the bleeding and
                blistering regimens endured by her niece Dora and her own use of Morrison’s Pills,
                arrowroot biscuits, and divers concoctions prepared by her faithful attendant Mr.
                Carr. Especially amid the political tumult surrounding the general election of early
                1835, Dorothy’s mood seems to have risen and fallen depending of how successful the
                Tories had been in staving off Whig offensives. Such is the case near the end of
                Notebook 15, when, in her <hi rend="color(#000000)">entry for 30 March 1835, she
                    initially expresses pleasure that the Wordsworths’ new neighbor Dr. Thomas
                    Arnold would be bringing to his family to the Lakes for Easter before
                    remembering that the last visit of this “active zealous Doctor” had been “to
                    vote for a Destructive Member” in the parliamentary election—a trip that, as she
                    wryly and triumphantly notes, was “Happily not successful.”</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
