<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3363</idno><idno type="nines">rce4634</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3363. Robert Southey to Neville White [fragment], 14 October 1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3363.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text
						is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
						(London, 1849–1850) .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 357–359 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3363" type="letter"><head>3363. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> [fragment],<date when="1819-10-14"> 14 October 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text
						is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
						(London, 1849–1850)<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 357–359 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1819-10-14">Oct. 14. 1819.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear
						Neville,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You need not be warned to remember that all other considerations ought to give way to that of
						health.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">White had taken the decision to give up his work in the hosiery
						trade and pursue a clerical career. He enrolled at Peterhouse, Cambridge, on 26 June 1819 to study for a Bachelor
						of Divinity degree as a ‘ten-year man’, i.e. a part-time, mature student (he graduated in 1829). However, he was
						more immediately concerned by his ordination examination, which required knowledge of Greek, Latin, works of
						divinity and the Bible. White passed and was ordained as a Deacon on 12 December 1819, becoming a Curate at St
						Edmund the King, Norwich.</note> A man had better break a bone, or even lose a limb, than shake his nervous
					system. I, who never talk about my nerves (and am supposed to have none by persons who see as far into me as they
					do into a stone wall), know this. Take care of yourself; and if you find your spirits fail, put off your
					ordination, and shorten your hours of study; Lord Coke requires only eight hours for a student of the law;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Edward Coke (1552–1634; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Institutes of the Lawes
							of England</title>, 4 vols (London, 1628–1644), I, Book 2, chapter 1, section 85: ‘Sex horas somno, totidem des
						legibus aequis/ Quatuor orabis, des epulisque duas’, which translates as ‘Six hours in sleep, in law’s grave study
						six,/ Four spend on prayer, the rest on nature fix’. Southey had, therefore, overestimated how much studying Coke
						advised. Coke was a leading lawyer who rose to be Chief Justice of the King’s Bench 1613–1616.</note> and Sir
					Matthew Hale thought six hours a day as much as any one could well bear; eight, he said, was too much.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Matthew Hale (1609–1676; <title>DNB</title>). ‘He said that he studied sixteen
						hours a day for the first two years that he came to the Inns of Court, but almost brought himself to his grave,
						though he were of a very strong constitution, and afterwards reduced himself to eight hours; but that he would not
						advise any body to do so much; that he thought six hours a day, with attention and constancy, was sufficient; that
						a man must use his body as he would use his horse and his stomach, not tire him at once, but rise with appetite’,
							<title>The Works, Moral and Religious, of Sir Matthew Hale, Knt.</title>, 2 vols (London, 1805), I, pp. 155–156.
						Hale was a prominent lawyer who rose to be Chief Justice of the King’s Bench 1671–1676.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I was about seven weeks absent from home.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
						toured Scotland from 17 August until 1 October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal of a Tour in
							Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> My route was from Edinburgh, Loch Katrine,
					and thence to Dunkeld and Dundee, up the east coast to Aberdeen, then to Banff and Inverness, and up the coast as
					far as Fleet Mound,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Fleet Mound was a massive causeway, commissioned in
						1803, designed by Telford, and built between 1814–1816, to carry the road over Loch Fleet. It comprised an
						earthwork, and a bridge with self-regulating sluice gates that allowed the waters from the river to flow out, but
						prevented seawater from coming in.</note> which is within sight of the Ord of Caithness. We crossed from Dingwall
					to the Western Sea, returned to Inverness, took the line of the Caledonian Canal, crossed Ballachulish Ferry, and
					so to Inverary, Lochlomond, Glasgow, and home. This took in the greatest and best part of Scotland; and I saw it
					under the most favourable circumstances of weather and season, in the midst of a joyous harvest, and with the best
					opportunities for seeing everything, and obtaining information. I travelled with my old friend<ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn"> Mr. Rickman</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Mr.
						Telford</ref>, the former secretary, and the latter engineer to the two committees for the Caledonian Canal and
					the Highland Roads and Bridges.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman was Secretary to the Commissioners
						for the Caledonian Canal and the Commissioners for Highland Roads and Bridges. Telford was largely responsible for
						surveying and designing these works.</note> They also are the persons upon whom the appropriation of the money
					from the forfeited estates, for improving and creating harbours, has devolved.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Some large Scottish estates were forfeited to the Crown after their owners supported the Jacobite
						rising of 1745. Most of these estates were returned to the descendants of their owners after new legislation in
						1784, but the accumulated profits were used for a series of public works. The remaining balances (about £14,000)
						were transferred to the Commissioners for Highland Roads and Bridges in 1806; they mainly used the money for the
						construction of new harbours at Peterhead, Fraserburgh, Port Gower, Thurso, Helensburgh and Burghead.</note> It
					was truly delightful to see how much Government has done and is doing for the improvement of that part of the
					kingdom, and how much, in consequence of that encouragement, the people are doing for themselves, which they would
					not have been able to do without it.</p><p rend="indent1"> So long an absence involves me, of course, in heavy arrears of business. I have to write half a
					volume of Wesley,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and
							Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> and to prepare a long paper for the Q. R. (a Life of
						Marlborough)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke
							of Marlborough, with his Original Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other
							Authentic Sources. Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818–1819) appeared in
							<title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (May 1820), 1–73.</note> before I can set my face toward London. So I shall
					probably pass the months of February and March in and about town. … A great many Cantabs have been summering here,
					where they go by the odd name of <hi rend="ital">Cathedrals</hi>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Cathedrals’ was the name given in Keswick and its environs to young men from the University of Cambridge who
						visited the Lakes in study parties. It arose, initially, from a ‘comical confusion’ between ‘Collegian’ and
						‘College’ and, later, between ‘College’ and ‘Cathedral’; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 19–20 August
						1821, Letter 3715.</note> Several of them brought introductions to me, and were good specimens of the rising
					generation. … God bless you, my dear Neville!</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R. SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>