<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3651</idno><idno type="nines">rce4922</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3651. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 14 March 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3651.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick
						Museum and Art Gallery, WC 204. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
							the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 235–237 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3651" type="letter"><head>3651. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>,<date when="1821-03-14"> 14 March 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend
						Herbert Hill/ Streatham./ Surry.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: 10 o’Clock/ MR.17/ 1821 F.N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 17 MR 17/ xxxx<lb/> Seal: black wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/> MS: Keswick
						Museum and Art Gallery, WC 204. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
							the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 235–237 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-03-14">14 March. 1821</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I blame myself for not having written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref>
					as soon as I knew you were gone to Bristol. It did not occur to me till I received your letter, – &amp; indeed I
					was not sure that you had not returned, hearing nothing of you either from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, or <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>. If poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> had been living, he would
					have been as he always was, – useful in time of need, always ready to perform any act of service &amp; of kindness.
					If <ref type="m" target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> had received my letter in regular time, he might have
					relieved you of some trouble during the last week of your stay, – a very mournful time you <del>xxx</del> must have
					past – I assure you it was often in my thoughts.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s aunt, and Herbert
						Hill’s half-sister, Elizabeth Tyler had died.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If there be one spot upon this earth that I remember with more feeling than any other, it is
						Ashton,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">All Saints Church, Long Ashton, Somerset, was the burial place of
						Southey’s father and many other relations.</note> such as it was forty years ago, – when those village lanes of
					which you speak were in their beauty. – The first time I ever rode on horseback was when you carried me thither,
					before you, from Bedminster.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of Southey’s maternal grandmother,
						Margaret Hill, née Bradford (1710–1782).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> wrote me a very good letter which
					pleased me very much. Tell him that I shall be glad to hear from him again, whenever he is disposed to write.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Vision<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title>
						(1821).</note> arrived here yesterday. There is a provoking error on the first page, where the printer has
					contrived to drop<del>x</del> the final <hi rend="ital">a</hi> in <del>Glam</del> Glaramar<hi rend="ital">a</hi>.
					And in the extract from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> essay the word <hi rend="ital">ac</hi> has crept in, nonsensically.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of
							Judgement</title> (London, 1821), p. xx; Canto 1, line 9.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has sent you a copy of his volume, which has found its way to
					me, &amp; must wait for an opportunity of conveyance.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor’s
							<title>Idyllia Heroica Decem Phaleuciorum Unum Partim jam Primo Partim Iterum atq Tertio Edit Savagius
							Landor</title> (1820), no. 1598 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Dedication was a good one, but I took an <hi rend="ital">official</hi> opinion concerning its
					etiquette, &amp; in conformity to that opinion, struck out the part which in the form of compliment conveyed a
						<del>political &amp;</del> well-timed warning.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of
							Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Dedication’, pp. [v]–viii. The ‘Dedication’ was controversial, not only
						praising Britain’s victory in the war against France, but stating: ‘The same perfect integrity has been manifested
						in the whole administration of public affairs’ (vi); not a view the Whig opposition endorsed. However, the earlier
						draft of the ‘Dedication’, in Huntington Library, San Marino, HM 2733, shows Southey had intended to go much
						further and urge that ‘adequate remedy should be applied to that intolerable licentiousness of the press … either
						by the vigorous application of existing laws or by the enactment of such new ones as the suspension of the abuse
						may render necessary’. Southey cut out these references after consulting Bedford and Herries.</note> The metre
					will probably attract <del>notx</del> some notice, &amp; possibly occasion some discussion <hi rend="ital">pro</hi>
					&amp; <hi rend="ital">con</hi>: the subject will provoke some abuse, to which I am perfectly indifferent. I do not
					expect that more than 500 copies will sell, but I am glad <del>that</del> the experiment has been made.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The first edition of <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821) only consisted of 500
						copies; Longman did not produce a second edition.</note> It was my intention to have printed two Odes with it; but
					finding that there was no want of <hi rend="ital">eking</hi>, &amp; <del>xxxx</del> knowing that short lines on a
					quarto page would have looked ridiculous, if printed in the same type as the hexameters, I laid them aside.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Warning Voice. Ode I’ and ‘The Warning Voice. Ode II’, the New Year’s Odes
						for 1820 and 1821, were not published until they appeared in <title>The Englishman’s Library: Comprising a Series
							of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (London, 1824), pp. 381–389. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> Lope de Aguirre’s adventures are gone to the printer, with considerable additions, such as were
					necessary to make the story compleat when it appeared as a separate publication.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821), originally
						intended to be part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) and first published in <title>Edinburgh
							Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i–l.</note> It will form one volume like the Life of Nelson,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Expedition of Orsua</title> (1821) was printed in duodecimo, like
						the second edition of Southey’s <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1814).</note> in the small size. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> printer proceeds very slowly with the history – I have corrected
					only 13 sheets.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
						(1823–1832), printed by Thomas Davison (1766–1831).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Correio Braziliense<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">London-based liberal journal
							<title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808–1822). Southey owned a complete set, no. 3203 in the sale catalogue of
						his library.</note> is now become an interesting work. My only hope for Portugal was that Ucalegons house<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Ucalegon was an elder of Troy, whose house was set on fire by the Greeks,
						Virgil (70–19 BC), <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 2, lines 311–312. The term became a common way of referring to a
						neighbour whose house was on fire – in this case, Portugal’s neighbour, Spain.</note> might be burnt to the
					ground, before the flames extended there. Ferdinand<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII
						(1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833). After an army revolt in January 1820, he had accepted the liberal
						Constitution of 1812 and was at this time virtually a prisoner.</note> I think can hardly escape death, – &amp;
					Spain will be from one sea to another the seat of a <hi rend="ital">Spanish</hi> civil war, which will be <hi rend="ital">plusquam civile</hi><note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">‘more than civil’.</note> with a
					vengeance. What will become of Portugal I cannot conjecture, – but it appears very likely that <del>betw</del> the
					poor King between his two stools will come to the ground.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI
						(1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826) had fled to Brazil following the French invasion of 1807. A liberal
						revolution in Portugal in August 1820 led to demands for his return to Europe to which he eventually acquiesced in
						July 1821. This led ultimately to Brazil’s declaration of independence in 1822.</note> To days paper brings news
					of the explosion at Para.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The liberal revolution in Portugal produced a
						number of sympathetic military revolts in Brazil; one in the Province of Para was reported in <title>The
							Times</title>, 13 March 1821.</note> The sure effect of revolution in Brazil will be to divide that country among
					as many <del>ruff</del> Artigases &amp; Aguirres<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">José Gervasio Artigas
						(1764–1850) had fought to create a Uruguayan state independent of Argentina and Brazil in 1816–1820; Lope de
						Aguirre (c. 1510–1561) had tried to create an independent state in Peru. However, Brazil did not disintegrate when
						it became independent in 1822.</note> as have ability to keep a regiment of ruffians together. I do not see what
					can save the interior from this: – &amp; the great maritime cities will probably run the same course as B
						Ayres.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Argentina was in a constant state of warfare and tension between
						centralists, based in Buenos Aires, and federalists from outlying provinces.</note> The end of these things I
					shall not live to see. But I have a good deal to say upon the prospects of Society, which I shall bring forward in
					my Colloquies.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and
							Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Did I tell you that two translations of Roderick have been published at Paris – &amp; a third is
					talked of. One of them has been sent me.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Translations of Southey’s
							<title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814) by Pierre Hippolyte Amillet de Sagrie (1785–1830),
							<title>Roderic, Dernier Roi des Goths</title> (1821), no. 2700 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library and
						Antoine André Brugière, Baron de Sorsum, <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title> (1820), no. 2697 in the
						sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey had been sent the first of these translations. The third translation
						was probably the material relating to <title>Roderick</title> in Abel Hugo (1798–1855), <title>Romances
							Historiques Traduites de l’Espagnol</title> (Paris, 1822), pp. 1–32.</note> If I wished to <del>teach</del>
					&lt;show&gt; any young poet what images &amp; expressions in the poem had any peculiar propriety, it might be done
					by telling him to mark every thing which the translator had either generalized, or skipt.</p><p rend="indent1"> We are tolerably well. I have a pitch plaister on my shoulder &amp; arm for what they tell me is
					rheumatism, tho I suspected a strain. It disables me from lateral motions <del>of</del> with the right arm, but is
					not otherwise inconvenient. Our weather has been &amp; is delightful. I shall be anxious to hear that you have
					recovered from your fatigue &amp; anxiety. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>
					&amp; the children – God bless you. RS.</p></div></body></text></TEI>