<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3584</idno><idno type="nines">rce4855</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3584. Robert Southey to John Abraham Heraud, 16 December
                  1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3584.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Edith Heraud, Memoirs of
                     John A. Heraud (London, 1898) .  Previously  published: Edith Heraud, Memoirs of John A. Heraud (London,
                  1898), pp. 19–22.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3584" type="letter"><head>3584. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>, <date when="1820-12-16">16 December
                  1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of
                     John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898)<lb/> Previously published: Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London,
                  1898), pp. 19–22.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1820-12-16">16<hi rend="ital">th Dec.</hi> 1820.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent0"> My dear Sir, – You will think that I am damping your hopes, because I tell you that they must be tamed and broken-in to
               the uses of the world.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to John Abraham Heraud, 8 December 1820, Letter 3578.</note>
               ‘The service of the Muses,’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a quotation from Heraud’s letter to Southey, which is
                  untraced.</note> to which you would devote yourself, is in reality very unlike what it appears to a youthful imagination. Their yoke
               is not easy, neither is their burthen light. Believe me, when I tell you that of all modes of life, that of the man who trusts to his
               literary exertions alone for support is the most miserable. And the very end at which he aims in his outset – that of improving and
               exalting his intellectual faculties – is most effectually defeated by the means which he pursues. They are worn and jaded by the daily
               labour to which they must be subjected; and they are inevitably degraded and polluted by the necessity of writing for immediate effect
               and sale, and consequently of following the humour of the times. Poetry will be the delight of your life if you cultivate it for its
               own sake – your bane if you trust to it for subsistence. In the latter case, it would not be expressing myself too strongly, were I to
               say that there is danger of destruction both to body and mind – in the former you will find hope, strength, consolation; and, if
               patience be not wanting, ultimately the honour and remembrance to which you aspire. </p><p rend="indent1"> You must not be discouraged if your ‘Legend’ finds little or no sale.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud’s
                     <title>The Legend of St Loy, with Other Poems</title> (1820).</note> Not one volume of poems out of twenty that are published
               pays the expense of publication. Works of this nature which would have obtained general admiration forty and even thirty years ago, are
               now still-born from the Press: the public appetite being palled, not only by the number of dishes which are set before it, but also by
               the high spicing with which too many of them are seasoned. And in the poems of a very young writer, the faults lie upon the surface,
               and are perceived by those (the great majority) who are quite incapable of perceiving the genius which is blended with them, and the
               seeds of excellence among the rubbish. Be not discouraged at this; but do not think of publishing more at present. At your age the
               growth of your mind, when under proper culture, will be so rapid, that before a poem had been published six months, you would wish to
               alter one half of it and perhaps to strike out the other.</p><p rend="indent1"> The first and most important advice which I would impress upon you is to attend to the business of life. In what
               business are you engaged? And what prospect or hope have you of bettering your condition in it? Let me know your domestic history. I
               would serve you, if I could, more substantially than by advice alone, but advice is good for something. You have found time to compose
               a very great number of verses; you will therefore be able to find time for disciplining and storing your mind and laying in knowledge.
               The great use of youthful composition is to acquire command of language and of versification. Having so far accomplished this, the next
               task is to learn how to employ that power – what faults to avoid, and at what excellences to aim. It would be useless to send me your
                  ‘Astrea’<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">An unpublished verse drama by Heraud, ‘written in less than six weeks, and under
                  emotions which are but feebly described in the text’, <title>The Legend of St Loy, with Other Poems</title> (London, 1820), p. 210
                  n. *.</note> – no bookseller would undertake the risk of publishing so long a poem. In long works the design is of as much
               importance as the execution; but the art of planning a long work is almost the last which is acquired. In small pieces there is not
               that difficulty; and the power of a youthful mind may as well be shown by a short poem as by a long one, by twenty or fifty lines as
               well as ten thousand. Take, for example, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">H. K. White</ref> and ‘The Rosemary,’ and
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnowlesHerbert">Herbert Knowles’s</ref> poem written in Richmond churchyard.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Examples of shorter works by two young poets in whose careers Southey had taken an active interest.
                  Henry Kirke White’s ‘The Rosemary’ was first published in his <title>Clifton Grove, a Sketch in Verse, with other Poems</title>
                  (1803). It was cited as a good example of White’s youthful promise and of the unfairness of contemporary reviewers in Southey’s
                     <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 19–20. Knowles’s ‘Lines written in the
                  Churchyard of Richmond, Yorkshire’ (sent to Southey in 1816 under its original title ‘The Three Tabernacles’), appeared in the
                     <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 7 (June 1817), 420–421, and was much reprinted. White and Knowles were also rather
                  unfortunate cases for Southey to cite, as both had died young. </note> If you have among your miscellanies any pieces which you
               yourself think good of that length, copy one or two of them in your small handwriting, which can put a great deal in a foolscap sheet,
               and let me have them when next you write. Your reading should be history, travels, and our best old poets, above all others
               Shakespeare, Milton, Spenser<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Shakespeare (1564–1616; <title>DNB</title>); John Milton
                  (1608–1674; <title>DNB</title>); and Edmund Spenser (c. 1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>).</note>- but above all books the Bible, and
               upon all accounts. In reading contemporary poets there is a danger of catching their manner, that is to say their faults. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is the one, and the only one among them, who is to be reckoned with the
               great names above.</p><p rend="indent1"> For the present, farewell. Be patient and prudent. Remember that happiness is of more importance than fame, and ought
               to be your first object. With patience and prudence you will attain both. God bless you. Your sincere well-wisher,</p><closer><signed rend="indent2">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>