<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3294</idno><idno type="nines">rce4565</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3294. Robert Southey to Wade Browne, 14 May
                  1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3294.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Cornell University Library. ALS; 4p. (c). .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3294" type="letter"><head>3294. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1819-05-14">14 May
                  1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Ludlow<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK<lb/> MS: Cornell University Library. ALS; 4p. (c).<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-05-14">14 May. 1819.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">My dear Sir </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You will wonder at seeing my letter dated from home, at a time when I hoped to have been thinking of leaving London on
               the way to Ludlow. My movements however are only delayed, &amp; the main cause of delay is, I trust, removed. – I have had a long train
               of anxieties since <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Brownes</ref> kind letter arrived. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> at the time when she should in the ordinary course of
               things have been recovering,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. recovering from the birth of Charles Cuthbert Southey on 24
                  February 1819.</note> was seized with a succession of maladies, one after another, some of them of a very distressing &amp; alarming
               kind, – by which she was confined more than four weeks to her bed, &amp; nearly ten weeks to her room. Nor was it till the day before
               yesterday that she &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">the child</ref> (who has had a serious illness also)
               were well enough to be taken to church.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Cuthbert Southey was baptised at St Kentigern,
                  Crosthwaite, Keswick on 12 May 1819.</note> It will be yet some time before she recovers her strength, but the season is favourable,
               &amp; I hope &amp; believe there is nothing now to apprehend.</p><p rend="indent1"> During this long interval I have frequently been under too much anxiety to sit calmly at my desk, &amp; thus have lost
               time when I could ill afford to lose it. The consequence is that I shall be going for London just when instinct would induce every man,
               woman, &amp; child to get out of it, if they had it in their power. My history of Brazil has grown tremendously under my hands. After
               having done so much, the desire of leaving nothing undone induced me to wind up the work with a view of the state of the country, as
               compleat as I could make it, at the time when the history concludes, which is with the removal of the Court thither in 1808.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was completing the third and final volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> and the final
                  chapter occupied more space and time than he had originally envisaged; see <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810–1819), III, pp. 696–879. It was not finished until ‘<hi rend="ital">June 23rd</hi>, 1819’ (p. 879). The book did not proceed
                  chronologically beyond the flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil in 1807–1808.</note> Perhaps if I had properly estimated the
               extent of this concluding Chapter I should have been tempted to make some excuse to myself for omitting it, in full assurance that no
               one would have had reason to complain of the book as being imperfect without it. It will however add as much to its value as to its
               bulk. But it will take me a month longer before I am fairly thro the press with it, – &amp; this I fear will make it August before I
               can reach Ludlow, on my homeward journey.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> has gained a
               fellowship at Oriel, – a great instance of good fortune, &amp; a fair proof of good desert. Thus early is his comfortable provision for
               life secured, &amp; the door open to situations of honour &amp; emolument.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge had
                  been elected to a Probationary Fellowship at Oriel College, Oxford, on 16 April 1819. Southey’s hopes for his future were to be
                  proved wrong, as Hartley lost his post at the end of the probationary year on grounds of intemperance.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> I believe will be going to the University after Christmas, but whether to Oxford
               or Cambridge is as yet undetermined.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Coleridge matriculated at St John’s College,
                  Cambridge in 1820.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> is very kind in repeating her
               invitation to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; Edith I trust will one day have great pleasure in
               accepting it. But I must travel alone now, – &amp; I believe she imagines that she could not be spared from home, now there is a baby
               in the house. Poor little <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> is I assure you in some danger of
               being pulled to pieces by his sisters<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                     May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> in their outrageous fondness. He is
               perpetually reminding me of Gulliver in the arms of the monkey.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Swift (1667–1745;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gulliver’s Travels</title> (London, 1726), Part II, ‘A Voyage to Brobdingnag’, Chapter 5.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother the Captain</ref> is now quietly settled in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Newlands">Newlands</ref>, very much pleased with his removal from the bleak east winds, &amp; the
               no-neighbourhood of his last place of abode, – three miles from Brough. Compared to that situation Newlands is in a polished part of
               the world, &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> a place where every thing may be had that can be wanted.
                  <del>From</del> &lt;At&gt; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Warcop">Warcop</ref> they were literally unable to get a wash-hands bason at
               any place nearer than Penrith, – which was nineteen miles off! And yet (it is a curious fact) <del>that</del> every fellow &lt;there&gt; was
               a coiner, till the new silver was issued;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">There had been a serious shortage of silver coins
                  until the Coinage Act (1816) had authorised a new issue, the first minted since 1787. To discourage people from melting them down,
                  and thus producing another shortage, the coins contained less than their face value in silver. Birmingham, the centre of the
                  ironmongery trade, was notorious for the number of forged coins it produced, including imitations of silver made from base metals.
                  Coining also had a long history in Westmorland, though, going back to the seventeenth century .</note> – honest coiners, however, in
               comparison with the Birmingham artists, for their <del>business</del> practise was to make silver sixpences by hammering them out of
               old spoons!</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> desire their kindest remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> &amp; your daughters.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Browne had three daughters from his first marriage: Lydia (c. 1789–1864), <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Elizabeth</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">Sarah</ref>; and one, Mary Browne (dates unknown), from his
                  second.</note> Present mine also,</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> &amp; believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>