<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3547</idno><idno type="nines">rce4818</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3547. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 29 October 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3547.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Art Library, London, MS Forster
                  48 D.32 MS 35. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Forster, Walter
                     Savage Landor. A Biography, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                  463–465.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3547" type="letter"><head>3547. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1820-10-29">29 October 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re_</hi>/ Pisa/ Italy<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE;
                  CHAMBERY; CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTER DA GENOA<lb/> Postmarks: F/
                  2[illegible]7 / 20; 17 NOVEMBRE<lb/> MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster
                  48 D.32 MS 35. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Forster, <title>Walter
                     Savage Landor. A Biography</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                  463–465.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-10-29">29 Oct. 1820</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I hope you have received the books<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth’s <title>Peter Bell, A Tale in Verse</title> (1819),
                     <title>The Waggoner. A Poem. To Which are Added Sonnets</title> (1819) and
                     <title>The River Duddon, A Series of Sonnets: Vaudracour and Julia: and Other
                     Poems</title> (1820); and Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and
                     Progress of Methodism</title> (1820) and the third and final volume of his
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819). See Southey to Walter Savage
                  Landor, 20 February 1820, Letter 3443.</note> long ago; they were “shipped by the
               Grace of God in good order &amp; well conditioned in &amp; upon the good ship called
               the Cosmopolite, “George Holland, Master”<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Cosmopolite</title> was a brig that sailed regularly between
                  Britain and Mediterranean ports, including Genoa. The ship’s master, George
                  Holland, is unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> June 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> – according to the invoice, which has been sent me since I
               wrote you last.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you heard of Sir Charles Wolseleys letter<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Wolseley, 7th Baronet (1769–1846;
                     <title>DNB</title>), radical politician. A public meeting in Birmingham on 12
                  July 1819 elected him ‘legislatorial attorney and representative’ for the town,
                  and in April 1820 he was sentenced to eighteen months imprisonment for sedition
                  and conspiracy for a speech he had given at Stockport on 28 June 1819. He had
                  written from prison to the government, offering to go to Italy and collect
                  information concerning Queen Caroline (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), who was
                  facing a Bill of Pains and Penalties that would have dissolved her marriage to
                  George IV on the grounds of her adultery. Not receiving a reply, Wolseley had
                  published the letter in <title>The Times</title>, 11 October 1820, and Southey
                  quotes from it here. </note> to Lord Castlereagh?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Stewart, Lord Castlereagh (1769–1822;
                  <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary and Leader of the House of Commons
                  1812–1822.</note> I fell upon it to day in one of the Times, some week or ten days
               old, &amp; copy for your astonishment the material paragraph. – “I beg leave to
               inform your Lordship, that if his Majestys Government will allow me a months leave of
               absence from my present place of confinement, I will undertake to be of the utmost
               service to her Majesty in the pending prosecution against her, by going from hence to
               Como, where during the year 1817, I lived several months with my family; &amp; from
               that circumstance, &amp; being acquainted with several people who were employed by
               the Queen, I have an opportunity of getting at evidence that would be of the greatest
               consequence, that no Englishman but myself, &amp; a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walter
                  Lando<hi rend="ital">n</hi>, who is now in Italy, can have had the same
               opportunity of knowing.” –</p><p rend="indent1"> You probably <del>kne</del> know that one of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Broughams</ref> brothers has been on the
               continent, beating up for witnesses.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham was Queen Caroline’s attorney-general and conducted her case against
                  the Bill of Pains and Penalties. He had sent his brother, James Brougham
                  (1780–1833), to Italy in March 1819 to report on Queen Caroline’s activities, and
                  James returned to Italy in June 1820 to find and prepare defence witnesses.</note>
               If this letter had appeared in time no doubt he would have gone in search of you,
               &amp; I should like to have been present at the interview. Sir Ch. W. must be half
               crazy. We may judge how capable he is of forming a sane opinion upon any subject,
               when he has so topsy-turvey a recollection of your knowledge upon this. His letter of
               course has not obtained the slightest notice, &amp; <del>xx an</del> therefore none
               can be needful on your part. Had the mention of your name been such as in any way to
               compromise you, I should without hesitation have written to the newspapers.</p><p rend="indent1"> Most persons seem to apprehend that this trial will not terminate
               without some violent explosion. Certain it is that every possible art is used for
               making the mob rise in open rebellion. But tho it is very possible to foresee the
               consequence of public opinions, – public madness must baffle all foresight; – &amp;
               this is an absolute insanity. It was well observed by an acquaintance of mine the
               other day upon hearing that Bedlam was <del>xxx</del> to be enlarged,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bethlehem Royal Hospital for the insane had
                  been rebuilt in Southwark in 1812–1815, but was already too small to accommodate
                  the inmates. It was not extended until the 1830s. The friend of Southey’s who made
                  this remark is unidentified.</note> – “enlarge Bedlam indeed! – better build a
               wall around London.” –</p><p rend="indent1"> The course of events in Spain &amp; Portugal<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In Spain, an army revolt in Cadiz in January 1820 had led to
                  the restoration of the liberal Constitution of 1812 in March 1820. An army revolt
                  in Porto on 24 August 1820 had established a junta to run Portugal; it declared
                  its intention of organising elections to a Cortes, which were held in December
                  1820, and demanded John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826) return from
                  Brazil, where the court had fled in 1807–1808. These events did not lead to the
                  dissolution of Spain or Portugal.</note> may perhaps lead to an union of the two
               Kingdoms, but not I think as <hi rend="ital">Kingdoms</hi>. I have long thought that
               the tendency of revolution in the peninsula was to break it up into its old
               subdivisions, give to each province its own Cortes &amp; its own <hi rend="ital">fueros</hi>, &amp; unite them in a federal compact, like the Americans. And if
               there were no rubs in the way, – &amp; if the example could do no <del>one</del> harm
               in other countries this might be desired. – Alas neither the Bourbons nor
                  Braganzas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The ruling dynasties of Spain
                  (since 1700) and Portugal (since 1640).</note> are worth a wish. <del>I am</del>
               As yet it is not known what course the King of Portugal will take; – probably he must
               yield to what he cannot oppose, &amp; what in fact is both reasonable &amp; right,
               considering the monstrous misgovernment which has so long prevailed. But <del>it is
                  very doubtful</del> concessions made under &lt;such&gt; circumstances are only likely to
               retard the catastrophe, not to alter it. In the present state of Europe the abuse of
               monarchy tends to produce <del>republics</del> democracy, &amp; democracy, which is
               more certain to produce immediate &amp; more intolerable abuse, brings on military
               despotism. – The first book which I shall have to send you will contain my
               speculations upon the progress of society, in the form of dialogue.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘dialogue’ project became <title>Sir Thomas
                     More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>
                  (1829).</note> This is evidently one of the climacteric periods of the world. I am
               not afraid of the issue of this crisis in England, where we have least at stake, –
               that is where we have most to lose &amp; [MS missing]. In Italy, whatever may happen,
               you will be only a lodger.”<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference
                  to the joke of an Irishman who, warned that the house he was living in was
                  collapsing, replied it did not worry him as he was ‘only a lodger’: Alexander Pope
                  (1688–1744; <title>DNB</title>) to Richard Steele (1672–1729; <title>DNB</title>),
                  15 June 1712, <title>Mr Pope’s Literary Correspondence for Thirty Years, from 1704
                     to 1735</title>, 5 vols (London, 1735), I, p. 166.</note> It is well however
               that we are not as young as we were at the commencement of the French Revolution. For
               my part, I look on it with a wholesome but not impatient interest, knowing perfectly
               what end to wish for, but so doubtful respecting the means, that I am well content to
               trust Providence, &amp; in that confidence I rest.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have none of the books which you mention; – &amp; shall prize them
               when they arrive.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor had written to
                  Southey in September 1820, giving details of a consignment of books that he
                  intended to send to Southey. The works he named were Vincent of Beauvais (c.
                  1190-c. 1264), <title>Speculum Historiale</title> (1494), no. 2899 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library, and Paul Hoste (1652–1700), <title>L’Art des
                     Armées Navales, ou Traité des Évolutions Navales </title>(1697), no. 1431 in
                  the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. See John Forster, <title>Walter Savage
                     Landor, a Biography</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp. 460–461. </note>
               direct them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> care.
               – Every day I expect the first proof of my Peninsular War.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823–1832).</note> The leaves are falling fast, – we have now long evenings,
               &amp; I have a long season of uninterrupted work before me, thank God with good
               health &amp; fair spirits for the prospect.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>