<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3243</idno><idno type="nines">rce4514</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3243. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 8 February 1819 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3243.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3243" type="letter"><head>3243. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1819-02-08">8 February 1819 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: [illegible]<lb/> Endorsements: 8 February 1819; 8 Feb<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1819<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute rend="indent0">My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have nothing to tell you, – unless it be worth telling that the high winds have given our high chimney a shake which
               has dislocated the upper part: that part cannot be thoroughly repaired while there is any likelihood of frost, – it happened to be so
               placed that if it should fall it will come into <del>my</del> &lt;our&gt; bed room; – &amp; tho I should be under no alarm myself in such a
               case (beyond that of the first start) having taken an observation, &amp; ascertained that by the just laws of projectiles,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey claimed to have calculated the chimney’s trajectory using the Laws of Motion first outlined in
                  Isaac Newton (1642–1727; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica</title> (1687).</note> if it came
               thro roof &amp; upper story it would miss the bed, – this sort of philosophy which does very well for me, does not do quite so well for
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife</ref>. My study therefore must be converted into a bedchamber for her
               accommodation. – It may be wanted any hour, – <del>it</del> or it may not, for three or four weeks. – I <del>should be in</del> get rid
               of anxiety pretty well by the help of close employment, – for this is an anxiety that can be put out of mind for the time. But I wish
               the interval were over. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have not seen the Magazine of which you speak: but from what you say I suspect that the letters cannot be
                  genuine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title>, 4 (January 1819), 396–404, ‘Letters
                  from the Lakes. (Translated from the German of Philip Kempferhausen – written in the Summer of 1818.)’, Letter II (400–404)
                  described the author meeting Southey at Greta Hall. The author was actually <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">John
                     Wilson</ref>.</note> The only German who ever visited me (except Kleinkopff of the Bible Society)<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> was D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Spiker, the King of Prussias Librarian, in 1816.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Heinrich Spiker (1786–1858). An English translation of his account of his experiences in Britain,
                  including his meeting with Southey, was later published as <title>Travels through England, Wales, &amp; Scotland, in the Year
                     1816</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 269–272. Naturally, Spiker was most interested in Southey’s library.</note> The only
               foreigners whom I saw last year were a Frenchman, &amp; two New-Englanders.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">M. Buchot (dates
                  unknown), nephew of Jean-François Ducis (1733–1816), French poet and translator of Shakespeare; and Joseph Green Cogswell
                  (1786–1871) and Edward Everett.</note> Your Magaziner therefore must be a fictitious personage. </p><p rend="indent1"> The girls were disappointed of the Almanachs when the QR. arrived. The last article has no other fault than that
                  <del>it</del> both the wit &amp; the severity are too <hi rend="ital">fine</hi> for the subject against which they are
                  directed.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of, among other items, <title>A Letter to Sir Samuel Romilly, M.P. from
                     Henry Brougham, Esq. M.P., F.R.S. upon the Abuse of Charities</title> (1818) and the Reports of the House of Commons Select
                  Committee on the Education of the Lower Orders 1816–1818 (chaired by Brougham), which severely criticised the lack of educational
                  provision and highlighted abuses in educational charities, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (July 1818), 492–569, published 2
                  February 1819. The reviewer was John Wilson Croker, with a number of helpers.</note> – The paper upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Milmans</ref> poem is the best poetical criticism that has appeard in the <del>revi</del>
                  review.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Henry Hart Milman, <title>Samor, Lord of the Bright City</title>
                  (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (July 1818), 328–347, by John Taylor Coleridge.</note> But on the whole there is <del>a
                  xx</del> much rubbish in the number. </p><p rend="indent1"> Of late I have written nothing but Brazilian history,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History
                     of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> – if it were but as profitable as it is pleasant I should desire no other employment. The
                  65<hi rend="sup">th</hi> sheet is now on my desk – so you may suppose I am not very far from the end, – probably about six weeks.
               The last sheet of the first vol. of Wesley<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress
                     of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> is also before me: – here the notes have given me a respite, which is now at an end; &amp; I
               must <del>xxx</del> prepare ‘more copy.’ – </p><p rend="indent1"> Buy in <del>it</del> in the <del>x</del> threes. I shall then have realized twelve pounds a year; – a good comment this
               upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Broughams</ref> speech <del>wher</del> in which he
               told <del>x</del> the mob of Westmorland that I was wallowing in wealth.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">During the General
                  Election contest in Westmorland in 1818, Brougham was reported to have attacked both Southey and Wordsworth from the hustings on 30
                  June 1818, including the statement that he ‘wished he could respect them in their affluence, which had been more pernicious than
                  their poverty’, <title>The Times</title>, 4 July 1818.</note> – Impudent as that slanderer is, I think he has laid himself so
               completely open by his arrogance, his blunders, &amp; his haste in accrediting any calumnious story, upon the Education-Committee, that
               if <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> were to put forth his strength against him when the question comes
               before Parliament, he might disgrace him for ever. </p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-02-08"> 8 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1819.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>