<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3654</idno><idno type="nines">rce4925</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3654. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 17 March 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3654.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3654" type="letter"><head>3654. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>,<date when="1821-03-17"> 17 March 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 20 MR 20/ 1821<lb/> Endorsements: 17
                  March 1820/ S. Turner 7.2.6<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1821-03-17">17 March. 1821</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It seems a long while since I have heard from you. – Your thoughts no doubt have been very much engaged with poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Herries’s wife, Sarah, née
                  Dorington (1787–1821), had died on 27 February 1821, leaving six young children. Her death was reported in, for example,
                     <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 1 March 1821.</note> I was shocked at reading of his loss in the papers. It is well for him
               that he has business to occupy part of his time.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am writing with a pitch plaister on my right shoulder to remedy what <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> pronounces rheumatism, but what I had for several weeks supposed to be a strain. He was probably right, for the
               plaister has very much relieved it; but the remedy is worse than the disease. A whole suit of leather, stockings, breeches &amp; jerkin
               in one, made to fit close, &amp; well lined with this said Burgundy pitch<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Resin made from the
                  spruce tree.</note> would enable a man to act the last scene of Hercules Furens to the life, &amp; with a perfect feeling of the
                  situation.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In the final scene of Lucius Annaeus Seneca (c. 4 BC–AD 65), <title>Hercules
                     Furens</title> (c. AD 54), the hero is driven mad by the gods and kills his whole family.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My enquiries concerning that part of Ld Somervilles property to which I was heir at law are now terminated.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Fitzhead estate in Somerset; the property of Southey’s third cousin, John Southey Somerville, 15th
                  Lord Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>).</note> A decision of the Court of K Bench<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">There were a number of legal disputes over the Fitzhead estate; Southey is here probably referring to the case between Lord
                  Somerville and seven others, heard in the Court of King’s Bench on 27 January 1795.</note> gave him what the testator<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cannon Southey (d. 1768), Lord Somerville’s great-uncle, who had left Somerville the Fitzhead
                  property.</note> never intended to give, a fee simple in his estates; he has willed away the part which he had not sold, – &amp;
               there remains to me nothing but a contingency so very unlikely &amp; remote that it is worth nothing. The cost of these enquiries in
               Extracts, Opinions &amp; consultations amounts to £7–2–6 which sum I shall be obliged to you to pay to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, who has with his usual kindness given me his own time &amp; trouble, &amp;
               saved me also that portion of fees which would have been the Solicitors share. I ask you the more willingly to take this trouble,
               because you know <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, &amp; know also that there is not a man in the world
                  <del>for</del> whom I respect more sincerely. If you should not know his present address, it is 32 Red Lion Square.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Vision arrived on Tuesday;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London,
                  1821), p. xx; Canto 1, line 9.</note> – with two provoking blunders the word <hi rend="ital">ac</hi> nonsensically inserted in the
               note from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor’s</ref> essay, – &amp; the final <hi rend="ital">a</hi> in
               Glaramara omitted. <del>Three</del> Of the letters which I have received concerning it one is from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, who, as he did in his theme rides upon an insuperable obstacle<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A joke played on Wynn at Westminster School. His theme ‘Pride is an insurmountable obstacle’ was
                  corrected by a friend (possibly Southey) to ‘I ride an insurmountable obstacle’. Wynn then proceeded innocently to read out the
                  amended version to the class, causing him much embarrassment.</note> &amp; fancies the measure unsuited to the construction grammar
               &amp; harmony of the language, – if I had foreseen the objection I could with ease have demonstrated it to be altogether erroneous. A
               second is from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G. Beaumont</ref>, who rather waits to see what opinion will be
               formed, than expresses one of his own, – a third is from a young poet, the most promising of the rising race, whose name is <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">Heraud</ref>, who enters into it with all a young poets ardour finds out beauties which
               exist in his own imagination only, &amp; talks of writing in it, one of the great works which he has planned. These are all the reports
               which I have as yet received. But I know that all the women who have heard it read are pleased with the metre, which is proof that it
               produces the intended effect.</p><p rend="indent1"> When you next happen to go near a seedsmans, will you get some <hi rend="ital">borecole</hi> seed,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Borecole is another name for the vegetable, kale.</note> which may be sent in a frank. We can get none
               here.</p><p rend="indent1"> Did you get my Ode on Monday last?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 9
                  March 1821, Letter 3649, containing Southey’s ‘Ode for St George’s Day’, unpublished until <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols
                  (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 258–262, and written for George IV’s official birthday on 23 April 1821.</note> Ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> if he will have the paper upon Brazil for the next number, – that is the number
               after this which is coming out. In the present state of Portugal &amp; that Country, I think it ought not to be deferred, &amp; will
               set about it, if he chuses.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write an article on Brazil at this time for the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Southey felt this would be useful, as there had been a liberal revolution in Portugal in 1820
                  and the Cortes was demanding John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826) should return from Brazil, where he had fled from the
                  French invasion in 1807.</note> Secure for me the proofs of the Sinner Saved,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                  review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William Huntington, S. S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence Chapel, Gray’s Inn Lane,
                     Completed to the Close of the Year 1806</title> (1811) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462–510,
                  published 6 April 1821.</note> which I requested both him &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Megistos</ref> to
               let me have, – for otherwise I know <hi rend="ital">certainly</hi> that great part, &amp; probably what I should think the <hi rend="ital">best</hi> part of the paper will be lost.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you my dear Grosvenor</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>