<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3445</idno><idno type="nines">rce4716</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3445. Robert Southey to John May, 22
						February 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3445.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS;
						4pp, .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
							Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 22–23 [in part]; Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of
							Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 184–186.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3445" type="letter"><head>3445. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1820-02-22">22
						February 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmarks: E/ 25FE25/ 1820; 10o’Clock/ FE.25/ 1820
							F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/> Watermark: WD &amp; Co/ 1819<lb/> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 211 1820/
						Robert Southey/ Keswick 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> February/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March<lb/> Seal: black wax; arm raising
						aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS;
						4pp,<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
							Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 22–23 [in part]; Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of
							Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 184–186.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-02-22">22 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1820</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My
						dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It seems a long while since I have heard from you, – no doubt you have been expecting to see me,
					– &amp; indeed I should about this time have been preparing for my departure, had not two circumstances occurred to
					delay it. First the Kings death.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738–1820; King of Great
						Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>) died on 29 January 1820.</note> Taking it for granted that some <hi rend="ital">ex officio</hi> composition<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. a composition produced by
						Southey as Poet Laureate, in this case <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> would be expected on
					this occasion, I shaped something like a plan, &amp; pitched the tune in December when the first alarm was given:
					but when that alarm subsided, the thing was laid aside till a more convenient season. A fortnights delay must be
					set down to this score, about as much more to a more agreeable employment. The first volume of Brazil<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819). A second edition of the first
						volume was published in 1822. </note> is to be reprinted to make up those sets which would otherwise be imperfect,
					about 170 in number. Very possibly I may never have another opportunity of sending it into the world, during my
					life time, with such improvements as fresh materials enable me to make. So I work at this also. A large insertion
					occurs in the first chapter, from an account of Cabrals discovery as given by one of the fleet to King Emanuel. The
					original is in the Torre do Tombo<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese National Archive in
						Lisbon.</note> &amp; it was first printed at the Rio in 1817.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires
						de Casal (1754–1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Relação Historico-Geografica do Reino do Brazil</title>, 2
						vols (Rio de Janeiro, 1817), I, pp. 12–34. This book was no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.
						Pedro Vaz de Caminha (c. 1450–1500) was a member of the fleet led by Pedro Alvares Cabral (c. 1467–c. 1520), which
						discovered Brazil in 1500. Caminha’s letter of 1 May 1500 announced the discovery to Manoel I (1469–1521; King of
						Portugal 1495–1521). Southey covered this new material in the second edition of the first volume of his
							<title>History of Brazil</title> (London, 1822), pp. 8–24.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I shall finish Wesley<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Wesley; and the
							Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> next week: but the printer<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Andrew Strahan (1749–1831; <title>DNB</title>), MP for various constituencies 1796–1820 and head of
						a highly successful printing business.</note> is far behind me. I am not sure whether or not I have told you of a
					singular bequest which has been made to me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#HamondElton">a person who shot
						himself on New Years day</ref>, – a great box of papers from which to prepare for the public an account of him
					&amp; his opinions. You shall see when we meet the very curious anonymous letters which he addressed to me on this
					subject about a year ago, leading me to suppose that he was dying of disease. The papers are probably at this time
					at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henry’s</ref>, to wait my arrival. I apprehend
					that there would be little difficulty in selecting from them matter enough for an interesting but a melancholy
						work.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey eventually decided not to publish an edition of Elton
						Hamond’s writings.</note> The question is whether it can be done without danger of doing mischief. In the present
					diseased state of the public mind frightful examples seem rather to excite imitation than abhorrence.</p><p rend="indent1"> You know what a rose-coloured politician I was during the worst years of the war. My nature
					inclines me to hope &amp; to exertion. And in spite of the evil aspects on every side, &amp; the indications which
					are blackening wherever we look, I think that if we do not avert the impending dangers, we shall get thro them
					victoriously, let them come thick &amp; threatening as they may. But it will not be without a heavy <del>p</del>
					cost. – The murder of the Duc de Berri<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Ferdinand d’Artoise, Duc de
						Berri (1778–1820), a nephew of Louis XVIII (1755–1824; King of France 1814–1824), had been mortally wounded at the
						Paris Opera on 13 February 1820 by Louis Pierre Louvel (1783–1820), a Bonapartist.</note> surprized me more than a
					like tragedy would have done at home, where such crimes have perseveringly been recommended in those infamous
					journals, most of which have been suppressed by the late wholesome acts,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A
						reference to the government’s ‘Six Acts’ of 1819, which included a new Criminal Libel Act (1819) and which
						extended stamp duty to those publications like Cobbett’s <title>Political Register</title> (1802–1836) that had
						hitherto avoided it by only publishing opinion rather than news, so allowing them to sell for only 2<hi rend="ital">d</hi>. per issue. The government had also made a determined effort to prosecute radical
						newspapers.</note> – to say nothing of John Cam Hobhouse, &amp; Co.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John
							Cam Hobhouse, 1st Baron Broughton (1786–1869; <title>DNB</title>), radical and friend of Byron. He was radical and
						then Whig MP for Westminster 1820–1833, Nottingham 1834–1847, Harwich 1848–1851. Hobhouse had been arrested on 14
						December 1819 and imprisoned in Newgate for his pamphlet <title>A Trifling Mistake in Lord Erskine’s
							Preface</title> (1819), which was deemed a breach of privilege by the House of Commons. He was not released until
						28 February 1820.</note> The effect of such things, (as it is the end also of all revolutions) must be to
					strengthen the executive power. As no man can abuse his fortune without injuring it, so no people can abuse their
					liberty, without being punished by the loss of it, in whole, or in part. The time will come in this country when a
					suspension of the H. Corpus will be as regularly past as a Mutiny Bill,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas corpus was the legal principle that prevented detention without trial; it was suspended for one year from
						March 1817. The Mutiny Act had been passed annually since 1689. It provided the legal framework to maintain
						discipline in the army and had to be renewed each year as an army could only be maintained in peacetime with
						parliament’s consent.</note> &amp; when Journals of every kind will pass under the eyes of a Censor, as dramatic
					compositions do at this day, before they can be brought on the stage.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The
						Licensing Act (1737) provided that the scripts of all plays had to be submitted to the Lord Chamberlain for
						approval before they could be performed.</note> My speculations lead <del>xx</del> me to look on to strong
					governments, &amp; to a police as inquisitorial as that of our Saxon forefathers in the days of Alfred,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Alfred the Great (849–899; King of Wessex 871–899; <title>DNB</title>). During his
						reign, groups of ten households were formed into ‘tythings’ to protect their property and deliver criminals to
						justice. In effect, members were responsible for each other’s actions and the community could be fined for
						individuals’ wrongdoing. </note> or of Japan.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">In Japan under the Tokugawa
						regime (1603–1867), appointed town magistrates combined the functions of police, prosecutors and judges, assisted
						by a professional police force. Commoners were organised into ‘five family associations’, collectively responsible
						for the actions of all their members. Southey noted Japan’s police system in his review of Benjamin Haydon,
							<title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of
							Painting</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549–591 (579).</note> We shall be
					driven to it, as a defence against Jacobinism, – or Jacobinism itself will still more certainly end in it. Come to
					it, I think we inevitably must. Is it within the <del>xxx</del> bounds of a reasonable hope that <del>the</del>
					&lt;an&gt; improved state of public opinion &amp; an extended influence of religion may prevent <del>what would</del> the
					degradation which in the common course of things would ensue, after one or two halcyon generations? – How justly
					did the Romans congratulate themselves upon the security which they enjoyed under Augustus,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Augustus (63 BC–AD 14; Emperor of Rome 27 BC–AD 14).</note> – but how sure was the
					tyranny &amp; corruption &amp; ruin which ensued! Our chance of escaping from the same process of decay depends
					upon the question whether religion or infidelity are gaining ground. And if I am asked this question I must comfort
					myself by the wise &amp; good old saying – Well Masters, God’s above.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have heard no doubt of the discovery of Cicero de Republicâ.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Tullius Cicero (106–43 BC), <title>De Re Publica</title>. Only part of the text survives.
						The largest part of this was uncovered in 1819 by the Cardinal and philologist Angelo Mai (1782–1852) as a
						palimpsest in the Vatican Library. </note> This was brought to my mind at this moment, by a thought whether we
					might not be verging towards <del>another</del> a state of things in which a general wreck of literature, &amp;
					destruction of libraries would make part of the plans of Reform. – The proposal of a new alphabet has been made by
					a German reformer &amp; approved by an English one<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear who the
						German reformer of the alphabet was; the Englishman was probably Thomas Spence (1750–1814; <title>DNB</title>),
							<title>The Grand Repository of the English Language</title> (1775).</note> because one of its effects would be to
					render all existing books useless! – It was said of old that there was nothing so foolish but some philosopher had
					said it.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Tullius Cicero, <title>De Divinatione</title> (44 BC), Book
						2, chapter 58, section 119: ‘Nihil tam absurde dici potest, quod non dicatur ab aliquo philosophorum’.</note> Alas
					there is nothing so mischievous or so atrocious, but that men are found in these days <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> mad
					enough &amp; malignant enough to recommend &amp; to defend it.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had an influenza thro the house here, being the second since the beginning of the year. I
					am the only person who have escaped it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your god daughter</ref>
					is gone for a few days to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">her Uncle Toms</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> who will be a year old on Thursday, continues to
					thrive. It would delight you to see the happiness of that little creature when he is sitting on my knee while I
					show him some prints of birds &amp; beasts. – One thing more let me add, because you will be glad to hear it. My
					infirmity has somewhat strangely left me during the winter, without any means whatever having been used to remove
					it: &amp; while my habits have been perhaps more sedentary than they ever were before.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was suffering from a rectal prolapse; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 3 October 1819,
						Letter 3356.</note> God bless you. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; my friends Susan &amp; Mary.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Two of May’s three
						daughters: Mary Charlotte (b. 1804) and Susanna Louisa (1805–1885).</note> I hope I shall see John<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s son John (1802–1879).</note> when I see you in April. – Remember me also to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert
					Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>