<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3389</idno><idno type="nines">rce4660</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3389. Robert Southey to Henry Koster, 16 November
                  1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3389.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text
                  taken from Sousa-Leão .  Previously  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Leão, ‘Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster,
                  anos de 1804 a 1819’, Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, 178 (1943), 58–60.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3389" type="letter"><head>3389. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref>, <date when="1819-11-16">16 November
                  1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text
                  taken from Sousa-Leão<lb/> Previously published: Joaquim de Sousa-Leão, ‘Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster,
                  anos de 1804 a 1819’, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943), 58–60.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-11-16">16 Nov. 1819.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Koster,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Having very foolishly neglected to bear in mind the connection between <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs. Coleridge’s</ref> journey to Liverpool, and a letter to you,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A letter to Koster could
                  be sent through his father, John Theodore Koster, of Birkenhead Priory, near Liverpool.</note> – the morning of her departure finds
               me unprepared with the despatches, and I must hurry thro them faster than I would otherwise have done.</p><p rend="indent1"> First I have to thank you for the paper concerning Para.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster had sent some
                  information for Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819), in the form of a paper that was probably by Thomaz Antonio
                  Maciel Monteiro (1780–1847), a Brazilian lawyer, who was later a member of the Supreme Court and 1st Baron Itamarca; see Southey to
                  Herbert Hill, 6 October 1819, Letter 3358. </note> It did not arrive till my third volume<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  third and last volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) was finally published in October 1819.</note> was
               thro the press, I am sorry for this, because it contains some information which I was not possessed of, and the more sorry, as I have
               thus missed an opportunity of saying something in praise of the Conde dos Arcos, he having deserved it, and especially at my
                  hands.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcos de Noronha e Brito, Conde dos Arcos (1771–1828), Governor of Para 1803–1806,
                  Governor of Rio de Janeiro 1806–1808, Governor of Bahia 1810–1818. He had arranged for the Public Library in Bahia to lend Southey a
                  copy of Manuel Calado (1584–1654), <title>Valeroso Lucideno e o Triunfo da Liberdade</title> (1648), and to send him as a gift their
                  duplicate copy of José de Anchieta (1534–1597), <title>Arte de Grammatica da Lingoa mais Usada na Costa do Brasil</title> (1595),
                  no. 1530 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 16 September 1812, <title>The
                     Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2146. Arcos was thanked in the ‘Preface’ to Southey’s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), II, [unpaginated].</note> Better late than never: – and there will
               be a second edition, one day or other, if not in my time, certainly after it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume
                  of the <title>History of Brazil</title> went into a revised second edition in 1822; the second and third did not.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Secondly – there is a Chaplain found.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1817, at Koster’s instigation, the
                  English expatriate community in Pernambuco had sent Southey a letter requesting his help in securing for them a chaplain, rather
                  than directly approaching the church authorities. Discovering that responsibility for such appointments lay with the Bishop of
                  London, Southey had endeavoured to help.</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bishop of London</ref> called
               on me in the summer just before I left home, and talked to me about this very person. His name is Sandby,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sandby (c. 1761–1832), B.A. Christ Church, Oxford 1783. He was Vicar of Swell, Gloucestershire 1795–1832, and
                  Rector of Honeychurch, Devon 1816–1832. He did not take up the post in Pernambuco. The bankruptcy of the merchant Samuel Palmer
                  (1762–1851), of Bourton-on-the-Water, in 1816 had led to actions by Palmer’s creditors to recover the debts that Sandby owed to
                  Palmer. As Sandby had already spent time in prison for debt, this may have encouraged him to consider a chaplaincy in Brazil.</note>
               and he was a Winchester man, by education therefore all that could be wished. I believe he is an elder man than myself, and takes this
               situation because he has been ruined by becoming surety for some near friend or relation, so that a broken fortune is in this case no
               drawback from his character. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">The Bishop</ref> said he should make full enquiry
               concerning him, but he himself remembered him at school, and if I remember rightly, at college. The Bishop of Hereford, formerly Warden
               of Winchester,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Isaac Huntingford (1748–1832; <title>DNB</title>). In 1789 he had been
                  elected Warden of Winchester College, a post he held until his death. He was also Bishop of Gloucester (1802–1815) and Bishop of
                  Hereford (1815–1832).</note> recommended him to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bp of London</ref> and last
               week I received a letter from the latter, enclosing one from Mr. Sandby, who desired to hear from me. I advised him to notify his
               appointment to the Consul<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lemprière (c. 1758–1839), British Consul in Pernambuco 1809–1826.
                  Southey had met his family in Faro, Portugal in April 1801.</note> and to you, if they did not mean to embark immediately, and told
               him that he might count upon your friendly offices at Pernambuco, and that if he sailed from Liverpool, <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">your father</ref> would be of use to him. Whether he is married or not I am not sure, but I rather
               think he is.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sandby had married Elizabeth Bourne (dates unknown) of Dalby, Lincolnshire
                  on 10 June 1795.</note> He is certainly a gentleman by his connections.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs. C.</ref> goes to Liverpool for the purpose of having some stays
               made for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> under the direction of Mr. Parks.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Park (1745–1831; <title>DNB</title>), a Surgeon at the Liverpool Infirmary 1767–1798, was a
                  leading expert in the treatment of diseases of the knee and elbow joints.</note> She is to be at Dr. Cromptons.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Peter Crompton (1760–1833) of Eaton House, Liverpool, a wealthy radical who supported John Thelwall
                  in the 1790s and who contested elections at Nottingham (1796, 1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820). At Preston in 1818
                  he won 1245 votes, only 353 votes behind the second elected candidate. In 1804 Crompton had visited Southey in Keswick; see Southey
                  to John Rickman, 6 August 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 975, where he described
                  Crompton as a ‘nondescript fish’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My third volume is, I trust, on the way to you ere this.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final
                  volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> The manuscript of the whole work in its first rude draught
               is now on the shelf before me, bound in five volumes,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The manuscript of both Southey’s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> and his ‘Collections for the History of Brazil’ (in two volumes) were nos 3154–3155 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library; Southey had all five volumes ‘half bound in calf’.</note> at which, you may well suppose, I look with no
               small satisfaction at having thus completed what will probably be the greatest labour of my life. You will see your own name very often
               in the margin.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster was thanked, and information he provided referred to, in Southey’s<title>
                     History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, ‘Preface’ (p. vi) and in the footnotes and marginal references (for
                  example pp. 552–553, 777).</note> Early in the year my Life of Wesley<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> will be published, of course it shall be sent to
               you as soon as it comes out. I am busy upon it at this time, and have about half a volume to write.</p><p rend="indent1"> My household is but an ailing one. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bel</ref> is by no means in good
               health, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> also is looking thin and pale. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> are well, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">infant</ref>, however, tho he has lately had two or three bilious attacks which
               make one feel sensibly the frailty of an infant’s life. A seven weeks journey in Scotland was of great service to me for the time, and
               I am still the better for it.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s tour of Scotland had lasted from 17 August until 1
                  October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).
               </note> As soon as Wesley is finished, which I expect will be at the end of January, I go to London.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">Mrs. Vardon</ref> is just brought to bed of another daughter.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Emily Bertha Vardon (1819–1891), born in France.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> would have been with me this summer if I had not been summoned upon my Scotch tour, an engagement of some years
               standing. He comes down to us next year, and will perhaps be my companion on my journey home. There is some chance that the death of
               Lord Somerville may involve me in the troubles of law.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord
                  Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>), agricultural reformer and third cousin of Southey, had died on 5 October 1819. This
                  produced a further round of legal tangles over the Fitzhead estate in Somerset that Somerville had inherited.</note> The property
               bequeathed to him by his Mother’s Uncle was intended to revert to the Southeys, in case of his dying without issue.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Somerville’s mother was Elizabeth Cannon Lethbridge (d. 1765), the daughter of Mary Southey (1704–1789)
                  and niece of John Cannon Southey (d. 1768). The latter had inherited the Fitzhead estate from his mother Mary Cannon (1678–1738). On
                  his death, John Cannon Southey had left a complex, ill-advised will which named Somerville as his primary heir, and Southey’s father
                  and two uncles as the residuary legatees should Somerville die without heirs – their rights passing, in turn, to their children. Of
                  the three Southey brothers only Southey’s father married, leading the poet to believe (after the death of his father and paternal
                  uncles) that he and his brothers were now the rightful heirs to the Fitzhead estate.</note> I know very little about the business at
               present, farther than that if any they can be recovered (for he sold the whole) it can only be by means of long law suits.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">After consultation, Southey did not pursue legal action.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard nothing from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Mr. Wilberforce</ref> for a long time.
               But I shall see him in London, and everybody else whom I wish to see.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you, my dear Koster,</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately,</salute><signed rend="indent3"><hi rend="ital">Robert Southey</hi>.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>