<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3324</idno><idno type="nines">rce4595</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3324. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey,
						25 June 1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3324.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3324" type="letter"><head>3324. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>,
						<date when="1819-06-25">25 June 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London <lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark:
						E/ 28 AU 28/ 1819<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The box is arrived – a very handsome &amp; welcome present – the “smallest contributions” you
					know &amp;c.</p><p rend="indent1"> My opus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>
						(1810–1819).</note> is compleated, – &amp; wound up much to my satisfaction. This evening I send<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">d: written over ‘t’.</note> off as many of the notes as belong to the first 700 pages.
					I thank every body in the Preface who has helped me in the work, – there is good policy in this because most people
					like to see themselves <hi rend="ital">civilly</hi> in print, – &amp; there is good reason for it, because it
					procures future help from those who are ambitious of a like acknowledgement. But there may be individuals who do
					not like it, &amp; you can <del>tell me</del> &lt;tell&gt; whether Mr March<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
						March (1781–1859), British merchant from a family prominent in the trade with Portugal; in 1816 he married Mary
						Anne Gonne (b. 1792), sister of Louisa, Henry Herbert Southey’s wife.</note> is one of that number or one of the
					δι παλλοι.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Hoi polloi’, i.e. the masses or the common people.</note> – If
					you think he would dislike to have his name mentioned, for giving me the Recordaçoens of Jacome Ratton, tell me so,
					&amp; I will expunge it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas March (as ‘Mr. March’) was thanked at
							<title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, p. vi, for providing Southey with Jacques
						Ratton (1736–1820), <title>Recordações de Jacome Ratton: Sobre Ocorrências do seu Tempo, de Maio de 1747 a
							Setembro de 1810</title> (1813). This was listed as no. 3442 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, with a
						note as to its origin: ‘This book was printed only for private distribution. <hi rend="ital">Robert Southey, from
							Mr. March, London, 15 Aug. 1817</hi>.’</note> And if it is to stand tell me whether I am to call him M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. or M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas M. for I know not whether he is the elder brother. I think
					you will like the way in which I have spoken of the imperfectness of the work, &amp; at the same expressed a proper
					sense of its value, – somewhat in the spirit of an ancient.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The final
						sentence of Southey’s work expressed indifference to its ‘immediate reception, in full reliance upon the approbation of those persons for whom it has been written, and of those ages to which it is bequeathed’, <title>History
							of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, p. 879.</note> There are yet some <del>six or seven</del>
					&lt;five or six&gt; sheets in the printers hands, besides notes, tables Index &amp;c – so that it will be a month or five
					weeks before the volume will be published.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am out of order at one end, – luckily it is not at the top. God keep me sound there, &amp; any
					other affliction will be comparatively light. What I used to take for hæmorrhoids I have reason to believe is
					prolapsus, the state of the part varies greatly at different times. A fortnight ago I walked up Saddleback without
					the slightest inconvenience, &amp; now it comes down not only with the shortest walk, but as I sit at my desk I
					rise free from the complaint. It comes on about half an hour after stool, – the <del>gut</del> &lt;ring&gt; descending
					after it has been properly replaced. The cause I believe to be this. – Rectum is <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> wrong with
					me; – &amp; <del>xxxx wrong xxx xxx</del> how I cannot tell, but wrong it &lt;certainly&gt; is. In my ordinary course of
					life I am obliged to remain a long while upon the seat, before a motion is produced, – not by straining, – the
					tripes know what they have to do, only they are a long while about it; – &amp; very <del>xxx</del> rarely discharge
					as much of their contents <del>then</del> at first as they ought to do. I suspect that the fæces which are brought
					lower down at that time, &amp; still retained, occasion the protrusion, – because if in the course of the morning I
					can <del>produ</del> effect a farther discharge, the annoyance ceases. – After a walk I return with a considerable
					protrusion, – in an inflamed state, the reaction would not be worth a thought, &amp; hardly occasion one, if I did
					not know what was the cause of it. I replace the &lt;part&gt; immediately when I come into the house, go to dinner, &amp;
					as if the excitement of food acted as a general tonic, feel no more of it for the day, unless I go again to stool,
					– or walk. – When I have &lt;been&gt; <del>xxxxxxx</del> taking continual exercise, eating of course with increased
					appetite (probably twice the quantity of food that I do at home) &amp; drinking liberally of good wine (Angels of
					Purgatory, revenge my case upon that wretched Pye,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry James Pye
						(1745–1813; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1790–1813, who had exchanged the Laureate’s traditional annual
						part-payment of wine (historically a tierce of canary or butt of sack) for an additional £27 per annum. This made
						him the enemy of Bacchus, the Greek god of wine, and of Phoebus, an attribute of Apollo, Greek god of the sun and
						poetry.</note> – inimical to Bacchus, &amp; therefore hated by Phœbus &amp; by all the Gods! – ) – then all has
					gone on well, the &amp; springs of life are in fully play, colon makes no <hi rend="ital">stop</hi>, but performs
					his business <hi rend="ital">punctually</hi>, &amp; rectum is right again.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s bladder and bowel movements.</note> – I want to know whether frequent spunging with cold water would
					brace the part, – &amp; if any tonics would be likely to <del>prevent relieve</del> &lt;xxxx xxx&gt; the infirmity, – or
					to prevent it from becoming worse. – The right cure would be to rescind that atrocious commutation for my lawful
					Butt, &amp; to restore unto me the wine in kind – kind indeed! &amp; kindly should I take the restoration as the
					true &amp; only restorative. To <del>be kept</del> &lt;keep a Poet like me&gt; upon bad white wine, &amp; worse port, –
					which at the best is bad, <del>for me</del> &lt;one&gt; who has a true tongue for Rhenish, Bourdeaux &amp; Burgundy –
					&amp; that too by the act of a water-gruel rhymester – Π Π! Φ Φ!<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A joke,
						using the Greek ‘Π’ (‘pi’) and ‘Φ’ (phi) to take another swipe at Henry James Pye: ‘Pye Pye! Fie fie’.</note> Thy
					name should have been prophetic of thy destiny <hi rend="sup">o</hi><del>x</del>4 Π <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A further part of Southey’s joke at Pye’s expense, it probably approximates to ‘O Pye’.</note> for
					that abominable deed.</p><p rend="indent1"> So, having drawn up my case,</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1819-06-25">25 June. 1819</date><address><placeName> <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>