<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">frank27.editions</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-04-01">May 1, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">STUDY AIDS : EDITIONS</title>
						<author>
							<persName>Curran, Stuart</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<editor>Curran, Stuart</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date>2009-05-01</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12 #g16" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="3" when="2009-05-01" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-05-01" who="#DR">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-05-01" who="#MQ">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>STUDY AIDS : EDITIONS of Mary Shelley's <title>Frankenstein</title>
				</head>
				<p>There are countless editions of Mary Shelley's novel, many ephemeral and even undated, so any catalogue is necessarily incomplete.
					Below are most of the major editions, reprints, and translations through 1996 that can be found in libraries. All texts after the
					first and second are based on the 1831 edition unless otherwise noted. Audio and video recordings are excluded, as are
					adaptations. For any single year, texts are arranged alphabetically by place of publication, with those in English preceding
					translations into foreign languages.</p>
				<list type="simple">
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, 3 vols. (London: Printed for Lackington, Hughes, Harding, Mavor,
						&amp; Jones, 1818). The first edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ou le Prométhée moderne</title>, 3 vols., by Mme. Shelly [<title>sic</title>], trans. J[ules] S[aladin]
						(Paris: Corréard, 1821). Translation into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, 2 vols. (London: Printed for G. and W. B. Whittaker, 1823). A
						two-volume reprint of the 1818 edition, supervised by William Godwin.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Henry Colburn and Richard Bentley, 1831). Issued as number 9
						in the Bentley's Standard Novels series; the text is revised, and includes an introduction and an engraved title page.
						Reprinted in 1832, 1836, 1839, 1849.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>. By Mary W. Shelly [<title>sic</title>]. (Philadelphia: Carey, Lea
						&amp; Blanchard, 1833).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: H. G. Daggers, 1845).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Hodgson, [1847]. The Parlour Library. A piracy reprinted in
						1856.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Halifax: Milner and Sowerby, 1865).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Milner, n.d. {ca. 1870]). The Cottage Library.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Boston: Sever, Francis, &amp; Co., 1869).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London, Glasgow and New York: G. Routledge and Sons, 1882). Reprinted
						in 1886, 1888.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: J. W. Lovell, 1882).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; Or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: George Munro, [1883]). Seaside Library, Vol. 76, No.
						1538.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Dicks, 1884). Dicks' English Library of Standard Works, vol.
						3, nos. 18-23.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (New York: R. Worthington, 1884).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The modern Prometheus</title> (Chicago, New York: Belford, Clarke, 1890).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: G. Routledge &amp; Sons, Limited; New York E. P. Dutton,
						1891). Reprinted in 1899.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Mershon Company, 1893).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Home Book Company: [1893]). The Premium Library. Reprinted in
						1898(?).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or The Modern Prometheus</title> (Chicago: Donohue, Henneberry, 1895).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Gibbings; Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1897).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The modern Prometheus</title> (London: Lever Brothers, 1899).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Review of reviews Office, 189?). Penny popular novels: No. 49
						of The Masterpiece library.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (New York: James Pott, 1901). Reprinted in 1910.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (Chicago: Henneberry Co., 1909).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. R. E. Dowse and D. J. Palmer (London &amp; Toronto: J. M. Dent
						&amp; Sons; New York: E. P. Dutton &amp; Co., 1912). Everyman's Library. <p>
							<title>Frankenstein oder der neue Prometheus</title>, trans. Heinz Widtmann (Leipzig: Altmann, 1912)&gt; Translation
							into German.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Boston: Cornhill Publishing Co., 1922).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London, Toronto, New York: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd.; E. P.
						Dutton &amp; Co., 1922).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Random House, 1922).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein ou le Prométhée Moderne</title>, trans. Germain d'Hangest (Paris: la Renaissance du livre, 1922).
						Translation into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Brentano's, 1923).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Brentano's, 1927).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap, 1931).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or. The modern Prometheus</title> (Cleveland: World Publishing Company, 1932).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Readers Library Publishing Co., [1932].</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Illustrated Editions Company, 1932). Illustrated by Nino
						Carbe.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London and Toronto: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons; New York: E. P. Dutton
						&amp; Co., 1933). Reprint of the 1912 Dent/Dutton edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Edmund Lester Pearson (New York: The Limited editions club, 1934).
						A limited edition of fifteen hundred copies printed for the members of the Limited editions club at the Walpole printing
						office in New Rochelle, N.Y. Illustrated by Everett Henry, with type design by F. W. Goudy. Reprinted in 1953.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Harrison Smith and Robert Haas; Toronto: George J. McLeod,
						1934). Illustrated by Lynd Ward.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Greenwich, Conn.: Appleby &amp; Co., 1939).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Horror Omnibus, containing two complete novels: Dracula, by Bram Stoker; Frankenstein, by Mary W. Shelley</title> (New
						York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap, 1939).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Books, Inc., 1940).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Caxton House, 1943). Reprinted in 1948.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: New York Books, 1943).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Ranieri Cochetti (Rome: Donatello De Luigi, 1944). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein (or, The Modern Prometheus)</title> (New York: Editions for the Armed Services, 1945).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ou Le Prométhée moderne</title>, trans. Eugène Rocart and Georges Cuvelier (Brussels: Éditions "La
						Boéie," 1945). Translation into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Rafael Giménez (Buenos Aires: Octrosa, 1945).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Henry Langon (Brussels: Le Scribe, 1946). Translation into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Laura Marazul (Buenos Aires: Lautaro, 1947). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: roman</title>, trans. Hannah Betjeman (Monaco: Editions du Rocher, 1947). Translation into French</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der neue Prometheus</title>, trans. Elisabette Lacroix (Hamburg: Johannes Angelus Keune, 1948).
						Translation into German. Reprinted in 1994, 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Garden City, NY: Halcyon House, 1949).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: J. M. Dent; New York: E. P. Dutton, 1949). Reprint of the 1912 Dent/Dutton
						edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London, J. M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd.; New York: E. P. Dutton &amp; Co., 1951). Reprint of
						the 1912 Dent/Dutton edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein ovvero il prometeo moderno</title>, trans. B. Tasso (Milano: Rizzoli, 1952). Translation into Italian;
						introduction by Mario Praz.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Lion Books, 1953).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Giichi Shihido (Tokyo: Nihon Shuppan Kyôdô Kabushiki-Gaisha, 1953). Translation into
						Japanese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Nripendra Krishna Chattopadhyay (Calcutta: Deva Sahitya Kutin, 1955). Translation into
						Bengali.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Pyramid Books, 1957). The first commercial paperback. Reprinted in 1959, 1960,
						etc..</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Caio Jardim (São Paulo: Ed. Universitária, 1957). Translation into Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. H. Goldmann. (Poznan: Wydawnictwa Pozanskie, 1958). Translation into Polish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London J. M. Dent; New York: E. P. Dutton, 1959). New format of Everyman edition. Reprinted as
						paperback in 1960.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Cairo: al-Daral-Qawmiyyah lel-Tiba'ah wa al-Nashr, 1959). Translation into Arabic.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Pretamanushyan</title>, trans. M. R. Narayana Pilla (Kozhikode: P. K. Bros., 1959). Text in Malayalam.</item>
					<item>
						<title>El Doctor Frankenstein o El moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. Antonio Gobernado (Madrid: Aguilar, 1959). Translation
						into Spanish. Reprinted in 1966.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Monica Stolpe (Stockholm: Christofer, 1959). Translation into Swedish. A Swedish edition
						of the same number of pages was published (Bromma: Delta) in 1974.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Taro Shioya (Tokyo: Kodan-sha, 1959). Translation into Japanese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein (or, The Modern Prometheus)</title> (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1960): Dolphin Books; London: Mayflower
						Books, 1960).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Collier Books, 1960). Reprinted by New York: Collier Books;
						London: Collier Macmillan Publishers, in 1961.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstajn ili moderni Prometej</title>, trans. Slavka Stevovic (Belgrade: Mlado pokolenje, 1960). Translation into
						Serbian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Mazharul Haq Alui (Lucknow: Nasim Book Depot, [1960?]. Translation into Urdu.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Avon, Conn.: Heritage Press, 1962). Illustrated by Everett
						Henry.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Dent; New York: Dutton, 1963). New format of the Everyman edition, with introduction by
						Robert E. Dowse and D. J. Palmer. Reprinted in 1965, 1973.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein or, the modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Airmont Books, 1963). In Braille.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: New American Library, 1963).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der neue Prometheus</title>, trans. Christian Barth (Munich: Heyne, 1963). Translation into German.
						Reprinted in 1968, 1969, 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Transworld Publishers, 1964).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Hannah Betjeman (Lausanne Rencontre; Paris: Union générale d'éditions, 1964).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ou, Le Prométhée moderne</title>, trans. Joe Ceurvost (Verviers, BEL: 1964). Translation into
						French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Dell, 1965).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: New American Library, 1965). Signet Classic. Afterword by
						Harold Bloom.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ili Sovremenyi Promethei</title>, trans. Z. Aleksandrova (Moscow: Khudozhestvennaia literatura, 1965).
						Foreword and notes by A[nna] A[rkad'evna] Elistratova.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Barcelona: Molino, 1966).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Kirsten Diemer (Copenhagen: Biilmann &amp; Eriksen, 1966). Translation into
						Danish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Elisabetta Bützeberger (Milano: Corno, 1966). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Tomás Korbar (Prague: Prace, 1966. Translation into Czech. Republished: Lidová
						nakladatelství, 1969). Reprinted in 1991.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Bantam Books, 1967). Introduction by Robert Donald
						Spector.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Scholastic Book Services, 1967).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o el Moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. Jorge Ferreiro (Mexico City: Novaro, 1967). Translation into
						Spanish.</item>
					<item>, trans. Eugène Rocart and Georges Cuvelier (see 1945) (Paris: Editions de la Renaissance, 1967). Translation into
						French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, in <title>Three Gothic novels</title>, ed. Peter Fairclough (Harmondsworth and New York: Penguin,
						1968). With an introduction by Mario Praz.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Minster Classics, 1968).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Lancer Books, 1968).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Raymonde de Gans ([Paris]: Editions de l'Erable; Geneva: Editions de la Hardiegrave;re,
						1968). Translation into French. Reprinted (Geneva: Ferni) in 1978.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ovvero il prometeo moderno</title> (Milan: Sugar, 1968). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Yamamoto Masaki (Tokyo: Kadokawa Shoten, 1968). Translation into Japanese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Het monster van Frankenstein</title>, trans. Else Hoog (Utrecht: Bruna, 1968). Reprinted under this title in
						1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. M. K. Joseph (London and New York: Oxford University Press, 1969).
						The standard edition of the 1831 text.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. E. Fariñas (Barcelona: Ferma, 1969). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, cize moderný Prometeus</title>, trans. Pavel Vilkovský (Bratislava: Tatran, 1969). Translation into
						Slovak.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Hannah Betjeman (see 1947, 1964) (Levallois-Perret: Cercle du bibliophile, 1969).
						Translation into French</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der moderne Prometheus</title>, trans. Karl Bruno Leder and Gert Leetz (Gütersloh: Bertelsmann;
						Stuttgart: Europea Buch- u. Phonoklub; Vienna: Donauland, 1969). Reprinted (Frankfurt-am-Main: Insel Verlag) in 1988, 1993.
						Translation into German.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: Roman</title>, trans. Friedrich Polakovics (Munich: Hanser, 1970). Reprinted in 1971, 1972, 1975, 1978,
						1980, 1987, 1993, 1994, 1996).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London and New York: Oxford University Press, 1971).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Manuel Serrat Crespo (Barcelona: Bruguera, 1971). Translation into Spanish. Reprinted in
						1972, 1974, 1975, 1980, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1989, 1991, 1994, 1995, 1997.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenþtayn</title>, trans. Giovanni Scognamillo (Istanbul: Milliyet, 1971). Translation into Turkish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Mexico: Juan Pablos, 1971). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Barcelona: Editorial Mateu, 1971). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Márion Martins Carvalho (Lisbon: Estampa, 1972). Translation into Portuguese. Reprinted in
						1992.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Arrow Books, 1973).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Dent; New York: Dutton, 1973). Reprint of the 1912 Dent/Dutton edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein sau Prometeul Modern</title>, trans. Adriana Calinescu (Bucharest: Editura Albatros, 1973). Translation
						into Romanian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ussi Prometheus</title>, trans. Paavo Lehtonen (Jyvaskyla Helsinki: Gummerus, 1973). Translation into
						Finnish. Reprinted in 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Pedro Reis (Lisbon: Amigos do Livro, 1973). Translation into Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Fernanda Pinto Rodrigues (Lisbon: Editorial Minerva, 1973). Translation into Portuguese.
						Reprinted in 1984, 1994, 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. James Rieger (Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, 1974). The first
						reprinting of the 1818 edition, and long the standard edition of the novel.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein ovvero il Prometeo moderno</title>, trans. Bruno Tasso; intro. Mario Praz (Milan: Biblioteca Universale
						Rizzoli, 1975). Translation into Italian. Reprinted in 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Cutchogue, NY: Buccaneer Books, 1976).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: Sphere, 1976).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap, 1976).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Robert Andrew Parker's Illustrated Frankenstein</title> (New York: C. N. Potter, 1976).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Joao Alves da Costa (Lisbon: Círcolo de Leitores, 1976). Translation into Portuguese.
						Reprinted in 1977, 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. R. Zavaleta (Mexico: Editores mexicanos unidos, 1976). Translated into Spanish. Reprinted
						in 1978, 1983, 1985.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Arne Moen (Oslo: Gyldendal, 1976). Translation into Norwegian. Reprinted in 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>The annotated Frankenstein</title>, ed. Leonard Wolf (New York: C. N. Potter; distributed by Crown Publishers,
						1977).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein vagy a modern Prométheusz</title>, trans. Göncz Arpád (Budapest: Kozmosz, 1977). Translation into
						Hungarian. Reprinted in 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Jannick Storm (Copenhagen: Lademann, 1977). Translation into Danish. Reprinted in 1986,
						1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Anton Adiwiyoto (Jakarta: Gramedia, 1977). Translation into Bahasa Indonesia.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Adriano do Vale (Lisbon: Portugal Press, 1977). Translation into Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York and Scarborough, Ont.: New American Library, 1978).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Dale Books, 1978).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: New American Library, 1978). A Signet Classic, bound with <title>Dracula</title> by
						Bram Stoker and <title>Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde</title> by Robert Louis Stevenson.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Frankfurt-am-Main: Zweitausendeins, 1978). Translation into German.</item>
					<item>
						<title>K'o hsueh kuai jen</title> (Hsiang-kang: Pi hui t'u shu ch'u pan she, 1978). Translation into Chinese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Mexico: Editores Epoca, 1978). Translation into Spanish. Reprinted in 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Mexico: Editores Mexicanos Unidos, 1978). Translation into Spanish. Reprinted in 1981,
						1985.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: New York: Dent; Dutton, 1979). Reprint (with corrections) of the 1912 Dent/Dutton
						edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (West Haven, Conn.: Pendulum, 1979).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Havana: Arte y Literatura, 1979). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ou le Prométhée moderne</title>, trans. Germain d'Hangest (Paris: Garnier-Flammarion, 1979). Translation
						into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Akira Usuda (Tokyo: Kokushokankokai, 1979). Translation into Japanese. Reprinted in
						1981.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Mahwah, NJ: Watermill Press, 1980).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. M. K. Joseph (Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press,
						1980).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: of, De moderne Prometheus,</title> trans. Else Hoog (Amsterdam: Loeb, 1980). Translation into Dutch.
						Reprinted in 1989.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Toronto and New York: Bantam Books, 1981). Introduction by Diane Johnson</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o el moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. Francisco Torres Oliver (Madrid: Alianza, 1981). Translation into
						Spanish. Reprinted in 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1998.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus, the 1818 Text</title>, ed. James Rieger (Chicago; London: University of
						Chicago Press, 1982). Reprint of the 1974 Bobbs-Merrill edition, with a new preface.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Morristown, NJ: Silver Burdett Co., 1982).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der neue Prometheus</title>, trans. Ralph Tegtmeier (Bergisch Gladbach: Bastei Lübbe, 1982).
						Reprinted 1994, and (with Bram Stoker's <title>Dracula</title>) in 1997. Translation into German.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein Chinese</title> (1982). Translation into Chinese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Niels Søndergaard, 1982 (Copenhagen: Apostrof, 1982). Translation into Danish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ossia Il moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. Chiara Zanolli and Laura Caretti (Milan: Mondadori, 1982).
						Translation into Italian. Reprinted in 1988, 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Stuttgart: Ehapa Verlag, 1982). Translation into German.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Anna Pyk (Uddevalla: Niloe, 1982). Translation into Swedish. Reprinted in 1992,
						1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Max Schuchart (Utrecht: Het Spectrum, 1982). Translation into Dutch.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Mattituck, N.Y.: Amereon House, 1983).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Dodd, Mead, 1983). Illustrated by Berni Wrightson.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Marvel Comics Group, 1983). Introduction by Stephen
						King.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York; Scarborough, Ont.: New American Library, 1983). Signet
						Classic, with a revised and updated bibliography.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Barry Moser (West Hatfield, Mass.: Pennyroyal, 1983). The 1818
						text. Printed by Harold McGrath in a limited edition of 350 copies. Slipcased, with an extra set of the illustrations in a
						portfolio.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o El Prometeu modern</title>, trans. Quim Monzó (Barcelona: La Magrana, 1983). Translation into Catalan.
						Reprinted in 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1994, 1995</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenshteyn, o. Promiteus ha-moderni</title> (Yerushalyim: Elisar, 1983). Translation into Hebrew.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der moderne Prometheus</title>, trans. Ursula von Wiese (Zürich: Manesse, 1983). Translation into
						German. Reprint (Munich: Dt. Taschenbuch-Verlag) in 1993.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Modern Library, 1984).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Miquel Rodriquez Cerro (Madrid: Anaya, 1984). Translation into Spanish. Reprinted in
						1987.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ou, Le Prométhée des temps modernes</title> (Paris: Albin Michel, 1984). Translated into French.
						Illustrated by Berni Wrightson.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus: The 1818 Text in Three Volumes</title>, ed. Barry Moser (Berkeley: University
						of California Press, 1984). One-volume reprint of the 1983 Pennyroyal edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Yumiko Morishita (Tokyo: Tokyosogensha, 1984). Translation into Japanese. Reprinted in
						1993.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Maurice Hindle (London and New York: Penguin Books, 1985).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. M. K. Joseph (Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press,
						1985).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Fernanda Pinto Rodrigues (Mem Martins, Portugal: Publicacoes Europa-America, 1985).
						Translated into Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Porto Alegre, Rio Grande del Sul: L &amp; PM Editores, 1985). Translation into
						Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. T. Ernesto Bethancourt (Belmont, California: Fearon Education, 1986).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, in <title>Three Gothic novels</title>, ed. Peter Fairclough (London and New York: Penguin Books,
						1986). Reprint of the 1968 edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, the Modern Prometheus</title> (Oxford: Isis Large Print; Santa Barbara: Clio Press, 1986). Published
						in large print.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: New Orchard Editions; Distributed in USA by Sterling Pub.
						Co., 1986). Illustrated by Lynd Ward.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o el Prometeu modern</title>, trans. Quim Monzó (Barcelona: La Magrana, 1986). Translation into Catalan.
						Reprinted in 1990, 1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, oder, Der moderne Prometheus</title>, trans. Christian and Ursula Grawe (Stuttgart: Reclam, 1986).
						Translation into German. Reprinted (Rastatt: Pabel Moewig) 1990, (Düsseldorf: ECON-Taschenbuch) 1994, (Stuttgart: Reclam)
						1995.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Philadelphia: Running Press, 1987).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Ana Maria Moix (Barcelona: Lumen, 1987). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein oder der neue Prometheus</title>, trans. Ana Maria Brock (Berlin: Verlag das neue Berlin, 1987).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, o, el moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. María Engracia Pujals (Madrid: Anaya, 1987). Translation into
						Spanish. Reprinted in 1988, 1993, 1995, 1996.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Miquel Angel Gallo (Mexico: Ediciones Quinto Sol, 1987). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus: With Supplementary Essays and Poems from the Twentieth Century</title>
						(Washington, D.C.: Orchises, 1988).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Bedrick/Blackie; London: Blackie, 1988). Illustrated by Charles Keeping</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Portland House Illustrated Classics: Distributed by Crown
						Publishers, 1988). Illustrated by Lynd Ward and Aristides Ruiz.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Tom Doherty Associates, 1988).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. John Turvey and Per Dahlberg (Harlow, Essex, England: Longman, 1988).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Larry Weinberg (New York: Random House, 1988). Illustrations by Ken Barr.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Aerie Books, 1988).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankinshtayin</title> (Beirut: Maktabat Lubnan, 1988). Translation into Arabic.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Paul Couturiau (Monaco: Éditions du Rocher, 1988). Translation into French. Reprinted
						(Paris: Gallimard) 1997.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Patrick Nobes (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1989).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Richard Sellwood (London: Macmillan, 1989).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Puffin, 1989).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Wendy Hobson (New York: P. Bedrick Books, 1989). Illustrated by
						Caroline Church.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Jørn E. Albert and Thorsten Villum Hansen (Copenhagen: Forum, 1989). Translation into
						Danish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenshtein, ili, Sovremennyi Prometei: roman</title>, trans. Z. Aleksandrovoi (Moscow: "Khudozhestvennaia
						literature," 1989). Translation into Russian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Poznan: Wydawnictwo Poznanskie, 1989). Translation into Polish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (Philadelphia: Courage Books, 1990).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: New American Library, 1990). Signet Classic.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, in <title>The Mary Shelley Reader: Containing "Frankenstein," "Mathilda," Tales and Stories,
							Essays and Reviews, and Letters</title>, ed. Betty T. Bennett and Charles E. Robinson (New York and Oxford: Oxford
						University Press, 1990). The 1818 edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. J. H. Brennan, trans. Alessandra Dugan (Trieste: E. Elle, 1990). Illustrated by Tim Sell.
						Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Bantam Books, 1991).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or The modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Quality Paperback Book Club, 1991). Reprinted in 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein cize moderný Prometeus</title>, trans. Pavel Vilikovský (Bratislava: Taran, 1991). Translation into
						Czech.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Ma'arof Saad (Kuala Lumpur: Fajar Bakti, 1991). Translation into Malay.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ovvero il moderno Prometeo</title>, trans. Maria Paola Saci and Fabio Troncarelli (Milan: Garzanti,
						1991). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ovvero Il Prometeo moderno</title>, ed. Malcolm Skey, trans. Stefania Censi (Rome: Theoria, 1991).
						Translation into Italian. Reissued (Milan: Bompiani) in 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Garden Grove, CA: World Library, Inc., 1991). Plain ASCII text on
						CD-ROM.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: J. M. Dent; Rutland, Vermont: C. E. Tuttle, 1992). Reprint of the 1912 Dent/Dutton
						edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: D. Campbell Publishers Ltd.: Distributed by the Random Century
						Group Ltd., 1992).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Knopf; distributed by Random House, 1992).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Maurice Hindle (London: Penguin, 1992).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Paddy Lyons (London: Dent, 1992).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: Complete, Authoritative Text with Biographical and Historical Contexts, Critical History, and Essays from
							Five Contemporary Critical Perspectives</title>, ed. Johanna M. Smith (Boston and New York: Bedford Books of St. Martin's
						Press, 1992). Reprinted Basingstoke: Macmillan, 2000.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o el Prometeu modern</title>, trans. Maria-Amntènia Oliver (Barcelona: Edicions de l'Eixample, 1992).
						Translation into Catalan. reprinted in 1993</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Carme Roig i Papiol (Barcelona: Barcanova, 1992). Translation into Catalan.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1993).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, in <title>Horror Classics</title> (London: Chancellor Press, 1993).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Modern Library, 1993).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or the Modern Prometheus: The 1818 Text</title>, ed. Marilyn Butler (London: William Pickering; Oxford
						and New York: Oxford University Press, 1993). Reprinted as Oxford World Classics, 1998.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Random House, 1993). Reprint of the 1922 edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, 2 vols. (Oxford; New York: Woodstock Books, 1993). Reprint of 1823 ed.
						Page size reduced to 77% of original; pages grouped four original to one of this reprint.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (Ware: Wordsworth Classics, 1993). Cover title: Frankenstein.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or The modern Prometheus</title> (Lisle, IL: Project Gutenberg, 1993). Electronic text.
						ftp://uiarchive.cso.uiuc.edu/pub/etext/gutenberg/etext93/frank11.txt</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein o El moderno Prometeo</title>, [trans. Ignacio Salido Amoroso] (Madrid: Gaviota, 1993). Translation into
						Spanish. Reprinted in 1994.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Chiara Belliti (Milan: Mondadori, 1993). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>P'urangk'en syut'ain: ch'angjo ui sinbi rul yotpon han kwahakcha ui mollak</title>, trans. Hye-gyong Chong (Soul-si:
						P'apirusu, 1993). Translation into Korean.</item>
					<item>
						<title>The Essential Frankenstein: Including the Complete Novel by Mary Shelley</title>, ed. Leonard Wolf (New York: Plume,
						1993). Previously published as <title>The Annotated Frankenstein</title>.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, the Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. David Lorne Macdonald and Kathleen Dorothy Scherf (Peterborough,
						Ontario: Broadview Press, 1994). The 1818 text.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (London: J. M. Dent; Rutland, Vermont: C. E. Tuttle, 1994). Reprint of the 1912 Dent-Dutton
						edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Dover Publications, 1994).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus, the 1818 text</title>, ed. Marilyn Butler (Oxford; New York: Oxford University
						Press, 1994).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (London: Pan, 1994). A reprint of the 1963 Signet Classic.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: or, The Modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Maurice Hindle (Harmondsworth and New York: Penguin Books,
						1994).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus: the 1818 text in three volumes</title>, ed. Barry Moser (Berkeley: University
						of California Press, 1994). One-volume reprint of the 1983 Pennyroyal edition.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Avenel, N.J.: Gramercy Books; Distributed by Random House
						Value Publishing, 1994). Illustrated by Lynd Ward.</item>
					<item>
						<title>The Mammoth Book of Frankenstein</title>, ed. Stephen Jones (New York: Carroll and Graf, 1994). With other
						"electrifying tales of cursed creation."</item>
					<item>
						<title>The Essential Frankenstein</title>, ed. Leonard Wolf (New York: Byron Preiss Multimedia, 1994). CD-ROM.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, [trans. Monserrat López] (Barcelona: Ediciones B, 1994). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Marta Pérez (Barcelona: Laertes, 1994). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, [trans. Miguel Giménez Sales] (Barcelona: Ultramar D. L., 1994). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Isabel Altés Yáñes (Madrid: Edicomunicación, 1994). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein ou le Prométhée moderne</title>, trans. Joe Cuervorst (Paris: J'ai lu, 1994). Translation into
						French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: roman</title> (Rastatt: Ullstein, 1994). Translation into German.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ovvero il Prometeo moderno</title> (Rome: Biblioteca economica Newton, 1994). Translation into
						Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Gerd Karin Nordlund (Stockholm: 1994). Translation into Swedish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Masaki Yamamoto (Tokyo: Kadokawashoten, 1994). Translation into Japanese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein; or, The modern Prometheus</title>, ed. Anne K. Mellor (New York: Pocket Books, 1995).</item>
					<item>
						<title>K'o hsueh kuai jen</title> (Hsiang-kang: Huang kuan ch'u pan she (Hsiang-kang) yu hsien kung ssu, 1995). Translation
						into Chinese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenshtain o Prometeus ha-moderni</title>, trans. Iris Bar'am (Hod ha-Sharon: Astrolog, 1995). Translation into
						Hebrew.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Barcelona: Plaza &amp; Janes, 1995). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Köln: Könemann Verlag, 1995). In English.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ovvero Il Prometeo moderno</title>, trans. Simona Fefe (Milan: Frassinelli, 1995). Translation into
						Italian. Reissued (Rome: Vignola) in 1996.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ovvero, Il moderno Prometeo</title> (Pordenone: Studio Tesi, 1995). Translation into Italian.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, trans. Franz Schrapfeneder (Vienna: Tosa Verlag, 1995). Translation into German. Illustrated by
						Christian Mogg.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (New York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap, 1995). Illustrated by Larry
						Schwinger.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Nora Crook (London, Brookfield, VT: Pickering &amp; Chatto, 1996). The most thorough and
						detailed edition to date.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: The 1818 Text, Contexts, Nineteenth-Century Responses, Modern Criticism</title>, ed. J. Paul Hunter (New
						York: W.W. Norton, 1996).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein yada, modern Prometheus</title>, trans. Elif OEzsayar (Istanbul: Arion Yayynevi, 1996). Translation into
						Turkish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein yada modern prometheus</title>, trans. Yeþim Seber (Istanbul: Mitos Yayynlary, 1996). Translation into
						Turkish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenshtain</title>, ed. Larry Weinberg; trans. Dalit Lev (Yerushalayim: Keter, 1996). Translation into
						Hebrew.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, [trans. J. M. Ortiz] (Donostia: Elkar, [1997]). Translation into Basque.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title>,ed. David Stevens (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>. Large print ed. ([Los Angeles]: Cyber Classics, 1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, the modern Prometheus</title>. New York Public Library collectors ed. (New York: Doubleday,
						1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Viking, 1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (Princeton: Xlibris, 1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Wickford, RI: North Books, 1998).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, [trans. E. A. B.] (Barcelona: Andrés Bello, [1998]). Translation into Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (Paris: Autrement, 1998). Translation into French.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, ou, O Prometeu moderno</title> (S&amp;aced;o Paulo: Editora Ática, 1998). Translation into
						Portuguese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>K'o hsüeh kuai jen</title> (Taipei: Wan hsiang t'u . . ., 1998). 2 vols. Translation into Chinese.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, tr. Pawla Kociolka (Warsaw: Muza Sa, 1998). Translation into Polish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, intro. Wendy Steiner (New York: Modern Library, 1999).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title> (New York: Playmore, Inc. and Waldmann Publishing Corp., 1999).</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein, or, The modern Prometheus</title> (Washington, D.C.: Braille International, 1999). 3 vols. In
						Braille.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein</title>, ed. Antonio Ballestero and Silvia Caporale ([Salamanca]: Ediciones Almar, 1999). Translation into
						Spanish.</item>
					<item>
						<title>Frankenstein: ou o moderno Prometeo</title>, trr. Fernando R. Tato Plaza ([Vigo]: Galaxia, 2000). Translation into
						Spanish.</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
