<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1363</idno><idno type="nines">rce2485</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4857 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 206–209.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1363" type="letter"><head>1363. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1807-09-22">22 September
                        1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb/>Endorsements: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 22 Dec<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4857 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 206–209.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is instructed to send you a copy of Palmerin,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> &amp; another to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frank Sayers
                        (1763–1817; <title>DNB</title>), whose 1792 collection, <title>Poems</title>, had influenced Southey’s early work.</note> whom
                    I beg you <del>to</del>will thank in my name for his poems. The volume<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1803 Sayers
                        published <title>Nugæ Poeticæ</title>, including versifications of ‘Jack the Giant-Killer’ and ‘Guy of Warwick’.</note> which
                    he directed for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is placed in my library, but he is not here to
                    receive it. I admire Jack the Giant Killer thoroughly; – it is the best burlesque I have seen, because it is not overdone. Guy is
                    not so good, – <del>because</del> it is not <del>as</del>so apparent what he is burlesquing. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers in his love of the ludicrous reminds me of the Italian
                    verse-romancers.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am almost as indignant at your No Bucerism<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had contributed to the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 24 (1807), 24–25, an article entitled ‘No Bucerism’, a reply to a critique made, in the
                            <title>Monthly</title>, 23 (1807), 327 and 418, by John Watkins (1786–1831?; <title>DNB</title>), (clergyman, biographer,
                        contributor to the <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>) of his earlier article ‘Concerning a War Whoop’, in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 23 (1807), 327–328. Martin Bucer (1491–1551) was a reformer whose early tolerance of other beliefs was
                        replaced in Strasbourg by enquiries designed to produce Protestant conformity and leading to the imprisonment of those whose
                        doctrine did not comply.</note> as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Watkins can be, – &amp; were the author of those articles unknown
                    should exclaim with equal virulence at his utter want of candour, &amp; his wilful ignorance. It is a little too bad to quote the
                    authority of Sanders!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Sander (c.1530–1581; <title>DNB</title>), Roman Catholic
                        controversialist who authored <title>De Origine ac Progressu Schismatis Anglicani</title> (1586), in which the relationship of
                        Henry VIII and Anne Boleyn is declared improper and invalid.</note> – the Abbé Barruel<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Abbé Augustin Barruel (1741–1820), the French Jesuit priest whose 1797 work <title>Mémoires pour servir à l’Histoire du
                            Jacobinisme</title> blamed the French Revolution on an international religious conspiracy.</note> of the English
                    Reformation, – in whom the lie originated that Ann Boleyn was Henrys own daughter, known by him to be so. If however you happen to
                    have this book it may be worth while to look in it &amp; see whether or not the opinion (still existing traditionally) that Henry
                    spayed both his daughters is <del>xxxx</del>to be found there, – for that lie must have had some author, &amp; none so likely as
                    this rascal of all rascals, on whom <hi rend="ital">you</hi> rely, tho the Catholicks themselves have long been ashamed of his
                    outrageous calumnies. Oh that you should take so strange a pleasure in playing off paradoxes, – creating with Chymic skill
                    Jack-a-lanthorns of your own, for the sake of following them astray yourself! The Persiles<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616), <title>Los Trabajos de Persiles y Sigismunda, Historia Septentrional</title>
                        (1617).</note> I have not read, &amp; have not at hand. A new edition of D Quixote is in contemplation of the booksellers,
                    with splendid prints from Smirkes designs. It is likely that I shall, for the lucre of gain, or more truly for want, than for love
                    of money, correct the old translation, annotate it, &amp; prefix such an account of the Knights Library, as my own studies enable
                    me to supply, – with a life of Cervantes &amp; an account of his other works.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did
                        not edit <title>Don Quixote</title> or write a life of Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616); the old edition he thought of
                        updating was Thomas Shelton (fl. 1598–1629; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Valorous and Witty Knight-Errant,
                            Don Quixote of the Mançha</title> (1612–1620). The illustrator was Robert Smirke (1752–1845), painter and illustrator of
                        editions of Shakespeare, the <title>Arabian Nights</title>, and, eventually, <title>Don Quixote</title> (translated by his
                        daughter, Mary Smirke, 1818).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">Neddy</hi>-asses – is the Somersetshire word, – &amp; the term Lion is used at Oxford,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> See letter 32 of <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807), in which it is explained that in Oxford a ‘Lion’ is a stranger.</note> as I have used it, &amp;
                    nowhere else to my knowledge. – I am not sensible of any thing new or striking in the letter about the theatre. It is one of the
                    very few which were written because the subject could not properly be passed over, but which I was not led by the wish of saying
                    anything. The tendency of the book you rightly appreciate. I am desirous of its sale, because I wish very much to say all that I
                    have left unsaid, which, should Espriella be encouraged to return to England &amp; travel again, may be done in two volumes more.
                    In those I should (I think) be able to <del>comprize a</del> compleat the picture of society in England.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A sequel to <title>Letters from England</title> did not appear.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I trace your Romance-reading in the M. Magazine’s Portfolio. &amp; you will find that I continue to persecute <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> with odd things which he utterly abominates, &amp; of which
                    he suppresses every one that he can invent any possible motives for suppressing. He beseeches more lifes like D Luisa<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had contributed a ‘Memoir of D. Luisa de Carvajal’ (Luisa Carvajal y Mendoza (1566–1614))
                        to the<title> Athenæum, a Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, 1 (April/May 1807), 270–277, 391–399,
                        495–500.</note> – where are such to be found? However I shall give him one of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis, which
                        Pitchford<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitchford (dates unknown), denizen of Taylor’s town of Norwich, where
                        he had a partnership in a chemist’s and druggist’s, was a Catholic defender of St Francis. See his letter of 11 July 1808 to
                        the <title>Antijacobin Review</title>, 30 (May-August 1808), 333, denying that St Francis had infected a lover with venereal
                        disease.</note> will not like, – &amp; one of Vieira the Portugueze painter, abstracted from that poem, which furnishes the
                    first note to Madoc.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A note to Part 1, Book 1, of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) cites a
                        poem, <title>O insignie Pintor e Leal Esposo Viera Lusitano, Historia Verdadeira, que elle escreve em Cantos Lyricos</title>
                        (1780) by Portuguese painter Francisco Vieira (1765–1805).</note> Am I not too paid too little for such things? <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Philips</ref><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The essays in Burnett’s <title> View of the Present State of Poland</title> (1807) first
                                appeared in Phillips’s <title>Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> gave <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> ten guineas for his four letters upon Poland which fall short of a sheet. And five is what the Athenæum pays
                    for every thing, no matter how good, nor how <hi rend="ital">Aikinish</hi>. I think <del>xxxx</del>&lt;such&gt; work is good
                    enough to be paid by the piece.</p><p rend="indent1"> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reeve’s<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Reeve (1780–1814;
                        <title>DNB</title>), physician and traveller, who after a European tour on which he met many leading men of science, settled
                        in Norwich, marrying in 1807 Susan Taylor (1788–1853; <title>DNB</title>).</note> marriage made me a little melancholy, – not
                        <del>that</del> &lt;because&gt; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> is ousted at Norwich, – but because
                    it forcibly brought to my mind the sense of that fickleness about women, which he might not have had if he found it less easy to
                    please them, but which is very mischievous in its effect to himself as well as them. Wherever he goes some new face supplants the
                    last – with Miss Noel<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Southey had met Emma Noel (d. 1873), while at the home of
                            <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> in <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. She was
                        the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of Exton Park, Rutland (1759–1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel
                        in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple’s plans to
                        marry, their relationship ended.</note> he was deeply smitten, &amp; was for a few weeks, miserable enough in all conscience –
                    – but it soon past off &amp; he has left a deeper impression in another quarter than he ought to have done. I wish no man in whose
                    welfare I am interested, to lead a single life, – but if he <del>will</del> &lt;must&gt; be single I had rather it were from a
                    disappointed attachment than for want of one. In the former case the heart may be purified, in the latter it is likely to be
                    hardened, – And if celibacy does not proceed from virtue, it very frequently leads to vice.</p><p rend="indent1"> I go to London some time during the winter – will any business lead you there so that we may contrive to meet? my
                    time will probably be early in the year, as soon as my family has received an expected addition.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you – remember me to your mother –</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> Sir Kay is the Seneschal. <hi rend="ital">read Mort Arthur</hi><note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Sir
                            Thomas Malory (1415/18–1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Morte d’Arthur</title>, which Southey would edit in 1817, Sir
                            Kay, Arthur’s ‘foster’ brother, is made seneschal of Arthur’s lands at his father Sir Ector’s request, immediately after
                            Arthur draws the sword from the stone.</note></p><p>The Cid<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published
                            by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Crónica particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions
                            from the <title>Crónica de España</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title>
                            (1632).</note> is in the press.</p><p rend="right"><date when="1807-09-22">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 22. 1807</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>