<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.927</idno><idno type="nines">rce2049</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp.
                    281–283.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="927" type="letter"><head>927. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1804-04-23">23 April 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ APR 26/
                        1804<lb/>Endorsement: 23. April 1804<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp.
                    281–283.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent2"> damn the pen!</p><p rend="indent4"> but in so swearing I recollected that you would say, Southey you had better mend it – &amp; so I did. &amp; so once
                    more </p><p>Dear Grosvenor.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thought to have seen you before this time. – &amp; am daily – indeed hourly in expectation of being enabled to
                    say when I set out – but as this expectation may last yet some days I may as well write meantime.</p><p rend="indent1"> You know that I design to take up with me the first part of Madoc &amp; leave it with the Printer.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805), which Southey had written in 1797–1799 and was revising for publication, was in fact printed by
                            <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> in Edinburgh.</note> Now have I been thinking that your
                    worship might perhaps be not unwilling to stand man-midwife upon the occasion, &amp; be appointed Grand Plenipotentiary over
                    commas semicolons &amp; periods – I except the <hi rend="ital">colons</hi> as no man can manage his own. My books have all
                    suffered by misprinting. – In fact there is a lurking hope at the bottom of this request, that when you have once been brought
                    into a habit of dealing with the Devil on my account, you may be induced to deal with him on your own. You shall – i.e. if you
                    will – do for Madoc what you have done for Kehama,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> was published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1810.</note> &amp; find fault
                    while those faults <del>be</del> may be amended in time. I will put the copy into your hands, &amp; when you have examined it at
                    your pleasure, you shall some day give me a beef-stake tete-a-tete– &amp; we will lay our two tetes together &amp; I will alter
                    all the passages that I cannot on some fair ground defend.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall bring up with me as much towards the Specimens<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), which Southey jointly edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>.</note> as can be supplied by Andersons Collection,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Anderson (1749–1830; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the British Poets</title>
                        (1792–1795), which included biographical and critical articles. The work consisted originally of thirteen volumes, to which a
                        fourteenth was added in 1807.</note> Cibbers Lives,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Colley Cibber (1671–1757;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Lives of the Poets</title> (1753).</note> &amp; an imperfect series of the European
                    Magazine.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>European Magazine, and London Review</title>, which was established as
                        the mouthpiece of the Philological Society of London in 1782, until its cessation in 1826.</note> The names omitted in these may beyond all doubt be supplied from the Obituary in the Gentlemans Magazine<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Gentleman’s Magazine</title> was founded in London, in 1731, by Edward Cave (1691–1754; <title>DNB</title>).
                        Published monthly, its intention was to provide news and commentary for the educated classes, and often contained quotations
                        and extracts from other published sources.</note> – alias the Old-womaniana, a work which I have begun to take <del>xx</del>
                    here at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> to enlighten a Portugueze-student among the mountains, &amp; which does
                    amuse me by its exquisite inanity, &amp; the glorious &amp; intense stupidity of its correspondents. It is in truth a disgrace to
                    the age &amp; the country. My list of names is already long enough to prove that there will be some difficulty in getting at the
                    volumes requisite, not that it is or can be a matter of conscience to read thro all the dull poetry of every rhymester. If a dog
                    be decidedly dull – mark him with a DD for damned dunce, &amp; put in the shortest specimen. the language of vituperative
                    criticism has not yet been so systematized as to afford terms for every shade of distraction. I had an idea of applying the
                    botanical nomenclature to novels &amp; dividing them into mongynia – monandria, cryptogamia<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Monogynia: a Linnæan order of plants, including those which have only one style; monandria: a Linnæan class of plants
                        embracing those having but a single stamen; cryptogamia: plants that do not bear seeds: ferns, mosses, algae, fungi.</note>
                    &amp;c. but for the poems the pun will not hold good.</p><p rend="indent1"> Meantime if they fall in your way, or you fall in theirs take in hand Sir C. Hanbury Williams,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles Hanbury Williams (1708–1759; <title>DNB</title>): diplomat, wit, satirist, author of
                            <title>Isabella, or the Morning</title> (1740), <title>The Country Girl</title> (1742),<title> Lessons for the Day</title>
                        (1742), and <title>Letter to Mr Dodsley</title> (1743). Extracts of his poetry feature in <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), II, pp. 279–283.</note> Anna Williams the pensioner of Johnson<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Williams (1706–1783; <title>DNB</title>): poet and translator who, impoverished by
                        blindness, lived as the companion of Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) for over thirty years. She was the author
                        of <title>Miscellanies in Prose and Verse</title> (1766). Williams is not included in <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets.</title></note> – Colley Cibber, quote one of his Laureate Odes &amp; notice the infinite absurdity &amp;
                    unapplicability of Popes <del>xxx</del> attack in the Dunciad,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Colley Cibber (see note 5): Poet Laureate, playwright and actor-manager, ridiculed by Alexander Pope (1688–1744;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in <title>The Dunciad</title> (1728–1743) for his vanity and for the dullness of his verse. His
                        laureate odes on royal birthdays were often parodied in his lifetime, not least, according to Cibber’s autobiography, by
                        Cibber himself. Cibber is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, II, pp. 251–254.</note> &amp; Hall
                    Stevenson, Sternes Friend who wrote the Crazy Tales, if it be possible to gather a weed from that dung hill which does not stink,
                    &amp; also without dirting ones fingers.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Hall Stevenson (1718–1785): poet and
                        satirist, friend of Laurence Sterne (1713–1768), who devoted his residence, Skelton Hall in Yorkshire (or as he called it,
                        Crazy Castle), to roistering with a circle of licentious friends. His satirical verse acquired a ‘lurid reputation for
                        licentiousness and blasphemy’ (<title>DNB</title>): <title>Crazy Tales</title> (1762) adapts Rabelais (c. 1494–1553) and
                        Chaucer (c.1340–1400; <title>DNB</title>) to fictionalise members of Hall-Stevenson’s circle. He was not included in
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> My plan in London will be to go to Stationers Hall<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Near Ludgate Hill, in the City of London: a repository for old books because the Stationers’
                        Company, whose headquarters it is, had a royal monopoly on book production in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries.</note>
                    with my list in my pocket. there to finger-read what are to be found, which may be done by a score in a morning, – carry a list of
                    extracts to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &amp; let him send an amanuensis to take off the manual part of
                    the labour. – Where the volumes are only to be found in private collections I must of course transcribe myself. There is one
                    curious part of the subject for which it would gratify me to find <del>xxx</del> materials in any quantity. I mean popular songs
                    or ballads, no matter how bad (if decent in a moral sense) provided they have actually been popular, that is the poetry of the
                    people, the genuine successors of the old Ballads. Unless they are upon real subjects it is almost impossible to guess even at
                    their age, for whatever is obsolete slips from the memory, or is omitted in a new impression. Still some will be found. I have
                    from the European Magazine, one upon Prince Eugenes victories over the Turks,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The European Magazine and London Review</title>, 39 (1801), 47–48, printed a ‘Ballad, translated from the German’
                        celebrating the exploits of Prince Eugene (1663–1736) against the Turks, which included victories at Vienna and
                        Belgrade.</note> &amp; from oral tradition one upon Lord Derwentwater which I sent <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this ballad; see Southey to Charles Watkin WilliamsWynn, 4 February
                        1804 (Letter 893) and [c. 18 February 1804], (Letter 898).</note> &amp; he has a <hi rend="ital">Privy-Gardener</hi> upon Lord
                        Mohoun.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> By ‘privy-gardener’ Southey means a ballad pasted up on the wall of the
                        former Privy Garden of the King, an area by St James’s Park just off Whitehall in London. It was commonplace to daub slogans
                        and hang up sheets of ballads for sale there. The ballad was perhaps the mid-eighteenth century broadsheet on the death in a
                        duel of Charles Mohun, 4th Baron Mohun (c. 1675–1712; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Excellent Ballad of the Lord Mohun and
                            Duke Hamilton. With an Exact Account of their Melancholy Deaths</title>. Mohun’s opponent James Douglas-Hamilton, 4th Duke
                        of Hamilton and 1st Duke of Brandon (1658–1712; <title>DNB</title>) was also killed in the fight.</note> indeed I expect to
                    find some at Privy Garden.</p><p rend="indent1"> Tis a long way to London! I wish all were well &amp; I were on my way – &amp; then shall I wish myself arrived –
                    &amp; then be wishing myself back again, for compleat rest, absolute, unprospective – rooted rest is the great object of my
                    desires. Near London must be my final settlement, unless any happy &amp; unforeseen fortune should enable me to remove to the
                    South, &amp; then take a longer lease of Life. in fact – if I could afford the money-sacrifice I would willingly make the offer,
                    &amp; keep my History unpublished all my life – that I might pass it in Portugal.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s projected ‘History of Portugal’ was indeed never published.</note> society – connections – native language – all
                    these are weighty things – but what are they to the permanent &amp; perpetual exhilaration of a climate, that not merely prolongs
                    life – but gives you double the life while it lasts. <del>xx xxxx xxxx</del> I have actually felt a positive pleasure in breathing
                    there &amp; even here, in this magnificent spot, the recollection of the Tagus &amp; the Serra de Ossa of Coimbra &amp; its
                    cypresses &amp; orange groves &amp; olives, its hills &amp; mountains, its venerable buildings &amp; its dear river, of the vale
                    of Algarve, the little islands of beauty amid the deserts of Alemtejo, &amp; above all of Cintra, the most blessed spot in the
                    habitable globe<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s delighted response to living at Cintra; see Southey to
                        Margaret Southey, 22 August 1800, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 542.</note> – will
                    almost bring tears into my eyes.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Vale!</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-04-23">April 23. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>