<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1479</idno><idno type="nines">rce2601</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4858 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 215–219.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1479" type="letter"><head>1479. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1808-07-11">11 July
                        1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 26 July<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4858 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 215–219.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1808-07-11">July 11. 1808</date></dateline><salute>Dear W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Whether you or I be most to blame for a long chasm in a never-very close correspondence, is more than my memory can
                    at present reach to decide, – but I suspect myself to be in fault.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have received D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers’s Disquisitions,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frank Sayers
                        (1763–1817; <title>DNB</title>), a Norwich friend of Taylor’s – whose 1792 collection <title>Poems, Containing Sketches of
                            Northern Mythology</title> had influenced Southey’s early work. His <title>Disquisitions Metaphysical and Literary</title>
                        (1793) appeared in a new edition in 1808.</note> &amp; placed the copy which he <del>xxxx</del> addrest to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> among his books, where with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S.s poems<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A new edition of Sayers’s <title>Poems, Containing Sketches of Northern Mythology</title>
                        was published in 1807.</note> it lies awaiting his return; which is rather more difficult to calculate than that of a comet.
                    He is at present with <ref target="people.html#ClarksonCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkson</ref> at Bury. Make my
                    acknowledgements for the book. I was pleased to see it had grown bulkier in its new edition. – Had Middleton<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Fanshaw Middleton (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>), a schoolmate of Coleridge’s at Christ’s
                        Hospital and a fellow undergraduate at Cambridge, became a clergyman resident in Lincolnshire, and published <title>The
                            Doctrine of the Greek Article Applied to the Criticism and the Illustration of the New Testament</title> in 1808.</note>
                    been now at Norwich it is possible that you might have seen Coleridge there, – for M. called upon him in London. it has been his
                    humour for time past to think, or rather to call, the Trinity a philosophical &amp; most important truth, &amp; he is very much
                    delighted with Middletons work upon the subject. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers would not find him now the warm Hartleian that he
                    has been. Hartley<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> David Hartley (1705–1757; <title>DNB</title>).</note> was ousted by
                        Berkeley.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Berkeley (1685–1753; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Berkeley by
                        Spinoza,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Baruch de/Benedict de Spinoza (1632–1677).</note> &amp; Spinoza by Plato.
                    When last I saw him Jacob Behmen<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jakob Böhme (1575–1624).</note> had some chance of coming
                    in. The truth is that he plays with systems, &amp; any nonsense will serve him for a text from which he can deduce something new
                    &amp; surprizing.</p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Martin<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Julia Martin, née Smith (dates
                        unknown) born in Norwich, sister of James Edward Smith (1759–1828; <title>DNB</title>) the botanist, who married in 1804
                        Thomas Martin (1769–1850), first a Unitarian minister in Yarmouth, then a Liverpool merchant and Secretary of the Liverpool
                        Royal Institution. The Martins were members of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William Roscoe</ref> circle; Southey
                        met them on his visit to Liverpool in February 1808.</note> has told me some ill news from Norwich, &amp; I suppose
                        <del>by</del> you have ere this lost a good man, who will long be regretted.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of late I have I had some interruptions in my ordinary goings on, first <del>by</del> from a sickness among the
                    children, &amp; latterly by one of my obstinate catarrhs which effected a lodgement three weeks ago in my nose &amp; eyes, &amp;
                    has not yet quitted its quarters, – tho it seems upon the move. You will receive the Cid<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> in the course of a month. How nobly have his
                    country men justified the opinion of them which I have so often expressed, &amp; so generally to the astonishment of those who
                    heard me! Spain will now be free. Buonaparte has but one favour more to confer upon them, – if he makes away with the royal
                    family, his crimes, &amp; their deliverance will then be compleat. It may perhaps be possible to prune down the rotten tree of
                    their monarchy, &amp; make it bear good fruit, – but I had rather, now that the Dynasty is, felo-de-se, see them bury the crown
                    &amp; sceptre where four roads meet, – &amp; form themselves into a federal Republick, to which Portugal might accede, <del>with
                        no sa</del> without any sacrifice of national pride, on equal terms.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am planning a poem upon Pelayo, the Restorer of Spain,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelagius/Pelayo
                        (c. 685–737), founder of the Kingdom of Asturias. Through his victory at the Battle of Covadonga, he is credited with
                        beginning the Christian reconquest of the Iberian peninsula from the Moors. The planned poem became <title>Roderick, Last of
                            the Goths</title> (1814).</note> – a subject which has long been in contemplation. My poetical schemes indeed were never
                    so extensive as they are at this time, when I literally cannot afford to write a verse at any time but what is fairly won for the
                    purpose; by rising before my former <del>time</del> hour. The cause of this has been a conversation at Bristol with <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, – the Gebir:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Landor’s oriental poem of 1798.</note> a marvellous man. it made me feel somewhat ashamed that I should not as a poet do all
                    which I am capable of doing. The plain reason I cannot afford to write poetry has a mercenary sound with it; unless it be
                    explained that it is not the love of money but the necessity of subsisting which is implied: &amp; tho I cannot prevent unjust
                    criticisms from impeding the sale of my books, yet if they prevent me from writing altogether, &amp; &lt;so&gt; cut off the
                    palm-head of my future fame, that is my own fault. I will therefore go on strenuously. When a poem is compleated, if I can get a
                    fair price for it, according to the ordinary trade-price of labour, well &amp; good. If not, the MS. shall lie by &amp; be left
                    for my children, &amp; I will accumulate something for them in this shape, which will produce its value <del>when</del> after my
                    death. And while the present unjust laws of copy-right exist, I believe this will be the wisest plan which a man, who
                        <del>xxxx</del> does not <del>xxxx</del> level himself down to the fashion of the times, can possibly pursue. I am now
                    proceeding in these morning hours with Kehama,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> – rhyming it: &amp; introducing modes of rhyme which give a new power in
                    versification. This poem will be in all its parts original, – the offence of all others which the present generation are least
                    willing to pardon.</p><p rend="indent1"> My last accounts from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> are of <del>xxxx</del> an old date,
                    – but he was picking up a few fees, &amp; his prospects seem good. My answer contained reasons why it was better to marry next
                    year than this, – advice which would not be very welcome. The Annual<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual
                            Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), in which Harry had reviewed, in Southey’s stead, Joseph Cooke (1775–1811),
                            <title>Methodism condemned by Methodist Preachers: or a Vindication of the Doctrines contained in Two Sermons on
                            Justification by Faith, and the Witness of the Spirit; for Which the Author was expelled from the Methodist
                            Connection</title> (1807) (169). Southey later complained that Harry’s review of George Burnett’s <title>View of the
                            Present State of Poland</title> (1807) was replaced by another, published on pages 110–113.</note> has not yet reached me:
                    I see however his articles in the new Medical Review,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>London Medical
                            Record</title>.</note> &amp; they manifest considerable improvements &amp; promise. By the by I was exceedingly pleased
                    with <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Robert Gooch</ref>, of whom I saw much in a few meetings. – I have sent <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> some Portugueze to translate &amp; abridge for Pinkertons
                        collection.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry was to translate and abridge Francisco Álvares (c. 1465–1536/1541),
                            <title>Verdadera Informacāom das Terras do Preste Joam</title> (1540), Joao Baptista Lavanha (mid 1550s-1625),
                            <title>Naufragia da Nao S. Alberto</title> (1597) and other travels for John Pinkerton (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>),
                        compiler of <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in All Parts of the World</title>
                        (1808–1814).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> What is become of your translations from Tressan?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis-Élisabeth de la
                        Vergne, Comte de Tressan (1705–1783), translator of the <title>Decameron</title> of Giovanni Boccaccio (1313–1375) into
                        French.</note> – a more important question is why do you not put together, systematize, &amp; embody your speculations upon
                    political economy? Of all things this is what I most wish to see from you.</p><p rend="indent1"> Lady Bedingfield,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Jerningham, Lady Bedingfield (1771–1854;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Betham’s friend since the 1790s.</note> of whom you probably know something, is painting a picture
                    from one of my poems, which is designed for me. It will come thro <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref>, – the
                    painter &amp; poetess, who is the largest damsel I have ever seen that is not out of the race of the Giants, – but a clever &amp;
                    interesting woman, &amp; likely to be the best Poetess of her age.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>