<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1294</idno><idno type="nines">rce2416</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 425–428.
                    </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1294" type="letter"><head>1294. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1807-03-22">22 March 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: 22 March 1807<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 425–428.
                    </note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1807-03-22">22 March 1807</date></dateline><salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> All the copy which I want is that of the <hi rend="ital">omitted authors</hi>, – not of any omitted <hi rend="ital">pieces</hi> of those from whom Specimens<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to amendments to the
                        anthology jointly edited by himself and Bedford, the <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> are
                    given. – i-e materials for a Supplement – if Our Fathers<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The publishing firm of
                        Longman, located in <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref> (‘Paternoster’ meaning ‘our father’).</note> chuse to have one, – not for a second edition, – for that
                    does not depend either upon them, or upon us.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A supplementary volume to the
                            <title>Specimens</title> was planned, but did not appear. There was no second edition.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Do not suppose that I have put down the Printers blunders to your account – they are such as <hi rend="ital">he</hi> ought to have corrected before they came to you. My Espriella printer sends me proofs in which I have very seldom any
                    errors to correct except my own.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781–1858; <title>DNB</title>) was
                        printing <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> I
                    have desired <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> not to let Hollingsworth<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> were printed by S. Hollingsworth (first name and dates unknown),
                        Crane Court, Fleet Street.</note> print any more for me, his blunders are quite intolerable – there is scarcely one Latin word
                    spelt aright.</p><p rend="indent1"> The poem upon Felton may be reprinted, only saying – that it is curious such a poem upon the assassin of his father
                    should be inserted among Buckinghams works – &amp; that it is quite in the manner of <hi rend="ital">its own time</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Felton (c. 1595–1628), an army officer who stabbed George Villiers, 1st Duke of
                        Buckingham (1592–1628; <title>DNB</title>) to death in Portsmouth on 23 August 1628. In the Specimens, no poem about Felton
                        was included in the selection of poetry by the son, George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham (1628–1687; <title>DNB</title>).
                        For the text of the poem, see <title>Poems and Songs Relating to George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham; and his Assassination by
                            John Felton, August 23, 1628</title>, ed. Frederick W. Fairholt (London, 1850), pp. 77–78.</note> – for the cancel from
                        Chesterfield<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip Dormer Stanhope, 4th Earl of Chesterfield (1694–1773;
                            <title>DNB</title>); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14 March 1807, Letter 1286.</note> I supplied matter &amp;
                    sent to Longman, by <hi rend="ital">more Cunningham</hi> – gladly getting rid thereby of a quotation from Anderson, who has
                    neither merit nor reputation enough to render it reputable to quote him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Cunningham’s (1729–1773; <title>DNB</title>) poem ‘Evening’ did indeed replace Chesterfield. Dr. Robert Anderson (1749–1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>) wrote of Chesterfield in his <title>The Works of the British Poets, with Prefaces Biographical and
                            Critical</title> (1792–1795).</note> Gildon &amp; Hinchliffes<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Gildon
                        (1665–1723; <title>DNB</title>); William Hinchcliffe (1692–1742).</note> will cost you no more time than is needful to look
                    out any thing that will fit the gap – when you <del>have</del> have the book before you. Were I reprinting their works their
                    coarseness should stand – but it is <del>xxx</del> a different thing to <hi rend="ital">select</hi> such passages from their
                    works, – &amp; neither you nor the bookseller are probably aware (were there no higher considerations) how much the sale of the
                    book would be affected by one whisper against it upon this score, – &amp; on the contrary what a wide field of sale is opened to
                    it should it be noticed as free from all such taint. Among the methodizing part of the reading world &amp; among the Quakers, – a
                    body of Xtians from whom in all important points, I feel little or no difference in my own state of mind</p><p rend="indent1"> The remaining cancel is that sonnet under the head of J. Warton.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> As a
                        result of this advice, Joseph Warton’s (1722–1800; <title>DNB</title>) ‘Ode to Content’ appeared in place of the
                        sonnet.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You judge very erroneously in slighting Russel<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Russel
                        (1728–1767; <title>DNB</title>), whose poetry did not feature in the <title>Specimens</title>.</note> merely because he wrote
                    Sonnets – a class of poems in which there must be innumerables which are good for nothing because such numbers have been written –
                    but their very number is an indication of something good in the <del>afresh</del> return of the species. As for my own, very few
                    are of any merit – that upon Winter<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘A wrinkled crabbed man they picture thee’,
                        published in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800) and <title>Metrical Tales</title> (1805); for the text see
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, vol. V, <title>Selected Shorter
                            Poems</title>, ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), p. 402.</note> perhaps the only thoroughly good one. Russell is a name of
                    great &amp; deserved eminence – however the Supplement will remedy these omissions – for which (except in the case of Burns<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Burns (1759–1796; <title>DNB</title>).</note>) want of room was evidently the
                    cause.</p><p rend="indent1"> Heres a kettle of fish about the Catholicks! &amp; I am on the Kings side. Not an inch of ground is to be given
                        them.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of All the Talents, of which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was a member, fell because the King would not accede to its plan to
                        introduce an act emancipating Catholics from the civil penalties and restrictions placed upon them.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> To return to our standing dish – be now as expeditious as possible with the cancels – because every days stoppage
                    of the sale is an injury to it. I am sorry to say books like mackerel &lt;not only&gt; sell best when they are fresh, <del>x</del>
                    &lt;but&gt; frequently do not sell afterwards. When <del>they</del> it is once more in sale I will take care that they shall send
                    you copies.</p><p rend="indent1"> You were to get some small Spanish folio books (poem about the Saints) bound for me – if they are done – send them
                    by the first opportunity to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> – to transmit them here in his next parcel.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am very sorry that, because of your illness, I could not send my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> to you when he was in town. You would have been well pleased with him, –
                    perhaps you have never seen a young man more made by nature to please man, woman &amp; child. He is gone for Lisbon. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is at sea in a frigate hardly half manned – when the whole weight of duty falls upon
                    him, &amp; he has almost killed himself with incessant exertion &amp; anxiety.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas
                        Southey was serving aboard the <title>Pallas</title>, a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was Thomas Cochrane,
                        10th Earl of Dundonald (1775–1860; <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the capture of many French and Spanish
                        warships. In 1807, command passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown).</note><ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> did mention him to <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">his Uncle</ref> –
                    but these hopes seem now to be over.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord Grenville, Wynn’s maternal uncle was Prime
                        Minister until his administration fell in March 1807.</note> I think if he had known how very very near my heart
                        <del>lies</del> his promotion is, &amp; how gladly I would forego any expectations of my own for it – he would have carried
                    this little point. If he had been made I should have been well content that he has remained unemployed – till a ship could have
                    been got for him than other interest – As for the change of ministry, except for <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> own sake I care nothing about it, – the sooner the people of England can be convinced that there must always be a
                    lack of talents in a house of commons so chosen, the better &amp; God knows a dismal lack there is! Draw a Parliament by lot,
                    &amp; you could not by <del>the</del> any chance fail of a better. I have some faint hope that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> may come in among the sort of legacy promotions of a dying first Lord – but
                    it is a very faint one. There is not any circumstance which could give me so much pleasure.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am very busy &amp; wish I were less so – a few months will relieve me of good part – &amp; then comes more –
                    &amp; so we go on – but withal, were you to <del>xxxxxx</del> see me <del>in</del> &lt;during&gt; my hybernation, when nobody sees
                    me – I think it would almost surprize you to behold my uninterupted <del>xxxxxxxx</del> high temperature of even boyish good
                    spirits. I go on steadily with the one object in view of making the best use of my talents, &amp; thereby ripening myself for a
                    better world, &amp; leaving behind &lt;me&gt; an everlasting memorial in this: tho the ‘ways &amp; means’ of life draw me aside
                    &amp; force me to unworthy work, still even that has some reference to the same object &amp; I take it chearfully. I get miserably
                    paid, but that is neither my fault, nor any body elses; it may not always be so, &amp; if it should I am sure my children will
                    receive full interest when I am gone – &amp; so I am easy about that.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1807-03-22">March 22. 1807</date></p><p>Now pray be speedy with the cancels. On some such occasion <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> gave <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">G. Dyer</ref> the title of the <hi rend="ital">Cancellarius Magnus</hi>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘The great canceller’: a pun on ‘great councillor’, or ‘Lord High
                        Chancellor’.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>