<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1562</idno><idno type="nines">rce2684</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 204–207 [with
                        omissions]. Note: ‘J C Herries’ (John Charles Herries), who used his parliamentary privilege to frank the letter for
                        Southey, was Bedford’s friend, was employed as private secretary to Spencer Perceval.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1562" type="letter"><head>1562. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1809-01-06">6 January 1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ [in another hand] Exchequer / J C Herries<lb/>Endorsements: 6 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1809; Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 6 1809<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 204–207 [with
                        omissions].<lb/> Note: ‘J C Herries’ (John Charles Herries), who used his parliamentary privilege to frank the letter for
                        Southey, was Bedford’s friend, was employed as private secretary to Spencer Perceval.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You make a confession respecting Milton which 999 persons out of the thousand would make if they were honest
                    enough, – for his main excellencies are like M. Angelos<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Renaissance painter and
                        sculptor, Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni (1475–1564), more commonly known as Michelangelo.</note> only to be
                    thoroughly appreciated by an artist. This however by no means incapacitates you from reviewing Hayleys book,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Letters by William Cowper (1731–1800; <title>DNB</title>) were published in William Hayley
                        (1745–1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Posthumous Writings [chiefly Letters] of W. Cowper</title> (1803–1804),
                        of which a new edition of this work, <title>The Life and Letters of William Cowper Esq.,</title> was published in 1809.
                        Bedford does not appear to have reviewed this work.</note> in which your business lies with Cowper &amp; with his biographer
                    –one of whose works (his Animal Ballads)<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals, with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title>
                        (1805).</note> I once reviewed<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Hayley’s <title>Ballads</title> in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 575–576.</note> by quoting from O Keefes song – <hi rend="ital">Hayley</hi>-gaily gamboraily higgledy piggedly galloping draggletail dreary dun.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        original lines of the song ‘Pedrillo’ are: ‘With a haily gaily, gambo raily,/ Giggling, niggling,/ Galloping galloway, draggle
                        tail, dreary dun’, from the comic opera by John O’Keeffe (1747–1833; <title>DNB</title>), entitled <title>The Castle of
                            Andalusia</title> (1782). See <title>The Dramatic Works of John O’Keeffe Esq.,</title> 4 vols (London, 1798), I, p.
                        119.</note> Hayley as <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref> has just remarked to me in a letter is perfectly
                    insane upon the subject of Cowpers resemblance to Milton,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For instance in Hayley’s
                            <title>The Life and Letters of William Cowper Esq.</title>, 4 vols (Chichester, 1809), IV, pp. 443–444.</note> – there is
                    no other resemblance between them than that both wrote in blank verse, – but blank verse as different as possible. You may compare
                    Cowpers translations (which I suppose are very bad, as many of his lesser pieces are, &amp; as <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref> tells me) with Langhornes,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Langhorne (1735–1779; <title>DNB</title>), poet and translator.</note> – &amp; you may estimate Cowper himself as a poet, as
                    man of intellect &amp; as a translator of Homer, showing that he is not overvalued, – but that his popularity is owing to his
                    piety – not his poetry, – &amp; that that piety was craziness. I like his Letters,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        note 3.</note> – but think their so great popularity one of the very many proofs of the imbecillity of the age. By the by a
                    very pretty <del>fam</del> piece of familiar verse by Cowper appeared about two years ago in the Monthly Magazine.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cowper’s ‘The Distressed Travellers, or Labour in Vain’ appeared in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 24 (1807), 566.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for pointing out a blunder of which I am not in the <hi rend="ital">least</hi> sensible, &amp; will
                    thank you to correct it in the MS. <hi rend="ital">lest</hi> it should be repeated in print. The length of my Mission Article will
                    not exceed that of Sidney Smiths in the Edinburgh upon the same subject, &amp; I believe not quite equal it.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), ‘Indian Missions’, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>,
                        12 (April 1808), 151–181. Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title>
                        (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the
                            Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the
                            Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their
                            Conversion to Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A
                            Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of
                            India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807), in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226.</note> I measured by it, &amp; scarcely allowed myself any
                    extract, – I do not think you will find the same thing said twice, except it be as summing up, – for this reviewal was written
                    with great care, – the history of the Mission is as brief as possible, entering into <del>de</del> no detail except upon those
                    circumstances which occasioned an appeal to the civil power, &amp; which therefore have been made of importance to the
                    question.</p><p rend="indent1"> Ah Grosvenor – the very way in which you admire that passage in Kehama<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        From Southey’s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (London, 1810), Book 10, lines 150–171. The lines were published as
                        ‘Love’ in <title>English Minstrelsy: Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors</title> (Edinburgh,
                        1810), II, pp. 236–237, and <title>The Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), xxxi.</note> convinces me that
                    it ought not to be there! – Did I not tell you it was <del>a</del> clap trappish &amp; – you are clapping as hard as you can to
                    prove the truth of my opinion. That it grew there naturally is certain, but does it suit with the poem? – is it of a piece or
                    colour with the whole? Is not the poet speaking in himself – whereas the whole character of the poem requires that he should be
                    out of himself! I know very well that three parts of the Public will agree with you in calling it the best thing in the Poem, –
                    but my Poem ought to have no things which do not necessarily belong to it. There will be a great deal to do to it, &amp; a good
                    deal is already done in the preceding parts.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have long expected a schism between the Grenvilles &amp; the Foxites.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Factions within the Whig party who were followers of the policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James
                            Fox</ref> or <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>.</note><ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> has been trying to unite the opposition with the Jacobines as they are
                    called – he <hi rend="ital">hurts</hi> the opposition &amp; he wrongs the Jacobines, – he hurts the former by associating them
                        <del>as unpopular a xxx xxx</del> with a name that is still unpopular, &amp; he wrongs the friends of liberty by supposing
                    that they are not the deadliest enemies of Bonaparte. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref><del>xxx xxx</del>, whom I look upon as as compleat of an Anti-Jacobine as need be, does not ring out more loudly Fight on my
                    merry men all, than I do. – General Moore<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784–1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna.</note> must feel himself stronger than we have supposed him to be, or he would not advance into
                    the plains of Castille. If he have 40,000, he will beat twice the number &amp; for my own part, superior as he is in cavalry &amp;
                    artillery (ours being the best in the world) I do not see what <del>xxx</del> we have to fear from numbers against him, for
                    nothing can withstand our cavalry in a flat country. You know Grosvenor I never felt a fear till it was said he was retreating, –
                    &amp; now that he is marching on, all my apprehensions are over. Huzza it will be Rule Britannia by land as well as by sea.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have had a grievous cold which has prevented me from rising as soon as it is light, &amp; thereby for a while
                    stopt Kehama. – This evening I have corrected the fourth sheet of Brazil, the volume will be ready in the spring<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> – I
                    am now busy in filling up some skeleton chapters in the middle of the volume. This will be as true a history, &amp; as
                    industriously &amp; painfully made as ever yet appeared, yet I cannot say that I expect much present approbation for it. It is
                    deficient in fine circumstances, &amp; as for what is called fine writing, the Public will get none of that article from me, –
                    sound sense, sound philosophy, &amp; sound English I will give them.</p><p rend="indent1"> I was beginning to wonder what was become of <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. – Can you procure
                    for me a copy of the Report of the Court of Inquiry,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey wished his friends with
                        influence in parliament to send him a copy of the report of the Court of Inquiry into the conduct of the generals who signed
                        the Convention of Cintra, on 30 August 1808. Through this agreement, the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot
                        (1771–1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769–1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley,
                        who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were
                        content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755–1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750–1830;<title>
                        DNB</title>). The Court of Inquiry failed to punish Burrard and Dalrymple, but they never took command again.</note> or will
                    you ask <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> if he can, – I do not write to him till the season of franking
                    returns. I shall want it hereafter as one of my documents. Lord Moira<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Rawdon
                        Hastings, 1st Marquess of Hastings and 2nd Earl of Moira (1754–1826; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and politician. On
                        taking his seat as Baron Hastings in the House of Lords on 19 January 1809, he blamed the faulty planning of British ministers
                        for the Convention of Cintra.</note> has risen in my estimation, – he is the only person who seems to have had any thing like
                    a feeling of the moral strength which was on our side, &amp; which we compleatly gave up by the Convention –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 6. 1809. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>