<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1149</idno><idno type="nines">rce2271</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1149" type="letter"><head>1149. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1806-01-24">24 January
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/
                        Staffordshire<lb/>Postmark: [partial] KESWICK<lb/>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, ‘The
                        Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 172–176.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> If you should have received a cargo of Espriellas letters<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> you will perceive that tho silent, I have not been unmindful of you: but
                    probably they are not yet sent, for it is necessary to wait for the Emperor of the Franks.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Rickman’s employer, the Speaker of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>. Southey
                        had dubbed him the ‘Emperor of the Franks’, because of his power to frank mail which Rickman used on Southey’s
                    behalf.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have had my visit from the Influenza, a pleasant visitor, who liked my company well enough to come twice. it cost
                    me some flesh, some physic, &amp; some time, – of the first &amp; last articles I have too little at all times to spare any with
                    convenience – however I am come up to my original standard of leanness, – the time there is no recovering – I am so much behind
                    hand with reviewing, &amp; so much the poorer. My journey to London will take place about the end of March – God willing, a
                    proviso which I also insist upon such occasions from a deep sense of the uncertainty of all human projects, impressed by frequent
                    disappointments. If you are in the way, that is if you are not out of it, for <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Penkridge</ref>
                    lies in the road, I will rest a day with you. My way home will be by another route, as in all probability I shall go to Norwich
                    for a week.</p><p rend="indent1"> This journey is a great undertaking, &amp; not a pleasurable one, tho I have many friends to see, &amp; shall feel
                    real pleasure in seeing them. But to emerge from the total seclusion of this place, for nothing can be more secluded than I am
                    during my hybernation – &amp; go at once to London, where every day I shall be dining with a party invited expressly to meet me, –
                    every morning to be past in walking &amp; every evening in talking, – where I shall not get to bed till after midnight, get too
                    little milk for breakfast – &amp; too much wine at dinner – Senhora all this is not agreable. it puts me out of my way, &amp; I
                    like my own way best. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> is a very comfortable house, &amp; ought to be more so
                    now if the <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Rickwoman</ref> be what I expect her to be. I like all my male friends to be
                    married – if I had many females ones, I am not quite sure whether selfishness would let me form the same wish for them.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> adventure has terminated. the young Lady has given him up
                    to please her parents.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> While at the home of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles
                            Lloyd</ref> near <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, in 1805, Harry had met Emma Noel (d. 1873). She was
                        the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of Exton Park, Rutland (1759–1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel
                        in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple’s plans to
                        marry, the relationship soon ended; see Southey to John May, 1 November 1805, Letter 1116.</note> She ought to have considered
                    them sooner. After going so far she ought to have considered that she had contracted a duty towards him. However it is not much
                    matter. First loves are blossoms that rarely bear fruit, – &amp; it is perhaps well that they do not. in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> case too I had rather he married into some less aspiring family because
                    he has in him a certain love of fashion &amp;c which needs no fostering, &amp; which if fostered would destroy all better
                    aspirations. I know he would rather be a member of Parliament than any thing else, &amp; shine away as an orator. I want him to be
                    contented in that station of life to which it has pleased God to call him, to write a good book, &amp; leave a fair remembrance of
                    himself to posterity.</p><p rend="indent1"> If you ever exhibit a picture, the <ref target="people.html#TuffinJohnFurnall">Rivers</ref> praise will be worth something, – he will talk you into more reputation
                    in a week, than the greatest possible merit would obtain for you in seven years.</p><p rend="indent1"> Two pink saucers are arrived. be pleased to send directions how they are to be used</p><p rend="indent1"> I can tell you nothing about Lisbon, for my motions must depend upon Bonaparte. If he does not eject the factory,
                    about September will be the time for my migration – &amp; most likely I shall leave <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> – for the sake of saving money &amp; returning sooner,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey never
                        returned to Portugal after his second residence there in 1800–1801.</note> – for it is time that I was fixed. I have been
                    married ten years – &amp; never yet settled! – &amp; as little prospect of being so now as there was the first day! – Perhaps <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> may go with me – it is my wish that he should, I shall want a companion
                    to travel with me over the Northern provinces, &amp; he will be a good one, &amp; the better for his Doctorship. Another motive
                    for wishing to be home again, is that my history might be put to press<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected
                        ‘History of Portugal’ which was never completed.</note> – I wish to see it fairly finished, &amp; life is so uncertain that it
                    is not justifiable to delay it longer than is absolutely necessary. – Meantime before my departure I have a world of work – a
                    months negro-like reviewing – this illness having thrown me back. Don Manuel &amp; then the Cid<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807) and <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> – Upon my soul I do not believe any man living does so much
                    in this way &amp; gets so little for it, – &amp; the reason is that I do not write novels, nor season my poems with personal
                    satire, or that sort of indecency which people think they may decently read. That rascal Little Moore, for I may call a man a
                    rascal who will be the pimp of posterity as long as his writings last – has got more by his of Oh Lady fair<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Moore (1779–1852; <title>DNB</title>), <title>O Lady Fair. A Ballad for Three
                            Voices</title> (1802).</note> – than I shall ever do by Madoc<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805).</note> – the best poem, tho I say it, in the language, except the Paradise Lost. However I have my pleasure for my
                    pains, &amp; am determined to have as much pleasure of that kind as possible. so next year instead of reviewing I shall publish
                        Kehama<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was not published until 1810.</note> for my
                    ways &amp; means, &amp; for the future will always work upon my own materials, instead of commenting upon others.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The Colonel</ref> has sent me half a collar of brawn &amp; a little barrel
                    of pickled sturgeon. An imperial Colonel! is he not? – I never look at the Lake without wishing summer were come that I might see
                    his wife upon the water gliding along alone in her little boat like a Lady of the Lake.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In the Arthurian romances, variously Vivien and Nimue. Southey’s edition <title>The Byrth, Lyf and Acts of King Arthur</title>
                        was published in 1817. He would picture Emma in her boat in the elegy he wrote after her death and published in 1815 in his
                            <title>Minor Poems</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), II, 131–132.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> gets dearer &amp; dearer daily – &amp; I very often wish
                    the next hundred years were past, so that she &amp; I &amp; all of us were safe in Heaven, settled for a few ages, &amp; to go on
                    thro the Universe together, with no more separations.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is this day mending from a weeks toothache. No news of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> – I am very seriously uneasy about him – as he would be at Vienna
                    about the time the French got there,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was in the process of returning from Malta
                        via the continent and reached England in August 1806.</note> &amp; soldiers in a country under such circumstances are the
                    worst banditti</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-01-24">Jany. 24. 1806.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>