<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.948</idno><idno type="nines">rce2070</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 58.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 288–290 [in part; misdated
                    1802].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="948" type="letter"><head>948. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-06-06">6 June 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ June 6:/
                        1804<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 58<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 288–290 [in part; misdated
                    1802].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1804-06-06">Wednesday June 6. 1804. </date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref></placeName></address></dateline><salute>Dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Here I am at length – at least all that remains of me – the skin &amp; bone of Robert Southey, including his blood
                    &amp; brains, being now at rest &amp; moreover egregiously hungry. the flesh which has &lt;been&gt; expended in stage coaches
                    &amp; in London streets will soon be replaced. Dulce est actorum meminisse – <hi rend="ital">laborum</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as ‘remembering acts of labour is pleasant’.</note> will not so fully conclude the line
                    as my meaning wishes. labour enough I had, but there are other things besides my labour in London to be remembered – more
                    pleasurable in themselves, but not making such pleasurable recollections because they are to be wished for again.</p><p rend="indent1"> However I found excellent society awaiting me at home. Florian de Ocampo<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        No. 3557 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was Florian de Ocampo (1499?–1555?),<title> Coronica General de Espana,
                            con las Antiguedades de las Ciudades de Espanae Opusculas de Ambrosio de Morales</title> (1791–1793).</note> &amp;
                    Ambrosio Morales,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ambrosio de Morales (1513–1591): a historian who in 1574 became
                        chronicler of Castile and continued Ocampo’s <title>Crónica General de España</title> to the date of the union of Castile and
                        Leon under Ferdinand I (1017–1065; reigned as Emperor of Spain 1056–1065).</note> – 13 of the little quartos bringing down
                    Spanish history to the point where Prudencio de Sandoval<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prudencio de Sandoval
                        (1553–1620), a pupil of Ambrosio de Morales, continued the <title>Crónica General de España</title> down to the year 1079. No.
                        3781 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was Sandoval’s <title>Historia de los Reyes de Castilla y de Leon</title>
                        (1615).</note> takes it up &amp; where I also begin the full tide of narration. Morales was the correspondent of
                        Resendius<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3446 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was L. A. Resendius
                        (1498–1573), <title>De Antiquitatibus Lusitaniæ</title> (1790).</note> into whose works you once looked, &amp; was like him an
                    excellent Latinist &amp; a patient, cautious, martyr-murdering antiquary. a excellent weeder of lies wherever they were to be
                    found. In company with them came the four folios of the Bibliotheca Hispanica.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gerhardus
                        Ernestus de Franckenau (1676–1749), <title>Bibliotheca Hispanica Historico-Genealogico-Heraldica</title> (1724).</note> there
                    is offered a portrait of the last King, so exquisitely engraved &amp; so exquisitely ugly that I know not whether it be most
                    honourable to Spain to have advanced so far in the arts or &lt;disgraceful&gt; to have exercised them upon such a fools face. I am
                    sure <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> will laugh at his Catholic majesty, but whether an interjection of
                    admiration at the priest, or the laugh (which is the next auxiliary part of speech to the Ohs &amp; Ahs interjectory) will come
                    first is only to be decided by experiment.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> is very strong &amp; very large – so as to be
                    wondered at. she is eke also main ugly; her profile strongly resembles mine &amp; gives hope of nose enough hereafter.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will read the Mabinogion,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was reading a translation of the
                        Welsh romances dating from the eleventh to the thirteenth centuries, collected in fourteenth-century Welsh manuscripts and
                        known as the Mabinogi. Some of these were published in the journal edited by William Owen Pughe, <title>The Cambrian
                            Register</title> (1796, 1799), where they are entitled <title>The Mabinogion, or Juvenile Amusements, being Ancient Welsh
                                Romances</title>. Southey seems to have been loaned a manuscript translation which he was circulating among his friends.</note> concerning which I ought to have talked to you. In the last – that most odd &amp; Arabian-like
                    story of the Mouse, mention is made of a begging scholar which helps to a date.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        begging scholar and the mouse appear in the story entitled ‘Manawyddan Son of Llyr’.</note> but where the Devil did the
                        Kimbri<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cymbri, an ancient tribe, conjectured by some early nineteenth-century
                        scholars to have descended from the Picts, who supposedly conquered Wales, Cornwall and Britanny after the fall of the Roman
                        empire.</note> get the imagination that could produce such a tale! that enchantment of the baron harping by the chair from
                    heaven is in the violent spirit of the Arabian <del>xxxx</del> Nights.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The story Southey
                        read in manuscript does not appear in the <title>Cambrian Register</title>.</note> I am perfectly astonished that such fiction
                    should exist in Welsh. they throw no light on the origin of Romance – every thing being utterly dissimilar to what we mean by that
                    term. but they do open a new world of fiction, &amp; if the date of the language should be fixed about the 12 or 13 century, I
                    cannot but [MS torn] the mythological substance is of far earlier date, very probably brought from the East by some of the first
                    settlers or conquerors – If <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref><note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        During his later years Pughe was chiefly occupied in preparing a full edition of the Mabinogion; but although the Cymmrodorion
                        Society in 1831 voted £50 for the publication of this work at Denbigh, it never appeared (<title>DNB</title>).</note> will go
                    on &amp; publish them I have hopes that the world will yet reward him for his labours. Let <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon</ref> make his language grammatical, but not alter the idiom in the slightest point. I will advise him about this,
                    &amp; <del>xxxx</del> being about to send him off a parcel of old German or Theotistic books of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> – which will occasion a letter.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me thankfully to your Aunt – &amp; add <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> thanks also,
                    taking a part in them yourself, thanks partaking of this mysterious nature of the orthodox Trimourtee.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The trimourtee of Hindu gods Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva was thought to be a Brahminic equivalent to the
                        Trinity.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> Have the goodness to send the Poor Abstract<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Poor Law Abstract of
                            1804. Its full title was ‘Abstract of Returns Relative to the Expense and Maintenance of the Poor’ (printed by order of
                            The House of Commons, 1804).</note> to <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">J<hi rend="sup">n</hi> Theodore
                            Koster</ref> Esq Liverpool – &amp; also occasionally such other Reports as thinking men ought to have. One of the Cow Pock
                            Pamphlets<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to one of the many pamphlets produced on behalf of
                            Edward Jenner (1749–1823; <title>DNB</title>) as part of his campaign to popularise vaccination with cow pox serum to
                            protect against contracting smallpox. He could have in mind Jenner’s 1801 pamphlet <title>The Origin of the Vaccine
                                Inoculation</title>.</note> would also be well bestowed upon our Apothecary here <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref> – a very skilful man, &amp; of unusual science for one in his situation. the
                        people here begin to suspect that the Cow Pock produces Nettle Rash. this last having become as terrible a scourge to the
                        children as the itch is in Scotland. they are probably wrong – but the damnd eruption is certainly more common than it has
                        ever been before remembered.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>