<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1500</idno><idno type="nines">rce2622</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>University of Rochester, Rare Books Library.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 92–96.Dating note: dating suggested by Curry in ‘Missing letters and missing names’.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1500" type="letter"><head>1500. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-08-31">[late August/early September 1808]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: University of Rochester, Rare Books Library<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 92–96.<lb/>Dating note: dating suggested by Curry in ‘Missing letters and missing names’.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1808-08-31">1808.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Wynn,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have been for the last seven days incessantly at work upon my old volume of Letters,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797), which were reprinted in 1808 in an
                        expanded form as <title>Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> which it
                    is thought proper to reprint at this time. By well weeding it, referring to the original journal, and hunting out local
                    information, it is made into a respectable book, and one which future travellers will find useful. It will be printed in two small
                    volumes, making the whole of my operas in that size twenty-two-a pretty regiment when in good uniform. It required some effort of
                    prudential patience in me not to write to you two days ago, immediately upon the receipt of an epistle from <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse Campbell</ref>. The Equus Evangelizans (who sayeth that he hath no taste in poetry
                    for anything above a tabernacle hymn?) has taken occasion from ‘Kirke White’s Remains’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title> (1807), which were edited by Southey.</note> to write and
                    inquire of me whether I may not have suppressed some edifying papers, because they differed from my own sentiments. This, however,
                    he has done with all possible civility, and it prefaces an attempt to convert me to the Calvinist faith, and an invitation to
                    Shrewsbury. The letter is by no means a bad one: you know there was always a spice of shrewdness in the <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse</ref>, which gave a finer flavour to his absurdity. I give him full credit for
                    sincerity, and had a gush of laughter upon discovering who the epistle came from, which was honestly worth five shillings, and
                    would have been worth five guineas if you and <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> had been here to have
                    participated in it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Nothing makes me so melancholy as to ‘call over the names’ at Westminster. I tried to find out <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref> in London, but he was not to be heard of at the Temple. It is about six years
                    since I saw him. Both he and I have grown into men with as little change as possible in either and yet, after a few minutes, there
                    was a dead weight upon me which was not to be shaken off. We met with the heartiness of old and thorough familiarity – something
                    like a family feeling; but it was necessary to go back to school, for the moment we ceased to be schoolboys there was nothing in
                    common between us. We had no common acquaintance or pursuit, and I feel that of all things in the world there is nothing more
                    mortifying than to meet an old friend from whom you have had no weaning, and to find your friendship cut through at the root.</p><p rend="indent1"> A Westminster man of our times, though I cannot for the life of me remember him, travelled with me from Liverpool –
                    a Captain Murray.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> He was certainly of our time,
                    and at the same boarding-house. He told me –––––<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> was a colonel in the
                    army, and has served in Egypt, where he was just as much detested by the soldiers as he had been at school. His halter, therefore,
                    has not yet got into the collection.</p><p rend="indent1"> I prophesied about the Spaniards at <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford’s</ref> to William
                    Nicol<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nicol (d. c. 1855), publisher, and friend of Grosvenor Bedford’s. He was the son of George Nicol (1740?-1828), in whose publishing firm he became a partner in 1800.</note> and
                    Bull Beresford,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey described this Westminster schoolmate thus in 1817: ‘A good
                        natured worthy fellow, who was in the same remove with me, &amp; expected to find himself with a competence after his fathers
                        death. The father has an office &lt;situation&gt; in the Stamp Office &amp; employed B. under him, – but he died worth nothing
                        &amp; B. needs some floatage of this kind, till he can commence practise as a Solicitor, for which he is preparing’.</note>
                    and Nicol has acknowledged me for a true prophet. It is indeed a scene unparalleled in history, and a more glorious one never has
                    and never can be exhibited to the world. <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> (Gebir) is gone as a volunteer.
                    I know not whether we ought to desire a renewal of the war in Germany or not. If North Germany could be roused, that would be
                    something; but from Austria it seems to me that no good can be expected till its Government be cut up root and branch. A diversion
                    there will give Bonaparte a pretext for abandoning Spain. He will beat the Austrians and freshen his popularity in France by so
                    doing; the Spaniards will be tempted to cross the Pyrenees, and there they would probably meet with defeats of which I have no
                    fear while they remain on the right side, even though their enemy were tenfold mightier than he is.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Mr. T. Southey’s</ref> conduct <hi rend="ital">is</hi> literal madness beyond a
                    doubt. My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, knowing nothing of his quarrel with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">his sister</ref>, called there on his way to Plymouth; he was with the haymakers, and had
                    his back towards him when he approached. ‘How d’ye do, sir?’ says <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>; and ‘How d’ye
                    do?’ he answered, without turning his face. ‘You seem very busy, sir.’ ‘Very busy.’ Not a word more; so that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> could not avoid saying, ‘I think, sir, you don’t seem glad to see me.’ ‘I never
                    desire to see any of the family.’ <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> then went to the house to look for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">his aunt</ref>, and heard from the servants that ‘he had used her worse than a dog,’ and
                    turned her out of doors. She herself is a woman whose spirit has been long since broken down, and who would bear, and did bear, a
                    great deal in the hope of serving us; and even now she begs me to say nothing which can offend him, because she thinks I am not
                    quite out of his good graces. And I believe this very fear of making him displeased with me prevents her from coming here, as I
                    have urgently requested her to do. It does not fall to every man’s lot to have had two such precious uncles.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second uncle in question was <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John
                    Southey</ref>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I wish you a boy with all my heart: for myself, it will perfectly satisfy me if what I look for about the same time
                    should prove a girl. The prospect of a large family gives me no uneasiness whatsoever. If it please God to let me go through the
                    career which I have begun, they will be well provided for; and if it be His will to call me away, they will find friends, and I
                    shall find that justice which is as seldom denied to the dead as it is granted to the living.</p><p rend="indent1"> Can you procure for me Dick Adderley’s address?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Boyle Adderley
                        (dates unknown), a friend of Southey’s during his time at Westminster School, admitted 1785.</note> I should like to send him
                    a copy of the ‘Cid,’<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        (1808).</note> for the sake of sending a letter with it, and getting one from him. He had the best heart for an Irishman that
                    I ever knew, and it grieves me that such a man should be so lost. There was another poor fellow in our remove whom I would have
                    travelled far to have shaken by the hand, and that was poor O’Keefe;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Tottenham
                        O’Keeffe (1775/76–1803), elder son of the dramatist John O’Keeffe of Dublin (1747–1833; <title>DNB</title>). O’Keeffe was a
                        schoolboy at Westminster with Southey; in 1791 he went up to Trinity College Cambridge but transferred to Exeter College
                        Oxford in 1798. He took his BA in 1801, was ordained, became a minister at Duke St Chapel, Westminster, and in 1803 gained a
                        living in Jamaica, where he died three weeks after his arrival.</note> but he was blighted and blasted by adversity more than
                    by imprudence. In fair weather and kindly sunshine he was one who would have flourished and brought forth fruit. I loved O’Keefe
                    because I never saw that man whose tears of mirth or of compassion were so suddenly excited. There was a drunkenness of joy in his
                    merriment which was catching, but when drunkenness was really superadded, it was madness, and then his ruin.</p><p rend="indent1"> God help us! it is perilous travelling, when a man turns out of the broad turnpike way of the world; and yet night
                    and morning do I thank God for leading me into the by-path which has brought me where I am. Oh, that you could at this moment see
                    the moonlight upon Derwentwater, and the cloud in which the moon herself is hidden!</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> R. S.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>