<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1719</idno><idno type="nines">rce2841</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890 .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1719" type="letter"><head>1719. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1809-12-02">2 December
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1809-12-02">Saturday. Dec. 2. 1809.</date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></dateline><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> These vile things from Bristol are not yet arrived, &amp; I begin to fear they never will, because there are a set
                    of thieves scattered thro these northern counties who have made the waggon warehouses their object, &amp; are said to have
                    plundered to a prodigious amount.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The box arrived on 17 December; see Southey to Charles
                        Danvers, 14 December 1809, Letter 1721.</note> Paracelsus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The name coined for himself
                        by Theophrastus Bombastus von Hohenheim (1493–1541) a Swiss alchemist, writer and physician, who was the author of numerous
                        treatises propounding his theories, many of which were published posthumously.</note> will not be much in their way, but my
                    shoes may be likely enough to fit some of their feet. At any rate I must trouble you to make enquiry at Bristol, – for if the
                    parcel be only delayed, they ought to have some trouble given them for delaying it so long.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have &lt;had&gt; the loveliest autumn that ever was remembered in this country. Our garden was in full flower
                    till the middle of November.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your information concerning <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> was not quite accurate, – the
                    choice of those two livings has been offered him, – it appears that he cannot <del>xxx xxx</del> either with his present
                    preferment, &amp; tho <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> is 1000£ a year he does not think it worth his while to
                    give up 600£ in one of the finest parts of Herefordshire in exchange for it. This was my latest account from him. He was then
                    about to leave London for Marydown, the seat of <ref>his wifes</ref> father M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wither,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lovelace Bigg (b. 1741) who assumed, on inheriting the Wither estates, the surname of the family.</note> –
                    &amp; there he meant to make up his mind upon the subject. It would be pleasanter for me to have him at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> than at <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref>, – nevertheless
                    I think the latter the best place for him.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> is provokingly slow with my book,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810.</note> which ought to have
                    &lt;been&gt; published ere this. I scarcely get a sheet a week from him. This looks as if he were at present in full employ. The
                        Register<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed the ‘History of Europe’ for 1808–1810
                        in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne’s</ref><title> Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> keeps me
                    close at work, – a business of more profit than pleasure, – but I am nearly thro the heaviest part of it, &amp; shall then get on
                    with more alacrity. The Scotchmen are not a little astonished at a certain way I have of speaking plain. – I have made minced meat
                    of the arguments for Catholick Emancipation,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The campaign for Catholic empancipation,
                        which took place largely during the late-eighteenth and early-nineteenth centuries in Britain and Ireland, aimed to reduce or
                        remove restrictions on Roman Catholics that had been introduced by the sixteenth and seventeenth- century Acts of Uniformity
                        and the Test Acts.</note> &amp; sung out stoutly to the tune of ‘Fight on my merry men all’.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A line which occurs in both the broadside ballad ‘John Armstrong’s Last farewel’ (c. 1701) and ‘The Ballad of
                        Chevy Chase’ (first recorded in the 15th century).</note> One thing I am sure of, – which is that you will feel the opinions
                    expressed in this book to be perfectly consistent with my old, unaltered, unalterable, Jacobinical principles, – if <del>you
                        &amp;</del> any body else chuses to call them so. By whatever name they may be christened mine they are, &amp; I shall always
                    be as ready to acknowledge them, as any body can be to father them upon me. I have spoken of all parties with bitter contempt, as
                    it becomes an Englishman to do.</p><p rend="indent1"> Kehama is finished.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>,
                        published in 1810.</note> the concluding stroke was put to it last Saturday (this day week) – &amp; to day I have begun
                        Pelayo.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note>
                    Huzza! – I wish you well thro it M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey! – There is nothing like having enough to do, <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Sir Charles</ref>, &amp; with a history of my own, a history of the booksellers, &amp; a
                    long poem in hand <del>in hand</del> &lt;at once&gt;, besides a few stray etceteras, I am not likely to yearn for want of
                    something to think about. Pelayo is in blank verse, – it is a noble subject, – the foundations are laid well, &amp; I hope &amp;
                    trust (if it please God that I live &amp; do well) to raise a goodly superstructure. By way however of not losing time it is my
                    intention to begin Robin Hood also,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had begun to plan a romance on this subject
                        in 1804; it was not until 1823 that he began drafting the verse, in collaboration with Caroline Bowles (1786–1854;
                            <title>DNB</title>). The poem remained unfinished, and was published posthumously as a fragment in an edition by Bowles:
                            <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment by the Late Robert Southey and Caroline Southey, with other Fragments and Poems</title>
                        (1847).</note> as soon as a good beginning suggests itself. This will be in rhyme, &amp; in the sort of time which you expect
                    from the title. The difficulties of the story (for it had great ones) are I think well overcome, – &amp; when the opening scene is
                    once hit upon, <del>xxx xxx</del> – when I have once got fairly under weigh, it will be smooth sailing to the end of the
                    voyage.</p><p rend="indent1"> We are not quite <del>xxx</del> easy about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, who is on the
                    point of getting her first upper teeth. – will you read this to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref>, – she is subject to
                    very frequent obstructions of bile, – that is to say the fæces are often white or clay coloured, a dose of calomel<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The common name for mercury chloride, which was taken for various ailments, including
                        syphilis.</note><del>xxx</del> makes them very green &amp; fœtid, – but things are hardly set right before they get wrong
                    again in the same way. And after the calomel has been taken about two hours it has the effect of vomiting her. – I am somewhat
                    alarmed at this because <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> died of some anomalous liver complaint, tho it was not
                    preceded by these symptoms. Nothing is more common among infants in this country than slight attacks of jaundice, – but in this
                    case the derangement occurs far more frequently than I have seen in any other instance</p><p rend="indent1"> Are you not astonished at <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> regularity?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge’s periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, was published in 26 instalments from 1 June
                        1809 to 15 March 1810.</note> As for that shocking story in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> number<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The thirteenth number was dated 16 November 1809 and included the story of Maria Eleonora Schoning, which
                        Coleridge claimed to have read on his visit to Germany in 1798–1799. See Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A
                            Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London, 1809), pp. 194–208. See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The
                            Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp. 172–183.</note> I can only say as
                    the old woman did about the transactions on Good Friday that I trust in God’s mercy there is not a word of truth in it; &amp; I
                    have convinced myself that there cannot be. The specific <del>madness</del> form of madness on which the fiction (as I take it to
                    be) is founded, really did exist some fifty years ago in Denmark, – as I well remember to have read, – &amp; was put a stop to by
                    condemning such fanatics to perpetual imprisonment instead of death. Their practise was to kill children, in order to be put to
                    death for it.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The story of this sect is given in the ‘History of Europe’ in the
                            <title>Annual Register for the Year 1767</title> (1768), 164.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The M Magazine<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> tells me that
                    Bristol is become quite a literary city. I am sorry however that some body there has forestalled me in a selection of George
                    Withers poems,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The journalist and author, John Mathew Gutch (1776–1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>) who in 1803 moved to Bristol to become the owner and printer of <title>Felix Farley’s Bristol
                            Journal</title>. He was an active member of the Bristol Philosophical and Literary Society during the twenty years he
                        resided there. Gutch’s edition of George Wither’s (1558–1667; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Poems</title>, was published (with
                        the assistance of his friend <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref>), in 1820.</note> – which I am sure he
                    will not make with either half the pains, or half the advantages, that I should have done.</p><p rend="indent1"> What a misfortune not to be in London during the war of Covent Garden!!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey is referring to the ‘Old Price Riots’ of 1809 which were caused by rising prices at the new theatre at Covent Garden
                        after the previous one had been destroyed by fire. The riots began 18 September 1809 and lasted three months, ending with the
                        theatre-manager, John Philip Kemble (1757–1823; <title>DNB</title>) being forced to make a public apology.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS. <hi rend="ital">O. P.</hi><note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Old Price disturbances were
                            known as the OP. riots.</note></signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>