<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1072</idno><idno type="nines">rce2194</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                    30928.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1072" type="letter"><head>1072. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1805-06-03">3 June
                        1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Seal: [partial, illegible]<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                    30928<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I shall be very glad to see <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref> &amp; only wish our house were
                    large enough to enable me to offer him a bed – but it will not be easy this early in the season to procure one at one of the inns.
                    he will do well to take this opportunity of seeing the Lakes when he has leisure, &amp; will have you to travel up with him, &amp;
                    me for a guide there.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your route will be the same as if you came by Liverpool, the roads joining at Preston. When you are at Coniston I
                    should advise you to go to the Ferry on Windermere, &amp; come up to <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> – or <ref target="places.html#LowoodInn">Low-Wood</ref> in a boat, by which you will see that Lake to the best advantage. From <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is sixteen miles, &amp; you
                    see three Lakes on the way. – If therefore you cross the sands from Lancaster – see Kirkstone Abbey<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey probably refers to what is usually known as <ref target="places.html#FurnessAbbey">Furness
                        Abbey</ref>, on the north side of the crossing, via the sands of Morecambe Bay, from Lancashire to Cumbria.</note> – come up
                    by Coniston Lake &amp; thence by way of Esthwaite Lake to the Ferry on Windermere, you will take the very best route possible,
                    &amp; one which few Lakers are fortunate enough to be informed of. Esthwaite is not remarkable, the other two are, but in all this
                    kind of scenery whether you begin at the right or the wrong end is of as much consequence as it is in cutting a cucumber.</p><p rend="indent1"> Shepherd &amp; Trinder<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sheppard and Trinder (first names and dates
                        unknown), a firm of woollen drapers who had premises at 7 Millsom Street, Bath.</note> specify the 15/<hi rend="sup">s</hi> to
                    have been received by <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith</ref> in their bills.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Expenditure incurred in kitting out <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref> for
                        the navy; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 19 May 1805, Letter 1068.</note> better leave the matter till you have been here,
                    when you shall take back the bill with you. It evidently shows that their account of the receipt is not accurate, as the supposed
                    overplus was differently received. </p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be glad to have the Parnasso.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This is more likely to be Miguel de
                        Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616), <title>Viage del Parnaso</title> (1614), listed in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library,
                        than the 56-volume Venetian edition, <title>Parnasso Italiano, overo Raccolta de’ Poeti Classici Itali</title> (1784–1791),
                        which he also owned.</note> had you not better send it forward with your luggage? directed by way of Manchester &amp; Penrith. </p><p rend="indent1"> You are very good to think of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>. he is well stacked
                    with books – perhaps a bat-ball &amp; shoe for trap would be as good a play thing as could be given him. any thing that could
                    teach him a love of common sports would be well to break that habit of musing which wears him out.</p><p rend="indent1"> On the opposite page I will write a note for the Annuals.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> This is
                        reproduced at the end of the letter.</note> You will be surprized to hear that I have received another letter by way of the
                    bottle &amp; Atlantic.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>
                        periodically sent letters in bottles addressed to his brother; see Southey to the Editor of the <title>Athenaeum</title>,
                        [April 1807] (Letter 1314) for an account of these.</note> thrown in June 6. 1802. Lat. 44. 40. Long. 45. 6. &amp; picked up
                    by a Bermudas fishing boat. 32. 16. – 64. 49. Dec. 2. 1804. – The letter has been fairly worn out before it reached me. it came
                    inclosed from Bristol, instead of re-directed. however for such a curiosity I did not begrudge the treble postage. Is it not
                    extraordinary that two should have thus reached me? as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> said when he heard that the
                    first had arrived never let sailor despair of making his friends hear of him. – Could I but have as good fortune in the lottery it
                    would be worth having.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> print – which you will see here – is from a picture
                    painted by Northcote for <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey refers to William Say’s (1768–1834) 1805 mezzotint after James Northcote’s (1746–1831; <title>DNB</title>) portrait of
                        Coleridge 1804.</note> it is in mezzotinto, &amp; is I suppose sold for five shillings. my portrait is in <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedfords</ref> hands, – whether or no it will ever be engraved by <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> as he proposes heaven knows.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In a letter
                        of 2 August 1803, Southey stated that he had sat for Duppa, who intended to engrave his likeness, while he was in London; see
                        Southey to Thomas Southey, 2 August 1803, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 815. No
                        engraving by Duppa has been traced. In 1804 <ref target="people.html#EdridgePainter">Henry Edridge</ref> painted Southey’s
                        portrait for Bedford (now held by the National Portrait Gallery, London).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I recollect no desideratum beyond your list – A letter from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> last
                    week <del>xxxx</del> gives me reason to hope that his best prizes have escaped. they were at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincents,
                    &amp; I do not understand that that Island has been visited by the French. But their value would be materially injured by the
                    general distress in the colonies. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Vincent is an island in the southern part of the
                        Windward Islands of the West Indies. It had been ceded to the British by the French in 1763. It was customary for naval
                        officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict, and Southey was concerned that his
                        brother would lose his prize money from Spanish ships taken by HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> in December 1804.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you! I heartily long to see you once more –</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yours, very affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey will be obliged to Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> to deliver to the Bearer the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        &amp; 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Vol. of the Annual Review, directed for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Lieutenant
                            Southey</ref> – <del>to the care of Nath</del> H. M. S. Amelia, to the care of Nathan Jackson Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The addressee of letters to Thomas Southey in the West Indies is
                            untraced.</note> – Barbadoes.</p><p><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1805-06-03">June 3. 1805.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>