<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1694</idno><idno type="nines">rce2816</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1694" type="letter"><head>1694. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1809-10-14">14 October
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Bristol
                        <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-10-14">Oct 14. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> If you did not know how fully &amp; overflowingly my time is occupied, I should feel it needful to begin this
                    letter with an excuse for its delay, – but I am busier than ever &amp; likely to be so for some time to come. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> arrived the very day you left us, &amp; staid here till the beginning of
                    September. I wish you were in London that you might see the pictures she took, before they are framed &amp; sent off to Keswick.
                    Of me there is a not very chearful likeness, yet a likeness; of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> a remarkably
                    good one. of the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> two whole length miniatures as good as they can possibly be. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Saras</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridges</ref> were not finished but
                    promised well, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovells</ref><del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; one of the most striking resemblances I ever saw. Had she come a week sooner I should have begged you to
                    sit, – &amp; very very much do I regret that this was not the case.</p><p rend="indent1"> The parcel had better set off without longer delay. About the shoes they would certainly be cheap at seven
                    shillings instead of six, – but the charge of an additional shilling looks ill, &amp; I will try this second batch before I order
                    more.</p><p rend="indent1"> My lease was executed about three weeks before poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jacksons</ref>
                        death.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In September 1809, Southey signed a twenty-one year lease to rent <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note><ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilson</ref> bears up well. She has hitherto had a good deal of
                    bustle, which keeps her spirits up. His two brothers are here, – the one who is now my Landlord is a very striking &amp; most
                    respectable man, about fifty years of age.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Joseph Jackson (dates unknown).</note>
                    I have seldom seen a man with so benign &amp; excellent a countenance, – &amp; that he does not belie those outward &amp; visible
                    signs of goodness is proved by this circumstance, – that having succeeded to a living of 250£ a year, &amp; the widow of the
                    former incumbent being left in poverty, – he <del>xxx</del> regularly paid her 100 of it, – &amp; that at a time when he had
                    nothing more.</p><p rend="indent1"> I was very sorry to hear of <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> accident, – it is however well that it
                    was no worse. It was unlucky that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Heineken<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Heineken (dates
                        unknown), a Unitarian lawyer who lived for some time in Bristol, then in Swansea.</note> did not receive your letter, – for
                    the future desire his brother to draw freely upon me for any civilities at Keswick.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> has just left me after a visit of four days only, &amp; with him I suppose our
                    visitors end for the season. Thank James<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac James (b. 1759), the son of Samuel James
                        (1716–1773), Baptist minister at Hitchin. Isaac came to Bristol in 1773 as a student at the Baptist Academy. He kept a shop as
                        a bookseller, dealer in tea (and sometimes undertaker), first in North Street and then in Wine Street.</note> for me for his
                    offer of Muratori, – but I have the original Italian.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lodovico Antonio Muratori
                        (1672–1750), <title>Il Cristianesimo Felice nelle Missioni de’ Padri della Compagnia di Gesu nel Paraguai</title> (1752),
                        translated as <title>A Relation of the Missions of Paraguay: Wrote Originally in Italian, by Mr. Muratori</title>
                        (1759).</note> You may tell him that I wrote the defence of the Baptist Mission in the Quarterly.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published
                        from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the
                            Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an
                            Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to
                            Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the
                            Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on
                            the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> What I wished Hort to do in the shape of a second volume was to draw up summaries of those other mythologies which
                    have extensively prevailed in former times, or are at present existing.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard
                        Hort (1764–1849), Unitarian minister and writer. Southey is referring to his work entitled <title>The New Pantheon, or, An
                            Introduction to the Mythology of the Ancients, in Question and Answer: Compiled Principally for the Use of Young
                            Persons</title> (1809).</note> There is no book of this kind, &amp; it could not fail of success. – the Druidical, – the
                    Runic, – the old Persian system of Zoroaster, Manicheism, the superstition of the Hindoos, that of the Boodhists as existing in
                    Siam, that <del>of the</del> or rather those of the Japanese, there being two established superstitions there, &amp; the
                    Mahommedan. If he thinks the hint worthy of attention I will with great pleasure write him a long letter upon the subject which
                    may save him some trouble by directing him to the best materials.</p><p rend="indent1"> I believe you know that <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has offered to take <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert Lovell</ref> as an apprentice without a premium. This offer <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> communicated to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Frank<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arnee Frank (1766–1858), a prominent Bristol Quaker and ironmonger. His first wife, Edith (d.
                        1799), was an aunt of Robert Lovell, Junior.</note> for the consideration of <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">his
                        fathers family</ref>, requesting that they would supply the boy with cloathing – she had no answer, – &amp; this is the more
                    unpleasant because it is time that Pople should have one. Will you be so good as to see Martha , &amp; by her to ask of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> King (Lydia Lovell)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lydia Lovell (1777–1830), an aunt of Robert
                        Lovell, Junior.</note> – whether M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Frank received the letter in question, &amp; immediately to write
                    &amp; let her sisters know. I am also charged to desire that she will be pleased to buy two half-crown dolls, who if their heads
                    are well covered with their night-caps may come <hi rend="ital">in</hi> two of my shoes in the parcel.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, – tho with little hope of success. He has
                    been prevented from coming here by the sudden death of his father, – a very fine old man.</p><p rend="indent1"> The last Friend ought to please every body, – I was not surprised that the former numbers gave little satisfaction.
                    He goes on to my great astonishment, – &amp; I have no doubt whatever that as he goes on &amp; gets thro his metaphysics enough
                    will be found to amuse &amp; delight every body.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge’s periodical, <title>The
                        Friend</title>, was published in 26 instalments from 1 June 1809 to 15 March 1810. The eighth number, of 5 October 1809, contained Coleridge’s speculations about illusions and ghosts, part of an entertaining biographical sketch of Luther. The ninth number, of 12 October, returned to the drier subject of ‘the grounds of government as laid exclusively in the pure reason’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is quitting the Post-service, selling his mule, – &amp; drawing bills upon
                        <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>. – this is the last news of him viâ Durham by a letter which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> has received from her father.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Her
                        father was Richard Sealy (dates unknown) a wealthy Lisbon merchant.</note> It will be lucky if nothing worse than Botany Bay
                    may be his lot at last.</p><p rend="indent1"> So <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is playing the game of getting into the army by charity a
                    second time! – I hold myself obliged to him for having thought proper to drop all correspondence with me, inasmuch as it has saved
                    me the unpleasant feeling of cutting it off on my part. Never was there a more melancholy instance of a man corrupting his own
                    nature. Had he staid in the army when he was there he would have been well provided for in time, – but he must needs go to Poland,
                        <del>&amp;</del> fall in love with a Princess, &amp; pinch up French morality at second hand! –</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be glad of the Miss: Numbers, being soon to write again upon the subject.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s review of [James Sedgwick (1775–1851; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Hints to the Public and the
                            Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), appeared in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480–514.</note> So the sooner the parcel sets off the better.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>