<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1541</idno><idno type="nines">rce2663</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42550.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 492–493.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1541" type="letter"><head>1541. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1808-11-23">23 November
                    1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray/ Bookseller/ Fleet Street/
                        London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ NOV26/ 1808<lb/>Watermark: 1807/ JW &amp; BB<lb/>Endorsement: 1808 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 23 – Keswick/ Southey. Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi>/ L.Q.R./ 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Letter acknowl Re/ceipt
                        of Bks on Missions &amp;/ assign others<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42550<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 492–493.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1808-11-23">Wedn. Nov. 23. 1808</date></dateline><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I shall with hearty good will enter upon a general view of the existing Protestant Missions, tho what I had
                    proposed related only to those in the East, my purpose being to show that the outcry raised against them <del>on</del> is as
                    impolitic &amp; as unphilosophical as it is irreligious; I am no fanatic myself, nor do I believe that salvation is exclusively
                    attached to a belief in the Christian faith; – but <del>th</del> it is only from that faith that any amelioration of mankind is to
                    be hoped for &amp; those institutions of society, &amp; habits of feeling &amp; of action, which are essential to the well-being
                    of nations &amp; individuals, are not communicable by any other means.</p><p rend="indent1"> The two associations with the History of which I am best acquainted are the Baptist, &amp; the Missionary Society,
                    – it is with this latter that I conceive the Thorntons<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Thornton (1760–1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and his wife Marianne, née Sykes (1765–1815; <title>DNB</title>), members of the evangelical Clapham
                        sect and supporters of the Church Missionary Society.</note> &amp; their party to be connected. Their transactions I reviewed
                    at length in the three first volumes of the Annual, &amp; those articles are the first which appeared upon the subject.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Volumes 1 (1803) and 2 (1806) of <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title>, were
                        reviewed by Southey as the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title> in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (1809), 24–61. He had reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title> (1800–1801), in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207–218. In the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), he reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (Vol.
                        1, 1803), 189–201. In the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805) he reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary
                            Society</title> (Vol. 2, 1804), 621–634.</note><del>With</del> &lt;Upon&gt; the proceedings of the Moravians I am not so well informed, &amp; it will be of service to me if you
                    can procure the first 39 numbers of their account, these which have arrived in your parcel being the first which I had seen.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Periodical Accounts Relating to the Missions of the Church of the United
                            Brethren, Established Among the Heathen</title> (1790– ).</note> Loskiels Hist. of their Missions in N America,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Henry Loskiel (1740–1814), <title>History of the Mission of the United Brethren among
                            the Indians in North America</title> (1794).</note> &amp; Crantz’s Greenland<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        David Cranz (1723–1777), <title>The History of Greenland: containing a description of the country, and its inhabitants: and
                            particularly, a relation of the Mission, carried on for above these thirty years by the Unitas Fratrum, at New Herrnhuth
                            and Lichtenfels, in that Country</title> (1767).</note> I have. These previous numbers, Claudius Buchanan’s book,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Claudius Buchanan (1766–1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoir of the Expediency of an
                            Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India</title> (1805).</note> &amp; the pamphlets of Waring &amp; Twining<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos
                            from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on
                            the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by
                            their Conversion to Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the
                            Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807).</note>
                    with the various publications to which they have given rise, I shall be glad to consult, &amp; it will be well to have Sidney
                    Smith’s reviewal sent with them,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), ‘Indian
                        Missions’, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 12:23 (April 1808), 151–181.</note> – that Review never falling in my way. The
                    Quaker accounts I have.</p><p rend="indent1"> There is another Society which has missionaries in Tartary, but of which I have never seen any account except some
                    brief notices in a few stray numbers of the Evangelical Magazine.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Morrison
                        (1782–1834; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish member of the London Missionary Society, had established the first protestant
                        mission at Canton in 1807.</note> I rather think it is a Scotch society. If <del>x</del> any documents concerning their
                    proceedings could be obtained, they would enable me to render this proposed summary compleat.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have now Sir to thank you for the pains you have already taken. You will perceive that my intention is to defend
                    the missions, not upon calvinistic grounds, but philosophically, in the spirit &amp; with the feeling of a Christian so as I trust
                    to accord with <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Giffords</ref> views of the subject.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I am Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yours with respect</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>