<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1480</idno><idno type="nines">rce2602</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1480" type="letter"><head>1480. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1808-07-16">16 July
                        1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Chas Danvers Esqr /
                        Bristol<lb/>Endorsements: London July twenty 1808// Wm Dear / R<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Sharp// [calculations]<lb/>Stamped:
                        None.<lb/>Postmarks: FREE/ 20 JY 20/1808// JY/20/1808<lb/>Seal: Partial<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1808-07-16">July 16 .1808.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Charles </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> was sorely disappointed in not finding you at Bristol when he fled thro on his way
                    to Plymouth. I supposed you were gone to London on no pleasant business. – &amp; the Gazette has since shown me that my fears were
                    right. – You ask me where <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is, that you may write to him &amp; remind him of
                    his debt: – I have heard nothing from him since he left this house, nor <hi rend="ital">of</hi> him except what came from you.</p><p rend="indent1"> In the course of the last ten weeks I have met with some unpleasant interruptions in my ordinary business – first
                    from a bilious fever which attacked <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref>; afterwards seized on <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, &amp; <del>made him</del> alarmed us a good deal for many days. And now for
                    the last month I have been plagued with one of my abominable catarrhs, – such as you saw me with when you were here. Tomorrow it
                    will be a month old, &amp; after a dozen variations from worse to better &amp; better to worse, it is now as bad as ever it was. I
                    generally calculate upon a six weeks spell when it begins, &amp; in this instance am not likely to be disappointed. It is a
                    comfort that the complaint is altogether confined to the head, &amp; not accompanied with any general indisposition, but it has
                    affected my eyes, &amp; made me lose many days work. – </p><p rend="indent1"> I told you I should proceed with Kehama,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &amp; write it before breakfast, that if the whole labour were lost in a
                    pecuniary point of view, as is very likely, there might be no loss of time, the time being fairly won from sleep.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, see Southey to Charles Danvers, 5 May 1808, Letter 1456.</note> These hindrances
                    have sadly kept me back, still however good progress has been made. When I returned home 910 lines were the sum of total of what
                    was written, &amp; it now amounts to 1560. I am in the vein, &amp; as soon as this troublesome cold will allow me time for any
                    thing besides sneezing &amp; flourishing my own trumpet, my progress will in all probability be a rapid one – All my old dreams of
                    poetry are rising, as it were, from the dead. I am planning a blank-verse poem upon Pelayo, the Restorer of Spain,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelagius/Pelayo (c. 685–737), founder of the Kingdom of Asturias. Through his victory at the
                        Battle of Covadonga, he is credited with beginning the Christian reconquest of the Iberian peninsula from the Moors. The
                        planned poem became <title>Roderick, Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> – an old subject taken up with new interest just
                    at this time. As soon as the plan is perfected I shall begin to write it, in those intervals when Kehama is at a stand, – for
                        <del>such</del> intervals <del>must</del> &lt;there&gt; occasionally <del>xxx</del> &lt;will be&gt;, when tho the whole story
                    is made, the immediate manner of passing from one part to another does not occur; – &amp; therefore time <del>xxx xxx</del>
                    &lt;is&gt; saved by having two upon the stocks at <del>x</del> once. My plan of operations will be a very simple, &amp; as it
                    appears to me, by no means an imprudent one. If Kehama does not pay me the fair trade price of the time bestowed upon it, I
                    publish no more poetry; – there is not much doubt but that this will be the case; &amp; if it be so, it then becomes me to think
                    something of posthumous profit, as well as posthumous fame, &amp; to secure copy rights to my children, after my death;
                        <del>when</del> for our wise laws of Literary Property would throw them open just when they became valuable. So I will write
                    on strenuously, &amp; go thro the whole series which was projected so many years ago; &amp; as many more, if I have life &amp;
                    health for it: dedicating to this sole employment the hours gained by rising at a reasonable hour, – not a very early one, because
                    that would be hurtful – but as soon as after six may be. And these poems shall be left behind me, they will then fetch their
                    value, as good drafts upon posterity. This scheme pleases me a good deal. There will be a great pleasure &amp; satisfaction in
                    accumulating property in this form; &amp; if it prove a vain &amp; fallacious one, I shall not have the mortification of seeing it
                    so. But this is not likely. Poets like woodcocks are not ranked till they are dead, &amp; then their very trail is food for the
                    most fastidious palate.</p><p rend="indent1"> This is a grand struggle which the Spaniards have begun. It is to be expected that they will meet with many
                    disasters, – they will often be defeated, often betrayed, – they will commit some excesses &amp; some errors, but of their
                    eventual success I do not entertain a doubt. The principle of Patriotism which is in them, – the remembrance of what their fathers
                    have been, &amp; the thought of what their children are to be, will bear them thro. You will see in this volume of the Annual what
                    were my <del>tho</del> opinions concerning Spain twelve months ago, – in the reviewal of Semples Travels.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey’s review of Robert Semple (1777–1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Observations on a Journey
                            through Spain and Italy to Naples; and thence to Smyrna and Constantinople</title> (1807), in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1807</title>, 6 (1808), 118–130.</note> There is a circumstance stated in todays paper, of which the Editor does not know
                    the importance, – that Gomes Freire is at the head of a body of insurgents in Portugal. Gomes Freire is an experienced &amp; good
                    soldier, the only man in the army in whom they had any confidence; &amp; in him they have the greatest.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gomes Freire de Andrade (1757–1817), Portuguese general.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday brought me a letter from <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">T. Smith</ref>, announcing the rug &amp; a
                    cheese, which are travelling companions in the waggon.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s letter acknowledging
                        these, see Southey to Thomas Smith, 15 August 1808, Letter 1492.</note> I delay my answer till these Lakers arrive. – You will
                    get the Cid<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> in
                    about a month.</p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Shepherd of Liverpool has been here with her husband<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Shepherd (d. 1829), née Nicholson, married, in 1792, the Rev. Dr William Shepherd (1768–1847; <title>DNB</title>),
                        pastor at the English Presbyterian Chapel, Gateacre, Liverpool, The couple lived at The Nook, Gateacre, from where they ran a
                        boarding school. Southey had met them in Liverpool when he visited <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> in
                        February 1808.</note> – perhaps you will not immediately recollect that I mean one of your cousins. The Lakers come pouring
                    in, &amp; as there will be one here tomorrow whose autograph is worth elevenpence at Bristol, I shall set up this letter in a
                    conspicuous place, that I may not forget to <del>make</del> deduce some good from his Parliamentary powers.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">That is, one of the visitors Southey expected – <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard
                            Sharp</ref> – was an MP and so had the privilege of sending mail without charge, thus saving Danvers the postage cost of Southey’s letter.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If you have heard from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> you will know that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. Southey</ref> turnd his back upon him, saying, he never
                    desired to see any of the family again. This man has turned <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">his sister</ref> out of doors, –
                    &amp; thus thought proper to break off all intercourse with us. Amen, so be it. He is treading in the steps of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">his brother</ref> ; &amp; I verily believe <del>there is</del> some sort of craziness <del>at
                        the bottom of</del> has occasioned the otherwise unaccountable conduct of both. So Charles if it should be my destiny to stick
                    in Heavens-gate, it will not be because my breeches pockets are too full.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is getting on at Durham, &amp; will in no very long time be able to
                    maintain himself well by his profession. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> when he wrote had not yet found his ship,
                    but had learnt that he was to be First Lieutenant. – for a chance appointment this is a remarkable one: &amp; it so happens that I
                    know a little of Adm. Sotheby, &amp; more of his brother.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom’s new posting was to HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi>, a 98-gun second rate ship of the line launched in 1801. She had fought at Trafalgar (1805)
                        and was now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby (1759–1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby
                        (1757–1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey’s acquaintance.</note><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> will be an Admiral yet: &amp; for myself I trust one of these days to have the post
                    of Historiographer<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey long coveted the post of Historiographer Royal. It was
                        occupied by Louis Dutens (1730–1812; <title>DNB</title>), and, on his death, given to James Stanier Clarke (1765?–1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> created for me. There will come a time when this may be done, &amp; till that time I shall be
                    making good my claims to it. So <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. Southey</ref> may make his
                    will to his own hearts desire. It was in his power to have benefited me &amp; given me pleasure, – it is not in his power to give
                    me one moments pain: Many persons who can do no good, can do mischief, – but the reverse <del>xxx</del> is the case here. –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>