<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1267</idno><idno type="nines">rce2389</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 404–408.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1267" type="letter"><head>1267. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1807-01-27">27 January 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ JAN31/ 1807; 10 o’Clock/ JA.31/ 1807<lb/>Endorsement: N.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 125 1807/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>/ rec.<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                            31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April<lb/>MS: Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 404–408.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1807-01-27">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 27. 1807.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I omitted to notice the heavy loss you sustained in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wakefield<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Revd. Thomas Wakefield (d.1806) held the living of May’s parish, Richmond, Surrey, for thirty years. He
                        was the brother of Gilbert Wakefield (1756–1801; <title>DNB</title>), the Unitarian classical scholar and radical pamphleteer,
                        whom <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and Southey admired and whose death after a period of
                        imprisonment was mourned by the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Aikin family</ref> and other Unitarian dissenters.</note>
                    from haste, letters &amp; a proof-sheet (which requires immediate attention) coming in while I was writing to you, which put it
                    out of my head. What your loss must have been struck me when I read his death in the newspaper, &amp; I sincerely condole with you
                    upon the occasion. The character which you sent me I like well, &amp; what you have (in your last) added to it better, because it
                    is more <del>xxxxx</del> discriminating. – You ask me for an inscription, – the successful one I conjecture will come from <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> ; a likely man – from family &amp; friendly feelings to
                    attempt one, &amp; a likely one to succeed in it. The <hi rend="ital">lapidary</hi> style is of all others the most difficult, – I
                    have a volume written upon it by a German – but it is not here, &amp; I have never yet read it. In my own judgement the shorter
                    such things are the better, – <hi rend="ital">all</hi> cannot be said upon stone, <del>some gain</del> comprehension therefore
                    should be aimed at, – not discrimination. I would enter his character at length in the register ‘by special desire of his
                    Parishioners’ – &amp; inscribe the stone with something to this purport</p><p rend="center">This Monument is erected</p><p rend="center">by</p><p rend="center">The Inhabitants</p><p rend="center">of</p><p rend="center">Richmond</p><p rend="center">in grateful &amp; honourable remembrance</p><p rend="center">of</p><p rend="center">Thomas Wakefield</p><p rend="center">Their Excellent Pastor.</p><p rend="indent1"> The full character would be equally copied from the register as from a monument into Magazines &amp; County
                    Histories, <del>x</del> from its unusuality it would have a better chance of being read, &amp; the circumstance of its being so
                    placed would ensure belief for it, which marble, having so long been taught to tell lies, could hardly expect. – Your loss in such
                    a man must indeed be serious, &amp; there is little hope that it can be replaced.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your fears least I should alter a plan deliberately formed, for the sake of temporary advantage,
                    &amp; so injure it. Such however will not be the case, – nor indeed is there any temporal advantage which could ever induce me in
                    any of my own literary plans to depart, in the slightest degree, from what I believed to be the best possible way. Portugueze
                    History naturally &amp; necessarily falls into three great divisions – that of the Mother Country &amp; of the <del>East
                        Indies</del> Asiatic Conquests, &amp; of Brazil. Barros<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey owned Joao de Barros
                        (1496–1570) and Diogo de Couto, <title>Decadas da Asia dos Feitos, que os Portuguezes Fizeram na conquista, e Descubrimento
                            das Terras, e Mares do Oriente</title> (1778–1788).</note> &amp; Favia e Sousa<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey owned Manuel de Faria y Sousa (1590–1649), <title>Asia Portuguesa</title> (1666–1675).</note> would be authorities
                    sufficient – if I <del>even</del> needed authority for my sanction. But <del>their</del> to divide the subject was the first
                    advice <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref> gave me, &amp; as soon as I got acquainted with my materials I
                    perceived that they could not be disposed of otherwise without an endless confusion, – of which – if you have read La Clede<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas de La Clede (1700–1736), <title>Histoire Generale de Portugal</title>
                        (1735).</note> you must have been sensible. I differ from Barros &amp; old Manoel<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Manuel de Faria e Sousa (1590–1649), the Portuguese historian whose works appeared posthumously as <title>Europa
                            Portugueza</title> (1667); <title>Ásia Portugueza</title> (1666–1675); <title>África Portugueza</title> (1681).</note> in
                    not seperating Africa from the Mother-Country, – in that they are wrong, <del>before</del> because those events are inseperably
                    connected with home politics, on which the colonies &amp; other conquests had no other effect whatever than what the revenues
                    which they sent home produced.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Brazilian history therefore is as distinct from that of the Mother Country as if it had no connection with it,
                    &amp; the only circumstance in which it will not be quite so compleat as if the other parts had been published is, that it is my
                    intention in each part to give an account of the authors referred to, <del>their lives</del> biographical &amp; critical; &amp;
                    there will be a few quoted here of whom the accounts must be in the other parts, Joan de Barros for instance, &amp; Antonio
                        Galvano,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Galvaō (c. 1490–1557), <title>Tratado dos Descobrimentos Antigos, e
                            Modernos Feitos ate a Era de 1550</title> (1731).</note> – who treat only incidentally of Brazil. </p><p rend="indent1"> You will perceive from this explanation that your friendly fears are causeless. </p><p rend="indent1"> We are going upon a wrong plan with respect to South America, &amp; a ruinous one, –which must occasion a
                    tremendous effusion of blood sooner or later, &amp; inevitably to our ultimate defeature.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In June 1806, with Spain, the colonial master of South America, under French sway and Britain’s enemy, a force under Admiral
                        Sir Home Riggs Popham (1762–1820; <title>DNB</title>) and William Carr Beresford (1768–1856; <title>DNB</title>), occupied
                        Buenos Aires and held it until 14 August. On 3 February 1807 the attack was renewed when the British took Montevideo from the
                        sea. In July a British attempt to retake Buenos Aires was repulsed with great loss of life.</note> What should be done is to
                    throw the Spanish Colonies open, &amp; leave them alone, by which means we should have the full benefit of commercial intercourse
                    – which is all the good the nation ever can derive from them, without expence or hazard; cut off their trade with the Mother
                    Country, and make a free trade with them the main article of peace. We should thus materially forward the improvement of that
                    wonderful country. But ministers want places to dispose of, – &amp; in this all ministers are alike. It seems as if there were
                    some law of nature by which Governments <del>never</del> were <del>th</del> always to be behind hand with the people in wisdom,
                    &amp; never to adopt sound principles of conduct till long after all thinking men had considered them as axiomatic. </p><p rend="indent1"> I am hurrying my printer with Don Manuel,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) was being printed by Richard Taylor (1781–1858;
                            <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with
                        his son William Francis (1817–1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> in whose letters, with much matter of a lighter cast,
                    you will see <del>some</del> a good deal of my mind poured out on subjects of <del>some</del> importance. But my limits have been
                    too constrained, &amp; the book would ha[MS torn] been better if it had suited me to have extended it to a fourth volume. The most
                    compleat part will be the view of the different religious sects in the country – in which I think no former historian of heresies
                    has equalled me, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Epiphanius<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saint Epiphanius (ca. 310–403), Bishop
                        of Salamis, compiled a huge compendium of heresies.</note> himself not excepted. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> grows finely, &amp; if it were for the Tartar-shaped eyes
                    which all my children have – I cannot divine by what right of inheritance – he would be a beauty. I tell <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> that she is like my old books, – ugly, but good; – tho sometimes sad to
                    say the latter part of the simily is not so accurate as the former. All her perceptions &amp; feelings are so fearfully quick,
                    that I am never without a dread <del>of their</del> that some tendency to organic disease occasions this exquisite acuteness.
                    Thank God she is well as yet, &amp; as strong as if she were own child to Hercules or Samson, before he had his hair cut.</p><p rend="indent1"> In my last, I recommended to you the Memoirs of Colonel Hutchinson<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy
                        Hutchinson (1620–1681; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806), a posthumously
                        published memoir by the widow of Colonel John Hutchinson (1615–1664; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan commander in the English
                        civil war and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I. For Southey’s letter to May, see Southey to John May, 29
                        December 1806, Letter 1252.</note> – let me now recommend D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jarrolds Dissertations on Man in reply to the
                    abominable book of Malthus<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Jarrold (1770–1853; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological, and Political; In Answer to Mr. Malthus’s ‘Essay on the
                            Principle of Population’</title> (1806).</note> – <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is with
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> in Leicestershire.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> At
                        Coleorton, seat of <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref>.</note><ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> &amp; the children are
                    to join him somewhere on the way to Ottery,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ottery St Mary, Devon, the birthplace of
                        Coleridge and the home of his mother and brothers.</note> early in the spring. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> joins me in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>. You have perhaps seen his <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctorship</ref> by this time – as he knows where &amp; when you are visible.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RSouthey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>