<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1221</idno><idno type="nines">rce2343</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library,
                        Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1221" type="letter"><head>1221. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-09-28">28–29 September
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Thomas Southey./ with Charles Danvers
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] E/ OCT/ 1806<lb/>MS: British Library,
                        Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1806-09-28">Sunday Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 28. 1806.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your inclosure did not catch my eye till the morning after your departure. it startled me – &amp; I shall not
                    attempt to say how much it made me feel upon opening it. I shall make use of the draft at present, rather than borrow of any else,
                    – &amp; replace the sum in your agents hands as soon as I can spare it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had
                        left his brother £50 of the prize money he had earned while in the West Indies; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 18 October
                        1806, Letter 1229.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I feel very lonely now you &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> are gone, &amp;
                    more deprest by your departure than his – because I know when to meet him again, but when you &amp; I separate, it is always
                    doubtful when or where we may meet again. Besides <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I were not boys
                    together. However whenever we have separated it has been each time with better hopes than the last, &amp; whenever we have met in
                    advanced circumstances – slow steps indeed, but sure ones. I have good hopes from the change in the Admiralty. By the by Admiral
                    Markhams answer to Burn’s application is ‘I will endeavour to meet your wish for the employment of Lieutenant Southey as soon as
                    opportunity offers’.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Markham (1761–1827; <title>DNB</title>): naval officer who was a
                        member of the Board of Admiralty (1801–1804 and 1806–1807) and MP for Portsmouth (1801–1818 and 1820–1826). William Burns
                        (dates unknown), a member of the English Factory, Lisbon. Southey had asked John May if he could get his brother mentioned to
                        Markham in the hope of securing promotion; see Southey to John May, 13 September 1806, Letter 1215. In the event, this attempt
                        was unsuccessful; see Southey to John Rickman, 26 June 1807, Letter 1336.</note> It is not impossible that this opportunity
                    may be some while delayed, but it is also not impossible that something better may come to you from a higher quarter. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> knows that nothing in the world would give me so much pleasure as your promotion
                    &amp; I have good hopes from him.</p><p rend="indent1"> The best remedy for uncomfortable feelings is hard work. I turned to as soon as you were gone, &amp; shipped off
                    yesterday a cargo of Espriella,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> being a fourth part of the second-volume. The humour
                    is on me &amp; I shall stick to it till another batch be put out of hand. I wait only for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> return to finish off the Preface, that he may give me a German
                    extract which is wanted there.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was writing the preface for <title>Specimens of the
                            Later English Poets</title> (1807), which was being prepared for the press. Southey cites Coleridge in the preface for
                        providing an extract from the German legend of St. Anno. <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London,
                        1807), I, xi.</note> There came a letter from him to night saying that he is still waiting to see Lord Howick<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764–1845; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1830–1834 and leading Whig; he became First
                            Lord of the Admiralty in 1806. He was briefly known by the courtesy title, Lord Howick, in 1806–1807, after his father, Charles Grey (1729–1807) was created Earl Grey.</note> &amp; hopes to
                    leave London on Monday; – but this is very uncertain. – My eyes are better &amp; I expect to get thro a world of work full speed.
                    As soon as Espriella is done, &amp; what little reviewing falls to my lot, I shall go to your letters. My heart is set upon this –
                    &amp; you will be surprized, when your information is methodized, to see how much you have collected.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> These notes were eventually worked into a book, Thomas Southey, <title>A Chronological History of the West
                            Indies</title> (1827).</note> Do you meantime open another commonplace book &amp; minute down all your recollections –
                    every little thing you <del>recollect</del> &lt;can call to mind&gt; whether of man or beast, fish flesh fowl or insect. &lt;– no
                    matter how insignificant it may appear.&gt; I shall send you letter by letter as launched to interleave &amp; comment upon, –
                    &amp; believe me <del>xxx</del> my fingers itch to be at it.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have been a good deal shocked since you left us. Miss Orton<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Unidentified.</note> is dead. The <del>xxx</del><ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref><del>had</del> &lt;sent to&gt; ask<del>ed</del> her to meet us at dinner last Wednesday – but she was gone on a visit to
                    Cockermouth, &amp; there on Thursday she died. From what I can understand she seems to have had some disease of the heart.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have forwarded two letters to you, three to that Dog of Dumplings <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref>. tell him I have manfully resolved to walk every day, that I began yesterday &amp; have persevered to day
                    &amp; shall continue so to do. <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> bids me say that both her
                    Aunts will be gone to Seaton – so will the Trurims<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> – so will the
                        Hallidays.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> Somersetshire will be the duller for all this. I will
                    however inclose a letter for <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> – which your sudden departure prevented me from
                    getting ready in time – he is a self-taught man, who has done wonders for himself, he has a strong head &amp; an honest heart,
                    &amp; I am mistaken if you do not like him – If you go to Minehead it will vary your route to go by way of <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> &amp; Watchett, – &amp; if not – it is but a pleasant ride there over Quantock, for
                    you &amp; the Physician.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have left the country too soon – Every day improves its beauty. If <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> comes I must make him go to the Caves<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his letter to Charles Danvers, 3 February 1806 (Letter 1151) Southey had expressed his desire to visit some
                        caves with a companion. They were probably those near Ingleton in Yorkshire, or those in the Peak District on the Derbyshire
                        and Yorkshire border.</note> with me – it is provoking that I can get no companion for this easy journey – &amp; to take it
                    alone is to lose half the pleasure, – nothing is so hateful as a lonely evening at an inn. As soon as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is safe in bed please God – I shall write to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Shall I send you the Poems, Joan of Arc &amp; Last Annual<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796) and the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806).</note> to Taunton? or will you wait
                    for them till you are housed on ship-board.</p><p rend="indent1"> Send me any memoranda of your whole road which may do for Espriella – also any thing about Somersetshire Devon
                    &amp; Cornwall – &amp; especially Plymouth – I shall gallop on with this book, &amp; expect to report progress at a great rate.
                    One walks on with the better will when half the journey is over, &amp; better still the nearer the end is in view.</p><p rend="indent1"> My daughter often enquires for you – where’s Uncle Tom? where’s <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Uncle
                        Doctor</ref>? I want’em. – Why dont em come to breakfast? was the question this evening when she called to tea.</p><p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> have not yet sent off my books, &amp; should in course of
                    search for them discover a most <del>xxx</del> incurable duck<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey named his more
                        dilapidated books ‘ducks’.</note> wrapt up in paper – without covers or with ragged ones, imperfect &amp; dirty to the last
                    degree of duckishness, being the work of John – somebody the The Servant of the Lamb<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Perrot (d. 1665; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Battering Rams Against Rome. Or, the Battel of John, the Follower of the Lamb,
                            Fought with the Pope, and His Priests, Whilst He Was a Prisoner in the Inquisition-Prison of Rome</title> (1661).</note> –
                    a Quaker who went to Rome to convert the Pope, let him put it in the box – (which is to come <hi rend="ital">by waggon</hi> –) But
                    do not I do not wish him to take any trouble <del>f</del> in looking for it – only to lay hands on it if it comes in his way. I
                    can make up an article from it for the Athenæum –<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was planning to contribute
                        articles to the <title>Athenæum, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807–1809). Perrot’s journey to
                        Rome to convert the Pope is alluded to in <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807), letter 57. Perrot is not discussed in the <title>Athenæum</title>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Remember me to all friends whom you may see at
                    Bristol. I should like to see them myself – not forgetting Joe &amp; Juniper<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joe was
                        Thomas Southey’s dog, in Danvers’s care. Juniper (first name and dates unknown) was a Bristol carpenter who built book cases
                        for Southey and also bound books for him.</note> in the number – you should show Juniper as one of the curiosities of Bristol
                    to that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">brother of ours who has given us Esculapius as an Uncle</ref>.</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-09-29">Monday evening. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 29. 1806</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>