<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1217</idno><idno type="nines">rce2339</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1217" type="letter"><head>1217. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-09-19">19 September
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb/>Endorsements: 66./ Madoc; John Savant/ if the [illegible word]/ Folio Dante; Folio [illegible words]<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E / SEP22/ 1806 <lb/>Seal: [illegible]<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1806-09-19">Friday. Sept. 19. 1806</date></dateline><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> For some days past I have refrained from writing to you, thinking it probable that a letter would arrive, &amp; my
                    expectation has this evening been fulfilled. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> are both reading by the light of my <del>xxx</del> single candle –
                    sad to say my eyes are ailing again &amp; I am thus obliged to sport Nicodemus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rembrandt
                        van Rijn (1606–1669) etched a picture of Jesus and Nicodemus, the Pharisee who, in John’s gospel (3.1–21) visited Jesus by
                        night. In the etching, the figures are illuminated only by one candle.</note> as the phrase is, which else, tho I do for
                    myself at all times – I should not for them. However the complaint is by no means violent &amp; I hope will speedily go off. Why
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has not written it would be difficult to say, &amp; yet is very easy to
                    understand – he has talked daily of doing it, &amp; thought daily of his daily procrastination as a neglect of duty, &amp; begs me
                    now to say that forgetfulness has not been the occasion. I think he will go to Taunton, &amp; if so you will of course see him on
                    his way. As for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref>, sheer idleness I suppose will continue to keep him
                    silent – I believe he makes about half a dozen &lt;new&gt; correspondents every year, who are regularly superseded by as many
                    more. He is to blame – but you will not judge too hardly of a fault which you foresaw. We very often talk of you &amp; never
                    without a wish that you were here again to mountaineer with us.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you heard that <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Fricker</ref> is turned Methodist? the grace of
                    God which passeth all understanding<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘And the peace of God, which passeth all understanding
                        shall keep your hearts and minds through Jesus Christ’, Philippians 4:7.</note> has turned his poor head – he has caught all
                    the language of the Evangelicals, &amp; is at present arduously employed in endeavouring to convert his mother &amp; sisters, an
                    enterprise in which he displays much zeal &amp; more ability than you would suppose. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> has secured from him a large packet of letters &amp; tracts published by the Society for
                    the promotion of religious knowledge,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge had
                        been publishing religious literature since 1698.</note> all of which are well calculated to make proselytes for Bedlam. On the
                    whole, as it will not stand in the way of his worldly interests I am more amused than vexed <del>x</del> at having a brother in
                    law among the Saints. Poor <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> too has made an attack upon me, &amp; has filled
                    half a sheet of <hi rend="ital">fools</hi> cap (aptly so employed) with wishes that I ‘might yet become a disciple of Jesus &amp;
                    not be condemned with the world, exhortations to the love of God, &amp; hopes that I ‘may yet obtain in common with himself an
                    inheritance among the Saints in light, &amp; an introduction in a better world to the Society of just men made perfect.’ I am less
                    angry than you would have been – or to speak more truly – not angry at all, – only thinking at the time that it was not very
                    modest in him to take it for granted that he had <del>xxx xxx</del> considered the subject more than I have done; or was better
                    qualified to understand it; &amp; not very decent in him to imply that I am not a disciple of Jesus.</p><p rend="indent1"> Nothing which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> does can possibly surprize me – unless it should
                    be any thing good. The best thing that can now be wished is, that he should do some thing which makes it necessary for him to run
                    away to America. If you have any more intercourse &lt;with him&gt; – (&amp; I think it is time you should not) tell him the best
                    thing he can do is to transport himself – least in waiting to get his passage paid by the government, he should unawares go beyond
                    transportation.</p><p rend="indent1"> Never – never – had I a heavier weight of work upon my poor shoulders. Imprimis<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘in the first place’.</note> the unhappy specimens are so near delivery that my Preface is wanted,
                    &amp; I am now finishing it – one of the things which I least like to do.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s and
                        Grosvenor Bedford’s jointly edited anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807) was being prepared for
                        the press.</note> Secondly half a sheet more finishes the first volume of Espriella<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> – I
                    have as much as another written – but not in sequence – &amp; the full quantity of the third part is yet to write. Thirdly <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has printed the first sheet of Palmerin,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> was published in 4 volumes in 1807.</note>
                    &amp; upon setting to this job in which I expected to have little more to do, than to strike out idle interpolations – I found
                    that about half must be retranslated. Had I made myself acquainted with this in time I would not have undertaken it, but it is too
                    late to retract – &amp; I must set my shoulder to the wheel – which you know, when there is occasion so to do, I can do lustily
                    &amp; with good will. Fourthly – Tho I have given up reviewing still so much of comes to my share, on the score of private good
                    will, or because the subject interests me that there is a full months work lying on the floor in waiting. Fifthly I have promised
                    both <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Aikin</ref> to contribute to the Athenæum<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The short-lived <title>Athenaeum, A Magazine
                            of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807–1809), which was owned by Longman and edited by John Aikin.</note>
                    – &amp; sixthly whenever I [MS torn] a little ahead of the printers &amp; think I have a day or two I set at the Chronicle of the
                        Cid<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>, which was published in 1808.</note>
                    ‘for love’ – as the boxers say [MS torn] are within two days work of being half thro it. – Judge whether or not I am likely to
                    pass an idle winter! <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> moves in a day or two. her visits here are always
                    unfortunate. One of her sisters has suddenly lost her senses – &amp; this recalls her. There are however good hopes of her speedy
                    recovery. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will soon
                    take their departure. It cannot be above a fortnight or three weeks at the farthest before <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will be in bed,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>,
                        the Southeys’ first son, was born 11 October 1806.</note> &amp; then, if by Gods blessing – all go on well – I shall be
                    settled quietly to my regular employments.</p><p rend="indent1"> I want my Missionary numbers because they must both be reviewed this year. <hi rend="ital">The last which I
                        have</hi> of the Transactions (from Barry<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown) was
                        Southey’s favourite Bristol bookseller and stationer; he frequently sent Danvers orders for books to be supplied by
                        Barry.</note>) is N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 12.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> were the periodical reports of the non-denominational London Missionary Society, founded in
                        1795, to establish missions in the South Pacific islands and Africa. They were published as bound volumes after 1804. Southey
                        reviewed the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        189–201, and in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 621–634. He did not review them again this year for the
                            <title>Annual</title>.</note> of the Periodical Accounts (from James<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac James
                        (b. 1759) was the son of Samuel James (1716–1773), Baptist minister at Hitchin. He came to Bristol in 1773 as a student at the
                        Baptist Academy. He kept a shop as a bookseller, dealer in tea (and sometimes undertaker), first in North Street and then in
                        Wine Street.</note>) N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 14.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Periodical Accounts
                            Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> were published as a periodical beginning in 1793, but also as bound
                        volumes from 1800. Southey owned a copy of the five-volume <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> (1800). He reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts</title> (1800–1801) in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1802</title> (1803), 207–218. Southey did not review them again in this year for the <title>Annual</title>.</note> With
                    them there are some books which <del>if</del> &lt;when&gt; you have leisure to look out would be useful to me. the first &amp;
                    most important is a single folio magnificently bound in red morocco, but in sad internal condition. Nobiliario do Conde D Pedro
                    its title.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Nobiliario de D. Pedro Conde de Bracelos Hijo del Rey D. Dionis de
                            Portugal</title> (1640) by Afonso Pedro, Count of Barcelos (1287–1354) and Juan Bautista Labaña (1555–1624) was no. 3571
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library after his death.</note> it is in the box marked N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 7. which
                    came from Falmouth by waggon, &amp; was never opened by me. Secondly Cronicas de Castilla,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Pedro López de Ayala (1332–1407), <title>Coronicas de los Reyes de Castilla Don Pedro, Don Enrique II, Don Juan I, Don
                            Enrique III</title>, which comprised part of a multi-volume collection; no. 3258 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> Volumes 3 &amp; 4, (not 1 &amp; 2.) I think these were left loose with you. half bound quartos. 3 Cardonne.
                    Hist. des Arabes d’Affriques &amp; d’Espagne.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Denis Dominique Cardonne (1721–1783),
                            <title>Histoire de l’Afrique et de l’Espagne, sous la Domination des Arabes; Composée sur Différens Manuscrits Arabes de
                            la Bibliothèque du Roi</title> (1765); no. 539 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> 3 Vol. 12.mo. &amp; the
                    two histories by Marigny<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Franćois Augier de Marigny (d. 1762), <title>Histoire des
                            Revolutions de l’Empire des Arabes</title> (1750), and <title>Histoire des Arabes sous le Gouvernement des Califes</title>
                        (1750); nos 1801 and 1802 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which you lent to Hort.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764–1849), Unitarian Minister and writer, who taught in the Bristol school run by John
                        Prior Estlin (1747–1817; <title>DNB</title>). Hort was one of many storers of books for Southey.</note> each is 4 V. 12.mo.
                    lastly (if you light upon them in your search –) my Port. &amp; Dutch grammars, &amp; the two volumes of Rankins Hist. of
                        France<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Ranken (1755–1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of France
                            from the Time of its Conquest by Clovis to the Death of Louis XVI</title>, 9 vols, (1801); no. 2321 in the sale catalogue
                        of Southey’s library.</note> – new books in 8vo. [MS illegible] boards. – I had nearly forgotten the whole set of Spanish
                    poets – in 19 or 21 volumes – all in marble paper – you will know them by their number &amp; the name D Ramon Fernandez as
                        editor.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Ramón Fernández [believed to be a pseudonym of Pedro Estala (1757–1815)],
                            <title>Coleccion de Diversos Poetas Españoles</title> (1786–1797); no. 3199 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> I am loath to set you on this fatiguing &amp; dusty business –</p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>. If we are both living &amp; doing well we
                    shall meet in the spring. Remember me to all my friends – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately </salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>box them up &amp; send by waggon</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>