<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.904</idno><idno type="nines">rce2026</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        353–355.Dating note: In his letter dated 1 March 1804 (Letter 905), Southey tells Danvers that he has begun a letter to
                        King. Therefore this letter was started on (or before) 1 March but not completed until 5 March.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="904" type="letter"><head>904. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">John King</ref>, <date when="1804-03-01">[1–]5 March 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John King Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Dowry Square/ Hot Wells/
                        Bristol./ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ MAR 8/ 1804<lb/>Endorsements: July 1803 £1. Bank of Engl N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 6661/ April 1803. d<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1686; M<hi rend="sup">rs </hi><del> Burney</del>/ Burney/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davies, Charles/ Temple Manning/ left hand Temple <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb/>Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        353–355.<lb/>Dating note: In his letter dated 1 March 1804 (Letter 905), Southey tells Danvers that he has begun a letter to
                        King. Therefore this letter was started on (or before) 1 March but not completed until 5 March.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> May it please your Majesty</p><p rend="indent1"> It does not please me that in the course of six months you have never written me one letter – &amp; if I had not a
                    favour to ask by way of atonement I should have waited some time longer before I had written you another.</p><p rend="indent1"> You know by <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> how it is settled that Madoc is to be published
                    next winter.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797–1799 and was
                        revising for publication. It was published in 1805.</note> now there are to be vignettes to it, some in copper, some in wood,
                    according to the subject, &amp; when I have explained to you of what kind these are to be, &amp; for what purpose designed, you
                    will see the fitness of the letter &amp; how you can do for me what no one else can do.</p><p rend="indent1"> What I aim at (besides making the book sell, which prints do by making it expensive, for the rich think whatever is
                    dear must be good) – is to elucidate the costume, the antiquities, &amp; the natural history of the poem, so as to make a dull eye
                    see, what a dull imagination could never comprehend. Thus for the first vignette I shall have a ship – copied from William
                    Conquerors tapestry.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bayeux tapestry; for Southey’s complaint that the illustrator
                        Nicholas Pocock (1740–1821) had spoilt the image by drawing a too-modern ship; see Southey to Joseph Cottle, 25 August 1805,
                        Letter 1097.</note> – in another Queen Emma in the Saxon dress of her age, from Strutt,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emma of Anjou (b. c. 1138) was the illegitimate half-sister of Henry II (1133–1189; King of England 1154–1189;
                            <title>DNB</title>) who married Dafydd (in English, David), King of Gwynedd, son of Owain Gwynedd (1100–1170, Prince of
                        Gwynedd 1137–1170; <title>DNB</title>). She is described in <title>Madoc</title>, Part 1, Book II and her Saxon costume was
                        probably to have been copied from Joseph Strutt, (1749–1802; <title>DNB</title>) <title>A Complete View of the Manners,
                            Customs, Arms, Habits, etc. of the Inhabitants of England, from the Arrival of the Saxons till the Reign of Henry
                            VIII</title> (1775–1776).</note> &amp;c. The one which I wish you to do for me relates to natural history – &amp; is, a
                    Water Spout. There are prints of <del>two</del> four in Nicholsons Journal,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Nicholson (1753–1815; <title>DNB</title>) began publishing his <title>Journal of Natural Philosophy, Chemistry and the
                            Arts</title> in 1797. It was generally known as ‘Nicholson’s journal’ and was the earliest work of its kind in Britain,
                        continuing to publish original research papers, reviews and summaries of other journals until 1814. Engravings of tornadoes,
                        seen from Nice, feature in Volume 1, 583.</note> &amp; I remember <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref> told
                    me his father had a drawing of one. Now will you at your leisure, any time between this &amp; midsummer make from either of these
                    such a drawing as will best suit these lines, or enable me to make a better description, for this is no great thing,</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent6"> Heaven too had there</l><l rend="indent3"> Its wonders, . . . from a deep, black, heavy cloud, </l><l rend="indent3"> What shall I say? a shoot . . . a trunk . . . an arm</l><l rend="indent3"> Came down, – yea like a Demons arm it seized</l><l rend="indent3"> The waters; Ocean smoked beneath its touch</l><l rend="indent3"> And rose like dust before the whirlwinds force.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title>,
                            Part 1, Book 5, lines 104–109.</note></l></lg><p rend="indent1">For the size let it be a fit vignette or tail piece for a common quarto, such as the great half-read which tho an
                    uncommon poem, is of the common size,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle’s <title>Alfred: An Epic Poem</title>
                        (1800).</note> &amp; I should think the subject will look better in wood than in copper, wood giving a greater blackness. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will spare no expence in employing the best artists.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not ask you for any thing more, but if you have any studies of tropical scenery which you think will suit this
                    purpose, I know they will be better than any I can get elsewhere, &amp; you know I shall be very thankful for your help. A group
                    of cocoa trees on the beach, or of mangoes, any thing of the kind characteristic of the country.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> (who has brought back with him a due share of admiration for
                    his surgeon as well as his physician) put me upon a plan of making something like soda water which did not succeed at all. I put
                    the acid which <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> sent me <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey
                        to Charles Danvers, 1 March 1804, Letter 905.</note>into a glass of water, with a double quantity of supercarbonated
                        kali,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A form of sodium bicarbonate.</note> &amp; the acid was instantly neutralized,
                    but no effervescence produced whatever, not even the slightest. perhaps his receipt was wrong, do you send me the right one, for I
                    am as desirous of making potable razors as ever the old chemists were of making potable gold,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Known in Latin as ‘aurum potabile’, this was a solution of gold particles in oil and alcohol that was believed
                        to bestow eternal life upon the drinker.</note> &amp; do send me some directions which may be useful to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> in the West Indies. I advised him, to drink no spirituous liquors, to eat less
                    animal food than he does here, &amp; to use fruit as freely as his bowels would permit him, &amp; the more spice the better. Poor
                    fellow he has promised to try &amp; bring home some live Land Crabs for me – &amp; I have besought him to add a live alligator to
                    the party – for <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> to dissect – but the Land-Crabs I will keep myself as
                    pets for the parlour.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although Thomas did bring some land crabs back with him, the last
                        of these died on the return journey; see Southey to Richard Duppa, 5 August 1806, Letter 1206.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> This place has agreed with me unaccountably well, but I am by no means disposed to fix here, the distance from
                    London is too inconvenient, a parcel by the waggon is a month reaching me. It is certain that I must draw nearer London so as to
                    be within reach of the museum,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> for I find myself daily in want
                    of documents which are only to be found there or in the University Libraries. – Have you <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwins</ref> most despicable &amp; catchpenny Life of Chaucer? It fell unhappily to my lot to review it,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Godwin, <title>Life of Geoffrey Chaucer ... Including Memoirs of ...
                            John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster; with Sketches of the Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in the Fourteenth
                            Century</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 462–473.</note> &amp; I, with a sort of
                    unconscientious conscience about abusing a man whom it is my lot to meet sometimes in company &amp; to speak to in the streets,
                    did spare the lash when it ought to have been more – yea most heavily laid on. <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> however it seems had somewhat less management about me. one night at <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lambs</ref> lately, he took it in to his fools head to say something very disrespectful of me to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> of all men living, who just gave him a decent set down, &amp;
                    thought he had done.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, February 1804, Letter
                        902.</note> Gobwin<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s habitual misspelling of William Godwin’s name was meant
                        to suggest his mouthiness.</note> walks off requesting <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> not to
                    go till he returned &amp; promising to be back in half an hour. he stays an hour &amp; half &amp; then makes his appearance with
                    his wife<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Jane Clairmont Godwin (1766–1841). She married Godwin in December
                        1801.</note> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Fenwick<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eliza Fenwick (1766–1840): wife of
                        Godwin’s friend and fellow radical John Fenwick (d. 1820), friend of <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref>,
                            <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">Mary Wollstonecraft</ref>, <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles</ref> and <ref target="people.html#LambMaryAnne">Mary Lamb</ref>, Henry Crabb Robinson (1775–1867). Fenwick was
                        an author, best known for her Jacobin novel <title>Secresy; or The Ruin on the Rock</title> (1795).</note> &amp; a party of
                    young women, meantime had <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> been drinking more punch than he was
                    aware of, &amp; Gobwin<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 12.</note> in a most unhappy hour for himself, for a
                    reason which you shall hear anon, thought proper to renew the conversation &amp; abuse me once more. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> beggd him not to provoke him but in vain. he did go on, &amp; did
                    provoke him, till <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> fell on him &amp; in the presence of all the
                    company anatomized him alive. He gave him so very <del>xxx</del> &lt;severe&gt; &amp; unmerciful a lecture, &amp; made the
                    philosophicide (as he calls him) look so utterly contemptible, that in the morning his heart relented, &amp; he thought himself in
                    decency bound to write a<del>n</del> letter of extenuation &amp; contrition – very foolishly as the upshot proved, for <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">the ugly-nosed metapothecary</ref> with his usual Godwinism confessed afterward to <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> that he had provoked him because his wife twitted him for being afraid of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleridge</ref>! So Jerry took heart upon the occasion –
                    &amp; actually went from the Temple to Somers Town to fetch M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sneak<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Jerry Sneak and Mrs Sneak are London characters in a play by Samuel Foote (bap. 1721–1777; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Mayor of Garratt: A Farce</title>, first performed in 1763.</note> that &lt;she might&gt; see how he would argufy with
                    Coleridge, &amp; prove that he was not afraid! – IS not this an excellent good story? – Tis a comfort to think that in reviewing
                        Malthus<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An
                            Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the future improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of
                            W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        292–301.</note> I have called him a dog by implication – having mentioned his <hi rend="ital">album græcum</hi>.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dog excrement that has become white through exposure to air.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. remember me kindly to <ref target="people.html#KingMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        K</ref>.</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-03-05">March 5. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>