<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1634</idno><idno type="nines">rce2756</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 143–147.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1634" type="letter"><head>1634. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1809-05-23">23 May 1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 143–147.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1809-05-23">May 23. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Friend,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> My last letter told you of the birth of a <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">daughter</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to John May, 27 March 1809, Letter 1606.</note> I have now to tell you of
                    the death of one. We have lost <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref>; it pleased God to take her after a very short but
                    severe bilious attack. Not half an hour before she expired we were assured there was no danger. Indeed, since I last wrote to you
                    we have had much sickness. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> was, during one part of her confinement, alarmingly
                    ill, and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has not yet thoroughly recovered his strength after the violent
                    remedies which saved him about three weeks ago, when he was attacked by the croup. The little girl was buried this morning. She
                    was, as our nurse says, ‘as sweet a child as ever woman bore,’ – just sixteen months; and it is not a week ago since I repeatedly remarked in what high
                    health she seemed, and how rapidly she was improving. These losses are but for a time, and this, severe as it is, is far less so
                    than the former. I have now broken ground in the churchyard here, and thus acquired a new tie to the place. Edith is as composed
                    as she should be. It is fortunate for her that she has an infant to take up much of her thoughts.</p><p rend="indent1"> You asked me about a new Review, which I suppose means the Quarterly, and about which I fancied I had written to
                    you. It was set on foot by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, to counteract the politics of the Edinburgh,
                    especially with regard to the subjects of peace with France, and of the Spanish patriots. I was applied to by the editor, who is
                    the ‘Baviad’ <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>. My answer contained a sort of political confession of faith,
                    stating that so far as such opinions would be tolerated by it I was ready to bear a part. Accordingly, the first number contains a
                    defence of the Baptist Missionaries in India against Scott Waring, &amp;c., and the Edinburgh Review.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of and leading contributors to the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title> reviewed the activities of British missionaries in India negatively, Southey opposed
                        his views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Smith’s review of ‘Ingram on Methodism’ appeared in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 11 (January 1808), 341–362, and he reviewed ‘Indian Missions’ in the next issue 12 (April 1808), 151–181.
                        In the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226, Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative
                            to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)],
                            <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the
                            Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the
                            Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas
                        Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of
                            Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society,
                            as Directed to India</title> (1807).</note> It has been a good deal mutilated by the editor, and therefore materially
                    weakened; still it has produced considerable effect, and made the Edinburgh Review very angry. Under cover of a methodistical book
                    written by a certain John Styles, they reply to it in their last number;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Smith reviewed
                        ‘Styles on Methodists and Missions’, in the <title>Edinburgh</title>, 14 (April 1809), 40–50, responding to Southey’s review
                        in the <title>Quarterly.</title> The subject was John Styles (1782–1849), who had authored <title>Strictures on Two Critiques
                            in the Edinburgh Review on the Subject of Methodism and Missions: with Remarks on the Influence of Reviews in General on
                            Morals and Happiness, in Three Letters to a Friend</title> (1808).</note> and their whole reply consists in calling one
                    part brutal, and another contemptible. Sidney Smith is my antagonist. It is not to be wondered at if I have the better of him; for
                    I plead for what I believe, and he is obliged to affect a belief in what he is in fact attacking. I am afraid, however, that this
                    Review is too much under the immediate influence of the Ministry. <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">One of the
                        publishers</ref> was here last week.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Rickman, 16 May [1809],
                        Letter 1629.</note> He expressed a hope that ‘they would let the Duke of York alone,’ which implied a fear that it was
                    intended to defend him;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763–1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798–1809, but was forced to resign in the wake
                        of allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776–1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept
                        money from army officers, in return for which promotion was arranged. In May 1811 the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent</ref> reinstated his brother as Commander-in-Chief of the army, a
                        post which he held for the rest of his life.</note> and he said also, that <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George
                        Ellis</ref> (who wrote that wretched article about Spain which begins the first number<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        George Ellis [with <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>] reviewed <title>Exposé des Manoeuvres et des
                            Intrigues qui ont Préparé l’Usurpation de la Couronne d’Espagne, et des Moyens Employés par l’Empereur des Francais pour
                            la Mettre á Exécution…; Traduit de l’Espagnol par M. Peltier</title> [alternative title <title>Affaires d’Espagne</title>]
                        (1808) and Pedro Cevallos Guerra (1760–1840), <title>Conféderation des Royaumes et Provinces d’Espagne contre
                            Buonaparte</title> ([1810]) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 1–19.</note>) “and some other of
                    its privy council, talked of ‘unmuzzling <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>,’ that is, of letting him set up
                    the old cry of Jacobinism against all who wish for reform. You will, I trust, have anticipated my reply to this – that in either
                    case I must withdraw from the work; and this, I suppose, will be the case. My communications are now franked through the Secretary
                    of State’s office, and this is a bad symptom.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Because of Southey’s fears that government
                        influence would be put on the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> The article upon the Lives of the Painters is by
                        Hoppner;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Hoppner (1758–1810; <title>DNB</title>) reviewed <title>Anecdotes of
                            Painters Who Have Resided or Been Born in England: With Critical Remarks on their Productions, by Edward Edwards,
                            Deceased, Late Teacher of Perspective, and Associate, in the Royal Academy; Intended as a Continuation to the Anecdotes of
                            painting by the late Horace Earl of Orford</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809),
                        36–49.</note> that upon Sanskreet Grammar by <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon Turner [with John Shore, 1st Baron Teignmouth (1751–1834; <title>DNB</title>)] reviewed
                        Charles Wilkins (bap. 1749–1836; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Grammar of the Sanskrîta Language</title> (1808); William
                        Carey (1761–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Grammar of the Sungskrit Language, Composed from the Works of the Most
                            Esteemed Grammarians; to Which are Added Examples for the Exercise of the Student, and a Complete List of the Dhatoos or
                            Roots</title> (1804); and Henry Thomas Colebrooke (1765–1837), <title>Grammar of the Sanskrit Language</title> (1805) in
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 53–69.</note> that upon Medals by <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">Barry Roberts</ref>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barré Charles Roberts
                        (Bedford’s cousin) reviewed John Pinkerton (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on Medals; or an Introduction to
                            the Knowledge of Ancient and Modern Coins and Medals, especially those of Greece, Rome, and Britain</title> (1808) in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 112–131.</note> a man whom I remember at school, and who is cousin to
                    my old friend <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>
                    has furnished many of the rest.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809): Robert Hartley Cromek (1770–1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques of Robert Burns, Consisting Chiefly of
                            Original Letters, Poems, and Critical Observations on Scottish Songs</title> (1808), 19–36; John Barrett (1753/4–1821),
                            <title>An Essay on the Earlier Part of the Life of Swift, by the Rev. John Barrett, D. D. and Vice Provost of Trinity
                            College, Dublin. To which are Subjoined Various Pieces Ascribed to Swift, Two of his Original Letters, and Extracts from
                            his Remarks on Bishop Burnett’s History</title> (1808), 162–177. Scott [and <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref>] reviewed Sir John Carr (1772–1832; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Caledonian Sketches, or a Tour
                            through Scotland in 1807</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 178–193. Scott also had
                        a hand in William Erskine’s (Lord Kinneder; bap. 1768–1822; <title>DNB</title>), review of John Philpot Curran (1750–1817),<title> Speeches of the
                            Right Honourable John Philpot Curran, Master of the Rolls in Ireland, on the late very Interesting State Trials</title>
                        (1808), 96–107.</note> On the whole, there is not much to be said for the first numbers; some articles are positively bad in
                    every point of view, especially <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis’s</ref>, which ought to have been the best, and which
                    I declined writing myself, merely because I thought they would get somebody to throw a sort of <hi rend="ital">official</hi>
                    importance over the pamphlet which would produce more immediate effect upon the public than my under views of the subject; – in
                    fact, they wanted party politics, and I could only have given them principles. To have defended what has been done would have been
                    degrading myself; and to have shown how a nation may become invincible, and must become so, if there be a general spirit of
                    patriotism, would have been to the Ministry foolishness, or worse than foolishness.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am, however, likely to have ample opportunities for saying this, and whatever else of importance I wish to say. A
                    plan has been suggested of publishing a Review which should not touch upon contemporary books, but choose its subjects from the
                    whole mass of antecedent literature. It originated in a hint of mine to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                        Scott</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> For which, see Southey to Walter Scott, 11 March 1809, Letter
                        1597.</note> The booksellers have taken it up, and are in treaty with me concerning it.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been approached by <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> concerning the
                        possibility of his editing a new review, to be called the <title>Rhadamanthus</title>; see Southey to John Rickman, 16 May
                        [1809], (Letter 1629), and Southey to Thomas Southey, [16 May 1809] (Letter 1630). In Greek mythology Rhadamanthus was a wise
                        king who was one of the judges of the dead. Southey’s plans for this periodical were never fulfilled.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My History has reached p. 336.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> My poem of Kehama<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> would have been finished this week had not my hand been palsied by this
                    unexpected stroke. I will crowd in here some lines from that poem (written many months ago), which are applicable to my present
                    state of mind. Whether they will stand in the poem or not is very doubtful: — </p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> They sin who tell us Love can die.</l><l rend="indent3"> With life all other passions fly:</l><l rend="indent3"> All others are but vanity.</l><l rend="indent3"> In Heaven Ambition cannot dwell,</l><l rend="indent3"> Nor Avarice in the vaults of Hell</l><l rend="indent3"> Earthly, these passions of low earth,</l><l rend="indent3"> They perish where they have their birth;</l><l rend="indent3"> But Love is indestructible.</l><l rend="indent3"> Its holy flame for ever burneth:</l><l rend="indent3"> From Heaven it came, to Heaven returneth.</l><l rend="indent3"> Too oft on earth a troubled guest,</l><l rend="indent3"> At times deceived, at times opprest;</l><l rend="indent3"> It here is tried and purified,</l><l rend="indent3"> And hath in Heaven its perfect rest.</l><l rend="indent3"> It soweth here with toil and care,</l><l rend="indent3"> But the harvest time of Love is there.</l><l rend="indent3"> Oh! when a mother meets on high</l><l rend="indent3"> The babe she lost in infancy,</l><l rend="indent3"> Hath she not then for all her fears,</l><l rend="indent4"> The day of woe, the watchful night,</l><l rend="indent3"> For all her sorrows, all her tears,</l><l rend="indent4"> An overpayment of delight?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Southey’s poem <title>The Curse of
                                Kehama</title> (London, 1810), Book 10, lines 150–171. The lines were published as ‘Love’ in <title>English
                                Minstrelsy: Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors</title> (Edinburgh, 2010), II, pp.
                            236–237, and <title>The Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), xxxi.</note></l></lg><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you. Remember us to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">Mrs. May</ref>, and believe me</salute><salute rend="indent1"> Very affectionately yours,</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>