<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.957</idno><idno type="nines">rce2079</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 60.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 279–280.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="957" type="letter"><head>957. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-06-30">30 June
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ June 30: 1804<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 60<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 279–280.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Rickman,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Herewith comes the key. the desk might pass safely through the Inquisition – but what is to be done about the <hi rend="ital">Irishness</hi> of Bruces Travels? which I am afraid renders it liable to confiscation, unless <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Abbotts</ref> bill <del>about</del> &lt;for&gt; extending Literary
                    Property to Ireland render that statute obsolete <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, as it of course must be hereafter.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is asking Rickman to supervise the movement of a cargo of books sent by his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref> from Cork, Ireland, through customs, where duty would be levied on it
                        according to its weight. He jokes that one of the books, James Bruce’s <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile, in
                            the Years 1768, 1769, 1770, 1771, 1772 and 1773</title> (1790), notoriously full of the implausible and the exaggerated,
                        was ‘Irish’ enough in character to be an Irish publication, and so exempt from duty. ‘Mr Abbott’s bill’ was an attempt by
                        Charles Abbott, the Speaker of the House of Commons and, in 1801–1802, Chief Secretary and Privy Seal for Ireland, to extend
                        British copyright law to Ireland (after the political union of Britain and Ireland in 1803) and so end the practice of pirate
                        editions being published there.</note> perhaps this plea with the help of a well-applied five shillings, may avail.
                        <del>Claus</del> &lt;Olaus&gt; Magnus must pay sixpence per pound weight, &amp; will still be a cheap purchase.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Olaus Magnus (Olaus Magni or Olaus Magni Gothus; 1490–1557): Swedish Catholic cleric and
                        historian of Scandanavia; author of <title>Historia de Gentibus Septentrionalibus</title> (1555). Southey’s edition was that
                        of Basle, 1567, and was no. 1936 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Bruce is not to be depended upon for any point of history. tho he understood Portugueze it is plain that he did not
                    write from Portugueze books by his misnomers. Vasco de Gama<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Vasco da Gama (c. 1460/9–1524):
                        Portuguese explorer who was the first European to reach India by sea, enabling the establishment of Portugal’s colonial empire
                        and commercial monopoly in Asia.</note> he calls Vasques de Gama. now, the <hi rend="ital">es</hi> is a <del>xxxxxx</del>
                    patronymic ending, equivalent to the ιδης<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Meaning ‘the son of’.</note> of the Greeks. the
                    son of Vasco would be called Joam or Antonio Vasques. this was sheer indolence in Bruce – but he sometimes from the &lt;same&gt;
                    trick of writing without authorities <del>xxxxxx</del> asserts what is absolutely false. – I make a critical bibliography as I go
                    on which will be found useful by those who come after me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I <del>xx</del> am just <del>comp</del> finishing the life of Alboquerque the founder of the Portuguese Empire in
                    the East, <del>&amp; to whom the very xxxx</del> a man who was indeed fit to found Empire.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Afonso de Albuquerque (1453–1515): naval officer and second governor of Portuguese colonies in India, which he greatly
                        expanded by conquest and fortification. His feats were celebrated in the epic poem <title>The Lusiads</title> (1572), by Luís
                        Vaz de Camões (1524–1580), of which Southey owned several editions.</note> his son was his historian – a very honest one – he
                    tells you that Alb&lt;oquerque&gt; finding the Tamorim continued to <del>relay</del> evade a disadvantageous treaty by perpetual
                    delays – advised <del>th</del> his brother to poison him, &amp; succeed to the throne – as then the business might be settled –
                    And so he did – Bras d’Alboquerque relates it in this cool way – &amp; it authenticates his whole history.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey owned an edition of the collection of Albuquerque’s papers and letters edited by his son, Brás de
                        Albuquerque (1500–1580), <title>Commentarios do Grande Affonso d’Alboquerque</title> (1774), no. 3165 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> Barros conceals the fact.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3180 of the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library was Joao de Barros (1496–1570) and Diogo de Couto (c. 1542–1616), <title>Decadas da Asia dos
                            Feitos, que os Portuguezes Fizeram na Conquista, e Descubrimento das Terras, e Mares do Oriente</title>
                        (1778–1788).</note> I have caught <del>so</del> &lt;out&gt; Barros in so many dishonesties that I now begin to feel a pleasure
                    in detecting more, that his character may be settled.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for some Parl. Pro. yesterday.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In June 1804 <ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref> once more presented a bill to abolish the slave trade.
                        It successfully passed through the House of Commons, but was too late in the parliamentary session to complete its passage
                        through the House of Lords, and on its reintroduction in 1805 was defeated.</note> I perceive an equal number of both sexes
                    among the negroes – contrary to what I had understood to be the case.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-06-30">Saturday. 30 June. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>