<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1131</idno><idno type="nines">rce2253</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3 .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 409–412.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1131" type="letter"><head>1131. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-12-10">10
                        December [1805]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: For/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                            <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthrie’s</ref>. Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh –
                        <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3 <lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 409–412.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I well remember that the passage in Gomara is inaccurate.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Southey was
                        soliciting information from his brother for his university dissertation to graduate as MD. This was on the origins and course
                        of syphilis, in which he suggested an American origin for the disease. The passage Southey refers to is in Francisco Lopez de
                        Gomara (c. 1511–1566?), <title>La Historia General de las Indias, con Todos los Descubrimientos, y Cosas Notables que han
                            Acaescido Enellas, dende que se Ganaron Hasta Agora</title> (Anvers, 1554), p. 36. Gomara quotes Luis Bertoman as to the
                        presence of the disease in Calicut.</note> some word or words must have been omitted. <hi rend="ital">por entonces</hi> is –
                    at that time, <hi rend="ital">entonces</hi> is <hi rend="ital">then</hi>. it means either that Luis Bertoman says so que (<hi rend="ital">fice</hi>) en Calicut – or that he says the disease was there – which is most likely. – There is no difficulty in
                    explaining why mention of the Bubas is not made till the second voyage – only recollect how very scanty the original accounts are,
                    &amp; in what manner made up. Barros published Decades<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao de Barros (1496–1570) and
                        Diogo de Couto (c. 1542–1616). Southey’s edition of their work was <title>Decadas da Asia fos Feitos, que os Portuguezes
                            Fizeram na Conquista, e Descombrimento das Terras, e Mares do Oriente</title> (1778–1788), no. 3180 in the sale catalogue
                        of his library.</note> in different years, the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> &amp; 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in 1553. the third 1563.
                    the fourth was not published till long after his death, by Joam Baptista Lavanha 1613.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Joao Baptista Lavanha (1555–1624), a Portuguese engineer who wrote on mathematics and navigation.</note> Thuanus<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques Auguste de Thou (Thuanus; 1553–1617), a French historian.</note> wrote at the close of
                    the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century – I have no documents to say in what precise year, but he is too late to be of any importance
                    as an authority. Oviedo is the great authority.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gonzalo Fernández de Oviedo y Valdés
                        (1478–1557), <title>Sumario de la Natural Historia de las Indias</title> (1526), or <title>Historia General y Natural de las
                            Indias, Islas y Tierra Firme del Mar Océano</title>, of which the first part was published in 1535 and publication of the
                        second part was interrupted by the author’s death.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You need not trouble more about the Magazines for I have been obliged to do without them.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is gone into Warwickshire – at least he told me so in a note, in which he made
                    no mention of your affairs,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to the consequences of Harry’s meeting
                        Emma Noel (d. 1873), while at the home of Charles Lloyd near Ambleside. She was the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of Exton
                        Park, Rutland (1759–1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to
                        become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple’s plans to marry, the relationship soon ended.</note> –
                        <del>x</del> at which omission I expressed my surprize in reply. It is precisely as I told you – these things are vinegar
                    &amp; mustard to season the insipidity of his existence, – &amp; in this instance he has taken so largely as to be in danger of
                    being taken by the nose. You begin to understand how totally he is wrecked &amp; ruined. However do, as I do, keep on good terms
                    with him, for the sake of what he has been. <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ll.</ref> too is
                    truly an estimable woman. Make her let Emma<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 6.</note> understand that you <hi rend="ital">will</hi> not give up the matter, <hi rend="ital">can</hi> not must be your language, potentially speaking, &amp;
                    perhaps you yourself <del>may</del> regard the words as synonymous – which <del>xxx</del> &lt;the&gt; German auxiliary
                        <del>show</del> verbs show not to be the case. If you persevere, she will, – but I do not think she uses you quite well,
                    things having gone so far, in not writing to you herself. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> of course pleaded
                    Quaker to the challenge.</p><p rend="indent1"> Be careful in the dissecting room – I know a man whose father lost his life by a scratch there, &amp; <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> has a very narrow escape.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has sent me a turtle! which happily has never arrived. I wrote in bodily fear to
                        <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to give it him, &amp; if it be not eat by the way he will get it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the letter to Wynn; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 24 November 1805,
                        Letter 1125. The turtle did not reach <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, but died in quarantine; see Southey to
                        Thomas Southey, 1–5 January 1806, Letter 1140.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">The Count</ref> was going tomorrow – but I have set him upon making Specimens of the
                    English prose writers,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett’s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the
                            Earliest Times to the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title> was published in three volumes with Longmans in 1807. This
                        compilation formed a companion work to George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn. 1801,
                        3rd edn. 1803) and Southey’s own anthology, jointly edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> &amp; he will find a fortnights work
                    here – I can give him so much help, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> so much, &amp; perhaps <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>, that he is sure of getting thro this, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will doubtless print it at my recommendation. I look upon the invention of a
                    job which he can do as only less extraordinary than squaring the circle or doubling the cube. To night he begins his labour, &amp;
                    is at this very time transcribing from Bishop Latimer<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hugh Latimer (c. 1485–1555), Bishop
                        of Worcester, preacher, and protestant martyr, whose sermons could be found in <title>The Sermons of the Right Reverend Father
                            in God, Master Hugh Latimer, ... Many of which were preached before King Edward VI</title> (1758).</note> – who, if you do
                    not happen to know it, is one of the most amusing writers in the language.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will have seen the Monthly Review of Madoc.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ferriar (1761–1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>) reviewed <title>Madoc</title> (1805) in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 48 (October 1805),
                        113–122.</note> bad could not be better – for never was any thing more clumsily overdone. In consequence of the extracts there
                    &amp; in the Edinburgh<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis Jeffrey</ref> reviewed <title>Madoc</title> in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1–29.</note><ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Windham</ref> has sent for the book, declaring himself to be completely at issue with the
                    Reviewers. this <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> tells me.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Spaniard goes on well.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> Have you time to write for him a sketch of
                    the system of medical education? &amp; of the Brunonian theory?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Brunonian system of
                        medicine was named after its founder, the Scottish medic John Brown (1735–1788; <title>DNB</title>), who argued that all
                        diseases were explicable as results of over, or under, stimulation of the nerves. Brown’s system attracted many followers –
                        notably <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Thomas Beddoes</ref>, who treated Southey’s nervous collapse in 1799–1800 – but it became discredited because Brown
                        prescribed opium and alcohol to achieve a healthy degree of stimulation, at the cost of his own addiction. Brown’s ideas are
                        not discussed in <title>Letters from England</title>, the medical topics of Letters 50, 51 and 52, being quackery, animal
                        magnetism and faith healing.</note> it matters not how briefly. Can you describe also the road from Melrose to Edinburgh. for
                    I would take him that way &amp; home by Berwick.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s fictional traveller did not
                        get as far as Scotland.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Your winter will not pass the more agreably for your <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> adventure.
                    the affair is intricate enough for a novel, &amp; rather too much so for real life. If indeed you were at full leisure &amp; could
                    play at bo-peep over the country it would be very well. However do not let your spirits be cast down, for if she does not use you
                    confoundedly ill, you may certainly have her, – &amp; if she does she is not worth having.</p><p rend="indent1"> I must go to town as soon as my reviewing is over to finish this business over which <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref><del>has</del> will then have dawdled for two years.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s and Bedford’s jointly
                        edited anthology, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> If <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> should not happen to meet me in London I will return,
                    or go, thro Norwich. My plans of emigration must in great measure be regulated by political affairs. It will not do to remove my
                    family, if there be any chance of the expulsion of the English, in which case I shall be quite enough of incumbrance to
                        myself.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey abandoned his plans to travel to Portugal owing to his wife’s
                        opposition.</note> We shall see how your novel goes on – as <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the Colonel</ref> calls
                    it, – if it should not keep you in England, perhaps a journey thro the north of Portugal would be the pleasantest way of passing a
                    few months, &amp; certainly the most profitable. It would suit me to travel with a family Physician.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Sarah Hutchinson</ref> is here – &amp; desires her love to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Fearon<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wife of Henry Fearon, MD (1780–1822).</note> – to whom &amp; to her husband I
                    will beg you to remember me –</p><p rend="indent1"> We have news of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> – he left Malta in September, to
                    return thro Naples &amp; Venice. so that his arrival may daily be expected.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had
                        been acting as Public Secretary to the British Civil Commissioner in Malta. Though due to return, he did not arrive back in
                        England until August 1806 and never returned to live in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you. You know what are the two things needful for going thro the world well. – that you are provided with
                    the one – viz. thin pantaloons, both Latrigg<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fell near Keswick on descending
                        which Harry had split his trousers.</note> &amp; I well know. but don’t let the cold pudding sit heavy enough upon your
                    stomach to make the heart heavy. You know by <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">G.D’s</ref><del>escape</del> care how the one is affected by the other. Keep up your spirits, mend your handwriting, &amp; above all things –
                    don’t go out in the streets without the muzzle.</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1805-12-10">Tuesday. Dec. 10.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>