<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1337</idno><idno type="nines">rce2459</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                    104–105.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1337" type="letter"><head>1337. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, <date when="1807-06-29">29 June 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850)<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                    104–105.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1807-06-29">June 29. 1807.</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sirs,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have been told by persons most capable of judging, that the old translation of Don Quixote<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Shelton (fl. 1598–1629; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Valorous and Witty
                            Knight-Errant, Don Quixote of the Mançha</title> (1612–1620).</note> is very beautiful. The book has never fallen in my
                    way. If it be well translated, the language of Elizabeth’s reign must needs accord better with the style of Cervantes<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616).</note> than more modern English would do; and I should
                    think it very probable that it would be better to correct this, than to translate the work anew. As for my undertaking any
                    translation, or indeed any revision, which might lead to the labour, or half the labour, which Palmerin<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> cost me, it is out of the question; but if <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Mr. Heber</ref> can lend you
                    this translation, I will give you my opinion upon it: and I will do for you, if you want it, what you would find much difficulty
                    in getting done by any other person, – add to a Life of Cervantes an account of all his other writings, and likewise of the books
                    in Don Quixote’s library, as far as my own stores will reach, and those which we may find access to; and make such notes upon the
                    whole book as my knowledge of the history and literature of Spain can supply. I believe a new translation has been announced by
                    Mr. ——,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Belfour (1768–1842; <title>DNB</title>), translator in 1804 of <title>Fables
                            on Subjects connected with Literature. Imitated from the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title>.</note> whose translation
                    of Yriarte proved that either he did not understand the original, or that of all translators he is the most impudent. Such
                    preliminaries as these which I propose might fill half a volume, or extend to a whole one, just as might be judged most expedient.
                    It gives me very great pleasure to hear that you have engaged for a genuine version of the Arabian Nights, – which I consider as
                    one of the greatest desideratums in modern Oriental literature. We have a number of imitations in our language, which I am still
                    boy enough to delight in; and were you, as the French have done, to publish a complete collection of them, I, for one, should be
                    glad of the opportunity of buying them. If you published them volume by volume, with good prints, like your Theatre, school-boys
                    would take off half an edition.</p><p rend="indent1"> As the new Joinville<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Memoirs of John Lord de Joinville ... containing a history of part of the life of Louis IX. ... To which are added, the
                            notes and dissertations of M. Du Cange on the above; together with the dissertations of M. le Baron de la Bastie on the
                            life of St. Louis, M. l’Évesque de la Ravaliere and M. Falconet on the Assassins of Syria. The whole translated by T.
                            Johnes</title> (1807).</note> is, beyond all comparison, the most unreasonably dear book I ever saw, so is your
                        Holinshed<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Holinshed’s Chronicles of England, Scotland and Ireland</title> (1807–1808).</note> the cheapest; and I shall keep the
                    copy you have sent accordingly. Dear books may not deter the rich from purchasing, but here is proof for you that cheap ones tempt
                    the poor.</p><p rend="indent1"> To-morrow I will make up my parcel for the Athenæum.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Athenæum, a
                        Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, ed. J. Aikin and published by Longmans.</note> At <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Dr. Aikin’s</ref> request I have undertaken (long since) the Spanish and Portuguese literary
                    part of his Biography.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin, <title>General Biography; or, Lives, Critical and
                            Historical, of the Most Eminent Persons of All Ages, Countries, Conditions and Professions, Arranged According to
                            Alphabetical Order</title> (1799–1815).</note> Some articles appeared in the last volume, and, few as they are, I suppose
                    they entitle me to it. Will you ask <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Dr. A.</ref> if this be the case?</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Yours truly,</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>