<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1404</idno><idno type="nines">rce2526</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 123.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 40–42.Dating note: From
                        Rickman’s endorsement</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1404" type="letter"><head>1404. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-12-22">[c. 22 December
                    1807]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ 22
                            Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1807<lb/> MS: Huntington Library, RS 123<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 40–42.<lb/>Dating note: From
                        Rickman’s endorsement</note></head><p rend="indent1"> As <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> dines with you Xmas Day the inclosed<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This has not survived.</note> will hit him flying.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have got a third through the French Anna-Comnena<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Comnena
                        (1083–1153), daughter of the Byzantine emperor Alexios I Komnenos. She wrote the <title>Alexiad</title>, a history of her
                        father’s reign. Southey may have been reading her narrative in the French-compiled dual Latin/Greek edition of Byzantine
                        texts, <title>Byzantinae Historiae Scriptores</title> (1645–1711). Southey had previously told Rickman: ‘It has long been one
                        of my greatest desires to read through the Byzantine Historians’; see Southey to John Rickman, 21 December [1807], Letter
                        1402.</note> today, &amp; shall <del>have</del> soon have all the remarkables out of the book, with references minute enough
                    to enable me to verify them by the original. The translation seems to be very good.</p><p rend="indent1"> Last night I was in too much haste to look for the ipsissima verba<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Meaning ‘exact words’.</note> of Fuller. They imply more than <del>th</del> stated. ‘It is better to fight naked than with bad
                    armour; for the rags of a bad <del>xxx</del> corselet make a deeper wound, &amp; worse to be healed than the bullet itself.’<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Fuller (1607/8–1661; <title>DNB</title>), makes this observation in a sermon
                        entitled ‘The First Reconciler’ in <title>A Triple Reconciler; Stating the Controversies, whether Ministers have an Exclusive
                            Power of Communicants from the Sacrament: Any Persons Unordained may Lawfully Preach: The Lord’s Prayer Ought not to be
                            Used by all Christians</title> (1654), p. 18.</note> – A good corselet would certainly repel a musket ball; <del>&amp;
                        xxxx xx</del> there [MS torn] enough in the Tower to show it: &amp; the contusion could seldom be of any consequence [MS torn]
                    the corselet did not, in great part, sit close. Besides many balls would slant off. It must have been the greater use of cannon
                    which occasioned the disuse of defensive armour, – &amp; now that battles are so decided by the bayonet, the breast plate ought to
                    be resumed.</p><p rend="indent1"> I think there is a suit of chain-mail at the Liverpool Museum – but it is Asiatic. This I will <hi rend="ital">see</hi> &amp; examine. My paper contains a great number of facts relative to ancient warfare in all its facts, – enough to
                    furnish matter for a curious chapter the question how far did the real state of society ever correspond to what the Romances
                    describe is a curious one, – <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> proposes to examine it as far as relates to this
                    country. He has <del>xxxx xxxxxxx</del> &lt;produced&gt; a Saxon romance anterior to the Crusades<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the third volume of his <title>History of the Anglo Saxons from the Earliest Period to the Norman
                            Conquest</title> (1799–1805), Turner discusses <title>Beowulf</title>, calling it a ‘romance’ and ‘the oldest poem in an
                        epic form that now exists in any of the vernacular languages of Europe’ (p. 408).</note> – &amp; that Latin poem which relates
                    to Attila &amp; is referred to in the notes on Madoc is another.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In a note to
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, book 15, lines 48–49, Southey cites the Latin poem <title>De Prima Expeditione
                            Attila, Regis Hunnorum, in Gallias, ac de Rebus Gestis Waltharii Aquitanorum Principis. Carmen Epicum Saeculi VI</title>
                        (1780). See <title>Madoc</title>, vol. 2 of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5
                        vols (London, 2004), pp. 342, 587.</note> One of the first things which appeared in Anna Comnena is that she describes her
                    father fighting like a Palmerin in battle – there is a good deal of this in Byzantine history, &amp; still more in Persian fable –
                    &lt;read Champion’s Fragment of Ferdusi,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Champion (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Poems of Ferdosi, Translated from the Persian</title> (1788).</note> when you can meet with it&gt; It is worth your while
                    to endure the disgust so villainous a translation will excite, for the sake of getting at the story. You know my opinion
                    concerning Romance, – that it is the natural growth of semi-barbarous ages, &amp; that Hercules &amp; Jason &amp; Theseus, were
                    the Guy of Warwick, the Rolands &amp; Launcelots<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Heroes of the romances ‘Guy of
                        Warwick’, ‘Childe Rowland’ and ‘Morte d’Arthur’.</note> of their day.</p><p rend="indent1"> These books were never meant to outrage probability. Amadis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hero of the
                        cycle of chivalric romances of which Southey had edited <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> in armour, was no more
                    than the Chicken or Gulley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two bare knuckle prizefighters: Henry Pearce (1777–1809),
                        the ‘Bristol Game-Chicken’, the champion of England, and John Gully (1783–1863; <title>DNB</title>). The two men had a famous
                        fight on 5 October 1805, won by Pearce when Gully was forced to retire.</note> without it, – the man of most science &amp;
                    most strength, – which ensured success in <del>them</del> the then mode of warfare. Their miracles also were believed; nothing is
                    so common in Romance as enchanted fountains, – yet for one which <del>is</del> there &lt;is&gt; in Romance, I can produce half a
                    dozen in old natural history.</p><p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you will make one mornings leisure &amp; go with me to the <del>xxxxxx</del> Tower<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tower of London.</note> – where we shall certainly find out something. I have long thought that the
                    disuse of defensive armour rendering personal strength less necessary, has led to the disuse of manly exercise, &amp;
                        <del>xxxxxxx</del> made us weaker than our forefathers. Thus much is certain, – that in former times the gentry excelled the
                    peasantry in bodily strength, – which assuredly is not the case now.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> 150 of Espriella are left, &amp; so they go to press with it again immediately. I am in good hope that this
                        book will turn out a prize for me.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                                Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). The second edition was published in 1808; but its
                            popularity dropped off once Southey’s authorship was known and a third was not called for until 1814.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>