<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.937</idno><idno type="nines">rce2059</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
							New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 358–359.Dating note: ‘? 9
						May 1804’ added in pencil. Dating of ‘Kendal Wednesday’ is the same as Southey’s letter to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [9
						May 1804], Letter 938, which has a postmark of 12 May 1804 (Saturday).</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="937" type="letter"><head>937. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-05-09">[9 May
						1804]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/
						Single<lb/>Stamped: KENDAL/ 261<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
							<title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 358–359.<lb/>Dating note: ‘? 9
						May 1804’ added in pencil. Dating of ‘Kendal Wednesday’ is the same as Southey’s letter to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [9
						May 1804], Letter 938, which has a postmark of 12 May 1804 (Saturday).</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>Kendal</placeName></address><date when="1804-05-09">Wednesday</date></dateline><salute>Dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Thus far well – &amp; and dry tho’ it rained during the last hour of my walk a little – &amp; is now set in for a
					wet afternoon. The coach arrives about four, &amp; will allow me to stay four &amp; twenty hours at Liverpool – very conveniently
					– so that I shall be there for five one evening till five the next. I have learnt nothing as yet of its farther motions.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WordsworthMary">Mrs Wordsworth</ref> looked as sadly lean as if she was my twin sister.
						<ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Johnny</ref> is one of the sons of the Anakim<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The race of long-necked people ‘of great height’ in Numbers 13: 32–33: ‘And there we saw the Nephilim (the
						sons of Anak, who come from the Nephilim), and we seemed to ourselves like grasshoppers, and so we seemed to them’.</note> –
					he would certainly make two <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sarahs</ref>. His head is as big as <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwents</ref> and his face less infantine. It seems quite unnatural that such a huge
					head and such a reasonable face should belong to a baby, but he is a grand fellow certainly. I rested till half past six at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>, and <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref> then walked with me
					half way to <ref target="places.html#LowoodInn">Lowood</ref> where I supt on fresh char and potted char and slept.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> tells me what I am sorely sorry to hear that <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">John Tobin</ref> is gone to Falmouth, hopelessly far gone in consumption. Poor blind <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">James</ref> ! What will become of him when he has lost his home-companion. It will be a
					second calamity as severe as his loss of sight.</p><p rend="indent1"> Make my excuses to Mr. Johnson<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> for not shaking hands
					with him before I set off &amp; inquire again if I can do anything for him in London. – Would that I were in my own home again. I
					am like a lock without a key or a bell without a clapper – Andandona<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The devilish sister
						of a giant, who resented the hero’s attempt to deprive her of her brother by converting him to Christianity, in <title>Amadis
							of Gaul</title>, Southey’s translation of which was published in 1803.</note> or the rhyme will tell you why, he is a good
						dog.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is rhyming ‘clapper’ with ‘Dapper’, the name of his dog, pining in his
						absence.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am cansaded – &amp; shall not get a decent descance<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s words
						‘cansaded’ and ‘descance’ are nonce ones derived by him from the Portuguese for ‘to tire’ and ‘rest/refreshment’.</note> till
					I find out <ref target="people.html#KosterMrs">Mrs Kosters</ref> tea table. For the inns of Lancaster &amp; Liverpool are <hi rend="ital">shameful</hi>. – tell me in your letter whether Mr Johnson has got the Historia Naturalis Brasiliæ<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did acquire Willem Piso (1611–1678), <title>Historia Naturalis Brasiliæ</title> (1648), no. 2158 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> for me at the sale<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
						sale at Ormathwaite Hall, near <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, of the books, pictures and scientific
						instruments of William Brownrigg, (1711–1800; <title>DNB</title>). A doctor and natural philosopher, his experiments on the
						gases found in the Whitehaven coal mines led to his being awarded the Copley medal of the Royal Society, and with Benjamin
						Franklin (1706–1790) he demonstrated on Lake Derwent that oil could be used to calm the motion of lakes and seas.</note> – I
					care little or nothing for the other books but am anxious about that for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
						Uncles</ref> sake. – At <ref target="places.html#LowoodInn">Lowood</ref><del>of xxx any sale xxx xxxxx xxxxx</del> they told
					me a world of people were gone to the sale, I fared there very well &amp; very reasonably. </p><p rend="indent1"> this is a very bad &amp; very suje<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Portuguese word meaning
						‘dirty’.</note> pen as my knife is neither able to mend or clean it</p><p rend="indent1"> So God bless you, take care of yourself, eat and drink! And make Nurse sit down, and drink – a for she does not do
					either the one or the other as she ought – and keep the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> quiet and in the
					dark. Let nobody talk to her or attempt to make her spracken up<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Sprack’ is a dialect word
						meaning to be ‘active’ or ‘alert.’</note> – for to her it would be deadly poison. Once more God bless you <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>!</p></div></body></text></TEI>