<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.913</idno><idno type="nines">rce2035</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850).  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp.
                        273–276.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="913" type="letter"><head>913. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1804-03-14">14
                        March 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850)<lb/>Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp.
                        273–276.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1804-03-14">March 14. 1804.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your departure<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge travelled abroad to Malta for his health, taking
                        up a temporary post as private secretary to Sir Alexander Ball (1757–1809; <title>DNB</title>), the naval officer governing
                        Malta.</note> hangs upon me with something the same effect that the heavy atmosphere presses upon you – an unpleasant thought,
                    that works like yeast, and makes me feel the animal functions going on. As for the manner of your going, you will be on the whole
                    better off than in a king’s ship. Now you are your own master; there you would have been a <hi rend="ital">guest</hi>, and, of
                    course, compelled to tolerate the worst of all possible society, except that of soldier-officers.</p><p rend="indent1"> I had hopes of seeing you in London; for almost as soon as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is
                    safe in bed,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s daughter, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
                            Southey</ref>, was born on 30 April 1804.</note> if safe she be (for my life has been so made up of sudden changes, that I
                    never even mentally look to what is to happen without that if, and the optative <hi rend="ital">utinam</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Latin for ‘would that it were’.</note>), – as soon, I say, as that takes place, I shall hurry to
                    town, principally to put to press this book of Specimens,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to the project that
                        Southey undertook with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref> and published with
                            <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English
                        Poets</title>.</note> which can only be finished there, for you will stare at the catalogue of dead authors whom I shall have
                    to resurrectionise. This will be a very curious and useful book of mine; how much the worse it will be for your voyage to Malta,
                    few but myself will feel. If it sells, I shall probably make a supplementary volume to <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis’s</ref>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title>
                        (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803). Due to the poor sales of Southey’s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807), this plan was not carried out.</note> to include the good pieces which he has overlooked, for he has not selected
                    well, and, perhaps, to analyse the epics and didactics, which nobody reads. Had I conceived that you would think of transcribing
                    any part of Madoc,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797–1799
                        and was revising for publication. It was published in 1805.</note> you should have been spared the trouble; but, in writing to
                    you, it has always appeared to me better to <hi rend="ital">write</hi> than to <hi rend="ital">copy</hi>, the mere babble having
                    the recommendation that it is exclusively your own, and created for you, and in this the feeling of exclusive property goes for
                    something. The poem shall be sent out to you, if there be a chance of its reaching you; but will you not have left Malta by the
                    time a book to be published about New Year’s Day can arrive there?</p><p rend="indent1"> Had you been with me, I should have talked with you about a preface; as it is, it will be best simply to state, and
                    as briefly as possible, what I have aimed at in my style, and wherein, in my own judgement, I have succeeded or failed. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has announced it, in his Cyclopӕdic List,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longman regularly published updated versions of <title>The Cyclopædia; or, Universal Dictionary of Arts,
                            Sciences, and Literature</title>.</note> under the title of an epic poem, which I assuredly shall not affix to it myself;
                    the name, of which I was once over-fond, has nauseated me, and, moreover, should seem to render me amenable to certain laws which
                    I do not acknowledge.</p><p rend="indent1"> If I were at Malta, the siege of that illustrious island should have a poem, and a good one too; and you ought to
                    think about it, for of all sieges that ever has been, or ever will be, it was the most glorious, and called forth the noblest
                        heroism.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The 1565 epic siege by the Ottomans of the Crusader Knights Hospitallers on
                        Malta, who had been granted the island by the Holy Roman Emperor after the fall to the Turks of their previous base,
                        Rhodes.</note> Look after some modern Greek books, in particular the poem from which the Teseide of Boccaccio and
                    the Knight’s Tale are derived; if, indeed, it be not a translation from the Italian.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Boccaccio (1313–1375) author of <title>The Teseida</title> (c. 1340–1341). The first
                        vernacular epic in Italian, it dealt with the Greek Theseus and was the chief source for the love story of Geoffrey Chaucer’s
                        (c.1340–1400; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Knight’s Tale.</title> Boccaccio’s Greek sources have not been traced; it is possible
                        that he derived his story from ancient myths and tales collected by his friend Paolo de Perugia (dates unknown).</note> Could you lay hand on some of these old
                    books, and, on <hi rend="ital">old</hi> Italian poetry, by selling them at Leigh and Sotheby’s<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Sotheby (1771–1842) and George Leigh (d. 1815), booksellers and auctioneers who set up in business in
                        1804.</note> you might almost pay your travels.</p><p rend="indent1"> More manuscripts of Davis come down to-day. I have run through his Life of Chatterton, which is flimsy and
                        worthless.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Davis (1774–1854), <title>The Life of Thomas Chatterton</title> was
                        published in London in 1806 by Thomas Tegg (1776–1846; <title>DNB</title>), rather than <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> I shall <hi rend="ital">not</hi> advise <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to print it, and shall <hi rend="ital">warn</hi> the writer to expunge an
                    insult to you and to myself, which is not to be paid for by his praise. We formed a just estimate of the man’s moral stamina, most
                    certainly, and as for man-mending, I have no hopes of it. The proverb of the silk purse and the sow’s ear, comprises my philosophy
                    upon that subject.</p><p rend="indent1"> I write rapidly and unthinkingly, to be in time for the post. Why have you not made Lamb declare war upon Mrs.
                        Bare-bald?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge’s</ref> derogatory name for <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Anna Letitia Barbauld</ref>, because
                        they attributed to her a hostile review of <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb’s</ref> play <title>John
                            Woodvil; a Tragedy</title> (1802) in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 688–692.</note> He should singe
                    her flaxen wig with squibs, and tie crackers to her petticoats till she leapt about like a parched pea for very torture. There is
                    not a man in the world who could so well revenge himself. The Annual Review (that is, the first vol.) came down in my parcel
                    today. My articles<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1802</title>, 1 (1803): Martin Sauer (dates unknown), <title>An Account of a Geographical and Astronomical Expedition to
                            the Northern Parts of Russia Performed by Joseph Billings in the Years 1785–1796</title> (1802), 7–17; Alexander MacKenzie
                        (1763/4–1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Voyages from Montreal, on the River St Laurence, through the Continent of North
                            America, to the Frozen and Pacific Oceans in the Years 1789 and 1793</title> (1802), 18–30; Frederick Augustus Fischer
                        (1771–1829), <title>Travels in Spain in 1797 and 1798</title> (1802), 35–43; Giuseppi Acerbi (1773–1846), <title>Travels
                            through Sweden, Finland and Lapland, to the North Cape, in the Years 1798 and 1799</title> (1802), 45–56; Maria Guthrie
                        (dates unknown), <title>A Tour Performed in the Years 1795–6, through the Taurida, or Crimea</title> (1802), 62–66; Peter
                        Simon Pallas (1741–1811), <title>Travels through the Southern Provinces of the Russian Empire, in the Years 1793 and
                            1794</title> (1802), 66–73; Guillaume Antoine Olivier (1756–1814), <title>Travels in the Ottoman Empire, Egypt and
                            Persia</title> (1801), 89–101; <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (1800–1801),
                        207–218; Augustin Louis Josse (1763–1841; <title>DNB</title>), <title>El Tesoro Espanol o Biblioteca Portatil Espanola</title>
                        (1802), 557–566; Henry Kett (1761–1825; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Elements of General Knowledge, Introductory to Useful
                            Books in the Principal Branches of Literature and Science</title> (1802), 579–584; Henri Louis Cain (1728–1778),
                            <title>Memoires de Henri Louis Le Kain</title> (1801), 595–599; William Coxe (1748–1828; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Memoirs of Horatio, Lord Walpole</title> (1802), 599–601; Francis Wrangham (1769–1842; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Poems</title> (1802), 655–657; Walter Savage Landor, <title>Poetry by the Author of Gebir</title> (1802), 663–666;
                        Pierre Lambinet (1742–1813), <title>Recherche Historiques, Litteraires et Critiques sur l’Origine de l’Imprimerie</title>
                        (1799), 704–711.</note> are wickedly misprinted, and, in many instances, made completely nonsensical. If I could write Latin
                    even as I could once, perhaps I should talk to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> of publishing a collection of
                    the best modern Latin poets; they were <hi rend="ital">dulli canes</hi><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin
                        translates as ‘dull dogs’.</note> many of them, but a poor fellow who has spent years and years in doing his best to be
                    remembered, does deserve well enough of posterity to be reprinted once in every millenium, and, in fact, there are enough good
                    ones to form a collection of some extent.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you! prays your</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Old friend and brother,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R. Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>