<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1147</idno><idno type="nines">rce2269</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 84.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 16–18 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1147" type="letter"><head>1147. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1806-01-15">15 January
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ 6 Janry/ 1806<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 84<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 16–18 [in part].</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Before I speak of myself let me say something upon a more important subject. Nature has given <hi rend="ital">offensive</hi> armour for two reasons. in the first place it is <hi rend="ital">defensive</hi> because it serves to
                    intimidate. a better reason is that claws &amp; teeth are the tools with which animals must get their living. <del>X</del> that
                    the general system of one creature eating another is a benevolent one needs little proof; – there <hi rend="ital">must</hi> be
                    death, &amp; what can be wiser than thus to make death subservient to life?</p><p rend="indent1"> As for a state of nature, the phrase as applied to man is stark naked nonsense. Savage man is a degenerated animal.
                    My own belief is that the present human race is not much more than six thousands years old – according to the concurrent testimony
                    of all rational history – the Indian records are good for nothing. But add as many millenniums as you will, the question how came
                    they here at first still recurs, this <del>xxx</del> infinite series, is an infinite absurdity, &amp; to suppose them growing like
                    mushrooms, or maggots in mud, is as bad. Man must have been <hi rend="ital">made</hi> here, or <hi rend="ital">placed</hi> here,
                    with sufficient powers bodily &amp; mental for his own support – I think the most reasonable opinion is that the first men
                        <del>were</del> had a knowledge of language &amp; of religion – in short that the tales of a golden or patriarchal age are in
                    their foundations true. How soon the <del>xxxxx</del> civilized being regenerates under unfavourable circumstances has been enough
                    proved by history. Free will – God, &amp; final retribution solve all difficulties. that Deity cannot be understood is a stupid
                    objection – without one we can understand nothing. – I cannot put down my thought methodically without much revision &amp;
                    re-arrangement – but you may see what I would be at – it is no difficult thing to harpoon the Leviathan<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Leviathan or The Matter, Forme and Power of a Common Wealth Ecclesiasticall and Civil</title>
                        (1651), Thomas Hobbes (1588–1679; <title>DNB</title>) argued that humanity in the state of nature tended towards chaos and
                        violence.</note> &amp; wound him mortally.</p><p rend="indent1"> London disorders me by over-stimulation. I dislike its society more from reflection than from feeling. Company to a
                    certain degree intoxicates me. I do not often commit the fault of talking too much, – but very often say what would be better
                    unsaid, &amp; that too in a manner not to be easily forgotten. People go away &amp; repeat single sentences <del>forgetting</del>
                    dropping all that led to them &amp; all that explains them – <del>xx</del> very probably too in my hearty hatred of assentation I
                    commit faults of the opposite kind. Now I am sure to find this out myself – &amp; to get out of humour with myself; – what
                    prudence I have is not ready at demand &amp; so it is that &lt;the&gt; society of any except my friends tho it may be sweet in the
                    mouth is bitter in the belly. Besides I get a head ache usually – how should it be otherwise when my habits are so thoroughly
                    recluse?</p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your offer &amp; your advice – &amp; will follow the one &amp; accept the other. Don Manuel may be
                    finished best in town – I <del>xxxx</del> can now see the extent of the subject &amp; think it likely to make a third volume if
                    indeed I should be able to give a true picture of this country as it now is.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> was published in three
                        volumes, by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807.</note> the book will have a permanent value – tho
                    designed only for the purpose of raising ways &amp; means. When the Emperor<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to
                        Rickman’s employer, the Speaker of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>. Southey
                        had dubbed him the ‘Emperor of the Franks’, because of his power to frank mail, which Rickman used on Southey’s behalf.</note>
                    comes to town I wish you would send the two cargoes in your hands to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> – <ref target="places.html#Congreve">Congreve</ref> – Penkridge – Staffordshire, where I shall pick them up on my way. You remember
                    her I dare say: she is to give me materials for a musical letter,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> No letters on this
                        subject are included in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> &amp; much incidental assistance – which she can well do
                    being the cleverest woman I know, as well as one of the pleasantest. </p><p rend="indent1"> Late in March I shall make my appearance, which is allowing myself a full month here to work at the Spaniard.</p><p rend="indent1"> You may account by other means for the spread of the Mexican religion than by any love of blood. man is by nature a
                    religious animal, &amp; if the elements &lt;of religion&gt; were not innate in him (as I am convinced they are) sickness would
                    make him so. You will find that all savages connect superstition with disease. – some cause which they can neither comprehend nor
                    controul affects them painfully, – &amp; the <del>uniform</del> remedy always is to appease an offended Spirit or drive away a
                    malignant one. Even in enlightened societies you will find that men more readily believe what they <hi rend="ital">fear</hi> than
                    what they hope. religions therefore which threaten damnation, &amp; which impose <del>xxxx</del> privations &amp; self-torture
                    have always been more popular than any other. How many of our boys amusements consist in bearing pain, – grown children like to do
                    the same from a different motive, – you will more easily persuade a man to wear a hair cloth drawers, to flog himself, or swing
                    upon a hook, than to conform to the plain rules of morality &amp; common sense. I shall have to <del>xxxxxx</del> look into this
                    subject when writing of the spirit of Catholicism, which furnishes as good an illustration as the practices of the Hindoos. Here
                    in England <del>you find</del> Calvinism is the popular faith, – where one man believes in universal restitution, there are fifty
                    who believe that he will be damned for his damnable opinion. Beyond all doubt the religion of the Mexicans is the most diabolical
                    that has ever existed – it is not however by any means so mischievous as the Braminical system of casts, which, wherever it
                    exists, has put a total stop to the amelioration of society. The Mexicans were rapidly advancing. Were you more at leisure I
                    should urge you to bestow a weeks study upon the Spanish language for the sake of the mass of information contained in their
                    travellers &amp; historians. I cannot express to you the utter contempt in which I hold Robertson in consequence of having read
                    what he ought to have studied.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Robertson (1721–1793; <title>DNB</title>),
                        historian, about whose <title>History of America</title> (1792) Southey was habitually dismissive.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My indisposition has thrown me back – or the campaign would have been nearly at an end.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to Southey’s reviewing work for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> I am in the midst of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoes</ref> book,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William
                        Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de’ Medici</title> (1805), in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>,
                        4 (1806), 449–467.</note> which improves upon a second perusal, &amp; satisfies my judgement tho it disappointed my curiosity.
                        <del>X</del> The new edition of Spenser, <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis’s</ref> Romances, &amp; the Ossian
                    controversy are the only remaining articles which will require any expence of labour<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806): George Ellis, <title>Specimens of Early English
                            Metrical Romances</title> (1805), 536–544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763-1845; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of
                            Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544–555; Malcolm Laing (1762–1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian,
                            Containing the Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with Notes and Illustrations</title> (1805),
                        615–620; Archibald Macdonald (1739–1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Some of Ossian’s Lesser Poems Rendered into Verse [from
                            Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing’s Critical and Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity
                            of Ossian’s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Henry Mackenzie (1745–1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of
                            the Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title>
                        (1805), 679–699.</note> – </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-01-15">Tuesday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 15. 1806.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>