<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1008</idno><idno type="nines">rce2130</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 309–311 [in part]. Note: Nathan Jackson is unidentified.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1008" type="letter"><head>1008. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-12-26">26 December
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: For/ Lieutenant Southey./ to be left with Nathan Jackson
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Barbadoes/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: [partial; obscured] E/
                        DEC<lb/>Endorsements: 3/ <hi rend="ital">1000</hi>/ 333/ <hi rend="ital">10</hi>/ 10 –<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 309–311 [in part].<lb/> Note: Nathan Jackson is unidentified.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1804-12-26">Dec 26. 1804.</date></dateline><salute>Dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your letter reached me about a fortnight ago. I answered it hastily the same evening,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, Southey to Thomas Southey, 17 December 1804, Letter 1004.</note> that no time might be lost, – &amp;
                    now write again, lest my reply should by any accident miscarry, to bid you draw on <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> for 30 £ – if you should be prest for money, as must needs be the case. <del>The</del> It had been stated in
                    the Whitehaven paper<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware’s Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note> that the first Lieutenant was killed, &amp; the
                    Lieutenant of Marines – so that I was in my heart persuaded that you &amp; Hall had both gone overboard to the sharks.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, made an
                        unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war
                            <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or
                        wounded and Southey suspected that his brother was among the dead. Thomas had been the first lieutenant but was absent from
                        the raid because he had been placed under arrest. Charles Hayman (d. 1804) was made first lieutenant in his stead and died in
                        the attack. Hall (first name and dates unknown) was the Lieutenant of Marines on board HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>.</note> I am sorry for him, but after the newspaper account have rather to congratulate him on being alive than
                    to console him for his loss of limb. As <del>you</del> for you – it is very well you were in the frying-pan. your rascally skipper
                    might have got rid of you less dishonourably for himself by sending you in the boats. – I look very anxiously for another letter.
                    long before this you must either be settled aboard once more, or else fairly adrift.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have made some use of your letters in the third Annual Review. M<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Kinnen – a brother of Mrs
                    Keenan who <del>d</del>made that chalk drawing of me which <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> has –
                    has published a tour thro the British West Indies – a decent book but dull. <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mrs Keenan
                        (dates unknown) was the sister of Daniel MacKinnen (fl. 1800s), whose <title>Tour through the British West Indies</title>
                        (1804) was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 50–56. Her husband, John Keenan (fl. c.
                        1780–1819), exhibited a portrait of Southey at the Royal Academy in 1803.</note> In reviewing it I eked out his account with
                    yours, &amp; contrasted his words upon the slave trade, with <del>some</del> a passage from your letters. In doing this I could
                    not help thinking what materials for a book you might bring home if you would take the trouble. as thus – describe the appearance
                    of all the Islands you touch at from the sea – their towns how situated, how built – what public buildings. what sort of houses,
                    the inside of the houses how furnished – what the mode of life of the towns people – of the planters in different ranks, &amp; of
                    the different European settlers. in short all you see &amp; all you hear, looking about the more earnestly, &amp; asking
                    questions. <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey did eventually publish such an account in his <title>A
                            Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1828).</note> Many anecdotes of this &amp; the last war you have
                    opportunities of collecting – particularly of Victor Hughes.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Victor Hughes (1770–1826) was
                        a Jacobin commissioner who overthrew the British on the island of Guadeloupe. The British had invaded and seized the island
                        from the French in 1794; Hughes, sent by the revolutionary government of France, rallied black resistance, expelled the
                        British and proclaimed slavery to be abolished. Many of the white French plantation owners fled to Martinique, and there
                        followed a period of black republican rule. In 1802, Napoleon Bonaparte sent a French force which re-took the island and
                        re-established slavery.</note> something also of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Domingo or Hayti as it must be now called<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 1 January 1804, Jean Jacques Dessalines (1758–1806) declared independence for Haiti (formerly
                        the French owned island of Saint-Domingue) becoming its first emperor.</note> – which I find means <hi rend="ital">asperosa</hi> in Spanish – <hi rend="ital">rugged</hi>. If you would bring home matter for a picture of the Islands as they
                    now are – I could delineate what they were from the old Spaniards &amp; there would be a very curious book between us.</p><p rend="indent1"> While I was thus writing there came a letter from <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to whom I had
                    written the history of your escape from the Lilly &amp;c.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, 18 December 1804, Letter 1006.</note> he says ‘if you think 50 £ will be of <del>any use</del> &lt;service&gt;
                    to him toward the heavy expence of an unemployed life in the West Indies that sum shall be ready for you whenever wanted.’ Draw
                    therefore upon <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> to that amount instead of the 30 – or, if you have already
                    drawn, for 20 more. – if for the whole sum at once, at ten days sight. – </p><p rend="indent1"> Lord Proby<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby (1779–1804), eldest son of Sir
                        John Joshua Proby 1st Earl of Carysfort (1751–1828; <title>DNB</title>). Proby was the captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, who, having been sent to the disease-ridden Leeward Islands station, died on 6 August at Surinam, from
                        yellow fever.</note> was sent to the West Indies by that old villain S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincent<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral of the Fleet John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735–1823; <title>DNB</title>).</note> because he
                    voted against the ministry. that vote has now cost him his life. Any other Captain who had gone in his place might have
                        <del>share</del> died in the same way, but <del>what</del> how infamous is it that the power of appointing to a pestilential
                    station should be exerted as one means of ministerial influence. I never hear that old villain mentioned without telling Groves
                        story.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Grove (d. 1817), naval officer and colleague of Thomas Southey’s. His
                        ‘story’ has not been recorded.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> They are printing the notes to Madoc which are to be all at the end. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> superintended the press.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805) was in the process of being printed by <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James
                            Ballantyne</ref> in Edinburgh, where Harry was studying for his degree in medicine.</note> he has been elected President
                    of the Speculative Society, &amp; also of the Medical Society, being the youngest man ever appointed to the last. I suppose the
                    book will be finished within three weeks, &amp; published in about six the journey to London requiring time, &amp; also the
                    putting the books in boards. Before that time I shall hope to hear what is become of you, &amp; shall wait that intelligence
                    before your copy be sent off. for if Commodore Hood<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir
                        Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>), in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey served.</note> does
                    not give you an appointment – you will be coming home, &amp; Madoc has already been very unlucky in his way to you, three letters
                    full of him – or four – having been lost in the captured Packets. the Review<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                            <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> shall also be sent you, according to your direction. by some Bristol vessel. – Amadis
                    has gained for me a world of praise in the Edinburgh Review &amp; British Critic.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s 1803 translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> was reviewed in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 5
                        (October1803), 109–136, and in the <title>British Critic</title>, 24 (1804), 471–481.</note> being only a translation it
                    excites no jealousy. I think I have a fair chance of the fifty pounds depending upon the sale of the edition. My Specimens<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The project that Southey undertook with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> are only now going to press – because <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> has charge of them, &amp; he is a lazy lubber. I am hard
                    at my annual work,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3
                        (1805): John Barrow (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of Travels into the Interior of Southern Africa, in the
                            years 1797 and 1798, including Observations on the Geology &amp; Geography, the Natural History ... and Sketches of the
                            Various Tribes Surrounding the Cape of Good Hope</title>, Vol. II (1804), 22–33; Robert Percival (1765–1826), <title>An
                            Account of the Cape of Good Hope</title> (1804), 34–41; Daniel Mackinnen (1767–1830), <title>A Tour Through the British
                            West Indies, in the years 1802 and 1803 giving a Particular Account of the Bahama Islands</title> (1804), 50–56; John
                        Barrow, <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a
                            Short Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804),
                        69–83; <title>Sir John Froissart’s Chronicles of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the
                            Reign of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans. Thomas Johnes (1748–1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804),
                        189–194; George Heriot (1766–1844), <title>The History of Canada, From its First Discovery: Comprehending an Account of the
                            Original Establishment of the Colony of Louisiana</title>, 194–197; <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from
                            the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the
                            Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 225–231; Edward Ledwich
                        (1738–1823), <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398–413; <title>Original Correspondence of Jean Jacques
                            Rousseau, with Mad. La Tour de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title> (1804), 485–488; Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the
                            Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804), 488–93; David Irving
                            (1778–1850),<title> The Lives of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary Dissertations on the Literary History of Scotland and
                            the Early Scotish Drama</title> (1804), 493–499; Walter Scott, <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of
                            Ercildoune</title> (1804), 555–563; Charles Abraham Elton (1778–1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804), 564–565; William Day
                        (dates unknown), <title>The Shepherd’s Boy: being Pastoral Tales</title> (1804), 567–568; E. Warren (dates unknown),
                            <title>The Poet’s Day, or, Imagination’s Ramble</title> (1804), 568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a Series of Prints,
                            Designed by her Royal Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with Poetical Illustrations
                            by T. P</title> [Thomas Park (1758/9–1834; <title>DNB</title>)] (1804), 568–580; Thomas Green Fessenden (1771–1837),
                            <title>Original Poems</title> (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777–1805), <title>The Powers of Genius</title> (1801), 571;
                        Thomas Clio Rickman (1761–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in Celebration of the Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint
                            Domingo, November 29, 1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield, <title>Good Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert
                        Spencer (1770–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of Sorrow</title> (1804), 574–575; <title>British Purity: or, the
                            World we Live in. A Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries…By Lory Lucian and Jerry Juvenal, … Assisted by S. Scriblerus,
                            etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804), 575; William Falconer (1732–1769), <title>The Shipwreck</title>, (1804), ed., James Stanier
                        Clarke (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), 577–580; William Tooke (1777–1863), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles
                            Churchill: with Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his Life</title>, (1804), 580–585; J. Amphlett (dates
                        unknown), <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title> (1804), 585; Joseph Jefferson (1766–1824), <title>Horae
                            Poeticæ. Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586–587; Alexander Campbell (1764–1824; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804), 587–591; William Crowe (bap. 1745, d. 1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593–594; John Finlay (1782–1810), <title>Wallace, or, The Vale
                            of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594–596; Jessie Stewart (dates unknown), <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas
                            Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768–1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected with Literature. Imitated from
                            the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597–598; <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (1804),
                        621–634; Edward Davies (1756–1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language,
                            of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive Society</title> (1804), 634–644; [Anon.] <title>No
                            Slaves - No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour of the African Trade by a Liverpool
                            Merchant</title> (1804), 644–648; William Tennant (1758–1813), <title>Indian Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures
                            on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title> (1803), 658–670; John Gardiner (fl. 1758–1792),
                            <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670–674; Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the Fresco
                            Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918–923.</note> &amp; upon the point of finishing it – which will be a
                    great relief. the history will then go on again<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected ‘History of Portgal’,
                        which he never completed.</note> – &amp; I must turn-to to raise supplies for the year</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> – now Count Burnetski – is gone to Poland to be librarian to a Polish Count
                    &amp; teach his sons English!!! Lord have mercy upon us. he has nothing to do but say what is English for such a thing when they
                    ask him. One has never dreamt of any thing stranger than this. – <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgan</ref> has
                    lost his mother. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> has bought an estate near Lyme, &amp; is going to build
                    there. for whom? – This is all the news I can recollect, – except that Hamilton<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel
                        Hamilton (dates unknown), owner of the <title>Critical Review</title> 1799–1804.</note> is broke whereby I shall lose from 20
                    to 30 £ which he owes me for Critical work, &amp; which I never was able to get. rather hard upon one whose brains &amp; eye sight
                    have quite enough to do by choice, &amp; are never overpaid for what they do by necessity. – For nearer matter the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> has the cow pock,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May had
                        been inoculated against smallpox, using cowpox serum; a method popularised by Edward Jenner (1749–1823; <title>DNB</title>) in
                            <title>An Inquiry Into the Causes and Effects of the Variolæ Vaccinæ</title> (1798).</note> which is now overblown – for
                    by the Lord eruptive diseases are just like flowers. you insert the seed – it takes root &amp; <hi rend="ital">blossoms</hi>,
                    &amp; that flower produces seed which would go propagating to all eternity if it finds a fit soil. Oh what a world of
                    unintelligible things do we live in! – The little girl is not pretty – but she is a sweet child – so excellently good tempered –
                    as joyous as a sky lark in a fine June morning, &amp; so quick of eye &amp; of action &amp; of intellect – that I have a sad
                    feeling about me of the little chance there is of rearing her. so do’nt think too much of her. –Whether this war with Spain will
                    involve one with Portugal also is what we are all speculating about at present. I think it very likely that Bonaparte will oblige
                    the Portugueze to turn the English out. a great evil to me in particular, tho should <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> be thus driven to England my settling will the sooner take place. At present I am as unsettled as ever, at a
                    distance from my books, perpetually in want of them; wishing &amp; wanting to be permanently fixed, &amp; still prevented by the
                    old cause. Make a capital prize Tom &amp; lend me a couple of hundreds<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">It was customary
                        for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ‘prizes’, meaning ships and their cargo, captured in armed
                        conflict.</note> – &amp; you shall see what a noble appearance my books will make. – N. B. I have a good many that wait for
                    your worship to letter them. This Spanish war may throw something in your way – but I do’nt like this war, &amp; think it is
                    unjust &amp; ungenerous to quarrel with an oppressed people, because they have not strength to resist the French.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spain declared war on Britain on 14 December 1804.</note> You know I greatly esteem the
                    Spaniards. As for France I am willing to pay half my last guinea to support a contest for national honour against her. but it
                    began foolishly &amp; well will it be if we do not end it even more foolishly than we began.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>