<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1512</idno><idno type="nines">rce2634</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1512" type="letter"><head>1512. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1808-09-27">27 September
                        1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb/>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                        Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, ‘The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 296–300.</note></head><opener><dateline><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick </ref><date when="1808-09-27"> Tuesday Sept. 27. 1808</date></dateline><salute rend="right"><hi rend="ital">Snow on Helvellin</hi>.</salute><salute>Dear Senhora</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> So long is it since I have written to you, that I know not even whether the receipt of the last letter has been
                    acknowledged, – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Piggarell</ref> I will be bound has not done it – &amp; whether I have
                    myself or not is more than my memory will reach to. As little can I remember whether or not you have been told that my old Letters
                    have been made fit for reading, &amp; sent again to the press, in which way, if the edition sells (as sooner or later it will)
                    these present politics will put about sixty or seventy pounds in my pocket.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>Letters written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797) were being reprinted in an expanded
                        form as <title>Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> Shortly after the
                    accomplishment of that job which took up just a weeks close application, Miss Wood<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Isabella Wood (dates unknown), cousin of <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>.</note> came over
                    &amp; staid with us nine days. In the course of that time I walked above fifty miles with her, &amp; showed her the Vale of St
                    Johns, Thirlmere, &amp;c – to the greatest possible advantage. – whenever you come again you will profit by the discoveries we
                    made of points of view &amp;c. I &amp; the two Ediths<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">wife</ref>, and daughter <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                        May</ref>.</note> went back with her to <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>, &amp; after a visit of five
                    clear days, we returned yesterday. Here I found a letter from the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Long Man in the
                        Row</ref> telling me that the edition of Thalaba has at last come to an end, &amp; he thinks with rather an accelerated pace,
                    &amp; recommending that another be sent to the press with as little delay as may be. Accordingly I am now making many little
                    emendations, inserting additional notes, &amp; doing my best to improve what is already so good as to be well worth improving, for
                    be it known Senhora, that I, who am in downright earnest a fair judge, think that said poem a very fine one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> appeared in 1809.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> As for Sir Arthur &amp; Sir Hew, – for the first time in my life I was so irritated by public news as to pass a
                    sleepless night in consequence. There is a straight &amp; easy way of proceeding in such a case – which is to break the
                    convention, &amp; shoot those who made it; or else, after the manner of the Romans, deliver these up to the enemy with ropes about
                    their necks. Sir Arthur ought to be shot for fighting when he did. he was afraid of being superseded before he won a battle, &amp;
                    for that reason fought with only half his own force, – for fear if he had waited till the other half came up Sir Hew should land
                    &amp; take the command. Sir Hew – Lady Hew I ought rather to say for the creature has long been known to be an old woman, – then
                    suffered Junot to fall back about thirty miles after the battle, &amp; during the negociations, – &amp; so between them they have
                    sacrificed the honour of England &amp; the interest of Spain.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s exasperation was
                        caused by the Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771–1813)
                        and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769–1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley,
                        who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were
                        content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755–1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750–1830;<title>
                        DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> But the root
                    of all evil lies in the Duke of York<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany
                        (1763–1827), Commander in Chief of the army.</note> who appoints such wretches. It is one comfort that the general opinion is
                    so openly &amp; loudly expressed, – &amp; I hope &amp; trust an example will be made of the commander. My own opinion is that no
                    man could possibly consent to let Junot carry off his plunder, unless he had been promised a share of it for so doing. This will
                    be laughed at &amp; generally scouted, – but the man who could subscribe such a convention is capable of any degree of baseness; –
                    &amp; there are but two possible motives for his conduct, – cowardice or corruption. the former with a victorious &amp; superior
                    army seems to be out of the question. &amp; for the latter – I am afraid Senhora that they who sell their votes at home would not
                    have much scruple at selling their country abroad.</p><p rend="indent1"> Mr. Horton<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Not otherwise identified.</note> seemed to be all that is deaf
                    &amp; good natured. His wife is as unpleasant a woman as one shall meet on a summers day. – out of humour with every thing,
                    Borrowdale was nothing to Dovedale, &amp; the roads were intolerable, too bad for any body’s horse or carriage. The daughter (whom
                    I named Miss Nobs from a strong likeness which she bears to the hero of that noble story of Dr Daniel Dove of Doncaster)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr. Daniel Dove’s horse in Southey’s novel <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847). On the
                        tale and its origin, and Coleridge’s role in disseminating it, see David Chandler, ‘“As Long-Winded as Possible”: Southey,
                        Coleridge, and <title>The Doctor &amp;c</title>.’, <title>Review of English Studies</title>, 60 (2009), 605–619.</note> has
                    more of her fathers temper &amp; would have been well enough pleased if she might.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard that the <ref target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Mountagues</ref> mean to travel hitherward. In this
                    marriage she risks something which he does not, – but having already taken the children, the worst part of the bargain was made
                    &amp; the rest to be expected. I am curious to see her. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is now
                    settled at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge, having
                        separated from his wife who remained living at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, took up residence with
                        the Wordsworths at Allan Bank, Grasmere.</note> &amp; the boys<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> are going to school at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. He has been over here
                    twice, – the last time while we were at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>, – &amp; then he was in villainous
                    humour &amp; there was a good deal of cat-&amp;-doggery going on, as I dare say Mrs Mountague will hear when she gets to Grasmere.
                    I do not expect to see much of him.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> comes next month, – a matter of great joy, he being one of the men whom I like
                    best in the world. – sound headed &amp; sound hearted.</p><p rend="indent1"> Heaven &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Mr Frere</ref><note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Three of Frere’s translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle
                            of the Cid</title>; publication was delayed because Frere took a long time to return proofs.</note> know why the Cid has
                    been delayed – I do not. But they tell me it was expected to be published yesterday – so I trust <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edwards</ref> copy will have arrived before this reaches you. I need not bid you
                    admire this book, a great part of which will assuredly be after your own heart.</p><p rend="indent1"> Kehama<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &amp; everything else have been standing still lately. I am now setting out
                    again on a fresh campaign. Paper may be expected to fall, &amp; the next news which I shall have to send you will, it is to be
                    hoped, be that my Brazil<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                        was published in 1810.</note> is in the press. Make my respects to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir
                        Edward</ref> – take <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love, &amp; believe me very affectionately yours –
                    Robert Southey.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">God daughter</ref> makes poor work with her pencil, &amp; cries
                    (literally) for Barker to come &amp; teach her to do it better. Oh that you could see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my
                        son</ref> such a beautiful fellow, &amp; so gloriously noisy – Train up a child<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Proverbs</title> 22: 6.</note> &amp;c says Solomon, – &amp; I am following his advice so well, that there is good
                    reason to think <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> will at least equal his father in this domestic
                    accomplishment.</p></div></body></text></TEI>