<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1235</idno><idno type="nines">rce2357</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30928.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1235" type="letter"><head>1235. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-11-06">6 November
                    1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ NOV10/ 1806<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30928<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is so likely that you may see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>  on his road
                    hitherward before a letter from me could reach him, that my motive for writing this evening rather than awhile hence, is to beg
                    you to send the Missionary Reports of both sorts,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to the
                            <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> and the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society.</title> The <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> were first issued as separate
                        numbers, each dealing with a specific mission, from 1798 onwards. They were gathered into volumes, the first including the
                        transactions for the years 1795–1802 in the Pacific and South Africa, the second, of 1804, beginning with further South
                        African transactions. The <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> were published as a
                        periodical from 1793 and then bound in volumes between 1800–1817.</note> by him rather than in the box: they will come sooner,
                    &amp; I want them as soon as they can come. I should also be glad of half a quire of marble paper (glazed) <del>xxx</del> of four
                    or five different sorts.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown), a Bristol bookseller
                        and stationer. Southey frequently sent Danvers orders to be supplied by Barry.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> When I mentioned putting up shelves I thought that only those books which were damp would be taken out of the
                    boxes. It will be necessary to keep the door locked – &amp; then they will be safe – but I hope the mice will not get at them. In
                    the spring most certainly I hope to settle them somewhere or other.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is come<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had
                        travelled abroad to Malta for his health in 1804, taking up a temporary post there as Public Secretary to the British Civil
                        Commissioner. He arrived back in England in August 1806, and came back to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> in
                        October, but did not live there for long.</note> &amp; grown quite fat, – a good symptom as it is the habit of his family.</p><p rend="indent1"> These elections make the newspapers very amusing. Had I a vote for Westminster, much as I abominate travelling, I
                    would go up for the pure pleasure of giving it that honest Paull against that thorough scoundrel Sheridan,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Paull (1770–1808; <title>DNB</title>), Indian trader (1790–1805) and radical politician, who stood
                        for Westminster in the general election of November 1806, against Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751–1816; <title>DNB</title>),
                        the famous radical Whig, and Sir Samuel Hood (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>) for the Tories. Sheridan (the son of an Irish
                        actor) had most to fear from Paull’s challenge, and he allied himself with Hood, hypocritically concentrating on Paull’s
                        humble origins as the son of a tailor in order to defeat him.</note> – a scoundrel who for the last twenty years of his life
                    has had nothing to keep him from utter infamy but his supposed political consistency, &amp; who has now compleatly forfeited that,
                    &amp; thrown away the last rag <del>that</del> &lt;which&gt; covered the nakedness of his rascality. – It is said &amp; with much
                    probability that the main reason for the dissolution was to get Paull out &amp; so put a stop to proceedings against <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref>, means having been taken to prevent him from
                    getting a borough, which was easily enough accomplished, all parties joining against a man who was too honest to belong to any. I
                    certainly wish his charges had affected any other man rather than the Marquis, – because had it not been for that pending
                    accusation I believe he would have succeeded to <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, as Foreign Secretary.</note> – &amp; tho the best thing for the national
                    character would be to mark him with the heavy hand of disgrace for his manifold iniquities in the East, the best thing under the
                    circumstances for the government would be to make him Minister, he being a man of great abilities, &amp; as ambitious as Bonaparte
                    himself. Just such a man do we want to have at the head of affairs, – one who would say to Bonaparte if you will have all the
                    continent we will have all the colonies – if you will exclude us from the land we will exclude you from the seas. Who would throw
                    open the ports of Spanish &amp; Portugueze America, take the Mauritius &amp; other French Isles in the East – expel them from the
                    West Indies, make Sicily English, take Sardinia under our protection, &amp; garrison Alexandria. If he cannot be sent over in
                    chains to India &amp; hung in the presence of the Embassador from the court of every native prince, &amp; then his skin strippt
                    &amp; sent round the country, – I would give him the reins at home.</p><p rend="indent1"> There is a grievous &amp; total want of talent not merely in administration but in the whole legislation, &amp;
                    that necessarily arising from the formation of the house of commons. Vide Espriella when he makes his appearance.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807), Letter 48.</note> Meantime the effect produced by such men as Robson<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Bateman Robson (1753–1827), MP for Okehampton, a radical Whig.</note> &amp; Paull, so below par as
                    they are in their abilities, by mere dint of unimpeachable honesty, &amp; plain straight-forward good intentions is highly
                    consolatory. For his own sake I wish Fox had died twelvemonths sooner, – otherwise I am not sure whether the sacrifice which he
                    made of his character was not desirable for the country. It has taught the country the true meaning of parties, &amp; the
                    no-meaning of all the obsolete words – Whig &amp; Tory.</p><p rend="indent1"> R<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Taylor<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781–1858;
                            <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with
                        his son William Francis (1817–1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> goes on so slowly with Espriella that if he does not
                    spur me I must even spur him – Do’nt expect over much from the book or you will be disappointed; – not that I am not myself well
                    pleased with it, for I like well what is done, – but this is the inevitable consequence of over-expectations. Can you procure for
                    me in Bristol (I have tried in London without success) Whitfields Journal,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> George
                        Whitefield (1714–1770; <title>DNB</title>), Calvinistic Methodist leader, whose <title>Journals</title> were published in an
                        unauthorised version in 1738. The authorised version, <title>The Two First Parts of Whitefield’s Life, with his Journals
                            Revised, Corrected and Abridged</title>, appeared in 1756. Whitefield is discussed in <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807), Letter 53.</note> &amp; the Life of Alexander
                    Kilham, the founder of the New Methodists?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The autobiographical <title>Life</title> of
                        Alexander Kilham (1762–1798), founder of the ‘methodist new connection’, was first published in 1799.</note> Both books are
                    what they call out of print, – but both likely enough to be found second-hand. I wish very much to <del>xxx</del> get them, as
                    they [?are] the only document I want for those letters in Espr. which relate to the state of religion in England, – perhaps the
                    most curious part of the book.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Letter 53 of <title>Letters from England</title>
                        discussed the Methodists.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; both the children<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert
                        Southey</ref>.</note> go on well. We know not whether <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> means to
                        lecture,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had previously informed Danvers that Coleridge intended to
                        lecture ‘at the Royal Institution upon the Principles common to the Fine Arts’; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 18 October
                        1806, Letter 1229. He did not in fact lecture there until 1808, on the subject of the Principles of Poetry, Shakespeare and
                        Milton.</note> nor how long he means to remain at home, – his plans &amp; purpose being as vague &amp; <hi rend="ital">weathercockical</hi> as ever –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-11-06">Thursday Nov 6. 1806</date></p><p rend="indent1"> If it could be so managed I should like to meet <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> at Kendal &amp;
                        go with him to the Caves<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Kendal is a starting point for a tour of the limestone
                            dales of the Lancashire/Yorkshire border, which contain many caves, including Yordas cave, described by Wordsworth in
                                <title>The Prelude</title> (1850), Book VIII, 560–589.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>