<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1117</idno><idno type="nines">rce2239</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30928.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        344–47 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1117" type="letter"><head>1117. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1805-11-07">7 November
                        1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol/
                        Single <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] E/ NOV 10 <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30928<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        344–47 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1805-11-07">Nov. 7. 1805</date></dateline><salute>Dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is very long since I have written to you, meantime you have heard of my intention to visit Portugal next year,
                    &amp; of my journey to Edinburgh. Of both these <del>xxx</del> &lt;subjects&gt; I have something to say.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> advised me to go over this winter with my family. this was impossible,
                    as there is a pretty hard winters work before me. I shall go in the spring if <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    does not chuse to accompany me, most likely in the autumn if she does – which indeed I expect. it would then be advisable or at
                    least pleasant to pass one more summer here, &amp; to have the young one a few months older. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> advises us to come by Carvalho’s ship<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> from Bristol. At any rate we shall come to Bristol, if not to go by him, on our way to
                    Falmouth. In case of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> going I shall make up my mind to at least a two years
                    residence, – &amp; of course leave <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> in England. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> does not like going, but she ought to go, &amp; I believe will. At all events my
                    going is so resolved a thing that I have desired <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> to fill up my place in the fifth Annual Review, &amp; after this year shall
                    have done with that sort of work for ever &amp; ever Amen.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &amp; I spent three days with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                        Scott</ref> on our way to Edinburgh. he enquired for you &amp; desired to be remembered when I wrote. Camp<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott’s bull terrier dog.</note> is in good health, &amp; put up a hare which Percy &amp;
                    Douglas the two greyhounds<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dogs belonging to Scott.</note> caught in a minute, &amp; which
                    made part of our next days dinner. I saw Newark, &amp; Branksome &amp; Melrose<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        visited Newark Castle (a ruin in the valley of the Yarrow Water, three miles west of Selkirk in the Scottish Borders),
                        Branxholme Castle (owned by Charles William Henry Montagu-Scott, 4th Duke of Buccleuch and 6th Duke of Queensberry
                        (1772–1819), friend and relation of Walter Scott who used the castle as a setting for his work <title>The Lay of the Last
                            Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805)) and Melrose Abbey (founded in 1136 by Cistercian monks; a picturesque ruin).</note> – the
                    Tiviot &amp; the Yarrow, &amp; went salmon-spearing upon the Tweed.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rivers in the Scottish
                        borders.</note> When we reached the great city <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> was invited by a friend
                    of Elmsleys to meet me at supper. as his review of Madoc was then printed,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey
                        reviewed <title>Madoc</title> (1805) in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1–29.</note> tho not published,
                    he thought proper to send it me first, that I might meet him or not as I felt disposed. This was gentlemanly conduct. Having been
                    reviewed now above threescore times it is not very likely that I should feel much affected by praise or censure. I met him in good
                    humour – which if I had not been disposed so to do I could not have helped on seeing an homunculus<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning a little or diminutive man; a mannikin.</note> of five foot one, with a face which upon a larger scale
                    would be handsome, but can now only be called pretty, ēēnunciating his words as if he had studied eelocution under <ref target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref>, of whom indeed he is an Elzevir edition<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Books printed and published by the Elzevir (or Elsevier) family of Dutch booksellers, publishers, and
                        printers, from about 1592 to 1680. They were best known for their editions of the Greek New Testament and the classics. The
                        Elzevir editions were valued for their neatness and elegant small type.</note> in better binding. After supper we got upon the
                    general question of taste. You would have been amused to have seen how he floundered about, endeavouring to imply an apology
                    without making one, &amp; talking <hi rend="ital">at</hi> what he did not talk <hi rend="ital">of</hi>, – &amp; how I on my part
                    without mentioning his review, quoted its phrases occasionally, took up his principles of criticism without once referring to
                    their application, &amp; in the best natured way in the world made him fully sensible that he was – but five foot one. – Upon my
                    soul I cannot feel offended with a thing so insignificant. He has wit &amp; readiness, but in taste &amp; learning so mere a child
                    &amp; so utterly feeble in intellect that I was actually astonished. Indeed the whole corps of Edinburgh reviewers appear
                    miserably puny to me who have been accustomed to live with strong men. <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> came
                    back in the stage with us, to visit the ladies, &amp; supt here, – so you see we are good friends. What I condemn in him is a
                    habit of speaking of <del>xxx</del> books worse than he thinks of them – because <del>xxx</del> ill-natured things are said with
                    better effect than good-natured ones, &amp; liked better, &amp; <del>xxx</del> for the sake of selling his review he often abuses
                    books in <del>public</del> print, which he makes no scruple to praise in conversation. But his praise &amp; censure are alike
                    hap-hazard &amp; worthless.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> instructed me to rig myself anew at Edinburgh with coat, hat, pantaloons &amp;
                    boots, – which I meant to do, – but considering that cash was low with me, &amp; that if learning was better than house &amp;
                    land, it certainly must be much better than fine <del>cloaths</del> &lt;apparel&gt;, which is but sanity, – <del>I returned with
                        the old</del> I resolved to make the old cloaths last till next summer – &amp; accordingly laid out the money at the
                    booksellers instead of the taylors. And a good box full did I send home, which it does my heart good to look at now that they are
                    arranged in due order upon the shelves.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Domine</ref> went on Tuesday last, &amp; was to reach Edinburgh last night. by
                    way of an episode in <del>the</del> his summer at the Lakes, he has fallen in love with Miss Noel, daughter of the member for
                    Rutlandshire, &amp; grand-daughter of Lord Barham,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emma Noel (d. 1873), daughter of Gerard
                        Noel Edwardes of Exton Park, Rutland (1759–1838; <title>DNB</title>), who adopted the surname Noel in 1798, and inherited a
                        baronetcy in 1813 to become the 2nd Baronet Barham. Her grandfather was Charles Middleton, 1st Baron Barham (1726–1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and administrator.</note> &amp; the young Lady has fallen in love with him, &amp; the
                    father is of course very indignant, &amp; the lady of course very resolute, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Dominie</ref> in a fair way of having plenty of anxiety, plenty of letters, plenty of trouble, &amp; the Lady at last
                    with 1500£ of her own when she comes of age, as much more on her fathers death &amp; that is all. It happened at <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> – for she was of the Bilberry party, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is perfectly happy having got into a correspondence with the young Lady, &amp; a
                    sort of paper war with her father, the very thing in the world which he likes best as a sort of seasoning to the insipidity of his
                    life.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have just begun my reviewing – &amp; alas – my eyes this very day began to ail again. <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> has applied to me for Spanish &amp; Port. literary lives in
                    his biography – which I have undertaken.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin’s <title>General Biography: or,
                            Lives, Critical and Historical, of the Most Eminent Persons of all Ages, Countries, Conditions, and Professions, Arranged
                            According to Alphabetical Order</title> was published in 10 volumes between 1799–1815. According to Kenneth Curry
                            (<title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, p. 403), Southey contributed the
                        following entries to volumes VI (1807), VII (1808) and VIII (1813): Volume VI: ‘Vasco Lobeira’, 314–317; ‘Francisco Rodrigues
                        Lobo’, 318; ‘Fernam Lopez’, 340; ‘Gregorio Lopez’, 340; ‘Francisco de Losa’, 344–345; ‘Joam de Lucena’, 371–372; ‘Miguel de
                        Luna’, 388; ‘Fr. Francisco de Santo Agostinho Macedo’, 434–435, ‘El Enamorado Macias’, 437–438; ‘P. Fr. Pedro Malon de
                        Chaide’, 506; ‘D. Jorge Manrique’, 523–524; ‘Don Juan Manuel’, 529–530; ‘Ausias March’, 542–543; ‘Juan de Mariana’, 555–557;
                        ‘Vicente Mariner’, 558; ‘Luis de Marmol Carvajal’, 569; ‘P. M. Fr. Juan Marquez’, 574–575. Volume VII: ‘Juan de Mena’, 28–30;
                        ‘Don Inigo Lopez de Mendoza’, 37–38; ‘D. Diego Hurtado de Mendoza’, 38–39; ‘Menezes’, 41–42; ‘Christoval de Mesa’, 59–60;
                        ‘George de Montemayor’, 174–175; ‘Ambrosio de Morales’, 194–198; ‘Alonso de Castro Nunez’, 466; ‘Antonio de Naxara’, 469;
                        ‘Abraham Nehemias’, 469; ‘Florian de Ocampo’, 471–472; ‘Fr. Diego de Olarte’, 487; ‘Fr. Andres de Olmos’, 497; ‘Jerome Osorio’
                        [with Thomas Morgan (1752–1821)], 530–533; ‘Alonso de Ovalle’, 548; ‘Andres de Oviedo’, 555–556; ‘Gonzalo Fernandez de
                        Oviedo’, 556–557; ‘Lorenzo de Padilla’, 578; ‘Pedro Paez’, 578–580; ‘D. Juan de Palafox y Mendoza’, 585. Volume VIII: ‘Josef
                        de Ossau, Salas y Pellicer’, 25–26; Bartholomé Pereira’, 46; ‘Luys Pereyra’, 46; ‘Antonio Perez’, 46–47; ‘Ruy de Pina’, 173;
                        ‘Juan de Pineda’, 175; ‘Fernam Mendes Pinto’, 178–179; ‘Thome Pires’, 182–184; ‘Fernando de Pulgar’, 385.</note> what with
                    this &amp; with Don Manuel<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                            Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> my winter will be fully &amp; laboriously employed, – but it
                    will set me even with the world, &amp; leave me the Spaniard over &amp; above. At Xmas I will send you a draft. – Of the sale of
                    Madoc I know nothing, &amp; expect little,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>Madoc</title>, published
                        in March 1805.</note> – of its ultimate effect on my reputation &amp; thereby on my well-doing I have <del>xxx</del> no doubt.
                    Almost I am tempted to trouble you to hunt for the books about the Cid that I might make a volume sure of popularity &amp; of
                    sale, which could be done almost without labour.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> No letter from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> of a later date than the last of July &amp; then he
                    had the fever worse than at any former attack. I am uneasy – but have been recollecting that ill news always travels fast, &amp;
                    that in silence therefore there is nothing which ought to alarm me. – For politics I am quite sick at heart. the worst news of all
                    is the Duke of Yorks appointment<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany
                        (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>): second son of King George III (1738–1820, King of Great Britain 1760–1820;
                        <title>DNB</title>). Notorious for his ineffectual generalship in Holland in 1799 which gave rise to the rhyme ‘The Grand Old
                        Duke of York’, he nevertheless retained his position as Commander in Chief of the army. He was appointed Colonel of the 1st
                        Regiment of Footguards in 1805.</note> – the most infamous &amp; shameless acquiescence on the part of Pitt<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759–1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783–1801,1804–1806.</note> – for the sake of
                    keeping his place! Oh for a day of reckoning! – the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Peachys</ref>, went yesterday.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Ediths remembrances</salute><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>