<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1644</idno><idno type="nines">rce2766</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 223–226 [in part, and
                        misdated 14 March 1809]. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1644" type="letter"><head>1644. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-06-15">15 June
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 223–226 [in part, and
                        misdated 14 March 1809]. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-06-15">June 15. 1809</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I returned from a visit to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; his bride. I
                    set off on Saturday the third after an early dinner, &amp; walked to Penrith, slept there &amp; took the mail next day to Bowes,
                    where <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert Lovell</ref> is at school, – from thence I walked on ten miles, the same
                    evening to Staindrop passing thro Bernard Castle, – a place very finely situated on the Tees. On the Monday I rose in time to walk
                    seven miles before breakfast – which meal I took at George Taylors,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Taylor
                        (1772–1851), gentleman farmer in Co. Durham, classicist and occasional contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.
                        Father of Southey’s friend, Sir Henry Taylor (1800–1886; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – whom I believe you once met at <ref target="places.html#Mirehouse">Mirehouse</ref>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Home of John Spedding (1770–1851),
                        Wordsworth’s schoolmate.</note> – a remarkably able &amp; pleasant man. From his house to Durham is thirteen miles. Just as I
                    reached the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctors</ref> house he was sallying forth in quest of me. He lives in a
                    street called by the unaccountable name of Old Elvet, – a lucky opening on the opposite side of the way leaves him a good view of
                    the Cathedral on its hill, &amp; the river is within a stones throw of his back door. Durham stands upon a peninsula, – that is to
                    say the main part of it, – a high bank, on which is the Cathedral &amp; the Castle &amp; the best houses, &amp; there are <del>the
                        most</del> delightful walks below such as no other city can boast, – thro fine old trees on the river side, from whence you
                    look to the noble building on the opposite side, &amp; see one bridge thro the other. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is well off there getting rapidly into practise &amp; living among all
                    sorts of people, Prebends &amp; Roman-Catholicks, Fox-hunters, Cock-fighters, &amp; Old women, with all of whom he seems to accord
                    equally well. There is an old lady whom they call his Mamma, because she takes such care of him, – as indeed she is bound to do,
                    for she lives by his rules, &amp; he keeps her alive on nothing but milk. It is a place where any person might live contentedly, –
                    among all these thousand &amp; one acquaintances there are some whom one might soon learn to love, <del>x</del> a great many with
                    whom <del>xxx</del> to be amused, &amp; none that are insufferable. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> seems
                    to think herself fortunate in finding so many kind-hearted persons.</p><p rend="indent1"> One day I dined with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Zouch who wrote the Life of Sir P. Sidney<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Zouch (1737–1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Sir Philip
                            Sydney</title> (1808), a work which was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809),
                        224–235.</note> – I never saw a gentler-minded man. The few sentences of bigotry which he has written must have cost him
                    strange efforts to bring forth, for I do not think a harsh expression ever could pass his lips, nor a harsh feeling ever enter his
                    heart. In spite of his deafness I contrived to have a good deal of talk <del>of</del> with him. <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> was there, the original <del>xxx</del> transplantor of that
                        <del>xxx</del> Hindoo system of teaching which Lancaster has adopted;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bell’s ‘madras’
                        system of monitorial teaching influenced the similar schemes of the Quaker school reformer Joseph Lancaster (1778–1838;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> he is a great friend of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref>, – a
                    man pleasant enough, certes a great benefactor to his country, – but a little given to flattery, &amp; knowing less about India
                    than a man ought to know who has lived there. Another day I dined with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fenwick,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr John Ralph Fenwick (d. 1855), of North Baily, Durham.</note> the ex-Physician of the place, &amp; long
                    considered as the leader of the democratic party. There we drank the Archduke Charles’s health<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the battle of Aspern-Essling (21–22 May 1809), the French attempted to cross the Danube near Vienna but
                        were driven back by Austrian forces commanded by their leader Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen (1771–1847).</note> in
                        Tokay<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tokaji wine (known as Tokay wine in nineteenth-century Britain) is produced in
                        Hungary.</note> a wine which I had never before tasted; – this is the first victory by which I ever got any thing. The Tokay
                    proved prolific. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> next door neighbour who was of the party, fancied some
                    unknown wine which had been presented to him might be the same as this, &amp; he proposed we walked home, to bring in a bottle
                    &amp; sup with us. I however recognised it for old sack,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fortified wine, often from
                        Jerez, Spain (sherry).</note> – itself no bad thing.</p><p rend="indent1"> On Monday last, after a weeks visit, I took coach to Newcastle, where I had appointd to pass a day with <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">James Losh</ref>, whom you know I have always mentioned as coming nearer the ideal of a perfect
                    man than any other person whom it has ever been my fortune I know, – so gentle, so firm; so zealous in all good things, so
                    equal-minded, so manly, so without speck or stain in his whole life. I slept at his house which is two miles from Newcastle, &amp;
                    the next day took the mail to Carlisle, – it is an interesting road, – frequently in sight of the Tyne before you reach Hexham,
                    &amp; then as frequently along the Eden. <del>xxx</del> We reached Carlisle at half-past ten. Yesterday I rose at five &amp;
                    walked to Hesket to breakfast – 14 miles, – a mile lost on the way made it 15. There was many a gentle growl within for the last
                    five miles. from thence another stage of 14 brought me home by half-after two – a good march, performed with less fatigue than any
                    other of equal length in the whole course of my pedestrian campaign.</p><p rend="indent1"> I found all well at home – God be praised. Your letter was waiting for me, &amp; one from <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, containing 16–8 for my articles in the second Quarterly,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s next review was of <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez; com as Palavras
                            Portuguezas Propriamente Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo d’Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 1 (May, 1809), 268–292.</note> with quant: suff. of praise, which I put down to the account of due desert.
                    He has <del>xxx</del> a reviewal of Holmes’s American Annals in his hands for the third number,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or, a Chronological History of America,
                            from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> in the<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319–337.</note> – I
                    am about the Polynesian Missions,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24–61.</note>
                    &amp; am to have Lord Valencias Travels as soon as they appear.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed George
                        Annesley, Viscount Valentia (1770–1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in
                            the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809),
                        88–126.</note> He requested me to chuse any subjects I pleased – I have named Barlows Columbiad,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The American writer and politician, Joel Barlow (1754–1812) whose <title>The Columbiad. A Poem</title> was
                        published in England in 1809. Southey did not review this work for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> – Eltons Hesiod<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hesiod was a Greek pastoral poet thought to have flourished between 750–650 BC. Charles
                        Abraham Elton (1778–1853; <title>DNB</title>) published <title>The Remains of Hesiod the Ascraean: Translated from the Greek
                            into English</title> in 1809. Southey did not review this work.</note> &amp; Whitakers Life of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Neots, the brother of Alfred<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Whitaker (1735–1808; <title>DNB</title>), historian
                        whose <title>The Life of St Neot, the Oldest of all the Brothers to King Alfred</title> was published posthumously in 1809.
                        Southey did not review this work for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> (the two latter conditionally that I shall not
                    review them, unless upon perusal it appears that they supply good subjects. And I have solicited the <del>xxx</del> office of
                    justifying <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> against Sir J Moores friends, being decidedly of opinion that he
                    was thoroughly in the right, &amp; the General utterly unequal to his situation.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        diplomatist <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">John Hookham Frere</ref> was sent to Spain as minister-plenipotentiary
                        to the Central Junta on 4 October 1808 and when the French marched on Madrid he urged Sir John Moore (1761–1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the Commander of the British forces in northern Spain to also advance upon Madrid, despite his
                        inclination to retreat through Portugal. After the disastrous retreat to Corunna, Frere was blamed for this advice and
                        recalled by the British government. Some of Frere’s and Moore’s correspondence was read out in the Commons on 27 April;
                        Moore’s side of matters was presented in James Moore (1763–1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of
                            the British Army in Spain, Commanded by His Excellency Sir John Moore. Authenticated by Official Papers and Original
                            Letters</title> (1809). Frere’s correspondence with Moore was published in 1810 in a work entitled <title>To the British
                            Nation is Presented by Colonel Venault de Charmilly, Knight of the Royal and Military Order of St. Louis, the Narrative of
                            his Transactions in Spain with the Rt. Hon. Hookham Frere, His Britannic Majesty’s Minister Plenipotentiary, and Lt. Gen.
                            Sir John Moore, K.B. Commander of the British Forces: with the Suppressed Correspondence of Sir J. Moore: Being a
                            Refutation of the Calumnies Invented Against Him, and Proving that He was Never Acquainted with General
                        Morla</title>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Send for <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> pamphlet,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the Convention of Cintra (signed 30 August 1808), British generals allowed a defeated French army to
                        evacuate Portugal. On 27 December 1808 and 13 January 1809 Wordsworth published, in <title>The Courier</title>, an article
                        condemning the Convention. In May 1809 Longmans published the article as a pamphlet: <title>Concerning the Relations of Great
                            Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the
                            Convention of Cintra</title>.</note> the more you read it, the higher will be your admiration. – Curwens bill<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756–1828; <title>DNB</title>), agriculturist and politician responsible
                        for Curwen’s Act, passed in 1809. The act was a significant attempt at parliamentary reform that intended to reduce the sale
                        of seats and the amount of government placemen in the House of Commons. The government’s opposition took the form of
                        suggesting modifications that watered down the bill so much that those who had supported it voted against it because it was
                        feared it would stand in the way of proper reform.</note> is worse than good-for-nothing. of this there can be but one opinion
                    among the true friends of liberty.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am almost as glad you have got Solly again as Solly himself can be, &amp; <del>will</del> forgive soft Tommy all
                    his past actions &amp; fatheadedness for letting you get him on board.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to the
                        fact that Southey’s acquaintance, William Sotheby (1757–1833; <title>DNB</title>), would be pleased that Thomas had been
                        commissioned onto HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi>, the flagship of his younger brother Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby
                        (1759–1831).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>