<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1689</idno><idno type="nines">rce2811</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 253–256 [in part]. Wilfred Partington, The Private
                            Letter-Books of Sir Walter Scott. Selections from the Abbotsford manuscripts ... Edited by Wilfred Partington
                        (London, 1930), 75–77.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1689" type="letter"><head>1689. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1809-10-02">2 October
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Ashistiel/
                        Selkirk <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Watermark: shield/ 1808/ T BOTFIELD<lb/>Endorsement: Southey/ 2 October 1809<lb/>MS:
                        National Library of Scotland, MS 3878<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 253–256 [in part]. Wilfred Partington, <title>The Private
                            Letter-Books of Sir Walter Scott. Selections from the Abbotsford manuscripts ... Edited by Wilfred Partington</title>
                        (London, 1930), 75–77.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Before I had leisure to thank you for your own letter &amp; for <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis’s</ref>
                    – &amp; for all that there is therein, a new game of Puss-catch-corner<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A child’s game in
                        which a room, or other square area with four corners, is inhabited by a player in each corner. A player in the centre is
                        nominated ‘Puss’ and while the corner players attempt to change places with each other in any direction, ‘Puss’ tries to gain
                        a corner during the exchange. If the central player succeeds in gaining a corner, the player without a corner becomes ‘Puss’
                        so that the game can begin again.</note> has been commenced at Westminster, &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> has done the most foolish thing he ever did in his life. He should have remembered that Ld Castlereagh was an
                    Irishman, &amp; that as the Union abolished the Irish Parliament, so ought the ill customs of that Parliament, duelling being one,
                    to have been abolished with it; that holding his rank &amp; station in the country it was as much a breach of decency in him to
                    accept a challenge as it would have been in an Archbishop, &amp; that he might have done more by his example towards checking a
                    mischievous <del>pr</del> &amp; absurd practise than has ever been done yet.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> George
                        Canning had held the office of Foreign Secretary in the government since 1807, but he threatened to resign several times in
                        1809 over the progress of the war with France. His disputes with Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh and 2nd Marquess of
                        Londonderry (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>) led to a plan to expel Castlereagh from the War Office, but when Castlereagh
                        discovered the plan he challenged Canning to a duel. This took place on 21 September 1809, and though both men survived, but
                        there was much public outrage over their behaviour.</note> He got much credit by replying to the Russian Manifesto,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> After his annihilation of the Prussians at Jena in October 1806, and the destruction of the
                        Russian army at Friedland in June 1807, Napoleon put pressure on both countries to discontinue trade with Britain, in line
                        with his plan to exclude British ships and commerce from continental Europe. This pressure led to public manifestos by both
                        countries in support of Napoleon’s policy. Canning, in his capacity as Foreign Secretary, replied to the Russian manifesto in
                        a state paper.</note> &amp; he would have got more by a proper reply to Castlereagh. – A single combat had some sense in it, –
                    there you relied upon your own heart &amp; hand, there was some pleasure in hewing &amp; thrusting, &amp; the bravest came off
                    best, – but as for our duels – all that has been said against villainous gunpowder holds true against them.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish to see <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref> in power because we want an
                    enterprizing minister, – one who would make the enemy feel the mighty power of Great Britain &amp; not waste our force so
                    pityfully as it has always hitherto been wasted. I wish to see him in power, because he has not &lt;been&gt; tried, &amp; all the
                    other performers upon the Westminster stage have. But I confess there is but little hope in my wishes. It appears to me that the
                    very constitution of our Cabinet necessarily produces indecision, half-measures &amp; imbecillity. it seems to me that a
                    Government so constituted is just like an army all whose operations are guided by a Council of War instead of a General. I am for
                    ministerial Dictatorships.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> has my first Chapter by this time.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed to the ‘History of Europe’ for 1808–1810 in James Ballantyne’s
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> He will think me a political Ishmaelite<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning an outcast, because in the Bible Ishmael was cast out by his father, Abraham. See Genesis
                        21:14.</note> &amp; no respector of persons. It would have been better had I had plenty of time for forethought, – &amp; for
                    arranging &amp; rearranging <del>my</del> the parts. Such as it is however it is not likely to be thought dull, &amp; tho it will
                    offend all parties in turn – yet I think its downright sincerity, manifest impartiality, &amp; right English feeling will bear it
                    thro, &amp; answer his purpose, better than any thing more cautious &amp; common-place. It must be remembered that the various
                    parties are spoken of according as they deserved at the beginning of that year, – in its progress the ministry deserve better
                    language &amp; all branches of the opposition worse, especially <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis Burdett</ref>, whose
                    utter want of sympathy <del>to</del> with the Spaniards has done him more injury in my estimation than any part of his former
                    conduct. Oh that we could but weed out the cursed spirit of party from this country, &amp; make our politicians ashamed of any
                    other denomination that that of Britons!</p><p rend="indent1"> What you say about Bruce weighs so much with me that I wish I had heard it sooner.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s renewed suspicions of the veracity of the African traveller James Bruce (1730–1794;<title>
                            DNB</title>), see Southey to Herbert Hill, 27 June 1809, Letter 1646. Southey reviewed the second edition of Bruce’s
                            <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768–73</title> (1804–1805), in the <title>Annual Review
                            for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 2–16.</note> – Your views about the Morte Arthur are wiser ones than mine, &amp; I do most
                    formally &amp; willingly resign it into your hands.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Despite his statement here, in 1817
                        Southey published an edition of Thomas Malory’s (c. 1415–1471; <title>DNB), The Birth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur: Of his
                            Noble Knyghtes of the Rounde Table, they’r Merveyllous Enquestes and Aduentures ... : and in the end, Le Morte D’Arthur,
                            with the Dolourous Deth and Departyng out of thys Worlde of them Al</title>.</note> – My intent was that the book should
                    be read, but people are not disposed to read such things generally, or the Cid<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> would not hang upon hand. Now a very limited edition is sure to find
                    purchasers, &amp; nothing need be sacrificed to ensure its success. I was not by the by aware that the book had been reformed by
                    the Godly Critics whose worthy descendants have lately set forth a Family Shakespere,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Family Shakespeare</title> was first published in 1807 by Henrietta Maria [Harriet] Bowdler (1750–1830;
                            <title>DNB</title>), writer and literary editor. It contained expurgated versions of twenty of Shakespeare’s plays,
                        primarily excising any material of a sexual or blasphemous nature. It was published anonymously, but her brother Thomas
                        Bowdler (1754–1825) was soon credited as its author and the two went on to produce more editions of the works together.</note>
                    &amp; will it is to be hoped in due time present us with an Edition Expurgata of the Bible, upon the plan proposed by Matthew
                        Lewis.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to Matthew Lewis’s (1775–1818; <title>DNB</title>) novel
                            <title>The Monk</title>, first published in 1796, in which the heroine, Antonia, is given an edited version of the Bible
                        to protect her innocence. Lewis’s implication that the Bible might be inappropriate for a young female reader was considered
                        blasphemous.</note> Oh I have a bill of indictment against those Eclectics &amp; Vice-Society-men,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The evangelical supporters of moral reform who ran the <title>Eclectic Review</title> (founded in 1805 by
                            dissenting Protestants) and the Society for the Suppression of Vice. Southey’s reviews of <title>Part the First of An Address
                            to the Public from the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the
                            Members, the Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803) appeared in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 187, and the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805),
                        225–231.</note> whenever <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will send me the needful documents, – for be it
                    known to you – that in one of the Eclectic Reviews there is a grand passage describing the <hi rend="ital">soul of Shakespeare in
                        Hell</hi>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The attack occurs in the review of ‘<title>A Complete verbal Index to the
                            Plays of Shakespeare</title>, adapted to all the Editions, comprehending every Substantive, Adjective, Verb, Participle,
                        and Adverb used by Shakspeare, with a distinct Reference to every individual Passage in which each Word occurs. By Francis
                        Twiss, Esq.’, <title>The Eclectic Review</title>, 3.1 (1807), 75–78 (77) Southey mentions it disparagingly in his review of
                        [James Sedgwick (1775–1851; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of
                            Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), 480–514 (507).</note> If I do not put some of these curst
                        Pharisees<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Members of an ancient Jewish sect who were strict observers of tradition
                        and law, the term ‘pharisee’ is often applied more generally to mean a self-righteous person.</note> into Purgatory for this,
                    for the edification of our Quarterly readers – then may my right hand forget its cunning. – <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A paraphrase of a passage from Psalm 137:5 ‘If I forget you, O Jerusalem, let my right hand forget its
                        cunning’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have not seen the last Review, which makes me suppose that <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is
                    still on his journey. Your Register will monopolize me for the next three months,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        note 3.</note> – unless I can steal time, by way of refreshing myself, for some light article. These Quarterly Reviews lose
                    much by giving up all those minor publications which served to play shuttlecock with, &amp; were put to death with a pun, or
                    served up in the sauce of their own humorous absurdity. Hence too they are less valuable as materials for the history of
                    literature. The old Annuals was the best plan, if it had not been starved by scanty pay, &amp; moreover choaked with
                        divinity.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Review</title> had closed earlier in the year, brought
                        down, in Southey’s opinion, by the tedious worthiness of the reviews of religious books commissioned by its editor <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref>, a dissenting Protestant.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My next Missionary article, when I have time to write it, will be singularly curious – it will relate to South
                        Africa,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Quarterly</title> did not publish a review by Southey of the
                        Moravians’ and London Missionary Society’s work in the Cape of Good Hope.</note> – &amp; I shall obtain from <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref> a manuscript of D’Anvilles concerning the Portugueze possessions there
                    &amp; his plan for establishing a communication by land between them<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean Baptiste
                        Bourguignon d’Anville (1697–1782), geographer and cartographer, who was appointed ‘géographe du roi’ to King Louis XV
                        (1710–1774). His manuscripts, which are housed at the Bibliothèque Nationale de France, are largely unstudied.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I want to hear that you have conceived of another poem &amp; are parturient. For myself I shall begin with Pelayo
                    the Spaniard,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early name for Southey’s poem <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title>, published in 1814.</note> as soon as I can make up my mind in what metre to write it. That of Kehama, tho
                    in rhyme, is almost as much my own as Thalaba, &amp; will I dare say excite as much censure</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1809-10-02">October 2. 1809. </date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>