<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1166</idno><idno type="nines">rce2288</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British
                        Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1166" type="letter"><head>1166. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-03-17">17 March
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb/>Endorsement: 17 Vols [MS illegible] <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>Postmark: E/ MAR 20/ 1806 <lb/>MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have been waiting for some time past in the hope of telling you the time of my departure &amp; the arrangement of
                    my operations, thinking it not impossible that we might meet. But my operations are very uncomfortably disconcerted by a request
                    on the part of <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; another friend of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> that I would go into Herefordshire &amp; myself make enquiry upon the spot what is the reason why a living
                    valued at nearly 400£ a year, does not pay its own expences.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Hill had the living
                        of a parish at Staunton-on-Wye, Herefordshire, which, while he was in Lisbon, he had left in the care of <ref target="people.html#ThomasDr">Dr Thomas</ref>, father of his business agent <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">William Bowyer Thomas</ref>, who had died in 1802. Southey intended to investigate the payment of tithes on Hill’s estate
                        for him while he was abroad.</note> Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Scott<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Scott,
                        Baron Stowell (1745–1836; <title>DNB</title>), judge and politician.</note> has given it as his opinion that there is roguery
                    in the Lawyer, – which I do not believe because <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> recommended him to me, as a man
                    whom he had been at school with, &amp; knew to be honest: he said also that some friend of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hills</ref> should go &amp; investigate there previous to any
                    farther steps. they very naturally look to me, – who am alas of all men living the least fitted for such a task – however I shall
                    go; &amp; have only proposed to them that it be on my return from London, instead of on my way there, – that I may learn when in
                    town what specific enquiries to make &amp; how to set about them. In either case I do not think it would be much out of my way to
                    call at Bristol, &amp; perhaps if it be on my return you would spare a few days to walk up the Wye with me.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barkers</ref> visit to Bath has been prevented – for which I am sorry as I wished you to
                    see both her &amp; her drawings. But if you go there about this time or some few weeks hence, you will find the Colonel &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">his wife</ref> – who will both be very glad to talk about the Lakes with you.</p><p rend="indent1"> As for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> – you know my mind about him too well to require any
                    repetition of the hopelessness with which I regard him. Carry his hat to my account – if he does not pay you – as I suppose he
                    never will. And as for his wax likeness – if it were meant for me I should consign it to the fire – but as it is for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> lay it aside – dont send it across the water</p><p rend="indent1"> We have heard <hi rend="ital">of</hi> 
                    <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, not from him. he was well at Naples in the early part of January,
                    having been forced to return there, &amp; so we are in daily expectation of hearing that he is arrived.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was returning across Europe from Malta and arrived back in Britain in August 1806.</note> I suppose
                    you have seen in the Monthly Magazine that one of his brothers children (a very fine boy) has been killed by a fall on shipboard:
                    – an accident which has very nearly killed the father.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Monthly</title>, 21.1
                        (February 1806) carried this report on p. 98: ‘On board the Phoenix, of 44 guns, in the Sound, Master Coleridge, a youth of
                        14, who had just made his naval <hi rend="ital">debut</hi> on board that ship. He was trying to go aloft, and taking hold of a
                        rope that was not fastened, he unfortunately came down by the run on the deck, and was killed on the spot. He was the son of
                        Lieutenant-Colonel Coleridge, of Ottery St. Mary’. The dead boy was Bernard Frederick Coleridge (1792–1805), the son of Lt.
                        Col. James Coleridge (1759–1836). The father’s reaction is described in Lord Coleridge, KC, <title>The Story of a Devonshire
                            House</title> (London, 1905), p. 114: ‘On December 9, 1805, he fell from the top-mast [of the ship <hi rend="ital">Phoenix</hi>] and was killed on the spot. He was then aged thirteen. …The news was carried to his home in a letter sent
                        by special messenger. His father, who was standing in the dining-room, gave a cry, and with the letter in his hand fell
                        senseless on the floor. He was carried to bed in a sort of fit, and for some weeks his reason, if not his life, was in
                        danger’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I expect to start on the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; if my Herefordshire business be delayed shall go first to
                    Norwich for a few days. Of the many persons who will be glad to see me in town I suppose poor <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has the greatest reason, as I shall <del>lend</del> give him a hearty
                        shove.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had encouraged George Burnett to produce an anthology of
                            <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Earliest Times to the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title>. It was
                        published in three volumes with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> in 1807 and formed a companion work to
                        George Ellis’s <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803) and Southey’s own
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> – <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is
                    about to be married, which will greatly improve his breakfast table. I have seen the Lady some years ago, but she was then young
                    &amp; I remember nothing of her – a daughter of Sir Foster Cunliffe.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn married Mary
                        Cunliffe (d. 1838), daughter of Foster Cunliffe, 3rd Baronet (1755–1834) on 9 April 1806.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Of the exordium to Madoc many persons I suppose think as you do, it is in fact conceit if the poem be bad,
                    confidence if it be good.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The exordium to <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published as:
                            <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Come, listen to a tale of times of old!</l><l rend="indent3"> Come, for ye know me! I am he who sung</l><l rend="indent3"> The Maid of Arc; I am he who framed</l><l rend="indent3"> Of Thalaba the wild &amp; wonderous song.</l><l rend="indent3"> Come, listen to my lay, &amp; ye shall hear</l><l rend="indent3"> How Madoc from the shores of Britain spread</l><l rend="indent3"> The adventurous sail, explored the ocean ways,</l><l rend="indent3"> And quelled Barbarian power, &amp; overthrew</l><l rend="indent3"> The bloody altars of idolatry,</l><l rend="indent3"> And planted in its fanes triumphantly</l><l rend="indent3"> The Cross of Christ. Come, listen to my lay.</l></lg> See volume 2 of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), p.
                        8.</note> I think the po[em] a good one, &amp; have no objection to say so. To omit it would be to confess that it ought not
                    to have been there. Now if I thought the poem would be improved by rewriting it half through – you know I would do it. I would
                    spend a week to weed out any real fault which a true critic could object to – but here the fault, if any there be, is in the
                    feeling – not in the expression – I do not think it faulty, &amp; stand it must. Tis an old part of the Poets privilege to be
                    allowed to praise themselves, &amp; it is almost the only one that I shall resolutely use whenever I see occasion so to do.</p><p rend="indent1"> One word more of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>. <hi rend="ital">he</hi> must certainly know
                    where <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref> is, &amp; ought to give <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith</ref> her address.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will go to Lisbon with me in the Autumn,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected visit to Portugal did not take place.</note> at least <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; I have so settled it, &amp; I have no reason to suppose but that he
                    will very gladly fall in with the plan, tho he has met your friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Auchterlony,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> &amp; likes him much.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am afraid I shall hardly have done with your Books yet. There is the long passage about the Lakes to be extracted
                    from your Aunt,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers’s aunt was the traveller Celia Fiennes (1662–1741;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Danvers gave Southey a manuscript of her diary, excerpts of which were included in his and
                        Coleridge’s <title>Omniana</title> (1812).</note> – &amp; nobody can make it for me, on account of the writing. Pray
                        <del>xxx</del> is the old traveller <hi rend="ital">Fynes Moryson</hi><note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fynes Moryson
                        (1565/6–1630), traveller and writer.</note> of the same family?</p><p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> has symptoms of angina pectoris, but they are
                    accompanied with other symptoms not described in the Scotch Cyclopædia,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Encyclopedia Britannica</title>, first published in Edinburgh 1768–1771.</note> which gives me some hope. I think
                    of sending the case to <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>, as soon as <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmundson</ref> will give it me. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> took <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Hartley</ref> in hand while he was here, &amp; I have gone on with him ever since.
                    I am sorry he is not satisfied with <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lambs</ref> taste which is infinitely better than his
                    own. <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> is a man whom I could trust to select for me – which is more than I could
                    poor <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> I will write &amp; tell you of my movements. if I come to Bristol perhaps <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> can give me a bed – I cannot stay more than three days – one with you one with him – &amp; one for the sake of old
                    times I cannot but give to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> – </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-03-17">March 17. 1806.</date></p><p>frost &amp; snow! the bitterest weather we have had this winter.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>