<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1597</idno><idno type="nines">rce2719</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland,
                        MS 3878.  Previously  published: W. Partington, Sir Walter’s Post-Bag (1932), 46 [in part]; Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 501–502.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1597" type="letter"><head>1597. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1809-03-11">11 March
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: J BUDGEN/ 1805<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland,
                        MS 3878<lb/>Previously published: W. Partington, <title>Sir Walter’s Post-Bag</title> (1932), 46 [in part]; Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 501–502.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I waited till the Carriers day thinking to have told you Lord Somers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                        1809 Scott published the first volume of Baron John Somers (1651–1716; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Scarce and
                            Valuable Tracts on the Most Interesting and Entertaining Subjects but Chiefly Such as Relate to the History and
                            Constitution of These Kingdoms, Selected from an Infinite Number in Print and Manuscript in the Royal Libraries</title>
                        (1809–1815).</note> was arrived when I thanked you for it – but he has disappointed me, I will not however delay longer to
                    answer your question respecting the selections. From <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> you could not I
                    think have chosen better among his pieces of suitable length.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott was selecting poems
                        for the anthology <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with some
                            Original Pieces hitherto unpublished</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 1810). Wordsworth’s ‘Tintern Abbey’ appeared on II, pp.
                        256–264.</note> From my own smaller poems I would rather trust your choice than my own.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott chose ‘Queen Urraca and the Five Martyrs of Morocco’ (<title>English Minstrelsy</title>, I, pp. 265–280).</note> I
                    have nothing by me which could possibly suit your purpose, – unless perhaps an extract from Kehama may be thought sufficiently
                    entire; – it is very short, &amp; I am disposed to strike it out of the poem, because tho most people would be likely to think it
                    the prettiest thing there, – it does not seem to me sufficiently in keeping.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The extract
                        from <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (London, 1810), Book 10, lines 150–171, was published as ‘Love’ in <title>English
                            Minstrelsy</title>, II, pp. 236–237.</note> Such as it is you have it on the other leaf – but do not use it unless you
                    think it suitable.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly is a little too much in the temper of the Edinburgh to please me.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, which the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was set up to rival in
                        1809.</note> No man dips his pen deeper in the very gall of bitterness than I can do – witness the Reviewals in the Annual of
                    Malthus, of the Methodists – of the Suppression-Society, &amp; of Moores Poems,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804): <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the
                            Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility
                            and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 187; William Myles (1756–1828),
                            <title>A Chronological History of the People called Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists of the Itinerant
                            Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803), 201–213; Thomas Malthus (1766–1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future Improvement of Society; with
                            Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), 292–301. In the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805) Southey reviewed <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for
                            the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity
                            of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 225–231. In the <title>Annual Review for
                            1806</title>, 5 (1807), he reviewed Thomas Moore (1779–1852; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epistles, Odes and Other
                            Poems</title> (1806), 498–499.</note> – but I do not like to see scorn &amp; indignation wasted on trivial objects, – they
                    should be reserved like the arrows of Hercules for occasions worthy of such weapons. I recognise you with great pleasure in Burns,
                    in Swift, &amp; I think, by that parallel with Scotland in the days of Edward<del>s</del> I – in the Spanish Article.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809): Robert Hartley Cromek
                        (1770–1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques of Robert Burns, Consisting Chiefly of Original Letters, Poems, and Critical
                            Observations on Scottish Songs</title> (1808), 19–36; John Barrett (1753/4–1821), <title>An Essay on the Earlier Part of
                            the Life of Swift, by the Rev. John Barrett, D. D. and Vice Provost of Trinity College, Dublin. To which are Subjoined
                            Various Pieces Ascribed to Swift, Two of his Original Letters, and Extracts from his Remarks on Bishop Burnett’s
                            History</title> (1808), 162–177; Scott did not write ‘the Spanish Article’; a review by <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis</ref> [with <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>] of
                            <title>Exposé des Manoeuvres et des Intrigues qui ont Préparé l’Usurpation de la Couronne d’Espagne, et des Moyens
                            Employés par l’Empereur des Francais pour la Mettre á Exécution…; Traduit de l’Espagnol par M. Peltier</title>
                        [alternative title <title>Affaires d’Espagne</title>] (1808) and Pedro Cevallos Guerra (1760–1840), <title>Conféderation des
                            Royaumes et Provinces d’Espagne Contre Buonaparte</title> ([1810]) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February
                        1809), 1–19.</note> So also in Sir John Carr, – an article in the best spirit of raillery.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott [and <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref>] reviewed Sir John Carr (1772–1832;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Caledonian Sketches, or a Tour through Scotland in 1807</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly
                                Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 178–193. Scott also had a hand in William Erskine’s (Lord Kinneder; bap. 1768–1822; <title>DNB</title>),
                        review of John Philpot Curran (1750–1817), <title>Speeches of the Right Honourable John Philpot Curran, Master of the Rolls in
                            Ireland, on the late very Interesting State Trials</title> (1808), 96–107.</note> It is a pity that any doubt was
                    intimated of the Cids conquest of Valencia.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Valencia was conquered in 1094 after a long
                        siege. The events are described in Southey’s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (London, 1808), p. 203. Scott had doubted
                        that the events had really occurred in his review of Southey’s <title>Cid</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809), 117–134.</note> No fact in history is better ascertained. I thought no more of bringing authorities to
                    confirm it, than I did for the succession of Kings.</p><p rend="indent1"> This diversion in the North<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diversion in the north involved fighting
                        between Russia and Sweden, which forced the latter to join Napoleon’s continental system for refusing trade with Britain, and
                        the Poles’ (also allies of France) successful defence of their country against the Austrians. Napoleon would attack Austria
                        himself later in 1809, and was kept from fighting in Spain by this.</note> affords a grand opportunity for striking a blow in
                    Spain, if our Ministry have leisure for any thing better than their pettyfogging defence of the D of York.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of
                        the army. He held the post from 1798–1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by
                        allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776–1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for
                        which promotion was arranged.</note> Austria will probably fall, – an event no otherwise to be deplored than for the immediate
                    triumph &amp; temporary aggrandizement <del>will</del> &lt;which&gt; it will afford to France, – but in that country, as &lt;it
                    was&gt; in Spain no good can arise till the spirit of Freedom is restored; &amp; the immediate restoration of Spain will
                        <del>far</del> infinitely outweigh<del>x</del> the fall of Austria. Had we Lord Chatham<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham (1708–1778; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister renowned for his successful
                        conduct of war policy in the Seven Years’ War.</note> alive again, King Joseph<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Joseph-Napoléon Bonaparte (1768–1844) was the elder brother of Napoleon Bonaparte who made him King of Spain as Joseph I in
                        1808.</note> would be our prisoner by the time his brother is at Vienna, – but I fear we shall have one more great occasion
                    lost to add to the long history of our misconduct.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> are bold speculators, &amp; their list seems to
                    prove them judicious ones. I am inclined to think that a Review of old Books conducted like the Quarterly would answer, – for if
                    the Censura Literaria<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Censura Literaria: Containing Titles, Abstracts, and Opinions of Old English Books, with Original Disquisitions,
                            Articles of Biography, and other Literary Antiquities</title> (1805–1809), ed. Samuel Egerton Brydges, (1762–1837;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> can pay its expences, a good publication of the same kind must needs do more. This is worth
                    mentioning to them. – I could be a very efficient assistant to such a work. </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Let me be remembered to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                            Scott</ref> – &amp; believe me</salute><salute rend="indent2"> very truly yours</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-03-11">March 11. 1809.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>