<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1038</idno><idno type="nines">rce2160</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1038" type="letter"><head>1038. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1805-02-18">[started before
                        and continued on] 18 February 1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers/ Bristol./ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] E/ FEB21<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Get for me the story of the Devil &amp; that poor girl who died at the brothel by the Infirmary <del>with</del> as
                    minutely as you can,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This story has not been traced.</note> – <del>xxx xxxxx xxxxx xxxxxx
                        xxxxxx xxx xxx xxxxxxxx xxxx xxx xxxxx xxxxxxx xxxxxxxxxx xxxxx xxxxx xxxxxxxxxxx</del> you will recollect what I mean. it
                    happened while we were abroad &amp; Biddulph<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bristol evangelical, Thomas Biddulph
                        (1763–1838; <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>Short Sermons by the R. John Biddulph</title> went through many editions.</note>
                    was a good deal concerned in it.</p><p rend="indent1"> This memorandum was made some days ago just as the recollection occurred. I have since been very unpleasantly
                    interrupted – having found it right to go over to poor <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">his sister</ref>, who are almost heart-broken by the loss of their favourite brother in
                    the Abergavenny.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wordsworth (1772–1805), captain of the East Indiaman, the
                            <title>Earl of Abergavenny</title>, went down with his ship on the Shambles rocks off Portland Bill, on 5 February
                        1805.</note> I came back on Friday &amp; am going again on Wednesday. Meantime I have uneasiness enough of my own. some
                    symptoms in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref> have alarmed us. as you may suppose we are soon alarmed –
                    &amp; I hope in time. <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Our apothecary</ref> is a skilful one, &amp; is doing precisely what I
                    should have done upon my own knowledge – he has lanced the gums, blistered behind both ears, &amp; given calomel.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The common name for mercury chloride, which was taken for various ailments.</note> this was done
                    yesterday, &amp; to day there seems nothing to excite apprehension, except her usual <hi rend="ital">unusual</hi> spirits when in
                    health, a sort of premature intelligence &amp; excitability which has always made me anxious. What terrified us was that she had
                    for two or three days hung down her head when in the open air, – which to day has not been the case: but there has been no fever,
                    &amp; we can hardly say any costiveness, certainly nothing habitual. We mean to keep <del>xxx xxx</del> up a discharge at the
                    ears, (which is also expedient because her eyes are subject to frequent weaknesses &amp; inflammations of the upper lids) &amp; to
                    administer calomel every other day. if any fever appears to give digitalis, – &amp; if any heaviness of the head manifest itself –
                    to blister it, so that if the disease be preventable, no effort to prevent it will have been omitted. tell King this that we may
                    have his opinion. She is just getting her two first upper teeth, which we believe are thro, about ten weeks after the two under
                    ones. for her age she is a large child &amp; unusually forward; standing great part of her time alone, &amp; beginning to
                        <del>spe</del> talk, tho not yet full ten months. There is no bad symptom in her eyes; &amp; she has never seemed heavy within
                    doors, only been very irritable instead of very good natured which is her disposition. she discovers no uneasiness at having her
                    head washed or handled. Indeed if it had not been for that ruinous drooping, &amp; for starting at times – I should not have had
                    any cause for alarm. As you may suppose this hangs upon me – &amp; bears my spirits down, tho I shall not cease to exert &amp; to
                    employ myself.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard again from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. during the month he had then been aboard
                    they had buried sixty! – &amp; were then lying in harbour for want of hands. he was well, &amp; wrote in better spirits than you
                    or I should be in in such circumstances.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had been made lieutenant of HMS
                            <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> (a 38-gun Hébé-class frigate of the French navy captured in 1796 and then commissioned into
                        the navy) whose crew had been hit by yellow fever. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> We have heard <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>. he is confidential Secretary to Sir
                    Alexander Ball,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander John Ball, 1st Baronet (1757–1809; <title>DNB</title>): Rear
                        Admiral who directed the blockade of Malta (1798–1800). Coleridge wrote a biography of Ball in <title>The Friend</title>
                        (1809–1810). See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II,
                        pp. 252–256, 287–294, 347–356, 359–369.</note> with a good salary &amp; apartment in the palace – &amp; has undertaken to go
                    into Greece &amp; up the Black Sea with Captain Leake,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain William Martin Leake
                        (1777–1860) of the Royal Artillery, explored and mapped Greece and the Levant. A collector of Greek coins, he befriended Byron
                        and became Britain’s negotiator with Muhammad Ali Pasha al-Mas’ud ibn Agha (1769–1849) during the Napoleonic invasion of the
                        Ottoman empire.</note> to purchase corn for government! his health is much better, indeed if he would but think fit to be
                    contented I think he would be well. – <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> goes on the same odd creature
                    as was. a visitor the other day was whispering in his presence to his friend <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilson</ref> – M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hall<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> – said he –
                    I must tell you that there’s one fault of mine, which I never shall mend; – indeed I never can mend it, nor I never will, nor
                    nobody can ever make me; &amp; that is that whenever &lt;I hear any thing or see&gt; any thing <del>xxx</del> going on, I never
                    can rest till I have got at the bottom of it; &amp; I do’nt suppose I ever shall as long as I live.</p><p rend="indent1"> No news of the wine.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had ordered wine from the firm of Danvers and
                        White (first name and date unknown).</note> – It cannot be long before Madoc will be published. believe me that I lose as much
                    pleasure in sending it you, as you yourself: – indeed the greatest which I should have derived from its publication. Two years ago
                    I never thought of the poem without thinking of your excellent mother &amp; looking on to the pleasure she would take in seeing it
                    thro all its stages. –</p><p rend="indent1"> I have all the sheets here, &amp; the vignettes, &amp; now my enjoyments are well nigh over. there is only one more
                    which is sight of the compleat volume. when that has arrived &amp; been cut open, as the book will then cease to be peculiarly my
                    own, &amp; is any bodys who chuses to purchase it, there is an end to half the pleasure or nine tenths, that it can ever afford
                    me.</p><p rend="indent1"> My history is now getting on.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘History of Portugal’, which was
                        never completed.</note> this unhappy <del>affair</del> &lt;loss&gt; of John Wordsworth will delay it, &amp; my own uneasiness
                    will make me work uncomfortably. however a very few months will decide upon these hopes &amp; fears, &amp; I am prepared for the
                    worst as a thing which I have always had in contemplation. A hundred years &lt;hence&gt; it will matter little what my joys &amp;
                    sorrows may have been, &amp; they who read my life will then be perfectly indifferent whether it be said that I reared my children
                    or lost them. And as I know assuredly that the loss is only for a time, the moment the evil is over it begins to mature itself as
                    a source of consolation &amp; hope.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> goes on as usual. I hear from him often, &amp; he franks half my town
                        letters down. – remember me to Hort.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764–1849), Unitarian
                            minister and writer. He was one of many acquaintances who stored books for Southey.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><date when="1805-02-18"> Monday Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 18. 1805.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>