<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                
                <title level="a">Version B of <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>: The Kenyon Transcript (1819)</title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Dorothy Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Paul Westover</editor> 
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.SP-B</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        
                        <title level="a" type="main">Version B of <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>: The Kenyon Transcript (1819)</title>
                        <ptr target="editions.2022.DW.SP-B.html"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND CHANGE THE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-10-01</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">         
                <head>Version B of  &#8220;Scawfell Excursion&#8221;: The Kenyon Transcript (1819)<lb/>
                <hi rend="small">Edited by Paul Westover</hi></head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Paul Westover</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Brigham Young University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
            <div type="paratext">          
                    <list type="unordered">                         
                        <item><ref target="#Editors_Note">Editor&#8217;s Note</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="#Transcription">Transcription</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="#Appendix">Appendix: Ongoing Research on the Kenyon Transcript</ref></item>
                    </list>
               
                <div type="section">               
                    <p><anchor xml:id="Editors_Note"/><hi rend="bold">[Editor&#8217;s note:</hi>
                    The Kenyon Transcript reproduces, in an attractive but unknown hand, most of the letter Dorothy Wordsworth wrote for William Johnson
                    in late 1818. It is itself a letter, sent to &#8220;Miss Hutchinson&#8221; (probably Sara) in January 1819.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Note that the Kenyon Transcript is probably the later of the two
                    surviving manuscripts, as the DCMS 51 copy likely would have been made in November or at latest December 1818, before the original
                    Johnson letter was posted.</note> Though it omits introductory material that occupies more than a page in Dorothy’s own copy (DCMS 51);
                    it also supplies roughly 300 words missing from DCMS 51 because of a tear in that manuscript&#8217;s last page. The Kenyon Transcript differs 
                    from DCMS 51 in punctuation, orthography, and other details.<note place="foot" resp="editors">In many cases it is difficult to tell 
                    whether the scribe intends a lowercase or uppercase letter. Like all transcriptions, this one requires educated guesswork, 
                    notwithstanding the general clarity and attractiveness of the handwriting.</note> Certain spelling variations (e.g., &#8220;Seathwate,&#8221; 
                    &#8220;Scar Fell&#8221;) may be hearing errors rather than transcription errors; possibly the scribe worked from dictation. For particulars on
                    this document, reasons for calling it the &#8220;Kenyon Transcript,&#8221; and ongoing research concerning it, please see the section <ref 
                    target="#Appendix">appendix</ref>.</p>
               </div>                
           </div>
                
               <lb/><milestone unit="paratext"/><lb/>
             
             <div type="section">
                 
            <head><anchor xml:id="Transcription"/>Kenyon Transcript, 6 total pages</head>
                 
            <p>[in pencil and in a different hand:<lb/>
            101<hi rend="indent1">  J. ? Dorothy Wordsworth]</hi>
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">This seems to be a label added by a later collector, editor, or conservator. Perhaps &#8220;J.&#8221; signifies 
                &#8220;Journal&#8221;?</note><lb/>
                <hi rend="indent2">October, 1818.</hi><lb/></p>
                
            <p>&#8220;I must inform you of a feat that Miss Barker and I performed<lb/>
            on Wednesday the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this Month - I remained in Borrowdale after<lb/>
            Sir G. and Lady Beaumont and the Wilberforces were gone and<lb/>
            Miss Barker proposed to me that the next Day she and I should<lb/>
            go to Seathwate,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">The usual spelling is &#8220;Seathwaite,&#8221; and the mistake suggests that the scribe may be unfamiliar 
                     with the place name and working from dictation.</note>
                beyond the Black lead mines at the head of<lb/>
            Borrowdale and thence up a mountain called at the top<lb/>
            <hi rend="underline">Ash Course</hi> &#8211; which we suppose may be a corruption<lb/>
            of Esk Hawes, as it is a settling between the mountains, over which<lb/>
            the people of Eskdale are accustomed to pass in going to Borrowdale,<lb/>
            and such settlings are generally called by the name of the Hawes<lb/>
            as Grisdale Hawes, Buttersmere
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly &#8220;Bullersmere.&#8221; In either case, this is a scribal error for
                &#8220;Buttermere.&#8221; In general, it seems that the scribe was not especially familiar with Lake District place names.</note>
                Hawes from the German word<lb/>
            Hals (the neck) &#8211; At the top of Ash Course &#8211; Miss Barker had<lb/>
            promised me that I should see a most magnificent prospect;<lb/>
            but we had some miles to travel to the foot of the mountain,<lb/>
            and accordingly we went thither in a Cart &#8211; Miss Barber,
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Another scribal error, as here and eight lines later &#8220;Barber&#8221; should read &#8220;Barker.&#8221;</note>
                her<lb/>
            maid and myself &#8211; we departed before nine oClock &#8211; The Sun<lb/>
            shone the sky was clear and blue, and light and shade fell in<lb/>
            huge masses upon the mountains, &#8211; the fields below <hi rend="underline">glittered</hi><lb/>
            with the dew where the beams of the Sun could reach them -<lb/>
            and every little stream tumbling down the hills seemed to add<lb/>
            to the chearfulness of the scene. &#8211; We left our Cart at<lb/>
            Stonethwaite,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">This mistake for &#8220;Seathwaite&#8221; presumably occurred in the original letter. DCMS 51 has 
                    &#8220;Stonethwaite&#8221; canceled and replaced with &#8220;Seathwaite.&#8221;</note>
                and proceeded with a man to carry our<lb/>
            provisions, and a kind neighbor of Miss Barbers, a states-<lb/>
            man and Shepherd of the Vale, as our Companion &amp; Guide. -<lb/>
            We found ourselves at the top of Ash Course, without a weary<lb/>
            limb, having had the fresh Air of Autumn to help us up by its<lb/>
            invigorating effects, and the sweet Warmth of the unclouded<lb/>
            sun to tempt us to sit and rest by the way. &#8211; From the top<lb/>
            of Ash Course, I beheld a prospect which would indeed have<lb/>
            amply repaid Me for a <hi rend="underline">toilsome</hi> journey, if such it had been;<lb/>
            and a sense of gratitude for the continuance of that <span change="brown">[end p 1. / 1r]</span>
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Here and elsewhere, we use conventional notation for <hi rend="italic">recto</hi> (the front or face of a sheet
                    of paper, or the right-hand page of an open book) and <hi rend="italic">verso</hi> (the underside of the sheet, paper, or the left-hand page of 
                    an open book). Thus, &#8220;1r&#8221; means &#8220;1 recto,&#8221; &#8220;2v&#8221; means &#8220;2 verso,&#8221; and so on.</note><lb/>
            </p> 
                 
           <p>vigour of body which enabled me to climb the high mountain<lb/>
            as in the days of my youth, inspiring me with fresh chearfulness<lb/>
            added a delight &#8211; a charm to the contemplation of the magnificent<lb/>
            views before me which I cannot describe &#8211; Still less can I tell<lb/>
            you the glories of what we saw. &#8211; Three Views each distinct<lb/>
            in its kind, we saw at once &#8211; the Vale of Borrowdale &#8211; of<lb/>
            Keswick, of Bassenthwaite, of Skiddow, of Saddleback, Helvellyn,<lb/>
            numerous other mountains &#8211; and still beyond &#8211; the Solway<lb/>
            Frith and the Mountains of Scotland &#8211; Nearer to us on the<lb/>
            otherside and below us, were the Langdale Pikes &#8211; their own<lb/>
            Vale below them, Windermere, and far beyond after a long<lb/>
            Long distance &#8211; We saw Ingleborough in Yorkshire &#8211; But how<lb/>
            shall I speak of the peculiar deliciousness of the third Prospect!<lb/>
            At this time that was most favoured by Sun shine and shade -<lb/>
            The green Vale of Esk &#8211; deep and green, with its glittering serpent<lb/>
            stream was below us, and on we looked to the mountains near<lb/>
            the Sea &#8211; Black Comb, and others and still beyond to the Sea itself<lb/>
            in dazzling brightness. &#8211; At this same Station making what may<lb/>
            be called a 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Division, turning round, we saw the mountains<lb/>
            of Wasdale in tumult, &amp; Great Gavel though the middle of the<lb/>
            mountain was to us as its base, looked very grand &#8211; We had<lb/>
            attained the object of our journey; but our ambition mounted<lb/>
            higher &#8211; We saw the summit of Scar Fell,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">This spelling gives us a hint at pronunciation (compare &#8220;Scawfell,&#8221; &#8220;Sca Fell&#8221;) 
                    and gives yet another indication that the scribe may be working from dictation.</note>
                as it seemed, very<lb/>
            near to us &#8211; We were indeed three parts up that mountain &amp; thither<lb/>
            we determined to go, we found the distance greater than it had<lb/>
            appeared to us, but our Courage did not fail; however, when<lb/>
            we came nearer we perceived that in order to attain that<lb/>
            summit which had invited us forward &#8211; we must make<lb/>
            a great dip, and that the ascent afterwards would be<lb/>
            exceedingly steep and difficult, so that we might have been<lb/>
            benighted if we had attempted it, therefore unwillingly we gave<lb/>
            it up, and resolved, instead, to ascend another pike of the<lb/>
            same mountain, called the pikes and which I have since <span change="brown">[end p. 2 / 2v]</span><lb/>
           </p>                 
                
           <p>found the measurers of the mountains estimate as higher than the<lb/>
            larger summit which bears the name of Scaw Fell, and where<lb/>
            the man is built, which we at the time considered as the point<lb/>
            of highest honour. &#8211; The Sun had never once been overshadowed<lb/>
            by a Cloud during the whole of our progress from the Center of<lb/>
            Borrowdale; at the summit of the pike there was not a breath<lb/>
            of air to stir even the papers which we spread out containing<lb/>
            our food &#8211; There we ate our dinner in summer warmth &#8211; and<lb/>
            the stillness seemed to be not of this world &#8211; We paused &amp; kept<lb/>
            silence to listen and not a sound of any kind was to be heard<lb/>
            &#8211; We were far out of the reach of the Cataracts of Scaw Fell, &amp; not an<lb/>
            Insect was there to hum in the Air &#8211; The Vales which I have<lb/>
            before described lay in view; &#8211; &amp;, side by side with Eskdale,<lb/>
            we now saw the sister Vale of Donnerdale terminated by the Duddon<lb/>
            Sands - but the Majesty of the mountains below us and close to us<lb/>
            is not to be conceived &#8211; We now saw the whole mass of Great Gavel<lb/>
            from its base &#8211; the den of Wasdale, at our feet &#8211; the Gulph im-<lb/>
            -measurable &#8211; Grassmere and the other mountains of Crummock<lb/>
            &#8211;Ennerdale and its mountains &#8211; and the Sea beyond. &#8211; While we<lb/>
            were looking round after dinner our Guide said to us that we<lb/>
            must not linger long for we should have a storm &#8211; We looked<lb/>
            in vain to espy the traces of it &#8211; for mountains, Vales, and Sea were<lb/>
            all touched with the clear light of the Sun &#8211; &#8220;It is there,&#8221; &#8211; he said,<lb/>
            pointing to the Sea beyond Whitehaven, and, sure enough, we there<lb/>
            perceived a little Cloud or Mist, unnoticeable, but by a Shepherd<lb/>
            accustomed to watch all mountain bodings &#8211; We gazed all round<lb/>
            again, and yet again, fearful to lose the remembrance of what lay<lb/>
            before us in that lofty solitude, and then prepared to depart &#8211; Mean<lb/>
            -while the Air changed to cold, and we saw that tiny Vapour<lb/>
            swelled into mighty Masses of Cloud which came boiling over<lb/>
            the Mountains &#8211; Great Gavel, Helvellyn &amp; Skiddew
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">This is an error for &#8220;Skiddaw,&#8221; a name that the scribe never seems to spell the same way twice. Compare
                    &#8220;Skidda&#8221; and &#8220;Sladdow&#8221; later on in the manuscript.</note> 
                were wrapped<lb/>
            in Storm; yet Langdale and the mountains in that quarter<lb/>
            were all bright with Sun shine &#8211; Soon the Storm reached us &#8211;<lb/>
            We sheltered under a Crag, and almost as rapidly as it had <span change="brown">[end p.3 / 2r]</span><lb/>           
            </p>
                
            <p>come, it passed away; and left us free to observe, the goings on of<lb/>
            storm and sunshine in other quarters
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">&#8220;Quarters&#8221; may be capitalized.</note>
                    &#8211; Langdale had now its<lb/>
            share, and the Pikes were decorated by two splendid Rainbows<lb/>
            &#8211; Skidda also had its Rainbows; but we were truly glad to see<lb/>
            them and the clouds disappear from that mountain, as we knew<lb/>
            that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilberforce and all their family (if they kept the intention<lb/>
            which they had formed when we parted the Night before) must certainly<lb/>
            be on Skaddow
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">This may read &#8220;Sladdow&#8221;; either way, the scribe intends &#8220;Skiddaw.&#8221; See n10.</note>
                    at that very time, &#8211; and so it was &#8211; They were there<lb/>
            and had much more rain than we had &#8211; We indeed were hardly<lb/>
            at all wetted, and before we found ourselves again upon that part of<lb/>
            the mountain called Ash Course every Cloud had vanished from<lb/>
            every summit &#8211; Do not think we here gave up our Spirit<lb/>
            of Enterprize &#8211; No! I had heard much of the Grandeur of the Pass<lb/>
            of the Stye from Borrowdale to Wasdale, &amp; of the Grandeur of the<lb/>
            view of Wasdale from Stye head the point from which Wasdale<lb/>
            is first seen in coming by the road from Borrowdale but though<lb/>
            I had been in Wa<del rend="strike">r</del>sdale I had never entered the Dale by that road,<lb/>
            and had often lamented that I had not seen what was so much<lb/>
            talked of by Travellers. &#8211; Down to that Pass then (for we were<lb/>
            yet far above it) we bent our course by the side of Ruddle Gill<lb/>
            a very deep red chasm in the mountain, which begins at a<lb/>
            spring &#8211; that spring forms a stream which must at times be<lb/>
            a mighty Torrent, as is evident from the Channel which it has<lb/>
            wrought out thence by sprinkling Tarn to Stye-head and<lb/>
            there we sat and looked down into Wasdale. &#8211; We were now<lb/>
            upon Great Gavel, which rose high above us &#8211; opposite was<lb/>
            Scaw fell, and we heard the roaring of the stream from one of<lb/>
            the ravines of that mountain, which though the bending of Wasdale<lb/>
            head lay between us and Scaw Fell, we could look into, as it<lb/>
            were, and the depth of the ravine appeared tremendous &#8211; it<lb/>
            was black, and the Crags were awful &#8211; We now proceeded<lb/>
            homewards by Stye head Tarn along the road into Borrowdale<lb/>
            Before we reached Stonethwaite a few Stars had appeared,<lb/>
            and we travelled home in our cart by moonlight. I ought&#8221;<lb/>
            <hi rend="indent9">to <span change="brown">[end p. 4 / 2v]</span></hi><lb/>             
            </p>              
                
            <p>&#8220;to have described the last part of our ascent to Scaw Fell Pike &#8211; There<lb/>
            not a Blade of Grass was to be seen &#8211; hardly a cushion of Moss, and<lb/>
            that was parched and brown and only growing rarely between the<lb/>
            huge blocks and stones which cover&#8217;d the summit &amp; lie in heaps<lb/>
            all round to a great distance &#8211; like Skeletons or bones of the Earth<lb/>
            not wanted at the Creation and there left to be covered by never<lb/>
            -dying lichens, which the Clouds and dews nourish and adorn<lb/>
            with Colours of the most varied and exquisite beau[ty]
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">As marked by brackets, parts of this word and various others on this page are missing because of 
                    small holes in the manuscript.</note> 
                and endless<lb/>
            in variety &#8211; No gems or flowers can surpass in colouring the beauty<lb/>
            of some of the masses of stone, which no human eye beholds,<lb/>
            except the Shepherd or Traveller is led thither by curiosity &#8211;<lb/>
            and how seldom must this happen! &#8211; The other eminence is<lb/>
            [that] which is visited by the adventurous Traveller; &#8211; and<lb/>
            [the Shep]herd has no temptation to go thither in quest of his
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">The ends of this line and the next are slightly obscured by sealing wax.</note><lb/>
            sheep; for on the Pike there is no food to tempt them. &#8211; [We]<lb/>
            certainly were singularly fortunate in the day; for when we<lb/>
            were seated on the summit, our Guide, turning his eyes<lb/>
            thoughtfully round said to us &#8220;I do not know that in my<lb/>
            whole life I was ever at any season of the Year so high<lb/>
            upon the mountains on so calm a day&#8221; &#8211; Afterwards, you<lb/>
            know we had the Storm which exhibited to us the grandeur<lb/>
            of earth and heaven commingled yet without terror &#8211; for we<lb/>
            knew that the Storm would pass away; for so our prophetic<lb/>
            Guide assured us - I forgot to tell you that I [esp]ied a Ship<lb/>
            upon the glittering Sea while we were looking over Eskdale &#8211;<lb/>
            &#8211; &#8220;Is it a Ship?&#8221; replied the Guide &#8211; &#8220;Yes it can be nothing else<lb/>
            dont
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Missed apostrophes (as in &#8220;don&#8217;t&#8221;), uncrossed <hi rend="italic">t&#8217;</hi>s, and the like are among
                    the indications that the scribe was writing quickly without pausing to review. See also &#8220;Miss Barbers&#8221; earlier in the text.</note> 
                you see the shape of it? &#8211; Miss Barker interposed &#8211; &#8220;It<lb/>
            is a Ship, of that I am certain &#8211; I cannot be mistaken, I am<lb/>
            so accustomed to the appearance of Ships at Sea &#8211;&#8221; The Guide<lb/>
            dropped the argument; but a minute was scarcely gone<lb/>
            when he quietly said &#8211; &#8220;Now look at your Ship, it is now<lb/>
            a horse&#8221; &#8211; So indeed it was, with a gallant neck and head<lb/>
            &#8211; We laughed heartily, and I hope when I am again<lb/>
            <hi rend="indent6">inclined <span change="brown">[end p. 5 / 3r]</span></hi><lb/>               
            </p>
                
            <p>inclined to positiveness I may remember the Ship and the<lb/>
            horse upon the glittering sea; and the calm confidence, yet<lb/>
            submission of our wise Man of the Mountains; who certainly<lb/>
            had more knowledge of <hi rend="underline">Clouds</hi> than we, whatever might be<lb/>
            our knowledge of <hi rend="underline">Ships</hi>. &#8211; To add to our uncommon performances<lb/>
            on this Day Miss Barker and I each wrote a letter from the top<lb/>
            of the Pike to our far distant Friend in South Wales &#8211; Sara Hutchinson<lb/>              
            </p>
                 
            <p><span change="brown">[Source and destination addresses written sideways in middle block of page]</span></p>                              
              
            <p>Ellesmere January three 1819</p>               
                
            <p>Miss Hutchinson<lb/>
            [free?]<hi rend="indent1">Hindwell</hi><lb/>
            Kenyon <hi rend="indent1">Radnor</hi>
                   <note place="foot" resp="editors">Miss Hutchinson, we assume, is SH, sister-in-law to WW. Hindwell is five miles from Presteigne, 
                    former county town of Radnorshire, Wales. The Grade 2–listed Georgian farmhouse, once home to the Hutchinsons, still stands, now
                    a luxury <ref target="http://hindwellfarm.co.uk/the-history-of-hindwell/">bed and breakfast</ref>. 
                    <p>In <title level="m">Prose, 2,</title> Owen and Smyser opine that the most difficult part of the address panel reads &#8220;per
                    Kenyon&#8221;&#8212;an equally reasonable guess, as the first word is nearly illegible (<title level="m">Prose</title>, 2:361).
                    We favor &#8220;free Kenyon,&#8221; but the conclusion must be the same: the letter goes to Miss Hutchinson at Hindwell under 
                    Lord Kenyon&#8217;s franking privilege. Owen and Smyser describe the document this way: &#8220;Unsigned in an unidentified hand, all
                    of it is enclosed in quotation marks; on a page reserved for it, there appears in a second unidentified hand the [address]
                    superscription&#8221; (361). We are pleased in our edition to identify at least one of the unidentified hands&#8212;Kenyon&#8217;s own.</p></note>        
                </p>
                
            <p>I believe that you are not much acquainted with the<lb/>
            Scenery of this Country, except in the Neighbourhood of Grasmere,<lb/>
            your duties when you were a resident here, having confined<lb/>
            you so much to that one Vale; I hope, however, that my long<lb/>
            Story will not be very dull; and, even I am not without<lb/>
            a further hope, that it may awaken in you a desire to<lb/>
            spend a long holiday among the mountains, and explore<lb/>
            their recesses. &#8211;&#8221;<lb/>
            <span change="brown">[end p. 6 / 3v]</span></p>
         
            </div>
                
                <lb/><milestone unit="section"/><lb/>                
                               
            <div type="section">
                <head><anchor xml:id="Appendix"/>Appendix: Ongoing Research on the Kenyon Transcript</head>   
                
            <p>Though known to scholars for decades, the document our edition calls the Kenyon
                Transcript remains mysterious. It has traditionally been catalogued as Dorothy&#8217;s
                &#8220;Letter to William Johnson,&#8221; but this designation is slightly misleading. 
                First of all, Dorothy had no direct part in creating this document; indeed, there is no way
                to know if she even authorized it. Second, it was not mailed to William Johnson. It
                might have been mailed <hi rend="italic">by</hi> him, or under his supervision, but 
                that is a separate matter&#8212;see our conjectures in the following
                paragraphs. It seems best, all things considered, to emphasize that this is a copy
                of the Johnson letter, not the letter itself. It was a new document created with a
                different audience in mind.
            </p>
                
            <p>We have limited information about the Kenyon Transcript&#8217;s making. The editors of
                William and Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s letters (second edition), Moorman and Hill,
                supposed that the copyist might be John Carter, William Wordsworth&#8217;s longtime clerk.
                However, handwriting comparison shows that this tentative attribution is incorrect.
                Ultimately, we do not know for certain who made the transcript or why, but we do
                have several clues.
            </p>
                
            <p>Though a letter, in some ways the Kenyon Transcript hardly seems like one: it
                includes no salutation, no signature, no epistolary framing at all aside from the
                fact that it is folded, addressed, and mailed. However, its address panel provides
                essential information (fig. 5.10). This panel features different handwriting from
                the body of the text (perhaps two different hands, in fact&#8212;one for the date line and
                the other for the address) and reads, &#8220;Ellesmere January three 1819 / Miss
                Hutchinson / Hindwell / Radnor.&#8221; Inserted on the left is &#8220;free[?] Kenyon,&#8221; which we
                take to be a parliamentary frank.
            </p>
                
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER"/>
                <figDesc>Figure 5.10: Detail from the Kenyon Transcript: the address panel directing the letter to &#8220;Miss Hutchinson.&#8221;
                The date line&#8212;&#8220;Ellesmere January three 1819&#8221;&#8212;appears to be in one hand, the rest of the panel in another. (Courtesy: 
                The Wordsworth Trust)</figDesc>
            </figure>
           
            <p>Ellesmere is a market town in Shropshire. &#8220;Miss Hutchinson,&#8221; presumably, is Sara
                Hutchinson, who is mentioned briefly in the transcription.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">SH&#8217;s younger sister Joanna was also at Hindwell at this time.
                    Consequently, though &#8220;Miss Hutchinson&#8221; probably designates SH, the elder sibling, 
                    we should admit to slight uncertainty. The transcript&#8217;s mention of SH comes at the end: 
                    &#8220;To add to our uncommon performances on this Day Miss Barker and I each wrote a letter 
                    from the top of the Pike to our far distant Friend in South Wales &#8211; Sara Hutchinson.&#8221;</note> 
                Hindwell is the Hutchinson family farm in Radnorshire, South Wales.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">The family&#8217;s long-term lease of the property began in 1809. 
                    On the history and importance of Hindwell to the Hutchinsons, see R. C. B. Oliver, 
                    &#8220;The (Wordsworth) Hutchinsons in Radnorshire and on the Border,&#8221; 24&#8211;46.</note>
                Kenyon must be an MP or a peer, since he can post a letter without charge.
            </p>
                
            <p>Summarizing, then, the Kenyon Transcript is a copy of Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s
                late-October 1818 letter to William Johnson that was made sometime between then and
                3 January 1819. It was sent from Ellesmere to the Hutchinsons&#8217; home in Radnor, some
                47 miles away, under a certain Kenyon&#8217;s franking privilege. With these facts in
                mind, we can begin to reconstruct a possible history of the manuscript.
            </p>
                
            <p>Who might Kenyon be? We propose that he is not, as some might suppose, John Kenyon,
                who appears frequently (in later years) in the Wordsworth family correspondence,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">John Kenyon (1784&#8211;1856), minor poet, cousin to
                    Elizabeth Barrett Browning, and friend to several nineteenth-century literary celebrities,
                    did not meet the Wordsworths until later in 1819.</note>
                but rather George, Lord Kenyon, 2nd Baron Kenyon (1776&#8211;1855). Comparing the signature
                on the address panel with signatures on known letters of Kenyon’s, we find a close match (fig. 5.11).
            </p>
                
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER"/>
                <figDesc>Figure 5.11: Handwriting sample (including signature): letter from Lord Kenyon to Thomas Davies, 31 December 1842. 
                    (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</figDesc>
            </figure>
                          
            <p>Lord Kenyon, a lawyer and staunch promoter of the Church of England, was among other
                things a patron of educational reform. Kenyon might not have known Dorothy
                Wordsworth personally,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">We have yet to ascertain this point. The Wordsworths
                    and Kenyon had so many common acquaintances that it would not be at all surprising to 
                    learn that they had met. William&#8217;s brother Christopher corresponded with Lord Kenyon 
                    (see, for instance, a letter of 5 December 1816, which Christopher sent to Kenyon at 
                    Gredington&#8212;cited in Royal Commission on Historical Manuscripts, 
                    <title level="m">Manuscripts of Lord Kenyon</title>, 564).</note> 
                but he knew several of her friends. Consequently, unfolding the history of this transcript 
                involves reconstructing a social network. The first character of note, naturally, is 
                Johnson himself, the recipient of Dorothy&#8217;s original letter, who had become close to 
                the Wordsworths during his 1811&#8211;1812 curacy in Grasmere. Johnson knew the 
                Hutchinsons as well and might have wished to forward Dorothy&#8217;s account to Hindwell 
                in any case. But what was Johnson&#8217;s connection, if any, to Kenyon? It turns out that
                Johnson was affiliated with an organization called the National Society for Promoting
                the Education of the Poor in the Principles of the Established Church in England and 
                Wales (hereafter &#8220;National Society&#8221;), founded in 1811, and that Kenyon was 
                one of that organization&#8217;s vice presidents.
            </p>
                
            <p>The National Society established schools employing the &#8220;Madras System&#8221; of 
                mutual instruction pioneered by Dr. Andrew Bell, the next important character in our story.
                Bell and Kenyon were allies in their shared educational projects; and Bell, like
                Johnson, was a friend to Dorothy and William Wordsworth.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">On Bell&#8217;s warm relationship with Dorothy, see 
                    <title level="m">DWB</title>, 273.</note>
                Indeed, it was Bell who hired Johnson away from Grasmere in January 1812 (supported by
                recommendations from the Wordsworths, though they were sorry to see him leave) to place
                him at the head of his model Central School in London. We also know that Bell was 
                acquainted with the Hutchinsons as well as with Dorothy&#8217;s climbing companion, Mary Barker.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Bell was one of the early visitors to Mary Barker&#8217;s
                    new Borrowdale home. See SH&#8217;s letter from Rosthwaite to Thomas Monkhouse (then at 
                    Anthony Harrison&#8217;s in Penrith), dated &#8220;c. 1815&#8221; in the Wordsworth Trust catalogue 
                    but probably written in the fall of 1817 (WLMS H/1/6/1).</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Robert Southey&#8217;s <hi rend="italic">Life of the Rev. Andrew Bell</hi> indicates that,
                through Bell, William Johnson had met Lord Kenyon by at least August 1812, when
                Kenyon visited the Central School and &#8220;spoke most highly of Mr. Johnson&#8217;s
                superintendence.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, <title level="m">Life of the Rev. Andrew Bell</title>, 2:441.</note> 
                Over time, the three men had numerous interactions, including at meetings of the National Society.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Minutes of these meetings survive in the
                    society&#8217;s annual reports. One such report puts Kenyon and Johnson in the same room earlier 
                    in 1818. See <title level="m">Seventh Annual Report of the National Society</title>, 283.</note>
            </p>
                                                    
            <p>In December 1818, not long after Dorothy&#8217;s Scafell Pike ascent, Johnson and Bell
                together visited Lord Kenyon at his seat, Gredington Hall, which was at Hanmer, near
                the Welsh-English border.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, <title level="m">Life of the Rev. Andrew Bell</title>, 3:173.</note>
                This could have been the occasion for Johnson to share with his two friends his remarkable 
                letter from Dorothy Wordsworth&#8212;the moment also when the copy was made and sent to 
                Hindwell. Why mail it from Ellesmere? This is also uncertain, but Ellesmere was just five miles from
                Gredington Hall, and Kenyon had established a school there. Possibly he, Bell, and
                Johnson went there for an inspection. Additional research may shed light on this
                question. In any case, we know that the document was mailed under Kenyon&#8217;s frank and
                that it originated at or near his home; this is our reason for calling it the Kenyon
                Transcript.
            </p>
                
            <p>After visiting Kenyon at the end of 1818, Bell went straight to the Lake District,
                where he spent several days with the Wordsworths before taking lodgings at Keswick,
                near the Southeys.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, <title level="m">Life of the Rev. Andrew Bell</title>,
                    3:174. Southey became Bell&#8217;s literary executor. Thomas Davies, Bell&#8217;s former clerk, gathered 
                    Bell&#8217;s papers and moved to Keswick to assist Southey with the writing of Bell&#8217;s biography. 
                    Sadly, Southey&#8217;s health failed in the middle of the project, which had to be completed by 
                    his widow, Caroline Bowles Southey, and his son, Charles Cuthbert Southey, with Davies&#8217;s 
                    assistance.</note>
                William Johnson, too, visited the Wordsworths in January 1819, arriving just five days after
                Bell&#8217;s departure.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">DW reports on the visits of Bell and Johnson in a 12 
                    January 1819 letter to Catherine Clarkson. Bell departed on the 11th, and Johnson was 
                    expected on the 16th. In this same letter, DW concludes, &#8220;All well at Hindwell&#8212;all 
                    well here&#8221; (<title level="m">Letters</title>, 3:519&#8211;20). See also 
                    <title level="m">LMW</title>, 49.</note>
                In short, Dorothy&#8217;s writing was probably circulating among this entire set of acquaintances&#8212;people
                who often communicated in person when not doing so by letter.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">One implication of this social context is that any number
                    of people might have known that DW and Mary Barker were the ones who made the Scafell Pike 
                    climb, despite the reticence of WW&#8217;s <title level="m">Guide</title>. Reports might have 
                    circulated in conversation as well as in writing. Many in DW&#8217;s extended circle might have 
                    said, with Jonathan Otley, &#8220;We have heard these stories of our kind Borrowdale neighbors 
                    so often, that . . . we, at least, think we know how they should be told&#8221; 
                    (<title level="m">Kendal Mercury</title>, 26 May 1855, 6).</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Several questions remain. Judging from the handwriting, Kenyon did not personally
                duplicate Dorothy&#8217;s remarkable ascent narrative, but who did? Not Bell or
                Johnson&#8212;their hands, too, were quite different. Possibly a clerk for one of these
                men was the scribe, or perhaps one of them wished to test an amanuensis.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">One interesting suspect is Thomas Davies, Bell&#8217;s
                    amanuensis, mentioned in n26. He was introduced to Bell by Kenyon in late 1817 or 
                    early 1818. One sample of Davies&#8217;s writing, an 1831 letter from Bell to Lady Burke,
                    survives in the archive at the Wordsworth Trust. Some features of his hand resemble
                    elements in the Kenyon Transcript, but others match less closely. Given that the 1818
                    letter to Hindwell was a fair copy of sorts, presumably in the transcriber&#8217;s finest
                    writing, and that the 1831 letter is a sample of quick dictation (written, moreover,
                    well over a decade later), it is hard to draw any certain conclusion. Additional 
                    samples of Davies&#8217;s writing reside in various archives, so we hope to update this
                    discussion as research advances.</note>
                Further research on Kenyon&#8217;s, Bell&#8217;s, or Johnson&#8217;s papers may yet allow us to identify
                the copyist with certainty. Even then, however, we shall be left with a puzzle, not
                knowing precisely why the copy was made and sent. One can, of course, imagine scenarios:
                for instance, Johnson, along with Bell and Kenyon, might suspect that the Hutchinson 
                family would enjoy reading Dorothy&#8217;s account, especially because Sara was mentioned 
                in it and had already been teased by &#8220;wish-you-were-here&#8221; notes written by Dorothy 
                and Mary Barker at the Scafell Pike summit. (Indeed, the fact that the Kenyon Transcript
                begins without preamble makes one wonder if the recipient were already expecting it.) And
                then, Johnson might appreciate an excuse to reach out to his old friends, the
                Hutchinsons&#8212;at one point, Sara and others thought that Johnson might be a good match
                for her younger sister Joanna, who was also at Hindwell in January 1819.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">For hints on Johnson as a marriage prospect for Joanna
                    Hutchinson, see SH&#8217;s letter to John Monkhouse of 28 March 1812 (Hutchinson, 
                    <title level="m">Letters</title>, 44) and DW&#8217;s letter to Mary Hutchinson (née Monkhouse) 
                    of 1 February 1813 (<hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 3:80).</note> 
                Perhaps Johnson, still unmarried, held on to similar thoughts. Of course, this is all speculation.</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
