<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1347</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2469</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1347" type="letter">
        <head>1347. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1807-07-28">28 July
                    1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol/ Single
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Pliny &#8211; Nat Hist<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-07-28">July 28. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have heard from <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref> that the precious cargo is reshipped for
                        Workington.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having decided earlier in the year to stay at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, Southey had sent for his books which were scattered between friends in
                        London and the West Country. Those kept in Bristol had been sent by sea. Samuel Reid, who lived in Liverpool, had promised to
                        look out for them when they arrived in port and have them forwarded on to Workington; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 20 April
                        1807, Letter 1308.</note> This is well, as all danger of capture is over, &amp; that of the sea comparatively so little that I
                    regard them as safe. He asks me whether he shall send me the account of freight so far, or deliver it to you. To this, as his
                    letter contains no address I could not reply except to you. Do you settle with him &amp; I will ere long send you a draft upon the
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Long Men</ref> of the Row to <del>settle</del> balance my money account with you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The picture came safe &#8211; which was a wonder for tho well secured behind, the front had nothing to <del>cover</del>
                    &lt;shield&gt; it, &amp; was compleatly covered with dust &amp; straws that had worked thro the case.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A print of the Armada; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 25 May 1807, Letter 1326.</note> The frame is not
                    as I directed &#8211; indeed it appears to have been a ready made one into which my print was squeezed at the expence of half-an-inch of
                    its breadth: a very abominable trick which the &lt;framer&gt; could not have practised if it had not been sent to a distance. My
                    directions were for a broad plain flat black frame with an inner rim of gold &#8211; it is neither broad, plain, nor flat, &#8211; &amp;
                    consequently looks not half so well as if it had. Of course I am fully sensible that you gave the directions which I sent, &amp;
                    my only motive for telling you all this is that you may never employ the same tradesman again, for nothing can be more abominable
                    than chipping a print to fill a frame, &#8211; especially so costly a one as this is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You would have heard from me sooner if I had known where to direct. The delay has had this good effect that it
                    saves me the trouble of telling you <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> history; as you know more of it now than
                    myself. His &amp; your joint letter greatly disappointed me. I have written to him expressing rather a more confident hope than I
                    feel, that he will soon be ordered into the country.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter does not appear to
                        have survived. For an account of Thomas Southey&#8217;s current troubles, see Southey to John Rickman, 26 June 1807, Letter
                        1336.</note> The surgeon will think that if <del>orders him</del> he gives this opinion now, it will be a confession that his
                    first opinion was a mistaken one, &amp; this I fear will stand in Toms way. The whole of this business has made me very
                    uncomfortable for a long time. There is an intolerable tyranny in the navy which we are not likely to see mended. Lord Cochranes
                        motion<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In parliament the newly elected Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald
                        (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), became a radical MP and critic of corruption and nepotism in the navy and in the government.
                        On 7 July he called for an inquiry into places, pensions, and sinecures held by, or for, members, but it was defeated by the
                        government. His call on the 10th for papers that would expose naval abuses did not even secure a division
                        (<title>DNB</title>).</note> was disposed of in a very disgraceful way, &amp; Sir S. Hood<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), like Cochrane a naval officer renowned for
                        courageous engagement of the enemy. Hood became MP for Westminster in 1806; in the 1807 election he was returned for Bridport
                        &#8211; a naval constituency &#8211; which he held until 1812.</note> is out of my good books for the part he took in answering it. Lord
                    C. is a true honest-hearted sailor; &amp; all who have sailed with him almost adore him. If he be not disheartened he will do much
                    good in that great Stilton-Cheese of the constitution, commonly called the House of Commons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This puts me in mind of the cheeses for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>. It is not I hope
                    too late to order him a couple.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your brother D. I hope will do well, for he has no family-claim to consumption to counteract the means which <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref>  will use for his recovery. Remember me to him &amp; say I hope to find him well
                    enough in the winter to play a rubber at whist. &#8211; You ought by this time to have received two copies of Espriella,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807).</note> one of which is for <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">his Majesty</ref>.
                        Palmerin<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert
                            Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> is still delayed by <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref>, &amp; it will be yet some weeks before it is finished: this will be no disappointment to you who have no more
                    taste for Chivalry than I have for music:</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam</ref> tells me also of the arrival at Liverpool of the books from Lisbon which were
                    wanted for the Cid. As soon as they reach me, which should be on Thursday next I shall make my bargain with the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Long-Men</ref> &amp; put the work to press.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s edition <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised
                        translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the <title>Cro&#769;nica de
                            Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632). The books had been
                        sent by his uncle <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Julius Hutchinson, the Editor of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> H.&#8217;s Memoirs has written to me, thanking me for my review
                    in the Annual. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 361&#8211;378
                        appeared Southey&#8217;s notice of Lucy Hutchinson (1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel
                            Hutchinson</title> (1806), a posthumously published memoir by the widow of Colonel John Hutchinson (1615&#8211;1664;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan commander in the English civil war and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I.
                        The editor thanking Southey was the Rev. Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown) a descendant.</note> He tells me that a second
                    edition is to be printed, &amp; asked for any advice that I could give, &#8211; which was a needless compliment. Earl Manvers,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Pierrepont, 1st Earl Manvers (1737&#8211;1816), the Nottinghamshire nobleman who owned
                        estates in the area of Owthorpe House, formerly the seat of the Hutchinsons but by 1807 semi-derelict. Manvers had inherited
                        the estates from his uncle, General Evelyn Pierrepont, 2nd Duke of Kingston-upon-Hull (1711&#8211;1773).</note> he says, a
                    descendant of Pierrepoint, has on account of this book, <del>made</del> &lt;got&gt; his son <del>a Lieu</del> promoted to a
                    Lieutenancy in the navy &amp; has promised to be his friend in every way within his power. This Earl has also ordered the Annual
                    Reviews upon the merits of this article of mine; &#8211; which said article has no other merit than that of fully acknowledging the
                        <del>merit</del> &lt;beauty&gt; of the book, &amp; being moreover a right republican one. &#8211; I have also had a letter from <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref>, containing such commendations of Madoc as perhaps never mortal man heard of
                    his works before.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805). For Southey&#8217;s reply to this letter, see
                        Southey to [Anna] Seward, 25 July 1807, Letter 1346.</note> Sir I am no longer a Crocodile &amp; a Hyena, &#8211; &amp; moreover I
                    am to stop at Litchfield on my way South.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Counts</ref>  is a very good &lt;book&gt; upon Poland, &amp;
                    we all like it much.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>View of the Present State of Poland</title> (1807).</note>
                    A few very few &#8211; omissions would improve it, but it is much to his credit. Here he is, working away at a book about the country,
                    for which the Senhora Barkera will give him some drawings.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett did not publish a
                        work on the Lake District.</note> We go to <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> as soon as his trunk
                    arrives.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">My son</ref>  &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>
                     go on prosperously. The next son I have is to be christened Danvers; I am likely to have a house full of books &amp;
                    of children, &#8211; the two best things a man can have.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>