<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1078</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2200</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 332&#8211;335 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1078" type="letter">
        <head>1078. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, <date when="1805-07-05">[c. 5 July 1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ Lincolns Inn/ London<lb />Postmark:
                        FREE/ JUL 5/ 1805<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 332&#8211;335 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Wynn,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> has written me a very civil letter of thanks, saying however that he has not
                    yet had time to read the poem,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his letter dated 19 February 1805 to Wynn (Letter 1039),
                        Southey had expressed his intention of sending <title>Madoc</title> (1805) to Fox, the leader of the Whigs in parliament who
                        was also a patron of pastoral poets. See also Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [22 June 1805], Letter 1075.</note> &#8211;
                    so his praise can only of course have been of detached parts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They tell me the duty upon foreign books is not worth collecting, &amp; that it might be repealed if any member
                    thought it worth while to take up the matter. If this be the case &#8211; I pray you to take into consideration the case of your
                    petitioner. There is now a room full of books lying for me at Lisbon. &#8211; all of use to me, yet literally &amp; truly such the major
                    part, that were they to be sold in England they would not yield the expence of the duty. I cannot smuggle them all in to my
                    sorrow, being obliged to get over only a box at a time of such smuggleable size that a man can easily carry it, &amp; this I
                    cannot do at London where I wish to have them. What <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has sent over &amp;
                    fairly paid for have cost above 100 &#163; freight &amp; duty, the freight <del>xxxx</del> far the smaller part. &#8211; Now if this
                    barbarous tax can be repealed, whoever effects its repeal certainly deserves to be esteemed a benefactor to literature &amp; it
                    may also be taken into the account that you would save me from the sin of smuggling, which also assuredly I have not virtue enough
                    to resist. Seriously if the thing could be done it would be some pride to me as well as some profit that you should be the man to
                    do it. &#8211; I think <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> would willingly supply you with any details you might want or
                    wish upon the subject. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Am I to congratulate you upon the honour of being one of the Committee,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey is referring to the parliamentary investigation into the actions of Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. During 1802&#8211;1805,
                        Melville&#8217;s use of public funds while Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800), was scrutinised by a Royal Commission. After its
                        report, on 9 April 1805, Melville was censured in the House of Commons for allowing Alexander Trotter (dates unknown), the
                        naval paymaster, to misuse public funds. Melville resigned and impeachment proceedings were commenced against him. The
                        articles of impeachment were delivered to the House of Lords on 9 July 1805.</note> or to condole with you on the confinement
                    &amp; the trouble? An honour it certainly is &amp; so I shall venture to offer my congratulations. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received a good &amp; valuable book from Lisbon, the Barbarorum Leges Antiquae well &amp; laboriously
                    edited by Canciani a Monk at Venice in five folios, the last published in 1792.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paolo
                        Canciani (1725&#8211;1810), <title>Barbarorum Leges Antiqu&#230;, cum Notis et Glossariis, acccendunt Formulari Fasciculi et Select&#230;
                            Constitutiones</title>, 5 vols (1781&#8211;1792), no. 483 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> An excellent work
                    it appears upon the slight inspection which I have just given it, one that by its painful &amp; patient labour reminds one of old
                    times, &#8211; such a book as Monasteries do sometimes produce, but Universities never. &#8211; My books here are few, but weighty &amp; every
                    day I meet with something or other so interesting to me, that <del>to</del> a wish arises for some friend to drop in, to whom
                        <del>x xxx</del> &amp; with whom I could talk over the facts which have appeared &amp; the speculations growing out of them.
                    What profit this History may ultimately produce Heaven knows, &#8211; but I would not for any thing that rank or fortune could give
                    forego the pleasure of the pursuit.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which he never
                        completed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The story of Pelayo the restorer of the Gothic, or founder of the Spanish monarchy has been for some time in my
                    thoughts as good for a poem.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;story of Pelayo&#8217; would become the subject-matter of
                        Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Roderick, The Last of the Goths</title> published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1814.</note> I would rather it were a Portuguese than a Spanish story &#8211; that however cannot be helped.
                    The historical facts are few &amp; striking &#8211; just what they should be, &amp; I could firstly give to the main character the
                    strong feelings &amp; passions which give life &amp; soul to poetry, &amp; in which I feel that Madoc is deficient. There is yet
                    half an hours day light &#8211; enough to show you what my present ideas are upon the subject in their crude state. &#8211; Pelayo revolted
                    because his sister was made by force the concubine of a Moorish governor &#8211; or by consent: &amp; because his own life was attempted
                    by that governor, in fear of his resentment he retreated to the mountains, where a cavern was his strong hold, &amp; from that
                    cavern miraculously defeated an army of the Unbelievers. The end is that he won the City or Castle of Gijon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A city in the principality of Asturias on the northern coast of Spain.</note> &amp; was chosen
                    King. &#8211; Here are for characters Pelayo himself, the young Alphonso who married his daughter &amp; succeeded to his throne. Oppas
                    the renegade Archbishop &#8211; killed in the battle of the cave. Count Julian. his daughter Florinda the innocent cause of all the
                    evil, who killed herself in consequence, &amp; lastly King Rodrigo himself, who certainly escaped from the battle &amp; lived as a
                    hermit the remainder of his days.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> On the characters of <title>Roderick, The Last of the
                            Goths</title>, see the editor&#8217;s introduction to <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1811&#8211;1838</title>, gen.
                        eds Tim Fulford and Lynda Pratt, 4 vols (London, 2012), II.</note> If I venture upon machinery of all subjects there is the most
                    tempting one, &#8211; what a scene would the famous cave of Toledo furnish!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Roderick,
                            The Last of the Goths</title>, Book 10, line 262, Southey cites sources concerning the cave, supposedly made by Hercules,
                        and occupied by a dragon, below an enchanted tower in the centre of Toledo: Florian de Ocampo, (1499?&#8211;1555?), <title>Las
                            Quatro Partes Enteras de la Cronica de Espa&#241;a que Mando Componer el Serenissimo Rey Don Alonso Llamado el Sabio Donde se Contienen los Acontecimientos y Haza&#241;as Mayores y mas Se&#241;alades que Sucedieron en Espa&#241;a </title> (Zamora, 1541), ff. viii(v)-ix(r). In Juan Yag&#252;e de Salas (1561&#8211;1621), <title>Los
                            Amantes de Teruel: Epopeya Tragica</title> (Valencia, 1616), p. 29, voices from the cave predict King Roderick&#8217;s downfall.
                        Southey also cites a similar story of prophesied doom from Lorenzo de Sepulveda (fl. 1551), <title>Romances Nuevamente Sacados
                            de Historias Antiguas dela
                            Cronica de Espa&#241;a</title> (Antwerp, 1551), ff. 94r-5r and Pedro de Corral (b. 1385?), <title>Cr&#243;nica del Rey Don Rodrigo</title>, I, pp. 172&#8211;81. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> used
                        the same legend in <title>The Vision of Don Roderick; a Poem</title> (Edinburgh, London, 1811), pp. 76&#8211;84.</note> &amp; what
                    might not be done with the ruined monasteries, with the relics &amp; images which the fugitives were hiding in the woods &amp;
                    mountains! &#8211; I had forgot to mention among the historical characters the wife of Rodrigo who married one of the Moorish governors.
                    Monks &amp; Nuns (the latter not yet cloistered in communities) persecuted Arians &amp; Jews, &amp; Slaves would furnish
                    fictitious &amp; incidental characters in abundance. &#8211; You see the raw materials. If English history could supply me as good a
                    subject it would on every account be better, but I can find none. That of Edmund Ironside<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Edmund Ironside or Edmund II (d. 1016, King of England 1016; <title>DNB</title>).</note> is the best which <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> threw out as a lure to me in the Annual
                    Review,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In Taylor&#8217;s review of the third volume of Sharon Turner&#8217;s <title>History of the
                        Anglo-Saxons</title> (1799&#8211;1805), he suggests subjects for an English epic, stating that &#8216;the frank, the daring, the generous
                        virtues of Edmund Ironside; the nationality and importance of his cause, fit him for a favourite hero&#8217;. See <title>Annual
                            Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 220&#8211;223, 222.</note> &#8211; but
                    where an historical <del>xx</del> story is taken the <del>fact</del> &lt;source&gt; ought to be of permanent importance. I have
                    thought so long at one time about Pelayo as while thus talking to you about him. But Madoc does not fully satisfy me, &amp; I
                    should like to produce something better &#8211; something pitched in a higher key. A Spanish subject has one advantage &#8211; that it will
                    cost me no additional labour of research. Only indeed were I to chuse Pelayo I would see his cave, which is fitted up as a chapel,
                    has a stream gushing from it, &amp; must be one of the finest <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> things in Spain.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>