<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1590</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2712</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1590" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1590" type="letter">
        <head>1590. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1809-02-28">28 February 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Endorsement: 28 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1809 <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmarks: E/ MAR 3/ 1809<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was mistaken about the quarter,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, about the period of time
                        covered by the most recent instalment of his government pension; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [18 February 1809],
                        Letter 1581.</note> &amp; it is not worth explaining how the mistake arose, &#8211; without recurring to dates I detected it. My
                    motive for writing now is this. If you will review the Cid, &amp; deliver the reviewal to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, I believe we can get it, thro <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capt Burney</ref>, into the
                        Monthly;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Bedford to write a review of his <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title> (1808). For Southey&#8217;s advice on this, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [c. 25 March 1809], Letter
                        1604. The book was reviewed in complimentary terms in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 63 (1810), 131&#8211;144.</note> &amp; a
                    good word there will make fifty Reading Societies order the book. Any questions relative to Spanish literature or history which
                    you may want to know more about &#8211; I can answer for you. It will be worth mentioning (&amp; perhaps <del>would</del> afford a good
                    beginning to the article) that the Proclamation of the Kingdom of Leon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Kingdom of
                        Le&#243;n was an independent kingdom situated in the northwest region of the Iberian peninsula. It was created as a separate
                        kingdom when the Asturian king, Alfonso III (c. 848&#8211;910), called &#8216;the Great&#8217;, divided his realm among his three sons. Le&#243;n was
                        joined to the Kingdom of Castile in 1230, enjoyed independence again from 1296 to 1301, and remained a kingdom until 1833, but
                        as part of a united Spain.</note> particularly referred to the Cid, &#8211; thus it is that the dead continue to act by the fame
                    which they leave behind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You mistook me if you understood that anxiety had made me suspend my employments; &#8211; it only makes me confine myself
                    to those <del>xxx</del> which can be carried on with least exertion of thought or feeling; &#8211; &amp; God knows I have always enough
                    of all kinds in hand to have choice of work at anytime. My secret of doing much, in direct opposition to common rules, is to do
                    many things at once. Thus I never disquiet myself by dwelling too intently upon any one, &amp; change serves as rest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am once more afloat with Kehama, &amp; three or four sections will bring me to the end of the voyage.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was not a little amused at <del>M</del> seeing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Glasse<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Henry Glasse (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman friend of Bedford&#8217;s who was an author, and
                        contributor to the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>.</note> among M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkes applicants.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), the former mistress of Prince Frederick,
                        Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. Clarke had been using her influence
                        with the Duke to procure advancement in the army for applicants prepared to offer her cash.</note> Another name which appeared
                    in the correspondence is that of one of our neighbours here, Spedding,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Spedding
                        (1770&#8211;1851) of Mirehouse, the house and estate near Bassenthwaite lake, north of Keswick. Spedding was a schoolfriend of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at Hawkshead.</note> from whom I had heard the story, years ago,
                    but who never knew who the Lady was, nor who Sandon<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Huxley Sandon (d. c. 1810)
                        was reportedly involved with Clarke in the office trafficking, and was a witness in the inquiry set up by parliament to
                        investigate the affair.</note> was till he saw the whole mystery explained in the course of the Inquiry. I believe he would
                    have written up to state the real circumstance but for a very sufficient reason, &#8211; that the <hi rend="ital">army agent</hi> who
                    made the proposal to him has not <del>xxx</del> been mentioned, &amp; he properly enough did not chuse to mention him in a
                    business from which he has been lucky enough to escape; had it not been for this he would have been a good evidence for
                        Wardle<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gwyllym Lloyd Wardle (c. 1761&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), elected M.P. for
                        Okehampton in 1807, had played a central role in exposing the Duke of York and Mary Anne Clarke&#8217;s involvement in office
                        trafficking.</note> &amp; Lord Folkstone.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pleydell-Bouverie, Viscount
                        Folkestone [and 3rd Earl of Radnor in 1828] (1779&#8211;1869), politician who rose to prominence in 1809 as the principal prosecutor
                        in the investigation into the sale of military commissions by Mary Anne Clarke.</note> I am right glad that <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> spoke as he did about <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percivals</ref>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spencer Perceval, Chancellor of the Exchequer and Leader of the House of Commons, was
                        called on to give evidence in the inquiry into Clarke&#8217;s activities.</note> petty-fogging brutality to Miss Taylor,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Ann Taylor (dates unknown), a witness for Mary Anne Clarke in the inquest into her
                        involvement in office trafficking. Perceval exposed her moral character to public infamy during the inquiry, although she was
                        not a defendant.</note> &#8211; &amp; that he will not let Clavering escape.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Brigadier-General Henry Mordaunt Clavering (1759&#8211;1850), was reportedly promoted from the rank of Colonel through the
                        intervention of Clarke.</note> What is law for the Captain should be law for the General also.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Meantime as you say Bonaparte is forgotten. What can have drawn him to Paris? What can have drawn the King of
                    Prussia to Petersburgh? If war breaks out in Germany the triumphs of last summer will be acted over again.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Both Russia and Prussia had suffered defeat by Napoleon in the previous years; Napoleon&#8217;s return to Paris
                        presaged not a renewal of war in Germany but a campaign against France&#8217;s ally Poland by Austria, followed by a French campaign
                        in Austria itself.</note> Be that as it may I have never lost faith in my own strong conviction that Spain will ultimately
                    deliver &amp; regenerate itself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I have an engagement to the Tupinamabas<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tupinamba,
                        one of the main ethnic groups of Brazilian indigenous people, are described in chapter 7 of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note> for the rest of the evening. They <del>were</del> are desperate cannibals,
                    but if people will kill one another for their amusement, the eating them afterwards is not of much consequence. If it does not
                    turn their stomachs it may sit easy enough upon their consciences. Were I Palafox I would certainly feed upon Frenchman rather
                    than surrender Zaragoza for famine<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Rebolledo de Palafox y Melzi (1780&#8211;1847),
                        Spanish general, who in 1808 and 1809 commanded the defending forces at the first and second sieges of Zaragosa. The city fell
                        to the French after a desperate defence involving hand-to-hand street fighting, starvation and disease.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I envy you the site of Drury Lane <del>xxx</del> &lt;theatre&gt; on fire.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Theatre Royal in Drury Lane burnt down on 24 February 1809.</note> Only one thing is wanting to make our theatres
                    more hideous than they are &amp; that is to have them of cast-iron which I dare say will be the next improvement.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-02-28">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 28. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>