<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1373</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2495</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1373" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1373" type="letter">
        <head>1373. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1807-10-24">24 October 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ OCT 27/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: 24 Oct
                        1807<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-10-24">24 Oct 1807</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr Glasse<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Henry Glasse (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman
                        friend of Bedford&#8217;s who lived near Acton. Glasse, known for his short, tubby, stature, was an author and contributor to the
                            <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>.</note> has been here &#8211; aptly is that man called Glasse, &#8211; because you may see thro
                    him. One likes to see any thing perfect in its kind &amp; therefore I am glad I have seen this perfect composition of
                    Rose-pomatum, flesh and flummery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Send whatever books of mine you have to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>, as a general
                    exportation is about to take place. I think you have two portraits of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>,
                    which were left with you when we left London in 1802. If you could get them packed securely I should be glad to have them, now
                    that I have a settled place of residence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am looking very anxiously for news from <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>  &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Brother</ref>  who were to leave Lisbon on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: their passage was taken &amp; <del>then</del>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> books on board: but if the precaution of sending a squadron <del>to
                        th</del> there has not been taken British property is not much more safe in the river than it would be on shore. There is a
                    degree of cruelty in Bonapartes mode of carrying on war against us which would make him detestable in the eyes of all Europe, if
                    we did not contrive to do things more shocking &amp; more stupid. When I remember the business of the Spanish Frigates<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 10 July 1807 the naval hero and MP for Westminster Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald
                        (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), denied prize money and promotion owed his crew after the capture of enemy frigates in 1801
                        and 1806, attempted to initiate in parliament an enquiry into naval corruption. His motion was not seconded.</note> &amp; now
                    of Copenhagen<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In summer 1807 the British, believing that France would gain possession
                        of Denmark and its fleet, amassed ships and troops and on 2 September launched a pre-emptive attack on Copenhagen, causing the
                        deaths of over two thousand townspeople.</note> I <hi rend="ital">almost</hi> tremble for what may be the fate of England in
                    this contest, of which, with God &amp; a good cause on our side I should hold it criminal to feel a doubt. But after two such
                    national sins our punishment cannot be heavier than our offence, &amp; if <del>it be</del> we fall, we shall fall unpitied. He who
                    first said <hi rend="ital">Fiat justitia ruat mundus</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;let justice be done
                        though the world fall&#8217;.</note> said well, but it is because justice is not done that ruin ensues.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr Glasse as soon as we met began talking of Our friends. In general<del>ly</del> I have a remarkably quick
                    comprehension, which is in fact <del>what most distinguishes my</del> the best faculty of &lt;my&gt; mind but this phrase puzzled
                    me, &amp; certainly I did not twig to use a Westminster phrase, till a lucky supplementary sentence made me see that he meant the
                    late ministers. He let me understand that their dismissal was a great misfortune to him. &#8211; You told me Grosvenor I should not like
                    him, &amp; in plain truth I have very seldom seen any one whom I disliked more. Now give me all due praise when I add that I
                    really did put on my very best behaviour &amp; prest him to dine with me with as much seriousness as if his heart had not been
                    hollower than a pumpkin. He introduced himself by a note beginning with &#8216;The name of Grosvenor Bedford&#8217; &amp; then came flammery,
                    &amp; something about a very dear fellow traveller, who proved to be a great piece of flesh which as far as flesh goes looks like
                    flesh of his flesh indeed, for such a rib must <del>ha</del> have needs have been taken <del>xx</del> out of a fat side. Do not
                    however suppose that I would speak ill-naturedly of her, she never held up her head while I was in the room.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you got Palmerin,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de
                            Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> &amp; have you had Espriella,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807).</note> as you should have had three months ago? &#8211; I have a quarto in the press &#8211; the Chronicle of
                    the Cid,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published
                        by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from
                        the <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title>
                        (1632).</note> &amp; it gets rapidly thro it. This will take me to London <del>xxxx</del> soon after Xmas, if not before
                        <del>xx</del>, for the notes &amp; introduction must be compleated from books at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The library of Spanish books assembled by <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Henry Richard Vassall-Fox</ref>.</note> It is likely too that if Lord Bute should be
                    at Luton<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute (1744&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), son of the
                        3rd Earl of Bute (1713&#8211;1792, Prime Minister 1762&#8211;1763; <title>DNB</title>) a literary patron, whose library the Marquess
                        inherited.</note> I may go there upon the same errand. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> will be at
                    England to introduce &amp; perhaps accompany me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaven send our Specimens to a second edition that we may retrieve our character, &#8211; but they are truly too bad for
                    me to have the least hope of this.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807), co-edited with Bedford, and published, to Southey&#8217;s dismay, with numerous errors. There was no second edition.</note>
                    I wish you would send me that Jack the Giant Killer squib<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Benjamin Tabart (1767&#8211;1833)
                        published <title>The History of Jack and the Bean-Stalk</title> in 1807. But perhaps Southey refers to Frank Sayers
                        (1763&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>) who in his 1803 collection <title>Nug&#230; Poetic&#230;</title> included a comic versification of &#8216;Jack
                        the Giant-Killer&#8217;.</note> which you most wickedly in some evil hour of dullness omitted. I have a place for it &amp; can turn
                    it to account.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> be in town I wish you would ask him for me if there be any
                    means of getting books from Italy. I want some modern works from thence &amp; some of older date from France. &amp; perhaps he
                    could put <del>them into the</del> the list into the hands of some bookseller who might be able to send it to the continent. The
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> of the <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Row</ref> know nothing
                    of this kind of business. They are all books relating to S. America, &amp; most of them are the last legacies of the Jesuits.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-10-24">Oct. 24. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>