<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.995</idno><idno type="nines">rce2117</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and
                        Art Gallery, KESMG.1996.5.54.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 299–302 [in part].Dating note: written over several
                    days.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="995" type="letter"><head>995. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-12-04">[started before and continued on 4 December 1804]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: For/ H. H.
                        Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ to the care of <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthrie</ref> –
                        Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: DE/ 1804/ 6<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and
                        Art Gallery, KESMG.1996.5.54<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 299–302 [in part].<lb/>Dating note: written over several
                    days.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> Why might a man compare the shores at Schaffhausen<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A city on the river
                        Rhine in northern Switzerland.</note> to a chamber pot? – because he might say to the river – is it not <hi rend="ital">you
                        Rhine</hi>? – Having let my joke, I proceed to your question which is of a more serious character.</p><p rend="indent1"> The best mode of promoting the civilization of <hi rend="ital">Hindostan</hi> would be by permitting Europeans to
                    colonize there. if you prove this you will lose the prize, inasmuch as to prove it would be to convict the East India Company of
                    impolicy. the first question therefore must be answered by resolving it into the second &amp; showing, as is in truth the fact,
                    that the best way of promoting the civilization of the <hi rend="ital">Hindoos</hi> is by converting them. the phrasing of the
                    question may thus conveniently be altered without any violence, &amp; only one query remain to be solved.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 21 November 1804, Letter 991.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> It is affirmed by many writers &amp; by many English East Indians that it is impossible to convert a Hindoo. if any
                    religious body be incapable of converting to Xtianity it is the Moslem, because they believe exactly all that is reasonable of our
                    belief, &amp; only chuse to have the unreasonable part <del>of</del> their own <del>xxxxx</del> instead of ours, – that is
                    speaking of doctrinals, &amp; doctrinals are all that are attended to in the business of conversion as it has hitherto been
                    managed. But the Hindoos did submit to be sprinkled in great numbers by the Jesuits – when they found it their interest. On the
                    Mohammedan conquest many became Mohammedans because it broke the fetters of their cast system – so Barros<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3180 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was Joao de Barros (1496–1570) and Diogo de Couto (c.
                        1542–1616), <title>Decadas da Asia dos Feitos, que os Portuguezes Fizeram na conquista, e Descubrimento das Terras, e Mares do
                            Oriente</title> (1778–1788), in which the Portuguese presence in India is discussed (see Decads I and II).</note> says expressly, who is for the
                    history of Hindostan the very first authority, – &amp; he says likewise that Alboquerque<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Afonso de Albuquerque (1453–1515): conqueror, governor and finally Viceroy of Portuguese possessions in East India,
                        1509–1515.</note> became exceedingly popular among the Hindoo women because he would not suffer the widows to burn themselves
                    with their dead husbands. In proof that interest will <del>always</del> bear down superstition take two instances. On the Malabar
                    coast it was the custom <del>to have</del> that a Rajah should reign no longer than his predecessor lived <del>in a</del> who was
                    a sort of priest in a pagoda, as soon as he died the Rajah took his place in the temple, &amp; his nephew (– for such was the mode
                    of succession for a very singular reason) reigned in his stead. The first Rajah of Cochin<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The town of Cochin, now Kochi, Kerala, India, colonised first by the Portuguese in the early sixteenth century.</note> whom
                    the Portugueze found obeyed this law (his name was Trimumpara,) the second preferred keeping the throne, he did so under
                    protection of the Portugueze, &amp; what makes as much to your argument, the people made no opposition to this breach of a
                    religious custom.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A discussion of the alliance between the Portuguese and Trimumpara may
                        be found in Barros and de Couto, <title>Decadas da Asia dos Feitos</title>, Decad I, book 8, and Decad II, books 1–4.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The <hi rend="ital">Poleas</hi> of the Malabar coast are the most degraded of all their casts. in Dalrymples
                    Oriental Repertory you will find some account of the wretched state to which this damnable superstition has condemned them.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Dalrymple, <title>Oriental Repertory</title> (1791–1808), 2 vols (1791–1808), II, pp. 545–7.</note> A body of these men were at work in the woods near Cochin, when a party of <hi rend="ital">Naires</hi><note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The nairs were the elite Hindu caste in Kerala, filling military and governmental
                        posts.</note> in the Zamorims<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Zamorin, the English form of Saamoothirippād or
                        Saamoothiri, was the title used by the Eradi Nair rulers of the erstwhile state of Kozhikode (Nediyirippu Swarūpam) located in
                        Kerala.</note> service effected the passage of the river. It was during the war when <del>Du</del> Duarte Pacheo<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duarte Pacheco Pereira (1460–1533), the sea captain who extended Portuguese conquests in India
                        and Africa.</note> with a handfull of Portugueze defeated the whole power of Calicut &amp; laid the foundation of the
                    Portugueze empire in India. But his efforts almost miraculous as they were, would have been frustrated that day, if the Poleas had
                    not been driven to despair at the approach of the Naires. They turned upon them, like stags at bay, tho at other times they would
                    have deemed it blasphemy to lift up their eyes towards so superior a cast. the Naires however were palsied by their superstition
                    &amp; actually fled before a handfull of wood cutters &amp; suffering themselves, tho tenfold in number, well armed, &amp;
                    excellent soldiers, to be cut down by these woodmen without resistance, &amp; thus Cochin was saved.</p><p rend="indent1"> Superstition therefore even among the Hindoos will yield to interest, but it is the interest of all the oppressed
                    casts to become Xtians, &amp; the oppressors are every where the few. As for the Bramins let them alone – convert those who pay
                    the Bramins &amp; who support them – &amp; the business is done. Xtianity would increase the temporal comforts of all. prove this
                    by detailing the inconveniences of the Brahminical ritual. spiritually considered it is a better bargain. In my Review of the
                    Baptist Periodical accounts you will see a case in point wherein a penitent (in the Hindoo sense I use the word) confessed this
                    &amp; acted upon it.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s reviews of <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the
                            Baptist Missionary Society</title> (1800–1801) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207–218,
                        and the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 189–201.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Read the Institutes of Menu by Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Jones,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir
                        William Jones (1746–1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Institutes of Hindu Law; or, the Ordinances of Menu, According to the
                            Gloss of Culbuca</title> (1796).</note> &amp; look into the Asiatic Researches,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The journal of the Asiatick Society of Bengal was first published in 1788 under the title <title>Asiatick Researches, or,
                            Transactions of the Society Instituted in Bengal, for Inquiring into the History and Antiquities, the Arts, Sciences, and
                            Literature of Asia</title>.</note> at such papers as touch upon your subjects. the best travels are those of Bernier,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> François Bernier (1625–1688), <title>Collections of Travels through Turkey into Persia and
                            the East-Indies. Giving an account of the present state of those countries. As also a full relation of the five years wars
                            between Aureng-Zebe and his brothers. ... And a voyage made by the Great Mogul (Aureng-Zebe) with his army from Dehli ...
                            to the Kingdom of Kachemire ... Together with a relation of the kingdom of Japan and Tunkin ... To which is added a new
                            description of the Grand Seignior’s Seraglio and also of the Kingdoms that encompass the Euxine and Caspian Seas</title>
                        (1684).</note> &amp; of Pietro della Valle – the latter are translated in one folio volume, &amp; Sir Thomas Roes<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas Roe (1581–1644; <title>DNB</title>): diplomat and Ambassador to Mughal India,
                        1615–1619.</note> account will be found in the same volume.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 2894 of the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library was Pietro della Valle (1586–1652), <title>The Travels of ... P. della V. into East India and
                            Arabia Deserta. ... Whereunto is added a relation of Sir T. Roe’s Voyage into the East Indies</title> (1665).</note> look
                    too in Picart for accounts of the Brahminical system by Abraham Roger &amp; by Lord,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bernard Picart (1673–1733), <title>The Ceremonies and Religious Customs of the Various Nations of the Known World</title>
                        (London, 1733) contains <title>A Dissertation on the Religion and Manners of the Bramins. Extracted from the Memoirs of the
                            Rev. Abraham Roger, a Hollander</title>, III, pp. 344–405, and <title>A Discovery of the Sect of the Banians. Containing
                            their History, law, Liturgy, Castes, Customs and Ceremonies. Gathered from their Bramins . . . By the Reverend Mr.
                            Lord</title>, III, pp. 305–340.</note> &amp; in Lentot &amp; Osborns Collection (which I believe is called Churchill)
                        <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Collection of Voyages and Travels</title> was originally produced for and published by John (c.1663–c.1714;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Awnsham Churchill (1658–1728; <title>DNB</title>) in four volumes in 1704; the third edition of
                        1744–1746, owned by Southey, featured additional volumes collected by Thomas Osborne (bap. 1704?–1767).</note> for
                        Baldæus.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillippus Baldaeus (1632–1672), <title>A True and Exact Description of the
                            Most Celebrated East-India Coasts of Malabar and Coromandel, as also of the Isle of Ceylon ... Also a most Circumstantial
                            and Compleat Account of the Idolatry of the Pagans in the East Indies</title>, in Churchill, <title>A Collection of
                            Voyages and Travels</title>, III, pp. 511–624.</note> all good books. Of modern writers Sonnerat<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition was Pierre Sonnerat (1748–1814), <title>Voyage to the East Indies and China; ... Between the
                            Years 1774 and 1781</title> (1788).</note> contains most but he is a systematic traveller – i.e. a man without eyes ears
                    or heart. Craufords Sketches of the Hindoos<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Quentin Crauford (1743–1819),
                        <title>Sketches Chiefly Relating to the History, Religion, Learning and Manners of the Hindoos</title> (1790).</note> contain
                    something. Tennants Indian Recreations<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Tennant (1784–1848; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Indian Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and
                            Hindoos</title> (1803).</note> almost nothing at all. Hodges<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Hodges
                        (1744–1797; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in India, During the Years 1780, 1781, 1782, and 1783</title> (1794).</note>
                    is worth reading. I learnt many images from his book. Grandpré<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Maria Joseph, Count
                        O’Hier de Grandpré (1761–1846), <title>A Voyage in the Indian Ocean, and to Bengal ... To which is added a Voyage in the Red
                            Sea, including a description of Mocha, and of the trade of the Arabs of Yemen</title> (1803).</note> a French dog.
                        Stavorinus<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition was Johan Splinter Stavorinus (1739–1788),
                            <title>Voyages to the East Indies</title> (1798).</note> an honest Dutchman, to me exceedingly useful – but not worth
                    consulting on your particular subject. So long a list will not terrify you if you have the true Southey pace in reading. As the
                    prize is to be written for by older men than yourself they will carry it by palaver, for in these things the matter goes for
                    little, if I may judge by Oxford prize essays. but you may as well try – for you will be well paid for the labour by the quantity
                    of knowledge which you will gain in the research [MS torn] may very likely win at Edinburgh which will be some credit.</p><p rend="indent1"> Soldiers are the worst missionaries. Priests indispensable but not the best. the Civil Government should be the
                    great agent. admit a converted Hindoo to the privileges of an Englishman, &amp; the whole system will crumble like snow in the
                    sunshine. never mind his sincerity – for you can make sure of his children.</p><p rend="indent1"> So much for that. the great Bellygerent<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr White (dates unknown), a local
                        man who negotiated to buy <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> from the builder and owner of the house, <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">William Jackson</ref>.</note> has broken off his bargain – so you may slide down
                        Latrigg<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fell near Keswick.</note> another year, &amp; go to Wastwater.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> A lake lying to the west of the fells Scafell and Great Gable.</note> – The Small Pox is in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; we are in quest of the cow pock matter.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> To provide inoculation.</note> if none is to be got I shall apply to you for some. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is at Bristol or was. We hear from <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Eliza</ref> that he had called on Charlton the manager<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Charlton (1779–1829)
                        was an actor and, from 1795, Deputy Manager of the Theatre Royal, Bath. From 1805–1827 he was its manager.</note> in full
                    uniform, bragging away &amp; offered to drive him to Bath in his gig. Most likely he is with <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref> but this is only a guess. I see nothing of the Fourcroy you enquire
                        for,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> As Harry Southey was studying medicine, this is probably by Antoine François,
                        Comte de Fourcroy (1755–1809): French doctor and chemist, author of many works on medicine, chemistry and entomology.</note> I
                    will write to London for the extract from the Cambrian Register for 1796 Vol 1.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Cambrian Register</title>, the journal edited by <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen
                            Pughe</ref>.</note><hi rend="ital">Lafiteau</hi><note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Francois Lafiteau (d. 1740), missionary to French
                        Canada and author of <title>Moeurs des Sauvages Américains, Compares aux Moeurs des Premieres Temps</title> (1723).</note> is one word – not as you have spelt it.</p><p rend="indent4"> ________</p><p rend="indent1"> Tuesday. – I am more alarmed than ever about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. the Whitehaven paper
                    of today in noticing the death of the Master of the Galatea who was killed in the action, says that the first Lieutenant fell
                        also.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware’s Whitehaven.</title> Thomas Southey’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a
                        fifth-rate 32-gun frigate, had, on 14 August 1804, made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near
                        Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission, 65 were killed or wounded, and Southey suspected that his brother was among the
                        dead. Thomas had been the first lieutenant but was absent from the raid because he had been placed under arrest. Charles
                        Hayman (d. 1804) was made first lieutenant in his stead and died in the attack.</note> I see some reason to doubt the accuracy
                    of other particulars in the paragraph – but none for doubting this, however I have written to London, tho in truth with little
                    hope. God bless you Harry!</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>