<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1342</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2464</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos
                        (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 112&#8211;114.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1342" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1342" type="letter">
        <head>1342. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1807-07-07">7 July 1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ JUL10/ 1807; 10o&#8217;Clock/ JY.10/ 1807F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsements: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 129 1807/ Robert Southey/ No place 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Sept<lb />Watermark: shield/ 1803/ T
                        Botfield<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos
                        (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 112&#8211;114.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> A letter which I have lately received from <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> contains the
                    following passage, &#8211; of which I send you the ipsissima verba<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;the very
                        words&#8217;.</note> rather than the substance because they will amuse you. &#8216;M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell has desired me to employ
                    you in executing a commission for a particular friend of his, who is fitting up a new house, &amp; wishes to have a set of the
                    best maps of the four quarters of the world, &amp; a General Map. His directions are such as will make you smile</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> 2 of the pannels are 12&#188; feet each</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> 1 _______________ 6 &#8531; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He expects that the maps should be as exactly as possible to these dimensions, &#8211; that is for instance, Asia &amp;
                    Europe should be squeezed or lengthened so as to fit in one of the wide pannels, Africa &amp; America in the other, &amp; the
                    great Mappa mundi in the pannel of 6 &#8531; feet. He has added the heighth 7&#189; feet, expecting that Arrowsmith<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790
                        large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map Exhibiting All the New Discoveries in the
                            Interior Parts of North America</title> (1795 rev. 1801, 1802, 1804), <title>Chart of the South Pacific</title> (1798),
                            <title>A New Map of Africa</title> (1802).</note> will make maps, according to this order, with the Lat: &amp; Long:
                    adjusted to his stucco pannels. All that we can do with this commission is to order four maps &amp; the General Map neatly mounted
                    on spring rollers, of the latest &amp; best that have been published. Should there be any on different scales, to take such as may
                    come the nearest to this Gentlemans Pannels, &#8211; to have them well packed in a box, embarked on board a merchantship, with a bill of
                    lading &amp; directed &#8211; Ao Ill<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> S&#241;r Francisco Soares de Aranjo e Silva. Deputado da Real Junta do Comercio
                    &amp;c &amp;c Lisboa. &amp; to desire <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> May</ref> would pay for them, who
                    will be immediately reimbursed from hence by means of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coppendale. And all that I have to desire of you is
                    that you would make it appear that you have used your influence with Arrowsmith on this occasion, as the people here have much
                    faith in your abilities &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; &amp; as the person <del>from</del> for whom these maps are may be useful to you if you
                    ever appear again in this country.&#8217;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is instructed to send you three copies of Espriella which is advertised for
                    this present week.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> Two are for
                    Lisbon, &amp; I will frank up to you a letter which is to accompany that directed for Francisco Xavier Baeta:<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter has not survived.</note> &#8211; a physician of very considerable talents, who brought over
                    letters to me from <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref>
                    when I was last in Portugal. &#8211; In reading this book you will easily distinguish what is written for Espriella from what is written
                        <hi rend="ital">thro</hi> him. Those letters which relate to the state of sectarianism contain some curious matter. Bryan I
                    knew personally, &amp; heard from his own lips his history, &amp; his explanation of the system of Brothers.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> included sections on the visit of the copperplate engraver and religious visionary William
                        Bryan (dates unknown) to the Soci&#233;t&#233; des Illumin&#233;s d&#8217;Avignon, and of his subsequent relationship with the self-proclaimed
                        prophet Richard Brothers (1757&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>). For these sections see <ref type="l" target="/editions/southey_prophecy/">
              <title>Robert Southey and Millenarianism: Documents Concerning
                                the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic Era</title>
            </ref>.</note> He it
                    was who took the knife to stab Brothers, as he himself told me. Where these letters are not written from personal knowledge the
                    materials have cost me some money &lt;in&gt; <del>x</del> procuring them, &amp; some time in examining them &#8211; the facts are not
                    affected by the Catholic colouring. It is the genuine heretical history of our own times.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The more I think of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> the less hope I have of him.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Edward Southey&#8217;s recent history, see Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, [c. 18 May 1807], (Letter
                        1324) and Southey to Charles Danvers, 25 May 1807 (Letter 1326).</note> I shall have an eye upon him, &amp; if he continues to
                    act decently in his strolling capacity <del>xxx</del> till I travel westward, will then see whether any thing can be planned for
                    him, &amp; anything obtained for him from the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">elder Thomas Southey</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> tells me of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>
                    arrival. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &#8211; I am sorry to say is fallen under a bad captain,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain George Miller (dates unknown), who in 1807 took command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Pallas</hi>, a 32 gun
                        fifth rate frigate launched in 1804.</note> &#8211; one whose name stinks in the navy, &amp; who makes every body miserable under
                    him. He is as much detested as Lord Cochrane,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald
                        (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), a daring ship&#8217;s captain in the Napoleonic war, under whom the Pallas was involved in the
                        capture of many French and Spanish warships.</note> who last commanded the Pallas, is beloved. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> suffers dreadfully from haemorrhoids, &amp; thinks he shall be obliged to quit the
                        ship.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> He was forced to do so; see Southey to John May, 12 August 1807, Letter
                        1352.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can any thing be so disgraceful as the Debates in Parliament! They compleatly remind one of the first scene in Ben
                    Jonsons Alchemist.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ben Jonson (1572&#8211;1637; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Alchemist</title> (1610). In Act I, scene i the characters Jeremy and Subtle argue over who is the more important to the
                        swindle they are contriving.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughter</ref> continues to do well. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Herbert</ref>, is bring weaned, &#8211; against our wishes. he <del>xxx</del> has for some
                    time ceased to grow, &amp; <del>xx</del> as his mother is not very well herself we hope weaning will be the remedy for both.
                    Otherwise just at teething <del>xx</del> is a bad time. &#8211; I miss <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> who for
                    the last three summers has bore a hand at the oar with me, on Derwentwater, &amp; footed it with me over the mountains.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1807-07-07">July 7. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>