<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1303</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2425</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 428&#8211;431.Dating note: The &#8216;Wednesday&#8217; dated by
                        Southey before 4 April 1807 (the date of the postmark) was 1 April.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1303" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1303" type="letter">
        <head>1303. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1807-04-01">[1 April 1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ APR 4/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: 4 April
                        1807<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 428&#8211;431.<lb />Dating note: The &#8216;Wednesday&#8217; dated by
                        Southey before 4 April 1807 (the date of the postmark) was 1 April.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is of all odd things in this world the oddest &#8211; not excepting my pension &#8211;) that you will persist in complaining
                    of the booksellers &amp; looking to them to do what they have no more business to do, &amp; are no more in the way of doing than
                    the Man <del>of</del> &lt;in&gt; the Moon. Dear dear Grosvenor just recollect what the business of a publisher is &#8211; it is to buy
                    &amp; sell books &#8211; not to make them, &#8211; to keep <del>an</del> accounts with <del>a</del> paper makers <del>another</del> with
                        <del>a</del> printers, &#8211; with country booksellers in almost every town throughout the Kingdom &#8211; with newspapers &#8211; with authors
                    &#8211; with bookbinders &#8211; folders &#8211; stickers &#8211; &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; &#8211; how in the very Devils name do you suppose that they can
                    find time to assist in making the book they publish? &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for petty faults, such as making a man die before he was born, they are trifles, &amp; must be let pass.
                    Altering them with a pen would be absurd nobody ever does such a thing except some country clergyman who prints a volume of
                    sermons &amp; fancies every body will be interested in them &#8211; Let all these things alone &#8211; only out with the abominations, &#8211; they
                    affect <hi rend="ital">us</hi>, the blunders concern the printer &amp; are after all of <del>xx</del> far less consequence. About
                    Chesterfield there need be no trouble &#8211; I &lt;have&gt; remedied that, &amp; also Buckingham.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had removed from his and Bedford&#8217;s anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807), at proof stage, what he viewed as immoral verse by Philip Dormer Stanhope, 4th Earl of Chesterfield (1694&#8211;1773;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Chesterfield was in the end represented only by one poem, &#8216;Advice to a Lady in Autumn&#8217;. Southey had
                        also removed a poem from the selection of poetry by George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham (1628&#8211;1687; <title>DNB</title>).
                        For the text of the omitted poem, see <title>Poems and Songs Relating to George Villiers, Duke of Buckingham; and his
                            Assassination by John Felton, August 23, 1628</title>, ed. Frederick W. Fairholt (London, 1850), pp. 77&#8211;78.</note>
                    Hinchcliffe &amp; Gildon<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poets William Hinchcliffe (1692&#8211;1742); Charles Gildon
                        (1665&#8211;1723; <title>DNB</title>).</note> are all that require any trouble &#8211; are they in the Museum?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> if not they will be in the Queenhithe collection,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The book collection of <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Thomas Hill</ref>.</note> &#8211;&amp; if you were at
                        <ref target="places.html#QueenHithe">Queenhithe</ref>, half an hour would do the business, Zounds &#8211; if I had wings upon my
                    shoulders &amp; could perch in London I would do it in less time than it takes to plague you with a letter: Leave the petty errors
                    alone, &#8211; cancel Chesterfield &#8211; Buckingham &#8211; &amp; the Sonnet <del>of</del> which is twice printed &#8211; Joseph Warton<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford had misattributed a sonnet to Joseph Warton (1722&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>), including it
                        under Warton&#8217;s name and elsewhere in the same volume. It was replaced by Warton&#8217;s &#8216;Ode to Content&#8217;.</note> works may be seen
                    at any booksellers &amp; this cannot take more time than is required for copying twenty verses. &#8211; if it be impossible to get the
                    other abominations out why I suppose I must grin &amp; endure it, being utterly unable to help myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The booksellers have determined upon a fourth volume in consequence of the complaints of omission<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fourth volume was not forthcoming.</note> &#8211; the main value of the book being as a work of
                    bibliography, &#8211; &amp; this value being materially lessened when it is known that are above 30 names omitted in the last volume. &#8211;
                    They ask me to bring it down to the present day &#8211; which I accede to because I believe that without so doing there will not be
                    enough for a volume: &#8211; now pray send me the papers, that my shoulder may without delay be set the wheel. If we can get to a second
                    edition I will take care that the book shall be a good one &#8211; but if we do it will be so much more than we deserve that I shall be
                    very greatly surprized. &#8211; And now no more about these unhappy volumes &#8211; you know what can be done without any trouble at all, &#8211;
                    you know whether you can take the trouble to do what is troublesome &amp; if not it must be left undone &#8211; you know that there must
                    be no pen-work of alteration &#8211; but the errors which are not worthy of standing in a table of errors must be left in their beauty,
                    &#8211; &amp; I hope you understand that <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> must think it quite as unreasonable in you to
                    apply to him for help &#8211; as you would think it if Hyde<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A London tailor frequented by
                        Southey, his first name and dates are unknown.</note> were to apply to you for buckram &amp; stay tape, &amp; ask you to
                    thread his needle when he is making you a coat.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you do not complain of the sale of the prints I trust they went as well as the books &#8211; I sent what I thought a
                    valiant commission for old Jacob Cats<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacob Cats (1577&#8211;1660), a Dutch author of humorous
                        and moralistic poems, renowned for his emblem books.</note> &#8211; but conclude that Jacob was <del>though</del> knocked down to a
                    more valiant bidder.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And so M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford I have a pension! &#8211; <del>which</del> some odd things have happened to me in
                    the world, &amp; this is one of them. &#8211; I am sorry however to hear that you are not punctual &#8211; for my expenditure is exceedingly
                    so, &amp; drives to the very nail &#8211; as you may suppose. Perhaps I could write a better practical treatise upon the art of
                    economizing with perfect comfort than any man living, &#8211; but if once my incomings are irregular that comfort is at an end &#8211; at
                    least till my books prove more productive than they &lt;have&gt; ever done yet. This I think will the case with my historical
                    works &#8211; &amp; so I live in hope. &#8211; Tell me if you can &#8211; when I am to expect payment &amp; how it is made &#8211; the deduction I
                        <del>xxx</del> suppose will be as Wynn says, <del>xxxx</del> a fifth, &#8211; <del>xxx</del> &amp; so peace will be worth twenty
                    pounds a year to me &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Canning, Foreign Secretary in the new government.</note> therefore had better begin to negociate</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry sorry sorry to hear of your side &amp; your shoulder, &#8211; &amp; wish to God you would put yourself under
                        <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>. If you do not I very seriously fear that you will go on from one attack
                    to another, each worse than the last. The pain in the shoulder sufficiently shows that the liver is the part affected &#8211; &amp; as
                    plainly that all which has yet been done has only suspended the disease. If any man can cure it <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> is that man. I know that lodgings &amp; physicians are dear &#8211; but <hi rend="ital">life</hi> is dearer. Had I been at Bristol things might easily have been concerted &#8211; as it is by all means go as
                    soon as you possibly can &#8211; &amp; I will give you letters to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &#8211; to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> &#8211; &amp; to <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> &#8211; the first will do
                    for you all that a friend can do &#8211; the second all that a surgeon &amp; a very pleasant acquaintance. &#8212; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Wednesday.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>