<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1539</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2661</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                        133.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 190&#8211;192 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1539" type="letter">
        <head>1539. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1808-11-20">20 November
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Endorsement: Fr[MS obscured]/ RS./ 20 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1808 <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ NOV 24/ 1808<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                        133<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 190&#8211;192 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The earliest Chronicle in French is that of Geoffrey Vilhardouin, so often quoted by Gibbon,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Geoffrey of Villehardouin (1160-c. 1212), <title>De la Conqu&#234;te de Constantinople (On the
                            Conquest of Constantinople)</title>, his eye-witness account of the Fourth Crusade. Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794;
                            <title>DNB</title>) draws on Villehardouin extensively in <title>The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman
                            Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1789).</note> which relates the capture of Constantinople by the Latins, &amp; is therefore long
                    subsequent to my Cid.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043&#8211;1099), <title>Chronica de la Famoso
                            Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (published 1593), on which Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808)
                        was based.</note> I believe the earliest histories of the Normans are in Latin, &amp; believe also that all Latin chronicles
                    will be found either as you describe them, &#8211; or florid &amp; pedantic. Men never write with feeling in any language but their own,
                    &#8211; they never write well upon subjects with which they do not sympathize, &#8211; &amp; what sympathy could there ever be between monks
                    &amp; chivalry! &#8211; My Cid is the oldest &amp; finest specimen of chivalrous history; &#8211; it is so true a book that it bespeaks belief
                    for the story of his <del>death</del> victory after death, &amp; it requires argument &amp; dates to prove that this part is not
                    authentick.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am brimful of this kind of knowledge, &#8211; &amp; much of it will appear in the first vol. of Portugueze history,
                    than is in the Cid.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s long-planned &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; was never
                        completed.</note> &#8211; There are two other subjects on which I am as well informed as on those for which you give me credit, &#8211;
                    savage manners; &amp; monastic history, &#8211; the latter not the least curious of the whole, &amp; &lt;certes&gt; the most out of the
                    way. It is a little unlucky that the least interesting of all my histories must come out the first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Saxon language you say ousted the Welsh as completely as its possessors. But there is reason to believe that a
                    part only of our prior population was Keltic. &amp; that we had previously hived Teutonic &amp; Cantabrian swarms. A Basque
                    Dictionary would be a treasure, &#8211; none of our etymologists have had recourse to it. I was told by the only person I ever met with
                    who had studied this language that there was far more of it than had been supposed both in the Spanish &amp; Portugueze, &#8211; about
                    as much probably as we have of Welsh. Bilbao would be the place to get Basque books, &#8211; but I will try to obtain a Dictionary thro
                        <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>, who has offered his services to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> in this line, &#8211; a new species of diplomacy, &amp; of more use than the
                    old.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In one point, &amp; only in one does China offer an exception to the evil consequences of Polygamy &amp; that is it
                    has remained an undivided empire. This I suppose is owing to the unique circumstance of its having a literary aristocracy, all
                    subordinate authority being in the hands of men whose education &amp; whole habits of life make them averse to war. Robbers are
                    the only rebels there. The demoralizing effects of the system are the same there as every where. &#8211; Shuey&#8211;ping&#8211;sin<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ping-hsin , the heroine of the seventeenth-century Ming work, the <title>Hao Ch&#8217;iu Chuan or The
                            Story of an Ideal Marriage</title> translated by Thomas Percy (1729&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>) as <title>Hau Kiou Choaan or
                            The Pleasing History, a Translation from the Chinese Language</title> (1761).</note> exemplifies that. I have not asserted
                    that it is a barrier to intellectual improvement, otherwise than as that must be checked by public disturbances &amp; private
                    voluptuousness. The want of an alphabet in China is certainly cause sufficient, but it is a supererogatory cause, &#8211; for those
                    Orientals who have one, are not advanced a step farther. For an effect so general there must be some general cause. <del>which
                        for</del> operating under so many varieties of age climate &amp; religion; &amp; this is the only which has universally
                    existed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our winter set in so prematurely that it <del>xxx</del> is lucky you postponed your journey hither. There is also
                    another consideration which <del>xx</del> reconciled me to our disappointment, &amp; that is &#8211; the hope that you will next year
                    bring <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref> &amp; leave her here while you advance into
                    the land of itch &amp; oatmeal.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scotland.</note> Her young one by that time will be well able to spare her &amp; to thrive upon Sussex air.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Spaniards fight well, &amp; will ultimately beat the French, sans doubt, in spite of all the Sir Hews &amp; Sir
                        Arthurs<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>); Sir Arthur Wellesley (later
                        the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>).</note> that we may send them. They will probably suffer much at
                    first, &amp; I am prepared to hear of such scenes at Zaragoza as have not been renewed since the destruction of Saguntum &amp;
                        Numantia.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Siege of Saguntum, Iberia (219&#8211;218 BC) Hannibal&#8217;s Carthaginian army
                        took the town after severe fighting. At the Siege of Numantia, in Hispania (134&#8211;133 BC) the army of the Roman republic, led by
                        Scipio, destroyed the town after reducing the inhabitants to starvation and cannibalism.</note>
          <del>A xxxx</del> The same country, &amp; <del>xxxx</del> the same invincible spirit still in its inhabitants.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your guess about the <hi rend="ital">armas de fuste</hi> is right I conclude so from this use of the word in old
                    French romance &#8211; toute la place estoit couverte de trefz &amp; de pavillons, et de<hi rend="ital"> loges de fust</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French translates as, &#8216;The whole place was covered with tents and pavilions and booths of canvas&#8217;.</note> &#8211; booths of canvas evidently. &#8211; Was the <hi rend="ital">fusta</hi> the foist,
                    so called from its <hi rend="ital">sails</hi> in opposition to a gallery? &#8211; In the same romance a man standing lost in thought is
                    compared to <hi rend="ital">ung homme da fust</hi> &#8211; a man of buckram &#8211;. Romances you see are not read for nothing, &#8211; the phrase
                    which you hit upon had puzzled the best antiquarians. I am reading in my idle hours Round-Table folios, &#8211; they are far inferior to
                        Amadis,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had translated the romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> in 1803; he
                        attributed the original to Vasco de Lobeira (d. 1403) a troubador knighted after the Battle of Aljubarrota (1385).</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; in morals even worse than Palmerin.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of Francisco de Moraes Cabral
                        (1500?-1572), <title>Palmerin of England</title> was published in 1807.</note> But I glean from them to good purpose.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was undertaking preliminary reading for <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng
                            Arthur ... With an introduction and notes by Robert Southey. (Printed from Caxton&#8217;s edition, 1485)</title>
                    (1817).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I recommend &amp; exhort you to read Capt-Beavers African Memoranda.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Philip Beaver (1766&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, who in 1791 participated in a scheme for colonizing the island
                        of Bulama, near Sierra Leone. The scheme failed and he returned in 1794, publishing his Bulama experiences in <title>African
                            Memoranda</title> (1805). In 1806 he was appointed to the 40-gun frigate <title>Acasta</title> and in her went to the West
                        Indies, where he remained until after the capture of Martinique in February 1809 (<title>DNB</title>).</note> you will find a
                    book &amp; a man after your own heart. I would walk to the Lands End to have the satisfaction of shaking hands with him. How comes
                    on the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> with his third volume? I want the History of the Buccaneers,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A work written by the buccaneer Alexandre Olivier Exquemelin (c. 1645&#8211;1707) in Dutch, and
                        much translated, with numerous additions, over the next two hundred years. In English it appeared, incorporating additions
                        from the Spanish translation, in 1684 as <title>Bucaniers of America: or, a True Account of the Most Remarkable Assaults
                            Committed of Late Years upon the Coasts of the West-Indies, by the Bucaniers of Jamaica and Tortuga, both English and
                            French</title>. A more recent translation of the material was derived from the German of Johann Wilhelm von Archenholz
                        (1743&#8211;1812), <title>The History of Pirates, Free-booters or Buccaneers of America</title> (1807). Exquemelin&#8217;s work was also
                        the basis of the fourth volume of Burney&#8217;s <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea</title>
                        (1816).</note> &#8211; will you ask him to buy it for me when he meets with one, &#8211; because he <del>xxx</del> knows which is the
                    right &amp; entire book, &amp; in sending from a catalogue there is a great chance of getting a wrong edition, &#8211; for I believe
                    there is a great difference in the editions of this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thalaba is at last a second time in the press, &#8211; its appearance will be very different inasmuch as the notes are
                    now, <hi rend="ital">more antiquo</hi>,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;in old fashioned style&#8217;.</note> appended to each book.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> was published in 1809. For the
                        alterations that were made to the poem in this edition see volume three of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen.
                        ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004).</note> You will not be displeased to hear that I have got half thro the long planned
                    Hindoo Romance,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> when you hear that it has been only written before breakfast.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My paper is nearly full, &amp; I have not yet told you of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> marriage. Somewhat late in life, &#8211; but he has done well to get a companion for his evening &#8211; a lovely parsonage
                    would else have been a comfortless lot. It was to me a matter of great satisfaction on this account. You perhaps may know
                    something of <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my new relation</ref>, as her father is a Hampshire man &#8211; his name Lovelace
                    Bigg Wither. &#8211; of the family of old George Wither the poet who I love so well.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lovelace
                        Bigg (1741&#8211;1813) inherited the estate of Manydown, Hampshire, in 1789. He then took the name Bigg-Withers and brought up his
                        children there. George Wither (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, was a distantly-related ancestor.</note> She invites
                    us into Herefordshire whenever we may be disposed to visit &#8216;the more civilized parts of England&#8217;. What an insult to come from the
                    Black Mountain<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A range of rough hills, scarcely inhabited, on the Welsh side of the rive
                        Wye near Hay on Wye, and a few miles from Hill&#8217;s parish of Staunton.</note> to <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>! &#8211; I have never seen her, nor had heard of her before. &#8211; neither do I know her age.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> She was thirty-three.</note> &#8211; a main point as to the fitness of the choice. I learn however that her fortune
                    is about 4000 &#8211; with the expectation of some thing more after her fathers death.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Brazilian History (about a third of the volume) returns here from my Uncle this week for certain insertions,
                    &amp; then travels to the printers.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> I wish it had been the days of the Tantarararas,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s parlance for MPs, producing noise and hot air on the benches of the House of Commons.
                            <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by John O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see
                            <title>The Dramatic Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1798), III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All
                        Fools All&#8217; was also a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>) play <title>The Lottery</title>
                        (1732). With Parliament in session, Rickman, as the Speaker&#8217;s secretary, was able to send mail free under parliamentary
                        franks.</note> &#8211; more in the hope that you would have found leisure to run your eye over the sheets, than for the sake of the
                    franks. &#8211; I forget whether <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was directed to send you my old book about Spain
                        newly-mended,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters written during a Short Residence in Spain and
                            Portugal</title> (1797) had been reprinted in an expanded form as <title>Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a
                            Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> &#8211; if not &#8211; tell me that the oversight may be remedied. &#8211; Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R</ref> &amp;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-20">Sunday night, Nov. 20. 1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>