<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1647</idno><idno type="nines">rce2769</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Cornell University, Healey 3117.  Previously  published: L. N. Broughton,
                        ‘Some Early Nineteenth Century Letters Hitherto Unpublished’, Nineteenth-Century Studies (Ithaca, NY:, 1940),
                        47–88.Dating note: from postmark.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1647" type="letter"><head>1647. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1809-07-01">[c. 1 July 1809]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E/ JUL 1/ 1809; [partial] 1809; 10 o’Clock/ JY.1/ 1809 F.Nn<lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.142.1809/ Robert Southey/ No date/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> July/ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Oct<lb/>MS: Cornell University, Healey 3117<lb/>Previously published: L. N. Broughton,
                        ‘Some Early Nineteenth Century Letters Hitherto Unpublished’, <title>Nineteenth-Century Studies</title> (Ithaca, NY:, 1940),
                        47–88.<lb/>Dating note: from postmark.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your direction has been duely transmitted to the publisher of the Friend;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Friend</title> was a periodical written by Coleridge in 1809 and 1810, spanning twenty-eight issues and ending in
                        March 1810. It was printed by John Brown (dates unknown) of Penrith, Cumbria.</note> &amp; I wish it were in my power to add
                    that you may expect to receive it regularly. The third number has not appeared at the stated time. – indeed it was a great
                    vexation both to myself &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> that the first ever came out. It had
                    been so long delayed, &amp; we were both so certainly assured that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    cannot possibly carry it on, that our earnest wish was he might never begin it. How he can have deceived himself into the
                    supposition that he could perform a weekly engagement to the public, or how he can excuse to himself the pain which he is
                    occasioning to all those who are interested about him, is as inexplicable as the strange disease, whether of body or mind, which
                    actually incapacitates him from doing any thing, the moment it becomes his duty to do it. I have lately had some serious talk, or
                    rather consultation with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, respecting the hopeless way in which he is
                    going on, &amp; the consequences to his family. The result was that as soon as the Friend shall be given up, we must interfere,
                    &amp; arrange some plan respecting the education of the boys .<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> Whenever things come to this crisis it will be proper to apply to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George Coleridge</ref>, &amp; before any thing of the kind is done I will write fully to
                    you, for your opinion upon the subject.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See the following letters in <title>The Collected
                        Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>: to John May, 15 July 1814 (Letter 2460), 22 August 1814 (Letter 2473) and 10
                        September 1814 (Letter 2480); see also Southey to George Coleridge, 12 October 1814 (Letter 2485).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> There is little of mine in the last Annual. Articles 8.9 of Chapter 1. 8.9. Chapt. 5. – 7.13 Chapt 6. – 1.3. Ch.
                    11. – 2.3 C12. – 33 Ch 7 are all,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to this list, Southey reviewed the following
                        in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809): <title>Tour Through Spain and Part of Portugal</title>, Volume 3 of
                        Richard Phillips, <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages and Travels</title> (1805–1810), 56–57;
                        Christian Augustus Fischer (1771–1829), <title>A Picture of Madrid: Taken on the Spot. Translated from the German</title>
                        (1808), 57–60; Thomas Clarkson, <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African
                            Slave-Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808), 127–148; <title>Report of the Committee of the African Institution,
                            Read to the General Meeting on the 15th July, 1807, Together with the Rules and Regulations which were then Adopted for
                            the Government of the Society</title> (1807); Thomas Zouch (1737–1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and
                            Writings of Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224–235; Robert Drury (1687–1734?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Adventures of Robert Drury, During Fifteen Years Captivity on the Island of Madagascar; Containing a Description of that
                            Island; an Account of its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; With an Account of the Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion,
                            and Civil Policy of the Inhabitants: to Which is Added, a Vocabulary of the Madagascar Language. Written by Himself, and
                            now Carefully Revised and Corrected from the Original</title> (1807), 253–263; John Finlay (1782–1810), <title>Scottish
                            Historical and Romantic Ballads: Chiefly Ancient with Explanatory Notes and a Glossary</title> (1808), 457–462; Charles
                        Kirkpatrick Sharpe (1781?-1851), <title>Metrical Legends</title> (1807), 473–473; Francis Douce (1757–1834),
                            <title>Illustrations of Shakespeare, and of Ancient Manners: with Dissertations on the Clown and Fool of Shakespeare; on
                            the Collection of Popular Tales entitled Gesta Romanorum; and on the English Morris Dance</title> (1807), 554–562; Charles
                        Lamb, <title>Specimens of English Dramatic Poets, who Lived about the Time of Shakespeare</title> (1808), 562–570; [Howard
                        Luke (1772–1864)], <title>A Brief Apology for Quakerism, Inscribed to the Edinburgh Reviewers</title> (1808), 354–356.</note>
                    &amp; certainly there is nothing good enough in these to make the volume worth purchasing. I shall do no more for it. As long as
                    the Quarterly does not drive me away by any intemperance in its politics I shall continue to write for it, – till the Rhadamanthus
                    be established,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had proposed through Scott to <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref> that he start up a new periodical which would review literary
                        works by dead authors; see Southey to Walter Scott, 11 March 1809 (Letter 1597) and Southey to John Rickman, 16 May [1809]
                        (Letter 1629). It was named after the Greek mythological figure Rhadamanthus, a wise king, who was one of the judges of the
                        dead. Southey’s plans for this periodical were never fulfilled.</note> – of this I have heard nothing farther, but the delay
                    is wholly owing to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> long tarriance in London – In the second Quarterly there is
                    only one article of mine,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s review of <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez;
                            com as Palavras Portuguezas Propriamente Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo d’Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May, 1809), 268–292.</note> – which if you have seen you will have of course have
                    recognised. I am sorry that Robert Walpole <del>has</del> ventured to attack Leckie, &amp; <del>having</del> &lt;thereby&gt; to
                    provoke Leckies letter in reply. It is true that Letter will not circulate so extensively as the review, but when it circulates it
                    will do him serious injury; – for that Leckies statements are true to the very letter I have known, long before his book was
                    published from the testimony of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, – who was necessarily – from his
                    official situation at Malta, intimately acquainted with the politics of Sicily.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gould
                        Francis Leckie (1760–1850), <title>An Historical Survey of the Foreign Affairs of Great Britain, with a View to Explain the
                            Causes of the Disasters of the Late and Present Wars</title> (1808). Leckie had run a farm in Sicily in 1800–1807 and
                        advocated anglicizing Sicily and similar islands in order to increase British trade. Robert Walpole (1781–1856;
                            <title>DNB</title>) with <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref> (and possibly <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>) reviewed this work in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May
                        1809), 405–419, leading to Leckie’s published response in return, entitled <title>A Letter to the Rev. R Walpole, in Answer to
                            his Criticism on the State of Sicily</title> (1809).</note> I myself object to the whole tendency of Reviews, – the only
                    way of lessening the evil which they do is to write for them with scrupulous conscientiousness, with a disposition to befriend the
                    author in question, rather than to <del>give him</del> injure him, above all things bearing in mind how highly probable it is that
                    the man who writes a book upon any given subject, <del>may</del> must be better acquainted with that subject than he who takes up
                    the book as one of the chance <del>xxxxx</del> texts of criticism. Latterly I hope I have done this, – &amp; whenever I have not I
                    have repented of it, &amp; do still repent. In the third Quarterly you will see some ‘American Annals’ which went from hence,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or, a Chronological
                            History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809),
                        319–337.</note> &amp; probably one more article, but whether it will be upon the Mission to the South Seas, or Ld Valentias
                    Travels, I do not know.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August
                            1809):<title> Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title>, 24–61; George Annesley, Viscount
                        Valentia (1770–1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in the Years 1802,
                            1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809), 88–126.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You ask me respecting <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>. I have heard nothing from him for two
                    years, – for which these would be his reasons, – that he owes me five &amp; twenty pounds, – &amp; that he knows I greatly
                    disapprove his conduct. I have heard however that he is far gone in consumption, &amp; in all probability the next news will be of
                    his death. How he has been living I know not, nor where he now is, – but from the time when he made that application to you,
                    (which made as it was so unwarrantably I ought not to have afterwards in any manner sanctioned) he has gone on worse &amp; worse,
                    having completely corrupted himself by picking up French morality at second hand in Poland. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have not seen <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref> articles in the
                        Critical.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to J. W. Robberds, Taylor wrote over sixty reviews for the
                            <title>Critical Review</title> during his employment between December 1803 and November 1804. Robberds provides a list of
                        them in <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        25–41.</note> He hates the Church of England just as a Dissen[MS cut] ought to have hated it in Charles the Seconds<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles II (1630–1685; <title>DNB</title>), King of England, Scotland and Ireland
                        1660–1685.</note> time, &amp; it is surprizing to see the absurdites to which that hatred will sometimes lead him. Professor
                    Paulus’s opinions I know,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Heinrich Eberhard Gottlob Paulus (1761–1851), German theologian
                        and rationalist who provided natural explanations for the miracles of Jesus described in the Bible.</note> – they will do
                    little harm &amp; little good in England. Socinianism<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A follower of a sixteenth-century
                        Italian sect holding unitarian beliefs, including the denial of Christ’s divinity.</note> exists in a perpetual state of
                    atrophy here, – &amp; this system which has even less of vitality than Socinianism will <del>be</del> not be able to exist at all,
                    – at least not beyond a few insulated individuals. I do not think <del>the</del> he much under-rates the Quarterly, but he
                    over-dislikes it. He loves opposition, &amp; if it gets round to be an opposition review, then he will fall in liking with it.
                    This I think it will do if the struggle in the Cabinet should end in <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref>
                        overthrow.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Canning had held the office of Foreign Secretary in the government
                        since 1807, but he offered to resign several times in 1809 over the progress of the war with France, his plans to expel Robert
                        Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh and 2nd Marquess of Londonderry (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>) from the War Office (with a duel
                        being fought between them on 21 September 1809), and his own ambitions to become Prime Minister. Canning lost his position
                        when <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref> became Prime Minister in October 1809.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Have you seen <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> pamphlet?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The defeated French army was allowed by the British to evacuate Portugal in 1808, under the terms of the
                        Convention of Cintra (30 August 1808). On 27 December 1808 and 13 January 1809 Wordsworth published, in <title>The
                            Courier</title>, an article condemning the Convention. In May 1809 Longmans published the article as a pamphlet:
                            <title>Concerning the Relations of Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this
                            Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the Convention of Cintra</title>.</note> Perhaps you could learn for me by means
                    of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burn,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burns (dates unknown), a member of the English
                        Factory, Lisbon.</note> whether the Portugueze Embassador<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Charles Villiers, 3rd
                        Earl of Clarendon (1757–1838; <title>DNB</title>), served as envoy to the Portuguese court in 1808, staying in Lisbon until
                        February 1810.</note> received the copy which was directed to be sent to him. This pamphlet has been obscure in some places by
                    the way in which his friend <ref target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref> has punctuated it, but I am sure you will
                    fully enter <del>it</del> into its spirit &amp; philosophy.</p><p rend="indent1"> My letter is nearly at its close, &amp; I have not yet told you of my visit to Durham. I past a week with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">my new sister</ref>.
                    Concerning her state of health he ought to know best, – but the sound of her cough, &amp; still more a way she has of occasionally
                    groaning when she breathes made me at times very melancholy –, &amp; would have made me unhappy had I been her husband. In all
                    other points of view he seems to have chosen well, – yet this is the most important of all. I saw some Ladies at Durham who knew
                    you – their names I think are the same as that French pie which I do not know how to spell.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> – Remember us to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>
                    &amp; believe me</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yours very affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>