<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1382</idno><idno type="nines">rce2504</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 118–20 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1382" type="letter"><head>1382. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1807-11-24">24 November 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>Postmark: E/ NOV 28/ 1807<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        24<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 118–20 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1807-11-24">Tuesday 24. Nov. 1807.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Gosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> If it had been possible that you could have answered my letter in the way you intimate, I should certainly not have
                    written it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his last letter to Bedford, Southey had complained about the delay it took
                        for his pension to be paid, asking: ‘if you can by any interest get my pension paid I pray you exert it’ and adding: ‘I
                        foresee that I shall be kept in hot water by it till I am lucky enough to get some little prize in the lottery of life which
                        will enable me to wait without inconvenience for arrears’; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 15 November 1807, Letter
                        1378. Earlier in 1807, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> had arranged that the pension he paid Southey from
                        his personal funds was replaced by a government pension.</note> It was written upon the supposition that a little hurrying
                    might be of as much use at the Exchequer as it is every where else in these days, when no one person whom I can find except <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; myself, looks upon punctuality as a duty.</p><p rend="indent1"> Mine is a strong spirit, &amp; I am very desirous that you should not suppose it to be more severely tried than it
                    is. The temporary inconvenience which I feel is solely produced by unavoidable expenses in settling myself, which will not occur
                    again, – &amp; if Espriella slides into a good sale,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). The book went into a second edition in 1808; but a
                        third was not called for until 1814.</note> or if one edition of our deplorable Specimens<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), co-edited with Bedford, and published, to Southey’s
                        dismay, with numerous errors.</note> should go off I shall be floated <del>xxx</del> into smooth water. Bear this in mind
                    also, that I can command an income fully equivalent to all my wants, whenever I choose to write for money &amp; for nothing else.
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Our fathers in the Row</ref> would find me task-work, to any amount which I
                        <del>should</del> might wish to undertake, &amp; I could assuredly make 300 a year as easily as I now make half the sum simply
                    by writing anonymously, &amp; doing what five hundred trading authors could do just as well. This is the worst which can befall
                    me, &amp; this is not so bad as the study of law, the practise of physic, or the profession of divinity in a church whose leading
                    tenets I disbelieve.</p><p rend="indent1"> Old <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> dealt unjustly by me, but it was what I expected, –
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">his brother</ref> will beyond all doubt, do just the same.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> When he died in 1806, Southey’s uncle John, left nothing to his nephews; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 26
                        June 1806, Letter 1194. Southey’s prediction about his uncle Thomas was also correct; see Southey to Henry Herbert Hill, 20
                        April 1811, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 1907.</note> In case of Ld
                        Somervilles<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819).</note> death
                    without a son, a considerable property devolves to me or my representatives, – encumbered however with a law-suit to recover it; –
                    &amp; as I should be compelled to enter into this, I have only to hope his Lordship will have the goodness to live as long as I
                    do, &amp; save me from the disquietude which this would occasion. I used to think that the reputation which I should establish
                    would ultimately turn to marketable account, &amp; that my books would sell as well as if they were seasoned with slander, or
                    obscenity. In time they will; – it will not be in my time, – I have however an easy means of securing some part of the advantage
                    to my family, by forbearing to publish any more corrected editions during my life time, &amp; leaving such corrections as will
                    avail to give a second lease of copy-right, &amp; make any booksellers editions of no value. As for my family I have no fears for
                    them, they would find friends enough when I am gone, – &amp; having &lt;this&gt; confidence you may rest assured that there is not
                    a lighter-hearted man in the world than myself. </p><p rend="indent1"> Basta,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘enough’ in Spanish.</note> or as we say in Latin Ohe jam
                    satis est.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘now, that’s enough’, Horace, <title>Epistles</title>, I, 5: 12.</note>
                    My eyes are better, which I attribute to an old velvet bonnet of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> – converted
                    without alteration into a most venerable studying-cap for my worship; it keeps my ears warm, &amp; I am disposed to believe that
                    having the sides of my head cold, as this Kamschatacan<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Kamchatka peninsula, in
                        Russia’s far east, is notorious for its freezing temperatures.</note> weather <del>xxxx</del> needs must make it, affected the
                    eyes. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford you may imagine what a venerable &amp; as the French say <hi rend="ital">penetrating</hi> air
                    this gives me. Hair, forehead, eyebrows &amp; eyes are hidden, nothing appears but nose; – but that is so cold that <del>xxx xxxx
                        xxx</del> I expect every morning when I get out of bed to see the snow lie on the summit of it. This complaint was not my old
                    Egyptian plague, but pure weakness, which makes what I have said probable.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Egyptian’
                        opthalmia, or keratoconjunctivitis, an eye disease thought to have originated in that country because many of the French
                        soldiers who campaigned there in 1798 became infected.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Did you ever get those Spanish volumes of poetry about the Saints bound which I left with you for that
                    purpose?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Bartolomé Cairasco de Figueroa (1538–1610), <title>Templo Militante
                        Flos Santorum, y Triumphos de sus Virtudes</title>, 4 vols in 2 (Lisboa, 1613–14), half bound calf, no. 3332 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – If so I wish they were at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> to take their place in the next parcel.</p><p rend="indent1"> We had an interesting guest here a few <del>xxx</del> evenings agone, who came to visit <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Guillem<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Quilliam (1771–1829), a farmer’s son of the Isle of Man, was made Lieutenant by Admiral Adam Duncan, 1st Viscount Duncan
                        (1731–1804; <title>DNB</title>) at the Battle of Camperdown in 1797. Noticed by Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke
                        of Bronté (1758–1805; <title>DNB</title>) for his coolness under fire, he became First Lieutenant on Nelson’s flagship, the
                        Victory, during the battle of Trafalgar (1805). He was made captain in 1807.</note> – Nelson’s first Lieutenant at Trafalgar,
                    a sailor of the old Blake &amp; Dampier<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral Robert Blake (1598–1657;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Captain William Dampier (1651–1715; <title>DNB</title>), naval heroes from humble
                        backgrounds.</note> breed, who has risen from before the mast, was in Duncans action, &amp; at Copenhagen,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Respectively, the battles of Camperdown (1797) and Copenhagen (1801).</note> &amp;c. He told us
                    more of Nelson than I can find room to write. He gave orders before the action to anchor the fleet after it, &amp; repeated them
                        <del>xxx</del> with almost his last breath. Those orders were repeated to Collingwood<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Vice Admiral Cuthbert Collingwood, 1st Baron Collingwood (1748–1810; <title>DNB</title>), assumed command of the fleet at
                        Trafalgar upon Nelson’s death.</note> &amp; disobeyed by that old Applewoman. Had they been executed every ship &amp; every
                    life on board <del>them</del> would have been saved. – The fire from his ship was so severe that the Spaniards leapt overboard
                    &amp; swam to it, as the safest place, – our sailors thro out the Foksl end (I do not vouch for the orthography of that word) –
                    handed them in thro the port holes, &amp; then past them along like glass said Capt G – as if they were afraid of handling them –
                    ‘here Jack – damn my eyes take care of the Spaniard’ – &amp; so they were past on from one to another, till they were put
                    somewhere out of the way. – Two men were concerned in Nelsons death, a soldier &amp; a sailor, one loaded &amp; the other fired.
                    Two midshipmen marked them &amp; brought down the sailor. After the ship had struck they went on board &amp; went aloft to look
                    for the other. He was lying there with both their shots thru him, one thru the head, one thru the body. Collingwood,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Midshipman (later Commander) Francis Edward Collingwood (1785–1835).</note> one of the mids, has
                    since been a mess mate of my brothers. The other got his death in a sad way, – they were both on board one of the French prizes,
                    when those vessels which escaped but which Sir R. Strachan<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Richard John Strachan, 4th
                        Baronet (1760–1828; <title>DNB</title>).</note> afterwards took, past her, &amp; fired into their own ships which had struck –
                    one of the most rascally things that ever was done. Collingwood saw them coming &amp; seeing he had no business to stand that –
                    got as low in the hold as he could, – the other poor fellow had his thigh broke – C had just time to quit the ship before she
                    sunk, in consequence of this broadside with all on board!</p><p rend="indent1"> You will guess that the snow has kept your letter on the road, &amp; will in like manner keep my reply. I inclose
                    the receipts to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, see
                        Southey to John Rickman, 24 November 1807, Letter 1381.</note> The best way of sending money is by a bank post bill but that
                    makes trouble, &amp; where there are franks there is no objection to cutting the notes.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        secure way of sending money in the post was to tear banknotes in half and send the two halves separately.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>