<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.899</idno><idno type="nines">rce2021</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850).  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 263–265
                        [in part]. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="899" type="letter"><head>899. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1804-02-19">19
                        February 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850)<lb/>Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 263–265
                        [in part]. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1804-02-19">Feb. 19. 1804</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> Parson-son,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Thomas Clarkson</ref>,
                        son of the Reverend John Clarkson (1710–1766). Southey is perhaps also punning on clerk, or cleric. Clarkson, the campaigner
                        for the abolition of the slave trade, a friend of the <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>, <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and Southey, moved to the Lake District in 1794 and lived in
                        retirement near <ref target="places.html#Ullswater">Ullswater</ref>, until 1806.</note> the Piscis Piscium sive
                        Piscissimus,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘the fish of fish, or biggest fish’.</note> left us to-day.      
                                   .                      .                      .                      .                      .                    
                     .                      He is piping-hot from Bristol, and brimful of admiration for <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>, who, indeed, seems to have done so much for <ref target="people.html#ClarksonCatherine">Mrs. C.</ref>, that
                    there are good hopes of her speedy recovery. He is in high spirits about the Slave Trade, for the West India merchants will not
                    consent to its suspension for five years, to prevent the importation of hands into the newly conquered islands; and what from that
                    jealousy, and from the blessed success of the St. Domingo negroes,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having defeated French
                        forces in November 1803, the black general and former slave Jean Jacques Dessalines (1758–1806) declared independence for the
                        French colony of Saint-Domingue on 1 January 1804, renaming it Haiti.</note> I believe we may hope to see the traffic
                    abolished.                      .                      .                      .                      .                      .</p><p rend="indent1"> If I were a single man and a Frenchman, I would go as a missionary to St. Domingo, where a world of good might be
                    done in that way: the climate may be defied by any man in a high state of mental excitement. I know not whether I sent you some
                    curious facts respecting vivaciousness, but I have met with enough to lead to important physiological conclusions, and in
                    particular to explain the sufficiently common fact of sick persons fixing the hour of their death, and living exactly to that
                    time; the simple solution is, that they would else have died <hi rend="ital">sooner</hi>. In proceeding with my History,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s unfinished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> I continually find something that leads
                    to interesting speculation: it would, perhaps, be better if there were always some one at hand, to whom I could communicate these
                    discoveries, and who should help me to hunt down the game when started; not that I feel any wish for such society, but still it
                    would at times be useful. It is a very odd, but a marked, characteristic of my mind, – the very nose in the face of my intellect,
                    – that it is either utterly idle, or uselessly active, without its tools. I never enter into any regular train of thought unless
                    the pen be in my hand; they then flow as fast as did the water from the rock in Horeb,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Exodus 17: 6.</note> but without that wand the source is dry. At these times conversation would be useful. However, I am going
                    on well, never better. The old cerebrum was never in higher activity. I find daily more and more reason to wonder at the miserable
                    ignorance of English historians, and to grieve with a sort of despondency, at seeing how much that has been laid up among the
                    stores of knowledge, has been neglected and utterly forgotten.</p><p rend="indent1"> Madoc goes on well; the whole detail of the alteration is satisfactorily completed, and I shall have it ready for
                    the press by Midsummer.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in
                        1797–1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in 1805.</note> I wish it could have been well examined first by
                    you and <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>; however, it will be well purged and purified in the last
                    transcription, and shall go into the world, not such as will obtain general approbation now, but such as may content most men to
                    read. I am not quite sure whether the story will not tempt me to have a cross in the title-page, and take for my motto, <hi rend="ital">In hoc signo.</hi><note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘in this sign’, alluding to the early Christian
                        tradition that the Emperor Constantine I (272–337) had a vision of the sun with a cross above it and the words ‘εν τούτῳ νίκα’
                        (meaning ‘by this, may you conquer’), which is often translated in Latin as ‘In hoc signo vinces’. Constantine adopted the
                        phrase for his battle standards. It did become the motto for <title>Madoc.</title></note>                      .              
                           .                      .                      .                      .</p><p rend="indent1"> If Μακρος Αυθρωπος<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Long Man’ in Greek. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> did publish Southey’s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        in 1807.</note> agrees with me about the Specimens, it will oblige me to go to London. Perhaps we may contrive to meet.       
                                 .                      .                      .                      .                      .                      .
                                         .                      .</p><p rend="indent1"> I am sorry, sir, to perceive by your letter that there is a scarcity of writing-paper in London; perhaps, the next
                    time you write, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Mr. Rickman</ref> or <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Mr. Poole</ref>
                    will have the goodness to accommodate you with a larger sheet, that you may have the goodness to accommodate me with a longer
                    letter; and if, sir, it be owing to the weakness of your sight that you write so large a hand, and in lines so far apart, there is
                    a very excellent optician, who lives at Charing Cross, where you may be supplied with the best spectacles, exactly of the number
                    which may suit your complaint.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I am, Sir,</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Your obedient humble servant,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>