<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1578</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2700</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1578" type="letter">
        <head>1578. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-02-07">7 February
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> has very kindly broken the laws of the Advocates Library at his peril,
                    &amp; sent Dobrizhoffer over the border,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had Scott borrow a copy for him from the
                        Advocates Library in Edinburgh, Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque
                            Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784). Southey eventually owned a copy of this work, no. 843 in the sale catalogue of his library.
                        It was translated by Sara Coleridge (with Southey&#8217;s encouragement), as <title>An Account of the Abipones, An Equestrian People
                            of Paraguay</title> (1822).</note> &#8211; the bourne which it ought not to pass. In like manner I am promised Ramusio,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigatione e Viaggi</title> (1565&#8211;1588).
                        Southey eventually owned an early edition (3 vols, 1588, 1583 and 1556), no. 2382 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
                    &amp; a French translation of Gumilla,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Gumilla (1686&#8211;1750), <title>Histoire
                            Naturelle, Civile et Geographique de L&#8217;Orenoque</title> (1758), a French version of the original <title>Historia Natural,
                            Civil, &amp; Geografica de las Naciones situadas en las Riveras del Rio Orinoco</title> (1731).</note> &#8211; the former I want
                    particularly for an account of the Orellana<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Amazon river was initially named the
                        Orellana after the Spanish explorer Francisco de Orellana (1511&#8211;1546).</note> by my old friend Oviedo, which is certainly not
                    to be found in his Spanish works.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de Oviedo (1478&#8211;1557), <title>Historia
                            General y Natural de las Indias</title> (1542).</note> Of all the works of the latter Jesuits which have come into my
                    hands Dobrizhoffers is beyond comparison the most interesting &amp; to me the most important. I have been at him four days, &amp;
                    if I can get thro his three <del>xxxx</del> octavos of Vienna printing in a fortnight it will be hard work. Gutting is frequently
                        <del>xxx xxx</del> &lt;soon done&gt;, &#8211; but this fellow is like a woodcock, &#8211; all trail, of which nothing is left to be lost.
                    I almost tremble to think how imperfect my history must have been in many parts, if I had not been able to procure this author. &#8211;
                    who is not only brimfull of the most curious information, but delivers that information in the pleasantest manner imaginable,
                    telling stories of himself in lively Latin, &amp; writing so honestly &amp; cheerfully that one marvels how he came to be a
                    Jesuit. &#8211; Here is the best account of the Yerva de Paraguay,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The herbal infusion, or tea,
                        known as <hi rend="ital">Yerba mate</hi> (also spelled <hi rend="ital">Yerva mate</hi>) or <hi rend="ital">Erva mate</hi>,
                        made from <hi rend="ital">Ilex paraguariensis</hi>, a species of holly.</note> &amp; a very curious one it is, &#8211; &amp;
                    connected with it is a beautiful story, which as soon as my prose duty is discharged, I shall set about relating in verse, &amp;
                    send to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> This poem, sixteen years in the planning and
                        drafting, was published as <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> in 1825.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> who is about to start an Edinburgh Annual Register, has applied to his
                    friend <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> &amp; to me for verses for it, &amp; I design out of this said
                    poem to buy myself an easy chair, &#8211; so it will put me to sleep, tho I hope nobody else will find it
                    soporif<del>xxxx</del>&lt;erous&gt;.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see in the Memorias de S Vincente p.39.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gaspar da Madre de Deos
                        (1715&#8211;1800), <title>Memorias para a Historia da Capitania de S. Vicente, hoje Chamada de S. Paulo, do Estado do Brazil,
                            Publicadas de Ordem da Academia R. das Sciencias</title> (1797).</note> why I wish for the Santuario Marianno<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> [Manoel Pereyra] Agostinho de Santa Maria (1642&#8211;1728), <title>Santuario Mariano e Historia das
                            Imagens Milagrosas de Nossa Senhora e das Milagrosamente Apparecidas</title> (1707&#8211;1723), no. 3222 in the sale catalogue
                        of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; which is doubtless in the main a grand collection of Catholick lies, but it seems that it
                    contains more early documents respecting Brazil than are to be found elsewhere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I detected De Bry<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The collection of travel narratives published by Theodor
                        and Johann Israel De Bry (1528&#8211;1598), <title>Peregrinationes</title> (1598&#8211;1613).</note> the other day in a right Catholick
                    piece of roguery. Two or three weeks ago <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> sent me the original French
                    edition of De Lery.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613), <title>Histoire d&#8217;un Voyage fait en la
                            Terre du Bresil</title> (1578), was no. 1709 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I was just then
                    transcribing a chapter in which the author is frequently quoted, &amp; knowing that when a man translates his own work he often
                    alters &amp; amplifies, &#8211; verified my references from the Latin by the French as I went on. Three or four times I found I had
                    misnumbered the chapters; &#8211; now I am so remarkably exact in these things that this soon excited suspicion, &amp; upon collating
                    the two copies it proved that De Bry had left out the whole chapter in which Villegagnons treachery to the Hugenots is
                        related,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Durand, de Villegaignon (or Villegagnon) (1510&#8211;1571), who invaded
                        Brazil in 1555 to claim it as a French colony, with a group of with a group of Huguenots who were escaping Catholic
                        persecution and some Catholics. Disgusted by disputes between the Protestant and Catholic colonists, Villegagnon condemned
                        some of the Calvinists to death, withdrew his support, and returned to France. In 1558 the colonists were defeated by the
                        Portuguese.</note> a long preface, &amp; most of the scattered passages in which the ignorance &amp; falsehood of Thevet are
                        exposed.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet (1502&#8211;1590), whose <title>Les Singularitez de la France
                            Antarctique</title> (1557) purported to be a first-hand account of a French expedition to Brazil.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I learn that the Annual Letters from Paraguay were published separately about the middle of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, &#8211; when the Jesuits were beginning to form their establishments there.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Cartas &#193;nuas de la Provincia del Paraguay</title> (or <title>Annual Letters from the Province of
                            Paraguay</title>) were published reports of the Jesuit missions in Paraguay (1607&#8211;1767).</note> Luckily I can leave this
                    for the second volume, &amp; by that time may possibly be able to hunt <del>xxx</del> them out in some of our public libraries, &#8211;
                    for in these it is that the history of the Paulistas &amp; their slave-wars is to be found.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although opposed to the slave-raids or bandeiras conducted by the seveneteenth century colonists of S&#227;o Paulo,
                        &#8216;Paulistas&#8217;, the Jesuits often accompanied them so as to minister to the raiders&#8217; spiritual welfare. Despite this, the raids
                        frequently targeted the Indians whom the Jesuits had brought into village settlements, &#8216;Reductions&#8217;, under their
                        supervision.</note> The Germans send books from their public libraries free by the post to any man of letters who wants them,
                    in any part of Germany.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Gumilla &amp; Ramusio are arrived. The whole of Oviedo is in the latter &amp; in addition to his <del>printed</del>
                    Spanish works, a letter to Card. Bembo<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cardinal Pietro Bembo (1470&#8211;1547).</note>
                    containing a summary of Orellanas Voyage,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Orellana (1511&#8211;1546) died during a
                        disastrous expedition, on which only 44 of 300 men survived, navigating the Amazon. His exploits were described in Oviedo&#8217;s
                            <title>Historia General y Natural de las Indias</title> (1542).</note> from which nothing is to be learned, except that we
                    have additional reason to regret the non-publication of the remainder of his history, &#8211; <del>in which</del> when he had given this
                    voyage at length in four &amp; twenty folios, as he received the account from Orellana himself. Ramusio contains nothing whatever
                    about Brazil, except two pages by a Frenchman, who urges the K of France to take possession of it. Gumilla seems to have a much
                    larger proportion of chaff than of wheat &#8211; but I hope to learn from him how far the Tupi tribes<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> An Indian tribe of the Amazon.</note> may be traced towards the North. &#8211; This smuggled importation from
                    Scotland has stopt my transcribing, I should else &lt;ere this&gt; have sent off the second portion <del>xx xxxx</del> which has
                    taken me a great deal of time. These chapters of manners, &amp; state of the country are to <del>xx</del> straight forward
                    narration what patch-work is to plain hemming.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Dobrizhoffer tells a story of Falkner which perhaps he has not told of himself.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia
                            and the Adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note> He used his hat for a plate, till it became so greasy that
                    the dogs fairly eat it up one night.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The new Review is named the Quarterly. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> I believe has reviewed the
                    Cid there, <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref> in the Annual.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) was reviewed by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> in
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 117&#8211;134. <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>
                        reviewed Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809),
                        91&#8211;99.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About this business of the D of York I have heard something very odd, from a man who is better acquainted with all
                    the secret history &amp; mystery of political rascality than any other <del>of my acquaintances</del> person I have ever met with,
                    &amp; certainly as well as any one in England.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany
                        (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in
                        the wake of allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to
                        accept money from army officers, in return for which promotion was arranged. According to Southey&#8217;s letter to Thomas Southey, 3 February 1809, Letter 1574, his informant was <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>.</note> From a number of
                    circumstances he is led to <del>xxx</del> believe that the D of Kent &amp; the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">P. of
                        Wales</ref> are the secret instigators of this accusation.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Edward, Duke of
                        Kent and Strathearn (1767&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), the fourth son of King George III (1738&#8211;1820, <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    Quem Jupiter vult &amp;c &#8211;<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> From an anonymous ancient proverb: &#8216;Quem Jupiter vult perdere,
                        dementat prius&#8217;. The Latin translates as &#8216;Whom the Gods (Jupiter) would destroy, they first make mad&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just bought the English Ulloa,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de Ulloa y de la
                        Torre-Giralt (1716&#8211;1795) travelled to South America in order to compile a confidential report for the Spanish government on
                        the state of its colonies. After the voyage he pubished <title>Relaci&#243;n Hist&#243;rica del Viaje &#225; la Am&#233;rica Meridional</title>
                        (1784). Southey owned the English version, <title>Voyage to South America</title> (1806), no. 2927 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library.</note> &amp; shall get Acosta<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; de Acosta (1539&#8211;1600),<title>
                            Historia Natural y Moral de las Indias</title> (1590). Southey came to own a copy of this work, no. 3220 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> from a library belonging to the Dissenters, in Red cross Street, which permits books to be
                    taken out by the Trustees.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Williams&#8217;s Library, established in Red Cross Street,
                        Cripplegate, in 1729, through the bequest of the Presbyterian minister and benefactor, Daniel Williams (c. 1643&#8211;1716;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> The Paraguay letters<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Cartas &#193;nuas de la
                            Provincia del Paraguay</title> (or <title>Annual Letters from the Province of Paraguay</title>) were published reports of
                        the Jesuit missions in Paraguay (1607&#8211;1767).</note> will then be the only desiderata of any consequence.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> RS.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 7. 1809.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">Both copies of Bapt Porta<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 2286 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                            library was Giambattista della (John Baptist) Porta (1537?-1615), <title>De Humana Physiognomonia</title> (1601).</note>
                        are here: &#8211; they came from Bristol, from whence all the books were sent without selection. I do not think there is a box lost:
                        but several volumes have been pilfered. Have you that Trigantiuuis<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Trigantius
                            (Nicolas Trigault) (1577&#8211;1628), a Flemish Jesuit compiler of a narrative of the Jesuit mission to China, <title>De
                                Christiana Expeditione apud Sinas suscepta ab Soc. lesu ex P. Matth. Ricci</title> (1615).</note> which you bought in
                            London?<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Post-script written upside-down across the top of the first page of the
                            letter.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>