<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1673</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2795</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1673" type="letter">
        <head>1673. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-08-31">31 August
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> two days ago announced to me the birth of <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">my cousin</ref>. I am glad you have a child, &amp; also that it is a boy, &#8211; I am glad too
                    that the name of Herbert has been taken care of, since you have for the present preferred another.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What I have done to Molina has been very little, &#8211; I have only the first volume in the original &amp; have seen
                    none of the translations, &#8211; which however the American translated, whoever he be seems diligently to have examined.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Ignazio Molina (1740&#8211;1829), <title>Compendio della Storia Geografica, Naturale, e Civile
                            del Regno del Chile</title> (1776). The American edition appeared as <title>A Geographical, Natural, and Civil History of
                            Chili</title> in 1808.</note> It seemed a proper place for abstracts from Agueros<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        No. 3480 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was Pedro Gonzales de Agueros, <title>Descripcio&#769;n Historial de la
                            Provincia y Archipie&#769;lago de Chilo&#769;e, en el Reyno de Chile, y Obispado de la Concepcion</title> (1791).</note> &amp;
                        Falkner,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose papers were published as
                            <title>A Description of Patagonia and the Adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note> &amp; accordingly there
                    I placed them, with a few stray notes thro the volume.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The English edition, containing
                        these additions made by Southey, was published in London in 1809, entitled <title>Geographical, Natural and Civil History of
                            Chile: Translated from the Italian</title>. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My authority about the Paraguay is your Noticias do Lago <del>Xx</del> Xarayes<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library records the manuscript &#8216;Noticias do Lago Xarayes&#8217; bound in with other
                        miscellaneous manuscripts in one volume (no. 3849). The Xarayes were an Indian tribe of the Amazon.</note> &#8211; by some nameless
                    traveler who drew up his narrative for the Academy, &#8211; I have re-collated what is written with the original, &amp; have certainly
                    made no mistake on my part. The question then is whether <del>xxxxxxx</del> &lt;this&gt; authority is to be relied on, &#8211; if you
                    think it is not, I will either cancel the leaf, or state in a note the contrary opinion.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Hill was helping Southey copy-edit his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the Anta,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The South American Tapir (also called the Brazilian Tapir,
                        or Lowland Tapir) is known as the Anta in Portuguese.</note> my note about him is certainly accurate; &#8211; he is as much an
                    amphibious animal as the Hippopotamus, &#8211; &amp; I dare say has upon that score been eaten with a safe conscience upon fast days.
                    Your &lt;two&gt; drawings to which the allusion was made are here. So is a drawing of the Tamandua or Ant-Eater,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tamandua is a genus of anteaters.</note> whom you seem to <del>Xxx</del> confound with the
                    Tapir or Anta in your letter. &#8211; Some of the errata I cannot turn to, my sheets reaching no farther than p 208. I sent off the
                        14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter about a fortnight ago by way of <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Perceval</ref> ; &amp; have the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> written &amp; ready to send, &#8211; &amp; about half the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> One more concludes the volume, for I fear there will not be room for Texeiras voyage<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Teixeira (d. 1641) was a Portuguese explorer who became, in 1637, the first European to
                        travel up the entire length of the Amazon, an expedition which helped extend Portuguese colonial possessions there at the
                        expense of Spain. Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;1676?), a member of Texeira&#8217;s expedition, published <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento del
                            Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title> (1641).</note> which should else come in. it occupies 19 pages in my first copy, which
                    are nearly equal to forty of the printers, &amp; this with the notes &amp; bibliography would I fear swell the book too much.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just concluded an engagement with the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> which will
                    occupy me closely till the end of the year, so that I shall be able to do nothing more than bring out this volume. It is to write
                    the historical part of the Edinburgh Annual Register which they are starting.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; section to the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> for 1808&#8211;1810.</note> They engaged
                    some other person,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either the poet and translator William Steward Rose (1775&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>) or his brother the diplomatist George Henry Rose (1770&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>). Their father was the
                        Pittite loyalist MP George Rose (1744&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; have paid for their sample &amp; cancelled it, &#8211;
                    upon which they came to me first for the Spanish affairs, &amp; shortly after for all. Their proposal was that I should regularly
                    undertake it, &amp; receive 400&#163; a year for the task. &#8211; I have consented only for one year that they may see how I suit them,
                    &amp; I how <del>the</del> far it is compatible with better pursuits. The pay is very great, &amp; will come seasonably. They
                    talked of 30 sheets &#8211; I stated the folly of spinning out matter beyond what it would bear, &amp; this therefore is at my
                    discretion. How completely unprepared I am for the task I have fully explained to them, &#8211; nevertheless they have no remedy. &#8211;
                    nobody else would be more <del>xx</del> &lt;prepared&gt; is to them a satisfactory answer, &#8211; so I must do my best, which will be a
                    great deal better than, under such circumstances, they can have any right to expect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Angola MSS<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey later owned a Portuguese manuscript on Angola and
                        the Congo; it may have descended to him from Hill. See no. 3842 of the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I ought to see,
                    &amp; indeed all your papers concerning P. Africa<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning Portuguese Africa.</note> about
                    which I am very ignorant.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese established several settlements, forts and
                        trading posts along the coast of Angola in the sixteenth century.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The running title of my book should have been as it stands upon the first MS. Hist. of Brazil &amp; Paraguay, &#8211; I
                    must say something equivalent to this in the Preface, &amp; then all that relates to the discovery of the countries will appear to
                    be integral as they are indispensable parts of the work. Their necessary connection will be manifest in the second volume. when
                    the foundation of the Guarani Reduction<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The name of the village colonies established by
                        the Jesuits around their missions to the Paraguayan Indians, or Guarani.</note> is described, &#8211; which I shall enter upon
                    immediately after finishing the Dutch War,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Dutch-Portuguese war took place between
                        1602 and 1661.</note> &#8211; but it will I fear cost me a journey to some publick Library wherever the Epist. Paraguaica<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit Relations of their missions in South America, published annually from 1632 in
                        Latin, French and Italian.</note> may happen to be accumulating dust &amp; cobwebs. I am gratified at finding you like the
                    work better upon a continuous perusal; &#8211; it pleases me better than I expected, for as you may perceive by the sort of exordium
                    which is prefixed I was fully sensible of the difficulties which were inseparable from the subject. The labour has been very
                    great, every part having been written twice over, &amp; the chapter about the savages three times. What I am doing for <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> will go to press in its first state, &amp; yet you will see that it will
                    be thought a fine style, &amp; a highly polished one, by persons who will call this <del>x</del> careless <del>xxx</del>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Those Rio Grandes have provoked me, &#8211; if I can discover any alias it shall be adopted.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810) Southey chose as an alias for the river
                        its&#8217; &#8216;native&#8217; name Potengi, complaining that there were other rivers of that name, a settlement and a province, p.
                    479.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your quarto MSS about Genoa was sent to <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref> because I thought
                    you wanted all the books connected with Italian history.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I could have the Derw. Stewardship if it suited me in spite of all the borough interest in Northumberland, &#8211; for
                        <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> can command it &amp; his interest would weigh down any two Dukes.
                    But it requires more time than I would sacrifice for any salary.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> In July 1809, Southey
                        was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the stewardship of the Derwentwater Estates
                        (which were owned by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the incumbent. Southey asked several friends
                        to intercede on his behalf, including his uncle Hill, <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> and
                            <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">George Beaumont</ref>, but in the end it was considered unsuitable for him;
                        see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 August 1809 (Letter 1666) and Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter
                        1669).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> has sent me word that if he has any influence when Dutens dies I shall
                    succeed him,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), a French Protestant, held the
                        post of Historiographer Royal until his death on 23 May 1812. Southey&#8217;s campaign for the post proved unsuccessful and it went
                        to James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; meantime to be Historiographer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Ballantyne is just as good a thing, &amp; so far better as that I have a chance of cheating the Income Tax &amp; a certainty of
                    escaping other deductions, to the tune of about 20 per cent more&#8211;The Annual Review is defunct<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 17 August 1809, Letter 1670. Southey reviewed at least 103 books for the
                            <title>Annual Review</title> during its publication (1800&#8211;1808).</note>&#8211; if the Coroners inquest should set upon its body
                    they may pronounce that it died of starvation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is beginning to write the History of the Crusades, &#8211; a subject which he
                    set his mind upon some years ago, &amp; which is a choice one in all respects. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">His
                        wife</ref> seems to be ambitious for him, &#8211; which is a good thing, &#8211; &amp; I think when he gets on a little way, the subject
                    itself will keep up <del>xx</del> &lt;his&gt; interest in it. He has both the Bishops &amp; the Chapter-Library at command,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Durham, where <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> lived.</note> &#8211;
                    in which there are most of the main documents, &#8211; &amp; Ville-Hardouin<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 1135 of the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was Geoffroy de Villehardouyn, Mare&#769;chal de Champagne (1148&#8211;1213), <title>L&#8217;Histoire de la
                            Conqueste de Constantinople par les Barons Franc&#807;ais Associez aux Venitients, l&#8217;an 1204</title> (1584).</note> which
                    happens to be one of the rarest I bought at Coimbra. I have given him my plan for keeping his books &#8211; which it cost me much
                    experience to discover, &amp; which will save him considerable labour. The chief Arabic documents have been translated into Latin. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If the sources of the Riv S Francisco are known insert them for me in an account of that river which you will find
                    in the 16 Ch.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> On p. 535 of chapter 16 of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810),
                        Southey discusses the sources of this river.</note> I expect to send that &amp; the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> together on
                    Sunday &#8211; &#8211; The passage about the Paraguay I inserted in the proof sheet, &#8211; it is not in the two Chapters which thro <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> carelessness were <del>not</del> &lt;never&gt; sent you. The note about the
                    Anta was also an insertion suggested as necessary by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>. &#8211; Do you see Murphys new
                    work announced?<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is probably referring to James Cavanah Murphy (1760&#8211;1814), who
                        published <title>Travels in Portugal; Through the Provinces of Entre Douro e Minho, Beira, Entremadura, and Alem-Tejo, in the
                            Years 1789 and 1790. Consisting of Observations on the Manners, ... Trade, Public Buildings, Arts, Antiquities &amp;c. of
                            that Kingdom</title>, in 1795. Murphy spent the last few years of his life preparing his work on The Arabian Antiquities
                        of Spain (1813&#8211;16) for the press; only part of it was published by his death.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-08-31">Aug 31. 1809</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>