<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1146</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2268</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. D. 3.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    415&#8211;17.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1146" type="letter">
        <head>1146. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-01-11">11
                        January 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esqr/ <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">Mr Guthrie&#8217;s</ref>. Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh/ Single <lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: JA/ 1806/ 14 <lb />Endorsement: 06 <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. D. 3<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    415&#8211;17.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must trouble you to call on <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> for me about the MS. &#8211; At
                    last I have received an answer from Froude<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Revd Robert Hurrell Froude (1770/71&#8211;1859;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Church of England clergyman of Dartington, South Devon, and later Archdeacon of Totnes.</note> to my
                    proposition. It is the property of a M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sherbrook<del>e</del>, who has given whatever it may produce to the
                    &lt;distressed&gt; widow of a <del>xxx</del> clergyman, &amp; leaves me full power to make the bargain.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Sherbrooke family of Oxton, Nottinghamshire had owned a manuscript volume containing rare medieval
                        metrical romances since the sixteenth century. It was compiled by one Richard Heege in the fifteenth century. Southey was
                        arranging for its purchase, through the good offices of Scott, by Scott&#8217;s friend Thomas Thomson (1768&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>), an Edinburgh advocate, record keeper and editor of medieval manuscripts. From Thomson the manuscript
                        went to the Advocates Library, Edinburgh. It remains in their collection today (National Library of Scotland, Advocates MS
                        19.3.1). For more information; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 3 October 1805, Letter 1109.</note> ten or twelve
                    guineas &#8211; or even fifteen was what Thomson said he should be willing to give &#8211; I mentioned twelve in my <del>lett</del> proposal.
                    What I wish you to do is to ask <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> how I shall direct the MSS. &#8211; &amp; I will
                    forward it as soon as your answer arrives. they in return will make their draft payable to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sherbrook,
                    &amp; inclose it to me, as it will be decorous that I should write to her, she having requested me when I travel that way to visit
                    her &amp; inspect other MSS. which are supposed to be on religious subjects, the whole being saved by one of her family from a
                    parochial library at the reformation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am quite recovered, &#8211; &amp; once more at work. reviewing is half done &#8211; I am come to <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref>, whose book rises much in my estimation upon a second perusal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de&#8217; Medici</title>
                        (1805), in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 449&#8211;467.</note> if it disappointed my curiosity or
                    expectation, it satisfies my reasonable judgement, &amp; I shall be able most truly to speak of it in terms of decided praise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref> has sent me half a collar of brawn, &amp; a little barrel
                    of pickled sturgeon &#8211; which of course have cost me a very civil letter.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This has not
                        survived.</note> &#8211; We had on Thursday the heaviest gale I ever remember to have felt. At Portinscale it has blown down M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Masons<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> An untraced neighbour in the nearby village of Portinscale,
                        on the shore of Derwentwater.</note> chimney, &amp; one of her trees &#8211; which I fear must be the great sycamore behind the
                    house. Two of Dentons<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rev. Isaac Denton (1758&#8211;1820), vicar of <ref target="places.html#CrosthwaiteChurch">Crosthwaite Church</ref>, near Southey&#8217;s home <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> windows have been driven in. We have escaped with only the loss of the holly at the top of the
                    garden &amp; a few tiles from the roof, &#8211; but the house rocked &amp; the timbers cracked like a ship in a storm. it lasted nearly
                    four &amp; twenty hours. the Cockermouth carriers who attempted to cross Winlatter<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Whinlatter pass in the Lake District.</note> were obliged to return, &amp; a chaise on the same road was nearly overturned by
                    the wind. &#8211; The house however is in more danger from below than from above. The rats nightly spring a mine in some part or other,
                    &amp; make me apprehensive of the fate of Bishop Hatto.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of many legends surrounding
                        Bishop Hatto was the account of his death. After refusing to give bread to starving peasants during a famine, the bishop
                        locked them up in a barn and set fire to it, burning all the occupants. Out of the ruins of the barn there appeared a great
                        many rats (or mice, in some versions of the story) who pursued the bishop and devoured him. Southey wrote a poem on this
                        subject entitled, &#8216;God&#8217;s Judgement On A Bishop&#8217;, published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 27 November 1799 and reprinted
                        in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1800), <title>Metrical Tales</title> (1805), <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815
                        and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works Collected by Himself</title> (1837&#8211;1838).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count</ref> is working at a collection of Specimens of English
                        Prose,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett&#8217;s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Earliest Times to
                            the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title> was published in three volumes by Longman in 1807. This compilation formed a
                        companion work to George Ellis&#8217;s, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803) and
                        Southey&#8217;s own anthology, jointly edited with Grosvenor Charles Bedford, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807).</note> chronologically arranged &#8211; with biographical sketches &#8211; a scheme of mine. &#8211; I gave myself at first
                        <del>credit</del> great credit for discovering what he could do &#8211; but after ten days labour here, his heart failed him, &amp;
                    he declared his resolution to give it up. however on reaching London he went to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <del>x</del> in consequence of the interview has resumed it, still more I suppose from <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lambs</ref> advice, who will be able very materially to help him, as I have already done,
                    &amp; shall do. I wrote to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> to ask him also to lend him
                    a hand &#8211; so the book will have as many fathers as Orion.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In classical mythology,  Poseidon, Apollo, Vulcan, Jupiter and Neptune are variously credited as Orion&#8217;s father.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have received my books concerning the Cid from Bristol, &amp; as soon as the reviewing is over shall begin to
                    make that ready for the press.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was
                        published in 1808. Southey owned several books on this topic, which he had requested <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, who was storing them, to send him, including Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043&#8211;1099), <title>Chronica
                            de la Famoso Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593) and Juan de Escobar (dates unknown), <title>Romancero e
                            Historia del Cid Ruy Diez de Bivar en Language Antigo</title> (1632). Southey had first asked Danvers to send the book in
                        March the previous year; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 13 March 1805, Letter 1048.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> has sent me two letters for Espriella &#8211;, which are in tune to a nicety, &#8211; I
                    shall have two or three more from him; &#8211; by what is done &amp; by the subjects which yet remain to be noticed, it seems likely to
                    make three small volumes instead of two.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> was published in three volumes, by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807. It is not evident how much Duppa contributed to the material on
                        Westminster Abbey, in Letter 23. He also contributed the discussion of shopping in London in Letters 7 and 11.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Turtle died at Cork performing quarantine, as did all the rest on board the same ship.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had sent a turtle back to England for his brother; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn,
                        24 November 1805 (Letter 1125) and Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806 (Letter 1140).</note> no letters from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, nor from Lisbon since my last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughters</ref> taste for the fine arts continues to increase. her favourite picture
                    at present is that of the Cacod&#230;mons clapper-clawing the Brasilians in John de Lery;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        illustration in Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613), <title>Historia Navigationis in Brasiliam, quae et America Dicitur</title>
                        (1578).</note> the Devil seems to be quite as great a source of amusement to her as he is to me. And now I believe you have
                    all the news &amp; the no-news that I can give you, &#8211; Except that crazy Harrison<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anthony
                        Harrison (1773&#8211;1827), a contemporary of Wordsworth in his childhood at Hawkshead and an attorney of Penrith, published in
                        1806, <title>Poetical Recreations</title>. The book was, as Southey forecast, damned by the critics. Harrison helped Coleridge
                        proof-read his journal <title>The Friend</title> in 1809.</note> is printing at his own expence those verses which you may
                    remember he made me hear &amp; peruse afterwards &#8211; poor fellow he will be gravely hurt to find that nobody will praise his book,
                    &amp; nobody buy it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One question more &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has desired me to inquire if there were any
                    large paper copies of the Minstrel Lay printed<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott, <title>The Lay of the Last
                            Minstrel</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; because he is illustrating it, &amp; some of the illustrations are rather too large for
                    the common quarto size. Ask the question for me&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The women desire to be remembered. Except one walk in the rain to <ref target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref> I
                    have never been out of our own premises since you left us &#8211; Still no tidings of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>. Heaven knows what is become of him<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had been working as
                        secretary to Sir Alexander Ball (1757&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), the naval officer governing Malta. His return to England was delayed by a trip to Sicily and Italy, and by difficulties, in time of war with France, in finding a sea passage. He
                        arrived in August 1806.</note> &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-01-11">Saturday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 11. 1806.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I believe I told you that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> has turned Roman Catholic by his
                        own account. Who was the primitive author of the expedition of Her: Cortez.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first eye witness account of the conquest of Mexico by Hern&#225;n Cort&#233;s de Monroy y Pizarro (1485&#8211;1547)
                            to appear was by Bernal D&#237;az del Castillo (1492&#8211;1585), <title>Historia verdadera de la conquista de la Nueva
                                Espa&#241;a</title> (published 1632). However, Cortes&#8217;s own despatches about his conquests were published as <title>Cartas
                                de relaci&#243;n</title> (1522&#8211;1525).</note> How long did Columbus remain at Lisbon on his return from his first
                            voyage<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Columbus (1451&#8211;1506) spent just over a week in Lisbon on his
                            return from his first voyage in March 1793, having been forced into port there by bad weather.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>