<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1190</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2312</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 42&#8211;44 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1190" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1190" type="letter">
        <head>1190. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1806-06-17">17 June 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KENDAL/ 261<lb />Postmark: E/ JUN20/ 1806<lb />Endorsement: 17
                        June 1806<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 42&#8211;44 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <date when="1806-06-17">17 June 1806.</date>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are two poets who must come into our series &amp; I do not remember their names in your list.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is instructing Bedford on texts for inclusion in their jointly edited anthology,
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> Sir John or Sir anything else Moore &#8211; of whom the only
                    poem which I have ever seen <del>of him</del> should be given &#8211; It is addressed to a lady, he himself being in a consumption<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Specimens</title>, II, pp. 254&#8211;257 feature a poem of this description by Edward
                        Moore (1712&#8211;1757; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Lover and the Friend&#8217;.</note> &#8211; if you do not remember it, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will, &amp; I think can help you to it for it is very beautiful. The other poor
                    rhymer is poor old <del>Botch</del> Botch Hayes, whom we are in duty bound not to forget, &amp; of whom you may say what you will,
                    only let it be in the best good humour, because poor Botchs heart was always in the right place, <del>when</del> tho
                    &lt;certainly&gt; his wig was not.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Botch Hayes&#8217; was Samuel Hayes (d. c. 1795), a master
                        at Westminster School during Southey&#8217;s time there. He was renowned for being lax on discipline, so much so that Southey later
                        recorded that pupils used to &#8216;stick his wig full of paper darts&#8217;. Hayes was also a writer of poems and sermons, and co-author
                        of a tragedy, <title>Eugenia</title> (1766). His work did not appear in the <title>Specimens</title>.</note> And you may say
                    that though his talent at producing common place English verses was not very convenient for his competitors &lt;at Cambridge&gt;
                    for the Setonian prize,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Seatonian Prize, established by Thomas Seaton (1684&#8211;1741;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a Church of England clergyman and religious writer, is awarded by the University of Cambridge for the
                        best English poem on a sacred subject.</note> that his talent of producing common place Latin ones was exceedingly so for his
                    pupils at Westminster. I do&#8217;nt say that I would wish to plant a laurel upon old Hayes&#8217;s grave; but I could find in my heart to
                    plant a vine &lt;there&gt; (if it would grow), as a more appropriate <del>xx</del> tree, &amp; to pour a brimming libation of its
                    juice, if we had any reason to think that the spirit of the grape could reach the spirit of &lt;the&gt; man. Poor fellow &#8211; that
                    phrase of being no ones enemy but his own, is not admitted as a set-off on earth; but in the other world, Grosvenor, if they do
                    not admit such men to pass thro S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peters <del>Gate</del> Great Gate, there must certainly be a little wicket
                        <del>xxxxxxx</del> hard by where they lift up the latch for themselves, which the old Porter winks with the right
                        eye<del>x</del> &amp; scolds at them all the while to keep up appearances.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been from home these ten days &#8211; a reason for not referring to your last, farther than in saying that M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Robinson<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Robinson (1757&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>): poet,
                        novelist, woman of fashion, courtesan, who contributed poetry to the <title>Morning Post</title>. She is not included in the
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> died in 1800 &amp; that all the persons for whom you
                    enquire departed about the same time or little earlier. I shall be at home again about the time that this reaches you. We are
                    visiting <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> near Ambleside, at his house by Clappersgate, to which said house I
                    shall take you, as to one of the prettiest places in this country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wanted your Frenchman <del>xxxxx</del> at Vauxhall &#8211; not in the Abbey &#8211; for this <del>xxxx</del> reason that the
                    Abbey letter was written &amp; only required certain insertions. I shall put in what of yours will fit. &amp; insert your wig <hi rend="ital">a-la Cheval</hi> elsewhere. but if you can write me one about Vauxhall I shall be glad, &amp; the sooner it comes
                    the better.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Bedford for information about London locations for inclusion
                        in <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807); see Southey to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 21 May 1806, Letter 1183. Westminster Abbey is discussed in Letter 23, but Vauxhall Gardens, which
                        was opened in 1661 and continued as a popular attraction until 1859, holding musical events and displays of artworks and
                        performers, is not.</note> And if you will send me any Memoranda for Letters &amp; any stories suitable for them, they will
                    set me thinking &amp; recollecting, &amp; may return to you in duodecimo with increase.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our last month has been so unusually fine that the farmers want rain. July will probably give them enough.
                    September &amp; October are the safest months to come down in: tho if you consider Gooseberry Pie as partaking of the nature of
                    the Summum Bonum<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning the &#8216;greatest good&#8217;.</note> (to speak modestly of it) about a
                    fortnight hence will be the happiest time you can choose. If <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> should be with me in time for the feat, I have thoughts of challenging
                    all England at a match of Gooseberry Pie; &#8211; barring Jack the Giganticides leathern bag,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        According to the children&#8217;s fairy story, while eating porridge with a giant, Jack the Giant Killer filled a leather bag under
                        his coat with the porridge rather than admit a lesser appetite than his adversary.</note> we are sure of the victory. &#8211; Four
                    letters from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> reached me the same evening with yours which told me of his return. he
                    said he was coming home with the May convoy &#8211; which in the West Indies I suppose is the same as the June one in England, there
                    named from the month in which it sets off, here from that in which it should arrive. Thank God he has escaped the yellow fever &#8211;
                    &amp; if ever he lives to be an Admiral, Grosvenor, as by Gods blessing he may, he shall give you &amp; I a good dinner on board
                    the flagship. We shall be so much the older by that time, that I fear good fortune would make neither of us much the happier.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On looking back I see I have spoken of October as a fit month for Laking. It is so; but will not be so for you to
                    lake this year, inasmuch as in October I expect to be entitled to another drawback of five per cent upon my assessed taxes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been inserting occasional rhymes in Kehama,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem,
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, was published in 1810.</note> &amp; have in this way altered &amp; amended about 600
                    lines. when what is already written shall be got thro in this manner I shall think the poem in a way of completion. indeed it will
                    most likely supply my ways &amp; means for the next winter instead of reviewing. <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> advised me to go on with it, &amp; the truth is that my own likings &amp; dislikings &lt;to it&gt; have been so
                    much upon the weigh-jolt that <del>xx</del> I stood in need of somebodys encouragement to settle the balance. It gains by rhyme, &#8211;
                    which is to passages of no inherent merit what rouge &amp; candle light are to ordinary [MS torn] merely ornamental parts also are
                    aided by it &#8211; as foil sets off paste. But where there is either passion or power, the plainer &amp; more straight forward the
                    language can be made the better. Now you will suppose that upon this system I am writing Kehama. My proceedings are not quite so
                    systematical &#8211; but what with revising &amp; rerevising over &amp; over again they will amount to something like it at last. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-06-17">Tuesday June 17. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>