<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.975</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2097</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 62.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.975" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="975" type="letter">
        <head>975. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-08-06">6 August
                        1804</date>
          </head><p>Address: <del>To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / New
                            Palace Yard/ Westminster</del>/ Single/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Postlethwaites/
                        Harting/ Petersfield<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; Fitzroy/ Square<lb />Postmarks: E/ AUG 10/ 1804; AU/ A 10/
                        1804<lb />Endorsement: RS./ 6 Aug<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1804<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 62<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-08-06">August 6 1804.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have to thank you for the remainder of the Slave Trade Report.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        parliamentary campaign to abolish the slave trade gained momentum in 1804 when <ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref> successfully brought a bill for abolition through the House of Commons. However it did not have
                        time to pass through the House of Lords and had to be reintroduced in 1805.</note> &amp; to acknowledge the empty frank. the
                    box arrived safe quoad the journey, but of its contents one table cloth &amp; two pair of stockings were gone. whether the Board
                    of Works-man, or some chance enterer into that little room were the thief God knows, &amp; it would be vain to enquire &#8211; only it
                    may be advisable to keep the books there locked up, &amp; remove the large folios &amp; those <del>xxx</del> bundles of papers to
                    some spare garret &#8211; if such you have.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of late my time has been much disturbed by sundry Lakers &amp; much occupied by Madoc.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and since then had been intermittently
                        revising. It was completed in October 1804 and published in 1805.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> the Scotch Printer works with some activity &amp; has just got half thro the printing the first part, before
                    I am half thro correcting the second. however the new matter is just &#8211; i.e. <hi rend="ital">quare</hi>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey probably means the Irish dialect form of &#8216;queer&#8217;, meaning &#8216;very&#8217; or &#8216;extremely&#8217;, than the Latin
                        meaning of &#8216;wherefore; for what reason; on what account&#8217;.</note> done. the section to be begun to day brings me into the old
                    story, &amp; then nothing but straight turnpike travelling lies before me for a long way. one little insertion remains to be made
                    above half way on, which will occupy one section, &amp; be easily written, the story being plain &amp; thoroughly made out in my
                    head. I have just got thro the most important part, &amp; most difficult &#8211; a fine Boa constrictor God, brought into the poem,
                    &amp; put out of the world with considerable effect<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The snake god features in
                            <title>Madoc</title>, Part 2, books 6 and 7.</note> &#8211; In reading the letters of Cortes, (now read with a view to collect
                    or correct materials for Madoc) I was very much surprized to find <hi rend="ital">money</hi> among certain Indians who lay within
                    his conquests.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letters or <title>Cartas de Relaci&#243;n</title> (1520&#8211;1525) of Hern&#225;n
                        Cort&#233;s de Monroy y Pizarro (1485&#8211;1547) explained to Charles V (1500&#8211;1558), Holy Roman Emperor and King of Spain, Cortes&#8217;s
                        conquest of the Aztecs. Cortes noted that the Aztecs had several forms of currency in use in their marketplaces.</note> tin
                    money &amp; in considerable quantity. Unless I am very much mistaken that dog of a Scotchman Robertson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Robertson (1721&#8211;1793), historian, about whose <title>History of America</title> Southey was habitually
                        dismissive. Robertson declares that the use of money was unknown to the Mexicans, <title>History of America</title>, 3 vols
                        (London, 1792), III, p. 173.</note> overlooked this. the fellow in all probability never read beyond the conquest of
                        Mexico,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de Solis, <title>The History of the Conquest of Mexico, by the
                            Celebrated Hernan Cortes</title> (1759).</note> as he was not to be paid for reading.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">hemp-stretch brother</ref> is at length shipped off by Dickenson<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dickinson (1771&#8211;1837), a fellow pupil at Westminster School with Southey, who later
                        went on to Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795). He was Civil Lord of the Admiralty, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> &#8211; &amp; this much
                    good have I got by the change of ministry. he was to go on board the Salvador del Mundo<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        HMS <hi rend="ital">Salvador del Mundo</hi> was a 112-gun ship of the line, captured from the Spanish at the battle of Cape St
                        Vincent in 1797.</note> till Admiral Colpoys<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Colpoys (c. 1742&#8211;1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>), British naval officer who achieved notoriety for inciting the mutiny at Spithead in 1797. He was
                        promoted to full Admiral in 1801 and appointed as Commander-in-Chief at Plymouth in 1803. In 1804 he gave up his command to
                        take a seat in the Admiralty.</note> sent him on a foreign station. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has made a
                    recapture which will yield him 120&#163; &#8211; enough to place him on the Creditor side of his Agents account, &amp; balance the heavy
                    expence of a West India station. they have detained a ship from Hambro,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hamburg.</note>
                    &amp; hope it will be condemned, in that case his prize money will double his half pay he says. this comes seasonably to put him
                    in good humour. for he was vexed &amp; disheartened to see men who were youngsters &amp; in a manner under his care, now made
                        post,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, gaining the rank of Captain, although the rank did not necessarily
                        entail a command of a vessel. Once the rank of Post Captain had been awarded, further promotion was by seniority, so becoming
                        an admiral was a matter of time.</note> while he after five years continues a Lieutenant no nearer promotion than he was the
                    first day. however we shall see him an Admiral yet. the fever is playing the Devil at Antigua. 120 men from the Carysfort<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Carysfort</hi> was a 28-gun <title>Coventry</title>-class sixth rate
                        ship of the Royal Navy, which sailed to the West Indies in 1804; the crew was afflicted by yellow fever.</note> in less than
                    one week! &amp; so well are things managed that all the stores &lt;for the Lee Isles&gt; are kept at this one Island<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antigua is one of the Leeward Islands of the West Indies.</note> &#8211; &amp; Tom in a ship that had
                    not a single sick man on board, was when he wrote going to the very head quarters of infection for spars! &#8211; the burial ground is
                    kept by Pompey a negro &#8211; so the Sailors call dying &#8211; going to Pompeys Parlour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Anthologies are going off to Longman this day that so many of my pieces as will make a volume may be reprinted
                    from them. <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Anthology</title> 1799 and 1800; Southey&#8217;s contributions to
                        these volumes were to be republished in his <title>Metrical Tales and Other Poems</title> (1805).</note> This which has cost
                    me only the trouble of reading them, <del>x</del> correcting a few blunders of my own &amp; a good many of the printers, &amp;
                    arranging a Table of Contents, will produce me about 25&#163; for every 500 copies which may sell. No mighty profit this &#8211; but worth
                    having. &amp; it is not unlikely that the book may sell from its presentable size &amp; price &#8211; for single volumes of poetry sell
                    chiefly as presents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The annual work is coming round again.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, reviewing books for the
                            <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> I have some subjects which will make me speculate usefully &#8211; that is on matters
                    connected with Portugueze history &#8211; a book called Indian Recreations which is a bad book but furnishes texts<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813), <title>Indian Recreations; Consisting Chiefly of
                            Strictures on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review
                            for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 658&#8211;670.</note> &#8211; Barrows second Volume<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of Travels into the Interior of Southern
                            Africa</title> (1804), in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 22&#8211;34.</note> &#8211; a <hi rend="ital">Dundas</hi>ish<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811): from 1804 First Lord
                        of the Admiralty; previously Secretary of State for War (1792&#8211;1801).</note> dissertation upon the Cape. I assent to all his
                    arguments for retaking &amp; retaining &amp; add to them the duty &amp; delight of erecting gallowses &amp; establishing a corps
                    of hangman for the Boors.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The navy was keen to have the use of the Cape of Good Hope as a
                        station for supplying and repairing its ships; Britain had occupied the colony there in 1795 after its enemy France had
                        acquired it on conquering its masters the Dutch. Ceded to the Dutch by the British in 1803, it was taken again by the British
                        in 1806.</note> &#8211; for lighter work there will be more Methodism &#8211; the Society for the suppression of Vice.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Part the First of an Address to the Public from the Society for the
                            Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of
                            such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3
                        (1805), 225&#8211;231.</note> &amp; Miss Sewards Life of Darwin &#8211; an admirable specimen of female English.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and
                            Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804), in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 488&#8211;493.</note> As much
                    of this as I can spare I shall turn over to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you know if <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> has received a parcel of books which I sent him?
                        <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> has been here &amp; appeared more Londonized than he did in London. he had
                    the most coxcombical coat on that ever came from a Bond street taylor, &amp; he contrived to make it seem suitable. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Crompton famous in the annals of Nottingham Electioneering was among our Lakers &#8211; a nondescript fish.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Peter Crompton (dates unknown) of Eton House, Liverpool, a radical reformer who
                        supported <ref target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref> in the 1790s and who contested elections at Nottingham
                        (1796, 1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820).</note> Young Roscoe <del>xxxxx</del> also<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Stanley Roscoe (1782&#8211;1843), poet and eldest son of William Roscoe, who was close to his father in
                        outlook and tastes. He became a partner in his father&#8217;s bank, but was also a student of Italian literature.</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">his fathers</ref> life of Leo X is to be four quartos.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roscoe&#8217;s <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de&#8217; Medici</title> was published in 1805. Southey
                        reviewed it in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 449&#8211;467.</note> it is a pity that good ground should be
                    encumbered by bad buildings. Roscoe is an excellently good man &amp; an excellently useful one, but with no strength of intellect.
                    he knows no German (as I am told) &amp; yet undertakes to write a history of Leo X<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Giovanni di Lorenzo de Medici of Florence, Pope Leo X (1475&#8211;1521), was Pope from 1513 to his death in 1521. He was the last
                        non-priest to be elected Pope. He is known primarily for the sale of indulgences to reconstruct St. Peter&#8217;s Basilica and his
                        opposition to the Lutheran Reformation in Germany.</note> &#8211; that is of the age of the Reformation. &#8211; History has flagged with
                    me from all these interruptions &amp; from my business with the Scotch printer. still it does proceed, &amp; if this written work
                    turn out well I may hope to be able to afford more time to it the next.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> One clear year in fact would bring the two leading divisions to a
                    close. I shall strive hard to get to Portugal by the winter of 1805 that that may be over &#8211; I may cast anchor. it is time for me
                    to be in port.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">The little one</ref> is well. there are however symptoms that most
                    certainly may, &amp; that most naturally, bear a bad aspect. I am on the watch &amp; will use every possible method of precaution,
                    as the time of teething comes on. It is the main evil of a remote situation that such medical advice as I could confidently
                    follow, is not within reach when wanted.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>The Whitehaven Paper has just told me that the days of franking are over.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Because
                            parliament would not be in session, and therefore parliamentary privileges would be suspended during the election period.
                            The local paper was <title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware&#8217;s Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>