<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1442</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2564</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom
                        Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 115&#8211;116.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1442" type="letter">
        <head>1442. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1808-04-16">16 April 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Hale/ Downton/
                        Wiltshire<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ APR20 /1808<lb />Watermark: shield/ 1803/ T Botfield <lb />Endorsement:
                            N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 134 1808/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June <lb />MS: Harry Ransom
                        Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 115&#8211;116.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-04-16">April 16. 1808</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> After leaving you this day fortnight I went thro the form of a supper at Salisbury, &amp; past that sort of unquiet
                    night which a man never fails to have at an inn, when he is to rise at five the next morning. Saturdays journey, except the first
                    chilling stage to Hinton, was pleasant enough, &amp; took me thro a part of Somersetshire which was new to me. About half past
                    eight I reached <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southeys</ref> &amp; was received with as much
                    cordiality as it is in his nature to show. My <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary</ref> advised me not to ask him in
                    plain terms to assist <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, but rather to let Harry make the application
                    himself, &#8211; for she thought he was hurt that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> should address his letters
                    to her instead of to him, &amp; that he liked to be made of consequence. I yielded to this, &amp; contented myself with preparing
                    the way for his application by talking of his fair prospects, his present difficulties, &amp; the little doubt there could be of
                    his final success if those difficulties could be surmounted. The weather played me a sad trick during this visit. My intention was
                    to have paid my Taunton visits on the Monday (his dinner hour rendering this impossible on the Sunday) on Tuesday to have got over
                    to <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> to see <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref>, return the next day,
                    &amp; start for Bristol on Thursday, &#8211; but the rain set in with such unabating violence that I was confined to the house from
                    Monday morning till Thursday, without any possibility of stirring out. Mine is a very accommodating disposition in most cases. I
                    read a pocket companion of excellent length &amp; dullness, expressly provided for such occasions, &amp; better as a practical
                    teacher of patience than the best commentary on the book of Job: &#8211; I talked with him of old Bristol elections &amp; old family
                    affairs, subjects on which his knowledge was far greater than mine, &amp; in which the interest I felt was equal to his own, &#8211; I
                    told him stories &amp; heard from him others in return <del>which</del> some of which my friend Espriella will turn to good
                        account,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s proposed sequel to <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) was not completed.</note> I drank his strong beer, got to
                    bed early, &amp; in short got thro the time with some satisfaction to him, &amp; as little dissatisfaction as could be to myself.
                    It is plain that he was well pleased, for he gave me 25 &#163;, &#8211; for him a considerable gift to make, &amp; by no means an unwelcome
                    one for me to receive.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thursday evening I reached Bristol &amp; found <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> rapidly recovering,
                    but a little in too much haste to run away from the surgeon, &#8211; for in spite of all dissuasion he would not stay behind me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had gone to Bristol to see <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">John
                            King</ref> who had treated him for haemorrhoids.</note> I remained there till Monday, &#8211; <del>left</del> started that night
                    for Birmingham in the mail; halted with <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> at <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward Littletons</ref> from Tuesday noon till the same hour on Wednesday, got to
                    Manchester by the mail at 12 on Wednesday night, &amp; left it in another mail in two hours, which brought me by two the next day
                    to Kendal, &amp; we reached home safely just as it became dark. I found <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp;
                    our three children as well as my heart could wish, &amp; <del>xxxx xxxx xxxx xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx at</del> finding myself
                    once more safe &amp; with my family about me, after an absence of nine weeks &amp; a journey of 800 miles, I feel a thankfulness
                    which heightens the joy it hallows.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Three tea chests of books which had for the sake of security &amp; dispatch been sent by land were here before me.
                    They are stored away; &#8211; my papers (the work of London hours) are put in order, &amp; I am resuming my habitual occupations. I
                    shall not be quite easy till some tidings arrive of the 22 cases on shipboard, &#8211; they will occasion a glorious confusion in the
                    house, &amp; some contrivance to find room for them.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having decided to remain at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> the previous year, Southey had been steadily arranging for his books,
                        which had been stored by friends in London and the West Country, to be collected together.</note> When they are all arranged I
                    shall feel that there are as many materials collected as it will be possible for me to get thro, in the longest lease of life: &#8211; a
                        <del>xxx</del> feeling more humiliating than melancholy: &#8211; there is nothing melancholy in looking forward to another world;
                    but it is humiliating to think how little one&#8217;s knowledge can amount to in this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I am glad that I have seen you &amp; <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">Mrs May</ref>, &amp;
                    those sweet children of yours. Remember me to her very kindly &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> with me.
                    Remember me also to your brothers &amp; make my respects to your excellent Mother.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> May&#8217;s
                        brothers included Joseph May, the first-born, of Hale manor, Wiltshire and William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), who spent much of
                        his life pursuing the family&#8217;s business interests in Portugal and Brazil. Their mother was Mary, n&#233;e Coppendale
                        (1745&#8211;1824).</note> &#8211; I think with great pleasure of the three days which past in Hampshire, &amp; shall heave many a sigh at
                    the thoughts of your Hale strong beer, when the miserable ale of this country puts me in mind of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I heard of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hairs sad loss at Bristol.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> With her
                        husband, a member of the British Factory at Lisbon. In 1797 John May had considered marrying Charlotte Hair, presumably their
                        daughter. Southey met the Hair family on both of his visits to Portugal.</note> What news from Lisbon? &#8211; The more success of
                    our blockade is talked of the more sensible I am of its cruelty &amp; impolicy. How long will it be before nations shall
                    practically acknowledge the first axioms of morality, &amp; the plainest laws of Xtianity!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yours very affectionately </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>