<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.887</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2009</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 348&#8211;349.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.887" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="887" type="letter">
        <head>887. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1804-01-21">21
                        January 1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ C
                        W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ <del>Wynnstay</del>/ <del>Wrexham</del> Stone Buildings/ Lincoln&#8217;s Inn/
                        London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; WREXHAM/ 202<lb />Postmark: [partial] FREE/ Ja 26/ 180<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 348&#8211;349.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> This time ten years, Wynn &#8211; you &amp; I were at Oxford together, &amp; in those ten years I have had my full share
                    of the contingencies of life. To live fast, is something more than a metaphor, we see it in the system of nature. the short life
                    of the ephemera is all action &amp; active joy &#8211; the toad in a stone<note n="" place="foot" resp="editors">An example of anecdotal
                        accounts of toads being found in stones is that of the <title>Annual Register, or a View of the History, Politicks, and
                            Literature, of the Year 1761</title>, which includes the account of Ambroise Par&#233;, the physician to Henry III of France,
                        who reported that &#8216;Being at my seat near the village of Meudon, and overlooking a quarryman whom I had sent to break some very
                        large and hard stones, in the middle of one we found a huge toad, full of life and without any visible aperture by which it
                        could get there. The laborer told me it was not the first time he had met with a toad and the like creatures within huge
                        blocks of stone.&#8217;</note> lives perhaps from one world to another. I have lived fast, for the wear &amp; tear of mind as well
                    as body must be taken into account &#8211; &amp; I am more than ten years older in constitution since you &amp; I used to
                        <del>think</del> talk over your Claret till midnight in Skeleton Corner.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Anatomy
                        School of Christ Church College, Oxford, where dead bodies were brought in for study.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now that this sort of mood is come upon &lt;me&gt; I will tell you some of my speculations upon this world of
                    mysteries in which we are placed. What the old Bards held of progressive transmigration appears to me a probable belief. There is
                    in all of us a living power distinct from intellect, or connected with it (as it surely is) by some hypostatic union altogether
                    unintelligible to our present capacities. I mean that wonderful wisdom which directs our bodily &amp; involuntary actions, that
                    makes &amp; disposes the secretions &#8211; &amp; fills the bosom with milk as the embryo ripens in the womb, this truly aweful life has
                    perhaps past through a long series of ascending habitations, gradually acquiring those instincts, which are in it perfect wisdom.
                    How well would such an opinion explain the original difference of human character, for the wolf &amp; the sheep would be equally
                    high in the scale, &amp; the <del>xxx</del> Life which took one road would go on in it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of all living being which have locomotion fish seem the lowest &#8211; Even propagation is with them a single &amp;
                    wholly selfish act, the male not impregnating the spawn till it has been ejected by the female &#8211; &amp; then both sexes without
                    sense or feeling eat it indiscriminately. The Whale &amp; Dolphin species are alone to be excepted. Animals have the &#959;&#961;&#947;&#951;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Anger&#8217; or &#8216;passion&#8217;.</note> most powerfully, but birds are of a higher nature &#8211; for they
                    have the cannibal affection, altogether distinct from the sexual appetite &#8211; &amp; lust is in them actually refined with love, &#8211;
                    that is the feeling which the appetite causes, exists after its cause is extinct. the greater length of life allotted to birds is
                    remarkable, &amp; at present inexplicable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are some valuable facts respecting instinct which rather strengthen a hypothesis of progressive life, for if
                    a link of the chain be broken instinct is destroyed. hens hatched in the Egyptian ovens<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        contemporary of Southey&#8217;s, the horticultural writer, John Claudius Loudon (1783&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>) mentions that
                        &#8216;hatching by artificial heat is an Egyptian practice&#8217; in <title>An Encyclopaedia of Agriculture: Comprising the Theory and
                            Practice of the Valuation, Transfer, Laying Out, Improvement, and Management of Landed Property: and the Cultivation and
                            Economy of the Animal and Vegetable Productions of Agriculture, Including all the Latest Improvements: A General History
                            of Agriculture in all Countries: and a Statistical View of its Present State, with Suggestions for its Future Progress in
                            the British Isles</title>, 2 vols (London, 1825), II, p. 1039.</note> sell for half the price of those <del>hat</del>
                    reared in the natural way, for they will very seldom sit. So again, the ducklings hatched under a hen take to the water &#8211; the
                    Drakes attempt to tread the hens instead of their own females. <hi rend="ital">how</hi> these things are who can tell? but <hi rend="ital">so</hi> they are, &amp; the more we know, the less shall we be disposed to disbelieve any thing because it is
                    mysterious.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I ever tell you a very extraordinary fact which happened under my own eyes? I had promised to kill some of the
                    horned beetles for <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>, &#8211; for the insect is common about the New Forest &amp;
                    rare, or unknown, in the other parts of England. he had directed me to pour oil upon them, which to all insects is certain death.
                    I had killed a female thus, who might have struggled with the poison for about two minutes &#8211; certainly not longer. I placed a buck
                    (as they are called for the love of their horns) in the same saucer, &amp; in like manner pourd about a teaspoonful of oil over
                    him, so as to touch every part. he also experienced the same suffocation, went thro the same struggles, &amp; was apparently
                    exhausted &amp; in the very point of death when he discovered the dead female. a paroxysm of lust came upon him, &amp; that insect
                    lived a full half-hour, in vain attempts to copulate with the dead body, which he could never so place as to effect his purpose. I
                    was as much shocked as astonished. perhaps a more extraordinary fact has <del>been</del> never been observed. Excitement will I
                    believe always protract death. one whom I knew fell into the water &amp; was taken out senseless &#8211; he had felt no pain &#8211; for the
                    accident was sudden. a person who had attempted suicide by drowning &amp; was restored, relates that the sufferings were long
                    &amp; painful, &#8211; the mind had been in the highest possible state of stimulation. &#8211; It is well known that in <del>cases</del> times
                    of contagion they who fear the disease rarely escape or survive it, but how many are the instances wherein courageous affection or
                        <del>danger</del> duty have braved &amp; escaped the danger!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now do I believe that among all the letters which in the course of thirteen years you have received from me &#8211; you
                        <del>had</del> never had one of this complexion before.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The subject-matter was unusual
                        for Southey but close to that of <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Anthony Carlisle&#8217;s</ref> Croonian lectures (Royal
                        Society lectures in the biological sciences) of 1804, on the motion and muscular form of fish. It is possible that in their
                        now lost, correspondence, Carlisle and Southey were discussing such matters.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-01-21">Saturday 21. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1804.</date>
          </p>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>. Keswick.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>