<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1586</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2708</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1586" type="letter">
        <head>1586. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-02-21">21 February
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The papers which you wrote respecting the state of the navy are I believe here, where you left them, in the little
                    writing desk. I think this application of the Captains affords a good opportunity for bringing the subject forward in the
                        Courier, as soon as M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarke &amp; the Duke of York shall be so far
                    forgotten as to leave room in the newspapers &amp; in the public mind for any thing else.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post
                        from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne
                        Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for which promotion was
                        arranged.</note> Send me any thing else that occurs to you upon this business, &#8211; but in particular, if you can, the exact pay
                    of officers of every description as far back as you can go, &amp; the additions which may have been made in it from time to time.
                    I will put the materials together in a series of Courier essays,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not produce
                        articles for the <title>Courier</title> on naval officers&#8217; pay.</note> &#8211; &amp; send them previously to their publication to
                    you in a Government frank.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has been very ill, &#8211; &amp; I believe the first cause of her illness was some
                    such cursed companions as you got rid of at Bristol. They brought on tenesmus,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A spurious
                        feeling of the need to evacuate the bowels, with little or no stool passed.</note>. &#8211; &amp; we were very apprehensive that
                    premature labour would have been the consequence. Leeching &amp; laudanum have removed the effect but not the cause, &#8211; &amp; she
                    is &lt;still&gt; very much out of spirits. She was confined to her bed for more than a week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be sorry that poor M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rathbone is dead.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Rathbone (1757&#8211;1809), a Liverpool ship-owner and merchant and a Quaker, who opposed the slave trade.</note> I had a
                    letter last week from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Martin<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Julia Martin, n&#233;e Smith
                        (dates unknown) born in Norwich, sister of James Edward Smith (1759&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>) the botanist, who married in
                        1804 Thomas Martin (1769&#8211;1850), first a Unitarian minister in Yarmouth, then a Liverpool merchant and Secretary of the
                        Liverpool Royal Institution. The Martins were members of the <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William Roscoe</ref>
                        circle; Southey met them on his visit to Liverpool in February 1808.</note> telling me so. This letter expressed a hope of
                    seeing you again at Liverpool one of these days, &#8211; where it seems you are in great odour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been working incessantly at those books which it was necessary to send back as soon as possible,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> had borrowed the following books for Southey from the Advocates
                        Library in Edinburgh for his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819): Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de
                            Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784); Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi et
                            Viaggi</title> (1550&#8211;1559); Jos&#233; Gumilla (1686&#8211;1750), <title>Histoire Naturelle, Civile et Geographique de
                            L&#8217;Orenoque</title> (1758), a French version of the original <title>Historia Natural, Civil, &amp; Geografica de las
                            Naciones situadas en las Riveras del Rio Orinoco</title> (1731).</note> &#8211; for unluckily there <del>was</del> is scarcely
                    any book that has ever fallen <del>into</del> in my way from which so much was to be extracted as from one of these in three
                    closely printed octavo volumes. They gave me three weeks hard work, &amp; now I must work double tides to fetch up my lea way,
                    &amp; get copy ready for the press, &#8211; for here also an unexpected hindrance has arisen. I had written twelve months ago all the
                    account I could then recollect of a famous voyage down the Orellana,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Teixeira (d.
                        1641) was a Portuguese explorer who became, in 1637, the first European to travel up the entire length of the Amazon, an
                        expedition which helped extend Portuguese colonial possessions there at the expense of Spain. Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;1676?),
                        a member of Texeira&#8217;s expedition, published <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title> (1641). Southey
                        read of the voyage in Joa&#771;o Pinto Ribeiro (d. 1649), <title>Observa&#231;&#245;es Historicas e Criticas para Servirem de Memorias ao
                            Systema da Diplomatica Portugueza Oferecidas ao Serenissimo Principe do Brazil</title> (1798). Francisco de Orellana
                        (1511&#8211;1546) died during a disastrous expedition, on which only 44 of 300 men survived, navigating the river that was then
                        named after him but is now known as the Amazon. His exploits were described in Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de Oviedo (1478&#8211;1557),
                            <title>Historia General y Natural de las Indias</title> (1542).</note> &#8211; lo &amp; behold among the books which have since
                    come to hand is so copious a history of this very voyage, that I had<del>x</del> between fifty &amp; sixty pages to write for the
                    middle of the first volume, where I only expected to have had a half a dozen to transcribe. I have broken the neck of this
                    business, &amp; shall in another week get thro it. This second batch of the first volume has taken me a great deal of time so much
                    has there been to fill up, &amp; to collect from very numerous authorities, &#8211; the last portion will neither require half the time
                    or trouble &#8211; the main part there will be smooth transcribing. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This morning after a long interruption I again resumed Kehama, &amp; hope to get on rapidly. There is another
                    number for you upon the stocks, &amp; I shall endeavour to <del>xxxxxxxxx xxxxxxxxx</del> finish the transcription with as little
                    delay as possible. The truth is that work how I will business seems to accumulate upon my hands, Here will be the Quarterly Review
                    published this week, &#8211; &amp; I have no time to lose in setting about my account of the Otaheitean mission for the second
                        number.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the
                            South Sea Islands</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61.</note> Here are my Letters from
                        Portugal<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Letters from Portugal&#8217; was a projected book that Southey never
                        completed.</note> &amp; the additional Espriellas<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey intended to publish a
                        fourth volume of his three-volume work <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title> (1807), but this
                        never appeared.</note> standing stock still. I shall hardly be able to take breath till my History of Brazil is
                        compleated.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was
                        published in 1810.</note> The Annual comes out this week.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Review
                            for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), in which Southey reviewed Thomas Clarkson, <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and
                            Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808), 127&#8211;148;
                            <title>Report of the Committee of the African Institution, Read to the General Meeting on the 15th July, 1807, Together
                            with the Rules and Regulations which were then Adopted for the Government of the Society</title> (1807), 149&#8211;152; Thomas
                        Zouch (1737&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224&#8211;235;
                        Robert Drury (1687&#8211;1734?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Adventures of Robert Drury, During Fifteen Years Captivity on the
                            Island of Madagascar; Containing a Description of that Island; an Account of its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; With
                            an Account of the Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion, and Civil Policy of the Inhabitants: to Which is Added, a
                            Vocabulary of the Madagascar Language. Written by Himself, and now Carefully Revised and Corrected from the
                            Original</title> (1807), 253&#8211;263; <title>Account of the Life and Writings of James Bruce ... Author of Travels to Discover
                            the Source of the Nile: in the Years 1768, 1769, 1770, 1771, 1772 &amp; 1773</title> (1808), 263&#8211;270; <title>Dona Ignez de
                            Castro, a Tragedy, from the Portuguese of Nicola Luiz, with Remarks on the History of that Unfortunate Lady</title>, tr.
                        John Adamson (1787&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>) (1808), 572&#8211;574.</note> &#8211; it shall be sent you with the edition of Thalaba,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) was
                        published in 1809.</note> of which only a single sheet more remains to be printed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had dreadful winds here, but <del>none</del> no such floods as seem to have deluged all the south &amp;
                    west of England. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt</ref> there tells me the people in Taunton whose houses
                        <del>were</del> are near the bridge, have been obliged to live in the upper rooms for a month. She is lodging at Bishops
                        Hull,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A village to the west of Taunton, now in its suburbs.</note> &amp; she says
                    John Capon<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A woolstapler of Bishop&#8217;s Hull, Somerset (his dates are unknown).</note> is
                    expecting to hear from you. Lloyd also wonders you do not write.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Your nephew</ref> is the softest, roundest fellow, &#8211; the most delicate kissing that can
                    be conceived, &amp; with a language of his own. You would delight in him. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> will
                    soon walk alone, she is kept back by teething, in which she suffers rather more than Herbert did. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your niece</ref> grows, &amp; begins to work &amp; read well. There is about to be a book
                    opened in which all her rewards are to be entered, &#8211; for she has already earned three sixpences for good behaviour, &#8211; &amp; these
                    rewards are to be laid out by me when I go to London, or any great town. &#8211; A good contrivance for <del>giving</del> &lt;making&gt;
                    her happy by sixpenny worths first, &#8211; &amp; then giving her the whole sum total of happiness at last. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; As for what is doing any where except in the House of Commons the newspapers say nothing. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clark<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to the current scandal surrounding Prince
                        Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from
                        1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke
                        (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for which promotion was arranged.</note> has
                    made a more effectual diversion in favour of Bonaparte &#8211; than we are likely to do in favour of the Spaniards.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is a good effusion which has been sent me upon one of his Majestys Lent Preachers &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent1"> If you wish to be pious &amp; mean to keep Lent</l>
          <l rend="indent1"> Pray go to the Chapel &amp; hear D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dent,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            Untraced.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent1"> And I&#8217;ll be damnd for you if you don&#8217;t repent.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent3">
            <date when="1809-02-21"> Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 21. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>