<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1009</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2131</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                        Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 135&#8211;139..  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        302&#8211;305.Dating note: [Kirkpatrick&#8217;s note:] Warter misdates the letter &#8220;24&#8221; December.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1009" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1009" type="letter">
        <head>1009. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1804-12-29">29 December
                        18[04]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/
                        Staffordshire<lb />Postmark: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                        Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 135&#8211;139.<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        302&#8211;305.<lb />Dating note: [Kirkpatrick&#8217;s note:] Warter misdates the letter &#8220;24&#8221; December.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Lovest thou a joke. Mary Barker?</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Lovest thou a joke like me?</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> If thou lovest not a joke</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> By the Lord be it spoke</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Never more will I love thee.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Look you what is going to the Review, if <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref> will put it in.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr. Dallas has prefixed to this novel<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> were reviewing Robert Charles Dallas (1754&#8211;1824), <title>Aubrey: a
                            Novel</title> (1804) for the <title>Annual Review</title>. However the review of this work (which appeared in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 551&#8211;553) does not seem to have been by Southey according to letter 1093
                        of this edition which states that his article was suppressed.</note> an engraving of the Labradore stone which represents the
                    profile of Louis XVI.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XVI (1754&#8211;1793), King of France from 1774&#8211;1792.</note> perhaps
                    the following paragraph from a provincial newspaper may furnish him with a companion print equally extraordinary for his next
                    publication. &#8216;The mountain commonly called Causey Pike near <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, having been observed
                    to present in its outline the exact profile of his present Magisty, the Pike forming the nose, a party of Gentlemen on Thursday
                    last ascended this difficult eminence, &amp; breaking a bottle of wine upon the summit, as is the custom when a ship is named,
                    they gave it the classical name of Georgris (Greek for Georges nose) in commemoration of this eternal likeness, executed by the
                    hand of Nature herself. They then drank another bottle to his Majistys health, &amp; sung God save the King while all the mountain
                    Echoes joined in the chorus of loyalty.&#8217; <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Causey Pike lies in the Newlands valley, south
                        of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> and visible from <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>. Seen
                        from Derwentwater, it displays a prominent bump on the ridge line near the summit, named &#8216;Georgris&#8217; by Southey because he
                        thought the bump made it resemble George III (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) in profile. In
                        letter 984 of this edition, Southey expressed his intention of sending &#8216;a paragraph about it to the Whitehaven paper&#8217;.</note>
                    The Labradore stone<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> An engraving of the Labradore stone, a small natural gem in which the
                        profile of Louis XVI could be discerned, is prefixed to the dedication of Dallas&#8217;s novel, <title>Aubrey</title>, and the stone
                        is described in the preface. See Dallas, <title>Aubrey: a Novel</title>, 4 vols (London, 1804), I, xxii&#8211;xxiv.</note> is nothing to this. Pyrrhuss ring<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        According to Pliny the Elder (AD 23&#8211;79), the stone in the ring worn by Pyrrhus, King of Epire (319&#8211;272 BC) had the figures of
                        Apollo and the nine muses in its veins.</note> &amp; the head of Chaucer<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> An agate
                        given to Hans Sloane (1660&#8211;1753; <title>DNB</title>) some time before 1740 and displayed at the British Museum since 1761. The
                        stone is described as a &#8216;rough Egyptian pebble, broke into two Parts; on each Piece is a perfect Resemblance of the Head of
                        Chaucer . . . entirely the Work of Nature&#8217;, in the catalogue <title>The General Contents of the British Museum</title>
                        (London, 1762), p. 85.</note> in the Museum are of the same description as the French wonder.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, the Labradore stone.</note> but what King&#8217;s head was ever like a mountain before? &amp; how
                    admirably, says the Paragraph writer &#8211; has Nature typified the greatness of his character, the elevation of his rank, the
                    immoveableness of his resolutions, &amp; that exalted piety which always looks up to Heaven!&#8217; &#8212;What newspaper you ask. &#8211; I made
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not know that Price has written any book about Spain, &amp; should be very glad to see the book if he has. his
                    Essays on the Picturesque are very satisfactory &amp; quite as good as they could be for their given purpose.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The book was by Udal ap Rhys, <title>An Account of the Most Remarkable Places and Curiosities in
                            Spain and Portugal</title> (1749). Price is an anglicised form of ap Rhys which led Southey to mistake the author and look
                        for a work on Spain by his contemporary Uvedale Price (1747&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), author of an <title>Essay on the
                            Picturesque</title> (1796), rather than one by Price&#8217;s grandfather Udal ap Rhys/Uvedale Tomkyns Price (1685&#8211;1764).
                        According to Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick (&#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD,
                        Harvard, 1967), pp. 144&#8211;147), after Southey wrote to Barker to declare his ignorance of the book, Sir Edward Littleton then
                        wrote on the blank third page of Southey&#8217;s letter, confusingly: &#8216;Uvedale Price Esq. of Foxly wrote an account of Spain said to
                        be a Plagiarism from some Spanish writer; a Pamphlet in ridicule of Whister; Fine Lady&#8217;s Catechism Conversation between 2 Lap
                        Dogs, Scipio &amp; Braganza&#8217;. Because Littleton still failed to distinguish between grandfather and grandson, Southey
                        continued to mistake the author.</note> Beckfords Tale is called Vathek an Arabian name Senhora. he wrote it in French, &amp;
                    the English translation is by Mr. Henley, who has added some of the most learned notes that ever appeared in any Book whatever!
                        &#8211;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French original of William Beckford&#8217;s (1760&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>)
                            <title>Vathek</title> was published in 1787, after the publication of its English translation with notes by Samuel Henley
                        (1740&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) in 1784.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I <hi rend="ital">did</hi> tell you that the secret history of the persons tried for returning from transportation
                    is that they never were transported at all, having by dint of money evaded the execution of the sentence. If <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir E</ref>. will consider the almost impossibility of getting from Botany Bay to
                    England, &amp; also how much less public &amp; less attended to the shipping off a gang of transported convicts is than any other
                    sentence of the law whatsoever, he will perceive that this is not very unlikely. I was told so by the man in the world who of all
                    my acquaintance is the least likely to believe any thing upon light grounds &#8211; &amp; he added that he had by accident received full
                    proof of what he was affirming &#8211; saying &#8211; it is a thing one does not like to say &#8211; because it will not be believed. I do not
                    believe that he has told any person but myself.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Southey&#8217;s friend, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, secretary to the Speaker of the House of Commons.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> has been providentially preserved in a strange way. he &amp; his
                        captain<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain (later Admiral) Henry Heathcote (1777&#8211;1851), in command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> 1803&#8211;1805.</note> quarrelled &#8211; he was brought to a Court Martial &#8211; for neglect of duty,
                    disobedience of orders, &amp; contempt of his superior officer. On the two first charges he was acquitted &#8211; but found guilty of
                    having said to his Captain, when accused of these offences &#8211; I beg your pardon Sir &#8211; I must contradict you. This is &#8216;contempt&#8217; in
                    the Court Martial sense &#8211; contempt is a crime &#8211; &amp; he is sentenced to be dismissed the ship. While he was under arrest the
                    attempt upon the Lilly took place, &amp; the Lieutenant who went in his stead fell!<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14
                        August 1804, the boats of Thomas&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French
                        privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the
                        Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or wounded. Southey had suspected that his brother
                        was among the dead, but he was absent from the raid because he had been placed under arrest. Charles Hayman (d. 1804) was made
                        first lieutenant in his stead and died in the attack.</note> &#8211; I do not wonder that Sailors are predestinarians. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is alive &amp; well. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc has four vignettes thus disposed. One in the title page &#8211; a groupe of all sorts of things Welsh &amp; Aztecan
                    among them Madocs shield, bearing three Eaglets displayed, which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> quarters,
                    being descended lineally from Madocs brother Rhodri.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The engraved titlepage of
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) appears as Southey describes it here. Rhodri (1135?&#8211;1195) was the son of Owain Gwynedd (c.
                        1100&#8211;1170; <title>DNB</title>) and brother of Dafydd (died 1203), from whom Wynn claimed descent.</note> &#8211; the Palm Tree &amp;
                    Cross engraved above the exordial lines. &amp; two others from the poem placed on the blank titles to the first &amp; second parts
                    of the poem. the one a ship in full sail &#8211; the other the Great Snake at the Cavern mouth.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) has only three illustrations: the engraved titlepage with Wynn&#8217;s shield upon a <hi rend="ital">troph&#233;e</hi>; the palm and cross upon the rock (after the Table of Contents); and the snake before the cave,
                        engraved on the titlepage for the second part, &#8216;Madoc in Aztlan&#8217; (bound incorrectly after 320 instead of after 184). It is
                        probable that the image of the ship by Nicholas Pocock (1740&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>) was omitted because Southey was
                        displeased with the vessel&#8217;s anachronistic modernity; see Southey to Joseph Cottle, 25 August 1805, Letter 1097.</note> &#8211; If the poem sells we will do as you say
                    &#8211; but I am not sanguine in my expectations. this night I expect to finish &amp; send off the last parcel of notes &#8211; &amp; if they
                    be not delayed on the road a fortnight will compleat the printing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> has had neither illness nor inconvenience from
                    vaccination.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May had been inoculated against smallpox, using cowpox serum; a method
                        popularised by Edward Jenner (1749&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>An Inquiry Into the Causes and Effects of the Variol&#230;
                            Vaccin&#230;</title> (1798).</note> I also have seen Richardsons letters,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Correspondence of Samuel Richardson</title>, ed. Anna Laetitia Barbauld, 6 vols (1804).</note> &amp; was more
                    pleased at finding him a good man than disappointed by finding him a dull correspondant. It is a most worthless book more
                    worthless than anything I ever saw except <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Mrs. Barebalds</ref> essay prefixed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>xxx</del> from all I know <del>xxx</del> rather suppose <del>xxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count Burnnetski</ref> yawns at his leisure in Poland where he has nothing to do but to
                    say what is English for this thing &amp; that thing when they ask him. &#8211; John<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John the
                        jackass, whose lovesickness Southey had previously described to Mary Barker; see Southey to Mary Barker, 10 December [1804] ,
                        Letter 1000.</note> seems to have got the better of his unfortunate attachment. he is a good ass, &amp; I am very fond of him
                    &#8211; for he is as fond of me as a dog could be. Come with the first spring weather. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is poorly &amp; I do not know what is the matter with her. she is being physicked for it however. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>A Merry Xmas &amp; a happy New Year.</p>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-12-29">Saturday. Dec 29. 18[MS torn]</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>