<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1046</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2168</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4850 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 74&#8211;79.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1046" type="letter">
        <head>1046. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1805-03-09">9 March
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 5 Apr<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4850 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 74&#8211;79.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-03-09">Saturday night. March 9. 1805.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for what you say about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> at the vacation, &amp;
                    thank you as truly as if your invitation were needful. We stay here the summer &#8211; &amp; here he may come if he pleases &#8211; or if he
                    does not please it must be his own fault if his finances do not allow him to ramble, or remain. but I suppose he likes <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> well enough to repeat his visit. &#8211; He has a wish to write a History of the Crusades
                    &#8211; which I encourage in him as a worthy &amp; adequate object; &amp; if the inclination continue in him shall set him to learn
                    Arabic for the purpose, which he is young enough to do. he will not I think object to <hi rend="ital">begin</hi> the language. The
                    subject is happily chosen for his chivalrous feelings, &#8211; &amp; for its own splendour &amp; exceeding importance.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was never completed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pray you, do not mention <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> again by the title of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. I have Uncles of the name of Mister, &#8211; but no brother. &amp; if ever <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>
                    &amp; you should meet under my roof, as by Gods blessing I hope you may, he would meet you with a very unMisterlike sort of
                    feeling, as his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> best friend; &amp; you would leave him with a
                    great liking for a man who has all the good parts of a Sailor without the bad ones, &amp; enough of the costume without the
                    pedantry: I love <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> dearly. we are near enough of an age to have all brotherly
                    recollections of boy hood, &amp; to have had our first serious feelings in common, to have partaken family distress when Harry was
                    too young to know any thing about it. So that as far as regards all my earliest life &amp; remembrances <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is to me the last of my family. I do not think that ever<del>y</del> human being had
                    a more affectionate heart. If he lives he is now on the road to promotion. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> never began his life of Lessing.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s intention to write the life of Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781), for which he travelled to
                        Germany and attended the University of G&#246;ttingen in 1799, was never achieved.</note> he made very ample collections for the
                    Introduction, which would have been a History of German literature: <hi rend="ital">very ample</hi>, for I have <hi rend="ital">seen</hi> them. but concerning Lessing nothing was ever written, &amp; in all probability never will. he has certainly given
                    up the intention altogether.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Review Madoc in the Annual. I was in hopes <hi rend="ital">you</hi> could have done it in the Critical also.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was given a complimentary review by Taylor in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806),
                        604&#8211;613. The poem was negatively reviewed in the <title>Critical Review</title>, ns 7 (1806), 72&#8211;83, by Charles Valentine Le
                        Grice (1773&#8211;1858).</note> We have talked here of the facility of writing satire defensively if need were, &#8211; only talked, &amp;
                    without the slightest intention of so doing. but if such retaliation were ever provoked from me, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Hunt<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Higgs Hunt (1780&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>) was joint-editor of the
                            <title>Critical Review</title> from 1805&#8211;1807, with Joseph Mawman (1763&#8211;1827). Southey had been called &#8216;an egregious
                        poetical coxcomb&#8217; in a review of his <title>Metrical Tales</title> for the <title>Critical Review</title>, 3rd series, 4
                        (February 1805), 118&#8211;121 (118).</note> should be one of the aggressors &#8211; what a happy motto would the old song furnish &#8211; a <hi rend="ital">hunting</hi> we will go. I hope by this time you have received Madoc. &#8211; if it does not get into your hands there I
                    am afraid of being bedaubed with water-gruel by <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Barbauld</ref>, for whom in spite of reciprocal civilities in all the externals of life, &amp; in spite of all the good that
                    was once in her, I have a dislike personally from instinct, &amp; literarily from reason &amp; feeling &amp; principle.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Would I could send you to another Review! for you like the work, &amp; much as I dislike reviews for the mischief
                    they inevitably do, yet as they will continue to exist, it is of consequence to occupy the posts. Are any of the new ones worth
                    entering into? &#8211; for you need only offer &amp; they will jump at such a prize.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your anecdote of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cuthbert &amp; the Gout should be sent to my friend Kinglake,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Kinglake (1765&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), an expert on gout.</note> who I suspect will
                    cure ninety nine patients by the practise, &amp; kill the hundredth.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stories of the
                        miraculous cures effected by St Cuthbert of Lindisfarne (c. 634&#8211;687), both in his lifetime and, after his death by virtue of
                        his relics, abound.</note> he writes abominably ill, but is a man of sterling sense in all things.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am historifying totis viribus,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;with all my strength&#8217;.</note>
                    &amp; should any circumstances bring or send <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to England should in all
                    likelihood put my first volume to press next winter.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; was
                        never completed.</note> Me judice<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;in my judgement&#8217;.</note> I am a good poet
                    but a better historian, because tho I read other poets &amp; am humbled, I read other historians with a very different feeling.
                    They who have talents want industry or virtue, they who have industry want talents. One writes like a French sensualist, another
                    like a Scotch scoundrel, calculating how to make the most per-sheet with the least expence of labour. one like a slave, another
                    like a fool. Now I know myself to be free from these staminal defects, &amp; feel that when the subject deserves it I write with a
                    poets feeling, without the slightest affectation of style or ornament, going always straight forward to the meaning by the
                    shortest road. My golden rule is to relate <hi rend="ital">every thing</hi>, as briefly, as perspicuously, &amp; as rememberably,
                    as possible. &#8211; I begin however to feel my brain budding for poetry, having lain fallow since November, &#8211; &amp; if I could afford
                    to do it should willingly finish Kehama<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, published 1810.</note> &#8211; but being like Shakesperes Apothecary lean, &amp; obliged to do
                    what I do not like,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Romeo and Juliet</title>, Act 5, scene 1, lines 39&#8211;56: <lg>
              <l rend="indent3"> &#8216;I do remember an apothecary, &#8211;</l>
              <l rend="indent3"> And hereabouts he dwells, &#8211; which late I noted</l>
              <l rend="indent3"> In tatter&#8217;d weeds, with overwhelming brows</l>
              <l rend="indent3"> &#8230; a needy man.&#8217;</l>
            </lg>
          </note>;my ways &amp; means lead me another way, &amp; I am prosing, not
                    altogether against my will, &amp; yet not with my will.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is almost heart-broken by the loss of his brother
                    in the Abergavenny &#8211; his best &amp; favourite brother.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wordsworth (1772&#8211;1805),
                        captain of the East Indiaman, the <hi rend="ital">Earl of Abergavenny</hi>, went down with his ship on the Shambles rocks off
                        Portland Bill, on 5 February 1805.</note> I have been twice over with him, &amp; never witnessed such affliction as his &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">his sisters</ref>. &#8211; Will you not come up to us before we quit the country that
                    you may see him? &#8211; if for no other motive &#8211; for soberly &amp; solemnly I do believe that of all the present generation he will
                    leave behind him the most durable &amp; valuable memorials &#8211; this I say knowingly of what he has written, hardly expecting credit
                    even from you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What proportion of your debt from Hamilton<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Hamilton (dates
                        unknown), owner of the <title>Critical Review</title> 1799&#8211;1804. His departure from the <title>Critical</title> left Southey
                        and Taylor unpaid for reviews they had written.</note> do you recover? I know not what my own is &#8211; <del>probably</del>
                    &lt;perhaps&gt; as much more than I expected as yours has proved &#8211; &amp; therefore ask to know whether it be worth while to make
                    any <del>xxxxxxx</del> enquiry concerning it. &#8211; I love Milton too well to like Bishop Hall.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Hall (1574&#8211;1656; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Exeter, later of Norwich. Hall wrote satires in his
                        youth, but after being ordained he turned to devotional and moralistic works, entering, like Milton, the religious
                        controversies of the Commonwealth period.</note> his style is less pregnant than yours.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have just read <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scotts</ref> Poem<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; with great delight. His
                        phraseology is sometime polluted with modern barbarisms, &amp; <del>xxx</del> sometimes obscure from a sort of unnatural
                        syntax which he seems to like. But it is a delightful poem, &amp; I am ashamed to think that I should speak of its faults
                        which are so infinitesimally little in comparison with its beauties. His conception of story is singularly happy in this as in
                        his ballads. of character there is as much as such limits would admit. his images often good &amp; sometimes, tho rarely,
                        quite excellent. I half envy him one about the foam of a turbid torrent in the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> canto.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Each wave was crested with tawny foam/ Like the mane of a chestnut steed&#8217;, Canto 1, stanza
                            28.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is instructed to send you Madoc. you cannot wish to see the book &#8211; more
                        than I do to know how you like it, for I have many qualms of doubt about it.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>