<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1331</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2453</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    12&#8211;15.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1331" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1331" type="letter">
        <head>1331. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-06-11">11
                        June 1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.
                        P./ Acton Park/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    12&#8211;15.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-06-11">Thursday June 11. 1807</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Day after day have I looked in the papers to see your return announced, that my <del>letters</del> epistles might
                    bear a red letter mark at the post office:<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was eager to hear of Wynn&#8217;s return to
                        parliament after the general election because he wished to avail himself of Wynn&#8217;s MP&#8217;s privilege of franking mail.</note> but
                    never could I find it till yesterday evening when the rascally Courier gave a list of all the returns.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>The Courier</title> for Thursday 11 June 1807 listed all &#8216;English members who were in the Last
                        Parliament and are not in the Present&#8217;.</note> &amp; yesterday I could not write, &#8211; for a whole hundred weight of books made
                    their appearance from the carriers, &amp; I was engaged with Portugueze Jesuits as long as my eyes would let me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Specimens shall be waiting for you when you reach London, &#8211; a dismal book you will find it worthy of a groan
                    whenever it is mentioned<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807),
                        co-edited with Grosvenor Charles Bedford, and published, to Southey&#8217;s dismay, with numerous errors.</note> &#8211; . The small
                    edition of Madoc<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second, duodecimo, edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1807).</note>
                    ought to have been advertised a fortnight ago &#8211; tho there &lt;are&gt; not above half a dozen alterations I shall direct <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Artaxerxes</ref> to send you a copy., &#8211; for it will be more lendable than the quarto, &amp;
                    one alteration (at the beginning of the interview with Llewelyn) greatly improves the passage by removing a clumsy abruptness in
                    the speech of Madoc.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this alteration see Part I, Book 13 of <title>Madoc</title>, ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, vol. II of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004),
                        p. 91.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are three, or perhaps four sheets of Espriella<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from
                            England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> still unprinted &#8211; It will
                    certainly be finished in <del>ten or</del> a fortnight: &amp; Palmerin<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of
                            England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> about the
                    same time. I expect the proof of the preface to the latter every day &#8211; the only proof which I see of it. The rest I left to <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> revision, for the sake of accommodating the printer &amp; not keeping his
                    types standing. He is a young beginner with little capital, whom I wish to serve, because when quite a boy he used to bring my
                    proofs to me at Bristol.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The printer of <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de
                            Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807) was <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">William Pople</ref>.</note> &#8211; was then one of the very finest boys I ever saw &amp; is now a man far above the common
                    standard of intellect &amp; morals. This preface is very bibliographical &amp; dull &#8211; but it contains all that can be made out
                    about the history of the Book &amp; of its author.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Next I go to press with the Cid,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of <title>Chronicle of
                            the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica
                            Particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541)
                        and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632).</note> &#8211; not however till certain books from Madrid arrive, which <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref> has sent for. I think this will certainly be the most curious
                        <del>chival</del> piece of chivalrous history that has ever appeared in our language. In the winter I must visit London to
                    compleat the introduction to it, &amp; the notes from books which will be to be found either at the Museum<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> or at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> To take advantage of the library of Spanish books assembled by <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Henry Richard Vassall-Fox</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My progress in S America is more satisfactory than that of our troops in the same country. I am in want of two
                    books &#8211; a Latin Hist: of Paraguay by P. Nicholas del Techo:<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicol&#225;s del Techo (dates
                        unknown), <title>Historia de la Provincia del Paraguay de la Compania de Jesus</title> (1673).</note> of which there is a
                    mutilated translation in Churchill,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Awnsham Churchill (1658&#8211;1728;
                            <title>DNB</title>),<title> A Collection of Voyages and Travels</title> (1744&#8211;1745).</note> and the France Antartique of
                        Thevet.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet (1516?-1592), <title>Singularitez de la France
                            Antarctique</title> (1557).</note> The former I must wait patiently for. But with respect to French Books my readiest way
                    will be to make out a list of all the titles I can collect and put <del>them</del> it into a booksellers hands to send &amp;
                    search for them in Paris. My first volume will I trust be written by the end of the year.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> &#8211; if I chose to sell it out &amp;
                    out as the phrase is, I might certainly get five hundred pounds for it, but it would be folly to do this, <del>xx</del>
                    &lt;considering&gt; the possible profits of a work on such a subject at this time, &amp; the very great value of my materials</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is very much against my inclination to interrupt these two works in both of which I take so much interest: <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> however writes to me that there is a dispute about the Edinburgh Review &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> wanting to take it out of his hands, in consequence of which he has
                    obtained an injunction on the sale in London &amp; must prepare to carry it on without him, &#8211; in this state of affairs he requests
                    me to review him two or three articles, in what he calls my best manner &#8211; at the Scotch price of ten guineas per sheet. The phrase
                    of my best manner tickled me. &#8211; I told him in reply<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Longmans, 5 June 1807,
                        Letter 1330.</note> that there were many articles of which the value was in exact proportion to the time &amp; trouble
                    bestowed upon them, but that these articles were not of that kind: that I could review no better for an Edinburgh Review than for
                    an Annual one. &amp; that the worst articles he had ever received from me had cost me more time &amp; trouble than the best: &#8211; In
                    such cases every thing depending upon the subject, &amp; the previous knowledge in the writer&#8217;s mind of which he could bring to
                    bear upon it. But that I would do my best, &amp; that upon one of the books which he mentions (Clavigero&#8217;s Mexico<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Javier Clavijero (1731&#8211;1787), <title>Storia Antica del Messico</title>
                        (1780&#8211;1781).</note>) I could promise him a better criticism than he could possibly obtain from any body else. Luckily he is
                    &lt;in&gt; a hurry which must hurry me &amp; when these books arrive I shall get then thro five &amp; twenty guineas worth in
                    about a fortnight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you seen <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turners</ref> new edition in quarto?<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of Turner&#8217;s <title>History of the Anglo Saxons</title> was published by Longmans
                        in 1807.</note> greatly altered amended &amp; enlarged. Some of his beauties still want weeding out. &#8211; but in point of matter
                    collected &amp; faithfully brought forward it stands before any historical work in the language. Have you also seen <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> new poems? some are very childish, &#8211; some very obscure, tho not so to
                    me who understand his opinions &#8211; others are of first rate excellence.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Poems in Two
                            Volumes</title> (1807).</note> Nothing comparable to them is to be found any where except in Shakespere &amp; Milton: of
                    this character are most of the sonnets which relate to the times. I never saw poetry at once so truly philosophical and heroic. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As a literary anecdote to conclude with &#8211; I have found in <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Hebers</ref>
                    Amadis of Greece besides Spenser Mask of Cupid, Sir Philip Sidneys Telmane &amp; Shakesperes Florisel<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had borrowed from Heber, Feliciano de Silva (1491&#8211;1554), <title>Noveno libro de Amad&#237;s de Gaula,
                            cr&#243;nica del muy valiente y esforzado pr&#237;ncipe y caballero de la Ardiente Espada Amad&#237;s de Grecia, hijo de Lisuarte de
                            Grecia, emperador de Constantinopla y de Trapisonda, y rey de Rodas</title> (1530). He found it to be a source for stories
                        and characters in Edmund Spenser (1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title>, Book 3, Canto 12, Philip
                        Sidney (1554&#8211;1586; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Arcadia</title> (1593) and Shakespeare. Florizel, whom Shakespeare dramatised
                        in the <title>Winter&#8217;s Tale</title>, is the subject of de Silva&#8217;s <title>Don Florisel de Niquea</title> (1532). These
                        borrowings are noted in Southey&#8217;s Preface to<title> Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey
                            from the Original Portugueze</title> (London, 1807), p. xliv&#8211;xlv.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have daily been in hopes to hear you were on your way here, &#8211; tho you would not have found me in my glory. My
                        books are not yet shipped, &amp; when they are they must be allowed full six weeks before they can be expected. Meantime I
                        have had the plaisterers in my study, &amp; now the painter has possession of it &#8211; I enter it again on Tuesday. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">his wife</ref> are likely
                        to come here when Parliament lets him loose <del>should</del> if they should that will prevent me from seeing Wales &#8211; for
                        which indeed I cannot well spare time, considering that in the winter I must go to town. &#8211; Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">godson</ref> is a very fine fellow &#8211; I <del>xxxx</del> should like to see whether <hi rend="ital">your</hi> daughter be as like you as <hi rend="ital">
              <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">mine</ref>
            </hi>
                        is for very like you she was till she fell down two days ago and made her upper lip strut out like a snout. Is the Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Strachey whose ship is taken off Dantzick <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Georges</ref> brother
                            Christopher?<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 16 May Captain Christopher Strachey (dates unknown), surrendered
                            his ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Dauntless</hi> to the French at Danzig after grounding and being bombarded by shore
                            batteries.</note> I fear it must be.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>