<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1554</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2676</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Morgan Library, Misc Ray (Oversize), MA
                        4500 [Attached to &#8216;Prospectus of The Friend&#8217;].  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1554" type="letter">
        <head>1554. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1808-12-13">13 December
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Humphrey Senhouse Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / Maryport &#8722;/ Cockermouth./ Single Sheet<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Seal: Red wax with ornamental
                        letter &#8216;S&#8217; and a banner with the words &#8216;IN LABOR QUIES&#8217;<lb />Watermark: 1808<lb />Endorsement: Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>:
                        13.1808/ Robt Southey to H. S./ Proposals for a Periodical Paper by Coleridge &#8211; MS: Morgan Library, Misc Ray (Oversize), MA
                        4500 [Attached to &#8216;Prospectus of The Friend&#8217;]<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-12-13">Dec. 13. 1808</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Senhouse</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is the Prospectus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prospectus for Coleridge&#8217;s self-published
                        journal <title>The Friend</title>, which he produced in 1809 and 1810. For the text see <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara
                        E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton, 1969).</note> of something which if it be carried into effect will embody more sound
                    principles of taste, morals &amp; philosophy, than have ever yet been brought together, but whether <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> will have <hi rend="ital">moral</hi> health enough to put together
                    his ready materials even in this form, is I fear even yet to be doubted . These Proposals are somewhat premature, for as he has
                    chosen to publish by subscription, it is not probable that his lists can be made out in time to begin so early as January; &#8722; &amp;
                    if many copies should go into the country, or to small towns, there will be no means of sending them regularly except by post, &#8722;
                    the m[MS torn] must then be stamped, &amp; stamps frank only a single sheet. This is the plan which will most likely [MS torn]
                    followed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I never felt a fear for Spain till last night &#8211; But if it be true that we are running away from Romana&#8217;s army<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la Romana (1761&#8211;1811), commanded, from 26 November,
                        the remnants of the Spanish army of Galicia that was destroyed by the French on 11 November. Romana&#8217;s troops assisted the
                        British while they retreated to Corunna in December and in January 1809.</note> as well as from the French, &amp; that we have
                    disembarked the troops at Portsmouth, instead of sending over every disposeable man that this country can furnish, &#8722; I think the
                    Spaniards will feel such contempt &amp; indignation at <del>you</del> our wretched folly &amp; imbecillity, as may reconcile them
                    to the Bonaparte dynasty. Who did not expect that the French would at first bear down every thing before them in the field? &#8211; but
                    by keeping the mountains &amp; strong holds against them, &amp; worrying them with a desultory warfare, the Spaniards would be
                    disciplined, &amp; they would be worn out. I hope the fears of this wretched ministry exaggerate the <del>danger</del>
                    &lt;evil&gt;, &#8722; they did so a fortnight ago. Then they believed that Blakes army was entirely destroyed, &amp; Sir John Moore in
                    imminent danger.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a
                        long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra
                        (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula.The army of Galicia, defeated while under
                        the command of General Joaqu&#237;n Blake y Joyes (1759&#8211;1827) on 11 November, was reduced to a mere 6000 men. Moore was indeed in
                        imminent danger of being surrounded by overwhelming French numbers; his disorderly retreat across the mountains during
                        December left his army in distress.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know perhaps that <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> is returned &#8211; for the express
                    purpose of fighting Stewart our Envoy at Coru&#241;a, who when L. made his offer to the Junta, said to them in his hearing il est fou,
                    &#8211; il n&#8217;a pas l&#8217;argent.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> French translates as &#8216;he is mad &#8211; he doesn&#8217;t have any money&#8217;, a
                        remark made about another person by Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), British envoy to
                        the Spanish juntas in French-occupied Spain. Landor mistook the comment as being directed at him. See John Forster,
                            <title>Walter Savage Landor</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp. 135&#8211;141.</note> Landor wrote him a tremendous letter
                    which he has circulated in England,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had privately printed his letter to Charles
                        Robert Vaughan (dates unknown), his former schoolmate and Stuart&#8217;s aide, complaining of the imagined slight.</note> &amp; came
                    over as soon as <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> was appointed, to put his threat in execution. He was at
                    Bilbao after the French entered it, &amp; saved some launches with ammunition, &#8722; &amp; his opinion is that the Spaniards will be
                    victorious in spite of their allies. But he said he could not bear the questions which were put to him concerning the Cintra
                        convention.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor&#8217;s exasperation was caused by the Convention of Cintra, signed on 30
                        August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir
                        Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to
                        retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by
                        two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813;
                        <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which
                        Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did you not tell me that Claudius Buchanan<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Claudius Buchanan (1766&#8211;1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>), author of the pro-missionary <title>Memoir of the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for
                            British India</title> (1805).</note> was born at Maryport? I am writing upon this Missionary Controversy for the unborn
                    Review, &#8722; in direct opposition to a thoroughly unfeeling &amp; unphilosophical article of Sidney Smiths in the Edinburgh.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226; Sydney Smith (1771&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Indian
                        Missions&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 12:23 (April 1808), 151&#8211;181.</note> Buchanan has wasted a great deal of money upon
                    College Essays &amp; University Sermons, but he is a good man, &amp; right in what he aims at &amp; in giving him his due praise I
                    shall take care to imply that he is an Englishman, &amp; not a Scotchman as might be suspected from his name.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Buchanan was Scottish by family, place of birth (Cambuslang, a village near Glasgow) and
                        upbringing.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>