<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.916</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2038</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.916" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="916" type="letter">
        <head>916. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-03-25">[25 March&#8211;]2
                        April [1804]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK/ 8<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ APR 5 MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: Clearly this letter was begun earlier than 2 April (the date given in the middle of
                        the letter). Given Southey&#8217;s statement that it was started &#8216;thirteen days&#8217; after the letter sent via Thomas Clarkson (Southey
                        to Charles Danvers, 12 March 1804, Letter 912), this letter was most likely begun on 25 March.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote to you thirteen days ago by <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Southey to Charles Danvers, 12 March 1804, Letter 912.</note> &#8211; which letter perhaps has not yet
                    reached you. in yours per-pocket-book you speak of a letter which perhaps has not reached me &#8211; at least by your mention of Danvers
                    &amp; White,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers&#8217; firm of wine merchants with his partner, who has not been
                        identified.</note> I conclude that this is your new firm, &amp; infer that you had told me so, in one which has miscarried, an
                    accident which has before happened to your letters.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Review of Thalaba<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                            Taylor</ref> reviewed <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 39
                        (December 1803), 369&#8211;379.</note> I have not yet seen &#8211; for expecting to receive it from Bristol I did not order it from
                    London, &amp; have now no parcel to come. no matter &#8211; I shall see it in town, whither, as my last tells you, I am bound next
                    month. <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> asks me how I bear such amicable dissection, which he says is
                    like tooth-drawing gratis. I can only answer him as yet, by saying that I take tooth drawing gratis very coolly, as <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> can testify.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of some great work undertaken by <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is
                    Greek &amp; Hebrew to me. he is by this time at Portsmouth, bound for Malta, &amp; so near going that he has paid the greatest
                    part of his passage-price. his last letter was written just after a violent bowel attack which had nearly killed him &#8211; it was of
                    course very short, but he therein stated that, if able, he should set out for Portsmouth as on Friday last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc in the Press is in the prophetic-present-future-tense of publishers language, a lie at present &#8211; only so far
                    differing from <del>xxxxxx</del> common lies that it will last to be true.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem
                            <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in
                        1805.</note> It has been promised him for the press by Midsummer day, &amp; not an hour sooner <hi rend="ital">can</hi> he
                    have it; &amp; if I live &amp; do well he shall have it to the hour. the present state of progress is this. the first part,
                    containing 3691 verses &#8211; done, &amp; some progress made in the transcript for the printers. Of the second part little more than
                    600 lines is written. I am now writing the new part which intervenes between the cidevant books 7. &amp; 8. &amp; which
                    &lt;will&gt; take me perhaps ten days or a fortnight to finish. But tho thus only half way thro the poem, I am more than two
                    thirds thro the work, for in all the latter books there is little to alter, &amp; not much to inweave. You have learnt from high
                    authority that an Author is the best judge of his own works. &#8211; I cannot however tell you what my judgement is upon this said poem,
                    because it is sometimes in favour &amp; sometimes out of it &#8211; &amp; I suspect its merit more than I ever did the merits of either
                    Joan of Arc<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796; 2nd edn 1798).</note> or
                    Thalaba. I am convinced that it has been a disadvantage to have had the story so long in my head &#8211; that I am working upon a plan
                    sketched ten years ago &#8211; in parts indeed fourteen years ago, which of necessity cannot be so good as it would have been had I
                    taken up the story with maturer powers.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> On the genesis of <title>Madoc</title> over a
                        period of ten years see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004),
                        II, introduction.</note> I see also great &amp; inherent defects in the story &#8211; particularly that, in which it resembles the
                    Odyssey, &#8211; that the first &amp; second parts differ so greatly. This want of unity is a grievous fault. But when I take up my
                    eye-delighting little manuscript, &amp; walk about the room, &amp; preach a passage to myself, then I get into good humour &amp;
                    assure my friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robert Southey that his poem is a very excellent poem, &amp; then I have a great regard
                    for his genius.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> ____</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1804-04-02">Monday. April 2.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This has lain unfinished in my desk <hi rend="ital">far over-long</hi> as we say in Cumberland. Meantime the new
                    news is &#8211; that Coleridge was at Portsmouth on Wednesday March 28, expecting to sail next day &#8211; that no letter has yet arrived from
                        <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref>, royal promises being proverbial &#8211; &amp; that <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">old Lovell</ref> has left <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref> fifty pounds
                    &#8211; to be paid after the death of his widow! supposing I presume to cheat the Devil by this precious legacy. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Frank,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> as Executor, apprized me of this, &amp; proposed that the boy
                    should for some years be supported by <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">his mothers</ref> relations (meaning me) till he be
                    old enough for his fathers friends to push him forward in life. I have written him a very decisive answer, assuring the Lovells,
                    one &amp; all, that I can not &amp; will not be burthened with all their debts of duty, &amp; that if they are determined to
                    abandon the child to common charity, a subscription for his education shall be set on foot among the Quakers. I am out of all
                    patience!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My box from Liverpool is arrived, with the additional comfort of having been smuggled. you may guess how happy the
                    cargo has made me my eyes still plague me at times &#8211; &amp; at times I am still &#8216;a fountain of running waters&#8217;&#8217;.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Song of Solomon</title> 4: 15.</note> all this is rather general debility than local
                    disease &#8211; but general debility is even a worse general than the Duke of York,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prince
                        Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827): second son of King George III (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>), he was notorious for his ineffectual generalship in Holland in 1799, which gave rise to the rhyme
                        &#8216;The Grand Old Duke of York&#8217;.</note> &amp; woe be to the Constitution wherein either should get the upper hand. I got sulphate
                    of iron in no very good state, but it answers its end. Exercise I do not take for want of a companion, &amp; because I am soon to
                    have a thorough spell &#8211; for as soon as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is in bed &amp; safe by Gods
                        blessing<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edith Southey gave birth to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                            May</ref> on 30 April 1804.</note> &#8211; I shall take my departure for the Great City, &amp; then as you know shall travel
                    over more ground day by day than a twopenny postman.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The concrete acid is certainly, &amp; <hi rend="ital">most</hi> certainly, mineral, if it be possible to exhibit
                    mineral acid in such a shape. I will swear to it by the unerring test of my tongue &amp; teeth.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers, 1 March 1804 (Letter 905) and Southey to John King, [1]&#8211;5 March 1804 (Letter
                        904).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It vexes me to hear that you cannot walk fast. by all means if the pain in your side proves obstinate, find
                    occasion to go yourself on business to Porto, &amp; take Lisbon as the shortest way, which <hi rend="ital">in time</hi> it would
                    probably be. If you do not get quite well in the summer, I shall rather hear of your embarkation than see you here, much as we
                    have built upon seeing you. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A letter last night from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> written at sea, sixteen days on his passage
                    &amp; expecting in 18 or 20 to reach Barbadoes. he writes in good spirits, having that day left off grog &amp; taken physic to
                    prepare for heat. he has put plenty of letters in the <del>Post Office</del> Atlantic Post Office General.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had agreed with his brother Thomas, whose ship had been posted to defend the West Indies
                        from French fleets, that he should send messages in bottles &#8211; several of which did indeed reach <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. For an account of these experiments; see Southey to the Editor of the
                        Athenaeum, [April 1807], Letter 1314.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Scape-grace</ref> is in Herefordshire at
                    board &amp; lodging under the eyes of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A native of Hereford
                        (first name and dates unknown), he was the father of William Bowyer Thomas (d. 1802). He was involved in the management of
                            <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill&#8217;s</ref> business affairs.</note> I am trying to ship him again &#8211;
                    &amp; wish he was on his way to the West Indies instead of poor Tom, who is far too good for the Land Crabs.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>