<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1575</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2697</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1575" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1575" type="letter">
        <head>1575. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, [begun a month before and continued on] <date when="1809-02-06">6 February 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss
                        Barker<lb />Endorsement: Bonaparte<lb /> MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert
                        Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 304&#8211;308.<lb />Dating note: the letter seems to
                        have been begun a month earlier than 6 Feb.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr. Walhouse &amp; I Senhora do not agree in opinion respecting Petitions to the Crown upon great public
                        occasions.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward John Walhouse (1791&#8211;1862), <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward Littleton&#8217;s</ref> nephew and heir. He assumed the name of Littleton on
                        Sir Edward&#8217;s death in 1812, and became MP for Stafford.</note> It is the legal, orderly, &amp; proper manner in which the
                    People are by the Bill of Rights entitled to express their feelings, &amp; it is their means of protesting against any measure
                    which may be oppressive to them &#8211; or injurious to the honour &amp; interest of the country. I believe it will now be admitted by
                    most men that the Convention of Cintra was deeply injurious both to its honour &amp; interests, &#8211; &amp; the King has seldom been
                    worse advised than when he made that most unmerited &amp; unconstitutional answer to the City of London.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Convention of Cintra was an agreement, signed on 30 August 1808, which allowed the defeated French troops
                        to leave Portugal without further conflict. Southey&#8217;s account of the petition of the City of London &#8216;to express to your
                        Majesty our grief and astonishment at the extraordinary and disgraceful Convention lately entered into by the Commander of
                        your Majesty&#8217;s forces in Portugal, and the Commander of the French army in Lisbon&#8217; and the King&#8217;s (George III (1738&#8211;1820, King
                        of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) court answer appears in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                        1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 211&#8211;212.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am inclined to think that you have misunderstood what I said about my uncles marriage, &amp; fancied it was <hi rend="ital">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Mr. Southey</ref>
          </hi> instead of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> i.e., Mr Hill , the only person to whom I ever apply that name.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter from Southey referred to here appears not to have survived.</note> You would not
                    else I am sure have talked of his being managed by some servant maid.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A vile cold of three weeks standing has kept me in bed till breakfast time every morning, &amp; thus stops
                        Kehama.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> I am hard at work transcribing &amp; filling up the skeleton chapters of my
                    first vol. of Brazil, which is now in the press, &#8211; &amp; five sheets thereof corrected. <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> It will be a good book, containing the truth, the whole truth,
                    &amp; nothing but the truth, &#8211; but I am by no means sanguine about its sale, nor tho I have no doubts about its final reputation,
                    do I expect that it can ever be popular. People will be expecting a fine History, because Brazil is a fine country, just as they
                    thought the history of Leo X<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope
                            Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de Medici</title> (1805) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806),
                        449&#8211;467.</note> must be splendid, because he had a splendid Court. I have begun with a sort of exordium very much to my own
                    liking in which they are told what they are to look for &amp; what they will find;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Introduction&#8217; to the first volume of <title>The History of Brazil</title> (1810), pp. 1&#8211;2, fulfils this
                        role.</note> &#8211; but it is in vain to tell them, &#8211; the public is a great ass that must have its ears tickled or it will bray
                    with disappointment in your face.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We go on pretty much as usual, &#8211; except that a Goose &amp; Turkey have arrived to day from <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherall</ref>, being the only visitors we are likely to have till the month of May. Your
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">God daughter</ref> is almost big enough to stand in need of your instruction about
                    the pencil, &#8211; for the use of which she certainly has not natural aptitude, &#8211; but all that is necessary is acquirable by anybody,
                    if well taught &amp; in time. We expect another about April.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref> born 27 March 1809.</note> Huzza! the more the merrier, &#8211; one
                    will help another; &#8211; the World pays me so badly that I shall leave it in debt to my children, &amp; I have not so bad an opinion
                    of it as not to believe that it will discharge its debt fairly &amp; liberally at last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is unlikely that great political changes will soon take place. The Grenvilles &amp; the Foxites<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Factions within the Whig party who were followers of the peace policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James Fox</ref> or who preferred the less conciliatory policy of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>.</note> must separate upon the question of peace, &amp;
                    as the People of England are not so mad as to join with the Foxites in their frantic wish for what would be little short of an act
                    of national suicide, even the Grenvilles may acquire some popularity for the ground on which they stand, &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> would be right glad to get them in &amp; rid himself by their help of some of
                    his wretched collegues. This change is very likely to take place,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Canning, Foreign
                        Secretary, wished to be rid of the Secretary for War and the Colonies, Robert Stewart, 2nd Marquess of Londonderry, Lord
                        Castlereagh (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), who had sent troops intended by Canning for Portugal to the Netherlands instead.
                        With the support of former Whig followers of William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), who were suspicious of the peace policy of Pitt&#8217;s former Whig rival
                        Fox, Canning might have been able to lead a Tory government. Later in 1809, he fought a duel with Castlereagh; the King
                        subsequently asked Spencer Perceval (1762&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), rather than Canning, to form a government.</note> &#8211; I
                    wish it may &#8211; because <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> makes an excellent franker of large packets when he gets
                    at Whitehall.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn had sat in parliament since 1797, and as the nephew of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>, Prime Minister 1806&#8211;1807, it was expected he would
                        hold government office again after his role as Under Secretary of State in the Home Office during the &#8216;Ministry of all the
                        Talents&#8217;. Although he moved his allegiance to the Tories, Wynn did not enter the cabinet again until 1822.</note> Of any other
                    benefit either to myself or the nation I have little hope &amp; no expectation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yet Senhora by the living God, as able ministers might in six months time hang up Bonaparte for the Spanish Crows
                    to feed upon, &amp; reduce France within her ancient limits, By sending our whole military force into Spain, No man who knows what
                    the French are, what the Spanish are, &amp; what the English are can doubt this. Now is the time to put out this fire which has
                    ravaged Europe, now when we can fairly get at it. Yet when we should be playing all our engines upon it, we do nothing more than
                    send the maids to empty their chamber pots there. On such an occasion as this England might spare 150,000 men, &#8211; for it is as much
                    our own cause as if it were upon our own ground. I would land 100,000 of them behind Bonaparte, seize the passes, &amp; shut him
                    in Spain, &amp; send the rest to fight him there.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 9 January 1809 <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Arthur Wellesley</ref> was dispatched to Portugal in command of 21,000
                        soldiers.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="right">
          <date when="1809-02-06">Feby. 6. 1809.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This letter has lain a month in this unfinished state. The truth is that I find the day too short for the business
                    it brings with it, &#8211; tho during that month I have only once been outside my own garden gate. Whether it will ever be in my power
                    to afford to be idle God knows, &#8211; I am sure it will never be in my inclination, &#8211; &amp; yet I should like to feel that I might be
                    idle if I pleased, &amp; that nobody had any right to blame me if it was my will &amp; pleasure to sleep a whole day long upon
                    yonder sofa. I am working like a negro at some borrowed books which must be returned as soon as possible,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> to borrow the following books for
                        him from the Advocates Library in Edinburgh, which he needed for writing his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819):
                        Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784); Jos&#233; Gumilla
                        (1686&#8211;1750), <title>Histoire Naturelle, Civile et Geographique de L&#8217;Orenoque</title> (1758), a French version of the original
                            <title>Historia Natural, Civil, &amp; Geografica de las Naciones situadas en las Riveras del Rio Orinoco</title> (1731);
                        Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi et Viaggi</title> (1550&#8211;1559).</note> &#8211; they throw me behind hand
                    with the press, &#8211; &amp; then I must work like ten negroes to fetch up my lea way there. &#8211; But it would be a long story to tell you
                    all I am doing &amp; have to do &#8211; Only I am tired sometimes, &amp; then I make a great noise &amp; that sets me right again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are soon about to compleat the study. have you got for us the brass rollers for the blinds, &#8211; &amp; the little
                    bellows for the books? for we stand in need of them. The juniperring<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning to add a
                        gold border and lettering to the bindings of Southey&#8217;s books. The allusion was possibly to Friar Juniper, disciple of St
                        Francis, who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to give to a poor woman begging alms.</note> is fairly
                    got thro, except a little lettering &#8211; &amp; I should be in my glory. if I were quite in full spirits, but little <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> is ailing, &amp; has been so so long that I am not at ease. It is my nature to be
                    over anxious about these things, &#8211; God be praised, not about any others.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I beg my remembrance to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward</ref>. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughter</ref> is
                    delighted with collecting seals, &#8211; &amp; as I know you delight in consuming sealing wax I pray you lose no opportunity of sending
                    her a new specimen upon your letters &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you yours as ever</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>