<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1346</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2468</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc MS. 3922
                    .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1346" type="letter">
        <head>1346. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">[Anna] Seward</ref>, <date when="1807-07-25">25 July
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Seward/ Litchfield<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Endorsement: July 1807<lb />MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc MS. 3922
                    <lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1807-07-25">July 25. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Had not your letter contained intelligence of your illness it would have been instantly answered, &#8211; on the spur of
                    the moment. But on that subject I neither knew what to say nor how to be silent, &amp; have therefore shrunk from writing as from
                    a task, instead of hastening to it as a gratification. I had a friend once who when above the age of seventy had an
                        <del>lesion</del> &#8211; abscess of the liver, she was feebler than is usual at that age, &amp; yet recovered so as to enjoy some
                    years of longer life. When an organic disease is not necessarily fatal the chances in a good constitution are for its favourable
                    termination; &#8211; &amp; where the heart &amp; the spirit are so young as they are in you, the power of life also will be strong.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have directed my publishers to send you a book which is just gone into the world under false colours;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; perhaps it
                    may beguile a few weary hours of confinement. It is smuggled into public chiefly with a hope that it may pass unknown thro the
                    hands of those Reviewers who are sure to detract from whatever is mine. My object was to give a picture of the present state of
                    England, but for this I have not left myself room, having for the sake of preserving the assumed character taken up too large a
                    portion in mere travelling. If however it should sell, the work may easily be lengthened so as to compleat the design. You will
                    easily distinguish what is written <hi rend="ital">for</hi> the Spaniard from what is written <hi rend="ital">thro</hi> him. &#8211; The
                    heretical history is really valuable, few persons would have had the patience to collect materials for it; it is written with full
                    knowledge, &amp; the strictest truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The great fault of Madoc is in the catastrophe, which is so managed as to transfer the feelings from the hero to
                        Yuhidthiton.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), recently issued in a smaller edition. The catastrophe referred to here is the earthquake
                        which brings about the Aztecas&#8217; defeat at the end of the poem.</note> Let me consult you concerning an alteration of this
                    part. Suppose that Tezozomoc encourages the thought of emigrating when it is first hinted at by the King, &amp; plots with Tlalala
                    to kill Madoc &amp; his chiefs at a conference: meaning to kill Yuhidthiton also in the fray, but this part of his design he dares
                    not entrust to Tlalala. The meeting takes place on an Island, &#8211; so that all the people are spectators. To make all sure the
                    priests poison their knives. At the moment of danger Yuhidthiton alarms Madoc, who stabs Tezozomoc, but is hurt in the arm, &amp;
                    the priest writhing in death tells him exaltingly the wound is mortal. Madoc heats his sword red hot upon the altar, &amp;
                        <del>burn</del> cauterizes his arm with it. Then he &amp; Yuhidthiton part in friendship, &amp; Tlalala, who seeing the Kings
                    life aimed at in the treason has saved him &amp; turned upon the Priests, gives his wife &amp; child to Madoc&#8217;s care<del>s</del>,
                    &amp; terminates the poem as at present.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Another part is ill executed &#8211; that sccene at Caer-madoc with the women &amp; Amalahta.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events in <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 2, Book 16.</note> I thought of making Erillyab arrive in time,
                    &amp; killing her son with her own hand, but from this I was dissuaded, &#8211; and perhaps justly. I now think of bringing a dog from
                    the field of battle in Arvon, who was found there watching his dead master, &#8211; &amp; making him save Goervyl after Malinal can do
                    no more. At any rate this section must be mended.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to Book 16 of Part 1 of
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805). The emendations suggested here were not made.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These are the only alterations which seem practicable: do you think them good? &#8211; I could not give Madoc a wife, &#8211;
                    he is past the age at which love is necessary for a hero, &amp; as it is to be taken for granted that he had loved at that age, it
                    would have lowered my conception of the character to have made him marry politically. Otherwise Erillyab would have been his fit
                    wife.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not upon the events of this unhappy reign that I am employed &#8211; there is nothing in them but what makes the
                    heart sick. My subject is the history of Portugal, its conquests &amp; colonies, &#8211; on this I have been for many years occupied,
                    &amp; to this it is that that half of my time is devoted which I can afford to give to labours worthy of myself &amp; of
                    posterity. This work is far advanced &#8211; that part of it which relates to Brazil will probably be put to press in the ensuing
                        winter;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in three volumes from
                        1810&#8211;1819.</note> &#8211; it would properly have been the last in order of publication, but when our ministers are taking such
                    frantic &amp; destructive measures with respect to South America, that information which I possess concerning the country ought
                    not to be withheld, for when the history &amp; real state of it is known, our &lt;true&gt; policy is plain. Of all follies that of
                    hoping to conquer South America is the wildest. all that we are now doing is to bring back the buccaneering spirit, &amp; revive
                    that hatred of England in the Spanish colonists, of which a century of peace had just obliterated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Ode<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps, Coleridge&#8217;s &#8216;Hymn before Sunrise&#8217;, published anonymously
                        in the <title>Morning Post</title> in 1802. Coleridge&#8217;s line &#8216;with dim eyes suffused with tears&#8217;, line 77 of the 1817
                        text given in S. T. Coleridge, <title>Poetical Works I Poems (Reading Text), Part 2</title>, ed. J.C.C. Mays (London and
                        Princeton NJ, 2001), pp. 717&#8211;723, echoes Southey&#8217;s &#8216;He saw his brother&#8217;s eyes, suffused with tears/ Shine in the moon beam&#8217; <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, Book 17, lines 113&#8211;114). See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical
                            Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, <title>Madoc</title>.</note> which you mention
                    is <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref>: the line which led you to impute it to me is my own,
                    pre-existing in Madoc, as compleated in 1799. He I believe shadows out himself both there &amp; in that poem beginning &#8216;Edmund thy
                    grave with aching eye I scan&#8217;.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge, &#8216;Lines on a Friend, Who Died of a Frenzy Fever,
                        Induced by Calumnious Reports&#8217; (1796). See S. T. Coleridge, <title>Poetical Works I Poems (Reading Text), Part 1</title>,
                        ed. J.C.C. Mays (London and Princeton NJ, 2001), pp. 148&#8211;150.</note> My <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund</ref>
                    bore your name, &amp; may perhaps have been distantly related to you, as he was of Worcestershire birth. I never can sufficiently
                    reverence his memory nor regret his loss. <del>xxx</del> he was [MS obscured] stay &amp; staff of my moral being, &#8211; a sort of
                    second conscience whose reproof I could not have borne. He it was who taught me to lay aside Rousseau for Epictetus;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The egotistical sentimentalism of Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712&#8211;1778); the stoic endurance of
                        Epictetus (55&#8211;135).</note> &amp; he <del>xxx</del> it was who settled &amp; strengthened me in those principles which are
                    &amp; will be the life &amp; spirit of whatever I may leave behind me, &#8211; I have acquired a habit of suppressing all outward &amp;
                    visible signs of strong feeling &#8211; partly perhaps from &lt;knowing&gt; how little those who indulge in such expressions live as
                    they write, &amp; how different (to use Crowes admirable expression) the Sunday garment of their minds is from the every day
                        dress.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Our better mind/ Is as a Sunday&#8217;s garment, then put on/ When we have naught to
                        do&#8217;. William Crowe (1745&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Lewesdon Hill&#8217; (1788), lines 519&#8211;521.</note>
          <del>But</del> Hence it is that my sentimental pieces are so few, <del>xxx</del> but what there are are in earnest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The lines which you addressed to me upon Joan of Arc were sent to me in Portugal immediately as they appeared.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Seward had authored a widely-published attack on <title>Joan of Arc</title>, &#8216;Philippic on
                        a Modern Epic&#8217; (1797).</note> Need it be said that I was well pleased to be so censured for the sake of being so praised! Of
                    that poem it ought to be said that when it was written the combined powers were victorious in every direction, the subject was not
                    chosen for its political bearing, but certainly when I felt how easily it could be &lt;done&gt; I caught with delight the
                    opportunity of pouring out sentiments favourable to what was then the cause of liberty. An ode which I began at the commencement
                    of the war in allusion to this poem never proceeded farther than this stanza &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> O dear, dear &#8211; England! O my Mother-Isle!</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> There was a time when, woe the while,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In thy proud triumphs I partook no part;</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> And even the tale of thy defeat</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In those unhappy days was doom&#8217;d to meet</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Unnatural welcome in an English heart;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> For thou wert leagued in an accursed cause</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> O dear, dear &#8211; England! &amp; thy holiest laws</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Were trampled under foot by insolent Power.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Dear as my own life-blood wert thou to me</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> But even thou less dear than Liberty.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> This poem was never
                            published.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">Thus it was that I felt in those days, &amp; that feeling I have never yet repented.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the course of the winter I must visit London, &amp; tho I never leave home without reluctance nor without
                    feeling that men as well as boys are subject to homesickness, I certainly look to this journey with pleasure, for the sake of
                    taking Litchfield in my way.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs truly &amp; respectfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>