<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1168</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2290</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 86.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 36&#8211;38 [in
                        part].Dating note: dating from JR&#8217;s endorsement</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1168" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1168" type="letter">
        <head>1168. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1806-03-19">19 March
                        [1806]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: R Southey/ 19 March 1806<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 86<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 36&#8211;38 [in
                        part].<lb />Dating note: dating from JR&#8217;s endorsement</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have been able to have told you when my operations would commence, had it not been for an ugly call to go
                    into Herefordshire &amp; look into some affairs of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> which must lead to a
                    lawsuit between him &amp; his parish.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Hill had the a living of a parish at Staunton-Upon-Wye,
                        Herefordshire, which, while he was in Lisbon, he had left in the care of <ref target="people.html#ThomasDr">Dr Thomas</ref>,
                        father of his business agent <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">William Bowyer Thomas</ref>, who had died in 1802.
                        Southey believed that Hill&#8217;s estate was being mismanaged while he was abroad and intended to investigate the payment of tithes
                        for him. See Southey to Charles Danvers, 17 March 1806, Letter 1166.</note> I have only proposed that this should be on my
                    return home, instead of on the way to town, for this reason that in London I can talk the matter over with some persons who will
                    instruct me in what manner to proceed. Be this as it may, I shall leave this place on Sunday 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &amp; be
                    about ten days before you see me, either in Herefordshire on this business &#8211; or at Norwich with <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>, a visit which was intended to be paid on my
                    return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My last week has been somewhat desultorily employed in going thro Beausobres Hist. of Manicheism,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac de Beausobre (1659&#8211;1738), <title>Histoire Critique de Manich&#233;e et du Manich&#233;isme</title>
                        (1734&#8211;1739).</note> &#8211; &amp; in sketching the life of D. Luisa de Carvajal, an extraordinary woman of high rank who came over
                    to London in James the firsts time to make proselytes to the Catholick religion, under the protection of the Spanish
                        Embassador.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza (1568&#8211;1614), was a Spanish missionary who
                        devoted herself to the cause of the Catholic faith in England during the reign of James VI and I (1566&#8211;1625, King of Scotland,
                        England, and Ireland 1603&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>). An account of her life was written by Luis Mun&#771;oz (d.1646) as <title>La
                            Vida Y Virtues de la Venerable Virgin Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title> in 1632, and was summarised by Southey in
                        the third edition of his <title>Letters from Spain and Portugal</title> (1808).</note> It is a very curious story, &amp; ought
                    to be related in the history of that wretched King who beheaded Ralegh<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Walter Ralegh
                        (1554&#8211;1618; <title>DNB</title>) was executed on James I&#8217;s orders after a failed final voyage to the Orinoco in South America
                        to find El Dorado.</note> to please the Spaniards.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Beausobres book is one of the most valuable that I have ever seen. It is a compleat Thesaurus of early opinions
                    philosophical &amp; theological. It is not the least curious circumstance in the Catholick religion that it has silently imbibed
                        <del>xxx the xxxxxx which</del> the most absurd parts of most of the heresies which it opposed &amp; persecuted. I do not
                    conceive Manes to have been a fanatic, there is too much philosophy in the whole of his system, even in the mythology, for
                        that.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manichaeism is a dualist religious philosophy, in which good (God) and evil
                        (Satan) are perceived to be in conflict, which originated in Persia (Iran) in the 3rd century. Its founding prophet was Mani
                        (or Manes in Latin).</note> the object seems to have been to unite the superstitions of the East &amp; of the West, &#8211;
                    unluckily both Priests &amp; Magi united against this grand scheme, &#8211; The Persians flayed him alive, &amp; the Catholicks roasted
                    his disciples wherever they could catch them. &#8211; Beausobre as I expected has perceived the similarity between Buddas &amp; the
                    Indian impostor but he supposes the lie came from the East. I am inclined to think otherwise because the story of an immaculate
                    conception had succeeded so well here that one going to set up a religion of his own would be likely to borrow it, &#8211; &amp; because
                    I have found elsewhere that the Adam whose footstep is shown in Ceylon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In central Sri
                        Lanka (formerly known as Ceylon) there is a mountain known as Adam&#8217;s Peak which has a rock formation near its summit, which in
                        Muslim tradition is believed to be the &#8216;sacred footprint&#8217; of Adam.</note> was a Manichaean travelling disciple, &#8211; tho both
                    Moors &amp; Portugueze very naturally attributed the story to their own acquaintance. A proof this that the immediate disciples of
                    Manes &lt;were&gt; successful. <del>in the East.</del> Besides the Asiatic fables are full of resemblances to Xtianity, which have
                    been advanced by Dupuis &amp; Volney on the one hand to prove that the whole is astronomical allegory,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Fran&#231;ois Dupuis (1742&#8211;1809), French scientist and politician, who published his extensive, twelve
                        volume, <title>Origine de tous les Cultes, ou la R&#233;ligion Universelle</title> in 1795, positing the common origin of all
                        astronomical and religious mythologies. He continued this argument in his <title>M&#233;moire Explicatif du Zodiaque, Chronologique
                            et Mythologique</title> (1806); Constantin Fran&#231;ois de Chasseb&#339;uf, Comte de Volney (1757&#8211;1820), French philosopher,
                        historian and orientalist, who predicted the union of the world&#8217;s religions in recognition of their shared common truths in
                            <title>Les Ruines, ou M&#233;ditations sur les R&#233;volutions des Empires</title> (1791).</note> &#8211; &amp; by Maurice &amp; Halhed
                    on the other to show that the mysteries of Religion were revealed to the Patriarchs. <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Maurice (1754&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), oriental scholar and historian, who published <title>Indian Antiquities</title> (1792&#8211;1796)
                        with the polemical intent of defending the historicity of the Bible against the French scholars, Dupuis and Volney, who argued
                        that all the world&#8217;s religious myths were allegorical; Nathaniel Brassey Halhed (1751&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>), orientalist
                        and philologist, who compared the Trimourtee of the Hindus with the Christian Trinity.</note> These gentlemen should first
                    have enquired <del>to all of these xxxxxxxxx xxxxx xxx the xxxxx &lt;xxxx&gt;</del> &lt;when&gt; this trade in
                        <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> mythology was carried on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If there be any one thing in which the world has decidedly regenerated it is in the breed of Heresiarchs.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The chief proponents or leaders of heretical movements.</note> They were really great men
                    in former times, devoting great knowledge &amp; powerful talents to great purposes. In our days they are either arrant mad men, or
                    half rogues who pick out the worst parts of the established creed. I am about to be the S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Epiphanius<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saint Epiphanius of Salamis was a 4th century bishop of Cyprus with a reputation for
                        defending orthodoxy and persecuting non-Christians; he compiled a huge compendium of heresies.</note> of Richard Brothers<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Brothers (1757&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), a self-proclaimed prophet of millennial
                        destruction, who attracted a large following in 1795 before being confined to an asylum by government order.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcote</ref> &#8211; what say you to paying these worthies a visit some morning? the
                    former is sure to be at home. Haslam<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Haslam (bap. 1764&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>),
                        physician and specialist in insanity who had superintended Brothers in his confinement.</note> would introduce us, &amp; we
                    might get <del>xxx</del> &lt;Gods Nephew<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of the titles Brothers appropriated for
                        himself was &#8216;Nephew of the Almighty&#8217;, claiming descent through the brother of Jesus Christ.</note> to give us his&gt; opinion
                    of <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna</ref>. I know some of his witnesses &amp; could enter into the depths of his
                    system with him. D. Manuel ought to see Bedlam.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). Southey&#8217;s pseudonymous traveller does not visit Bedlam
                        (Bethlem) Hospital in London, but Richard Brothers is discussed in Letter 69 and Joanna Southcott in Letter 70.</note> As for
                        <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna</ref>, though tolerably versed in the history of human credulity, I have
                    never seen any thing so disgraceful to common sense as her previous publications; &#8211; but I am afraid that in all these cases it may
                    be laid down as a general rule that the more nonsense the better. Whenever a point of doctrine has been discussed the most absurd
                    has carried the day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Metaphysicians have become less mischievous but a good deal more troublesome. There was some excuse for them when
                    they believed their opinions were necessary to salvation &#8211; &amp; it was certainly better for plain people like you &amp; I that
                    they should write by the folio, than talk by the hour. What a happy thing would it have been for Stoddart<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), writer and lawyer, who in the 1790s was an associate of
                            <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> as a fellow enthusiast of the philosophy of <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref>. Stoddart visited <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and Wordsworth in the Lakes in 1800; from 1803 to 1807 was an advocate for the crown and the admiralty at
                        Malta, in which capacity he renewed his acquaintance with Coleridge.</note> had he been born in those ages when
                    transubstantiation was <del>xxx</del> philosophically explained, &amp; the divine &amp; human natures subjected to synthesis &amp;
                    analysis in the crucible of a metaphysicians skill.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The reign of fabulous Xtianity must be drawing to its end. In France it is over, unless Bonaparte should take it in
                    his head to endow the church better,&#8211; for which I do not think he wants inclination so much as money. In Germany the thing is
                    done. the clergy are philosophizing Xtians, or Xtianizing philosophers. In my countries Spain &amp; Portugal the old house stands,
                    but there is the dry rot in its timbers, the foundations are undermined, &amp; the next earthquake will bring it down. Here I do
                    not like the prospects, &#8211; sooner or later a hungry government will snap at the tithes; &#8211; the clergy will then become state
                    pensioners, or parish pensioners, <del>x</del> in the latter case more odious to the farmers than they are now, in the former the
                    first pensioners to be ame[MS torn] of their stipends. Meantime the damned system of Calvinism spreads like a pestilence among the
                    lower classes. I have not the slightest doubt that the Calvinists will be the majority in less than half a century; &#8211; we see how
                    catching the distemper is &amp; do not see any means of stopping it. There is a good opening for a new religion, but the founder
                    must start up in some of the darker parts of the world &#8211; it is Americas turn to send out apostles. A new one there must be when
                    the old one is worn out &#8211; I am a believer in the truth of Christianity, but truth will never do for the multitude; there is an
                    appetite for faith in us, which if it be not duly indulged turns to green sickness &amp; <del>xxxx</del> feeds upon chalk &amp;
                    cinders. The truth is man is not made for this world alone, &amp; speculations concerning the next will be found at last the most
                    interesting to all of us &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope my <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little girl</ref> has past the most dangerous age &#8211; but she is
                    more premature in intellect than any child I ever saw &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-03-19">Wednesday 19 March.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>