<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1097</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2219</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library.  Previously  published:
                        Joseph Cottle, Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey (London, 1847), p. 228; Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 394&#8211;396. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1097" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1097" type="letter">
        <head>1097. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1805-08-25">25 August
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ Portland Square/ Bristol/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />Postmark: E/ AUG29/ 1805<lb />Endorsement: <del>174</del>
            <hi rend="ital">72</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: J LLOYD<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb />Previously published:
                        Joseph Cottle, <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (London, 1847), p. 228; Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 394&#8211;396. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-08-25">Sunday. Aug 25. 1805.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter has very much affected me &#8211; I lose no time in answering it, in the hope of suggesting something which
                    may be found useful. For twelvemonths past I have used that sort of case-hardening which Franklin calls the air-bath, &#8211; rubbing
                    myself every morning when I get out of bed with a coarse towel, <del>xxxxxx xxxxxxxx</del> &lt;for five minutes&gt; this
                        <del>practice</del> &lt;exposure&gt; I believe tends very much to diminish the susceptibility of the body to cold. if you are
                    disposed to try <del>this</del> it begin gradually, &amp; do not expose yourself at first above half a minute. but friction either
                    with coarse towels or with the flesh-brush you cannot use too much; &#8211; it may in great measure supply the want of exercise. &#8211; I do
                    not myself believe that sedentary habits are so prejudicial to health as they are supposed to be. We know they are not in hot
                    climates. Might it not however prevent some of the possible inconveniences to which you may be otherwise liable, if you changed
                    your chair once or twice a day, &#8211; &amp; when <del>not</del> only employed in conversation &#8211; preferred the settee? The increased
                    lameness I hope is only for a time, whatever weakens the whole system must necessarily have weakened the weakest part. as you get
                    strength this affliction will diminish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now then to more chearful topics. Your ship on the stocks I saw announced in the Monthly Magazine.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cottle&#8217;s <title>The Fall of Cambria</title> (1808).</note> You will do well to introduce lyrical
                    pieces when the subject requires them &#8211; I am doing the same in Madoc, converting the odes of Cyveilioc &amp; Caradoc &amp; the
                    song of Hoel into lyrical measures.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, &#8216;Madoc in
                        Wales&#8217;, Book 2, lines 142&#8211;167; Book 10, lines 42&#8211;110; Book 11, lines 98&#8211;160.</note> Do you take a Welsh or <del>Saxon</del>
                    English interest in the story? Edward Williams<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg; 1747&#8211;1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s friend, the influential Welsh antiquarian, poet, scholar of Welsh poetry and history,
                        reviver of bardism, and literary forger.</note> if you write to him will gladly tell you all that either history or tradition
                    has preserved concerning the event you have chosen. some anecdotes you may perhaps find in Yorkes Royal Tribes of Wales,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip Yorke (1743&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Royal Tribes of Wales</title> (1799).</note> &amp; the History of
                    the Gwedir family<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wynn, 1st Baronet (1553&#8211;1627; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            History of the Gwedir Family</title> (1770).</note> which is a very curious book. If we were nearer I would turn over to
                    you such unused notes <del>of Welsh</del> respecting the Welsh as were collected for Madoc &#8211; they might save you perhaps some
                    trouble. If <del>x</del> you had not begun the poem I should perhaps have advised you to try it in Spensers stanza<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spenserian stanza is a fixed verse form used by Edmund Spenser (1552?&#8211;1599) in <title>The
                            Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596). Each stanza contains eight lines of iambic pentameter followed by a last Alexandrine
                        line, of iambic hexameter. The rhyme scheme is ABABBCBCC.</note> &#8211; to have thus made your narrative in the best form of rhyme,
                    which is favourably to the redundancy that narrative sometimes requires, &amp; to have had your dialogues in a dramatic form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will of course have something to do with the Bards. In the last Annual you will see a review of Davies&#8217;s Celtic
                        Researches<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language, of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory
                            Sketches, on Primitive Society</title> (1804) in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 634&#8211;644.</note>
          <del>xx</del> in which I have stated his very curious speculations upon Welsh antiquities. I myself very much incline to believe
                    that the patriarchal system was preserved more purely by the Bards than by any other race of men; &#8211; if this could be proved it
                    would add the sanction of faith to a creed which will stand the test of reason. You will find specimens of Taliesin<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taliesin (dates unknown) was a sixth-century Welsh poet.</note> &amp; many other Bards in <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref> Vindication of the Welsh Poems,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon
                        Turner, <title>A Vindication of the Genuineness of the Antient British Poems of Aneurin, Taliesin, Llywarch Hen and Merdhin
                            with Specimens of their Poems</title> (1803).</note> &amp; much curious matter mixed with some ignorance &amp; clumsily
                    put together in Jones&#8217;s Musical Relics.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Jones [Bardd y Brenin] (1752&#8211;1824),
                            <title>The Musical and Poetical Relicks of the Welsh Bards</title> (1784).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have neither seen nor heard of Forsters book:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Foster (1770&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Baptist minister at Downend, near Bristol, from 1800&#8211;1804, he moved to Frome and published his <title>Essays
                        in a Series of Letters to a Friend</title> there in 1805.</note> nor do I remember to have heard you mention him, unless he be a
                    person who was once deranged &#8211; certainly on your recommendation I shall buy or borrow it the first opportunity, &#8211; but no new book
                    ever reaches these mountains except such as come to me to be killed off,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers to
                        his review work for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> which are more than are good I assure you. &#8211; My own heavy
                    quarto stands I believe better with the world than it does with me:<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> I do not think I could have executed it better, but the subject is bad, it was chosen
                    too soon, &amp; has been too long in hand. I propose to alter the catastrophe, by omitting the two last sections, &amp; inserting
                    something in their place in which Madoc shall still be the Agent, &amp; the person on whom the interest hangs; for at present
                    there is an injudicious transfer of the interest to Yuhidthiton.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem ends with
                        Yuhidthiton, the remaining leader of the defeated and chastened Aztecas, leading his people into exile, rather than with
                        Madoc, the Welsh colonist, presiding over a new American civilisation. This was not altered. On the history of the poem&#8217;s
                        drafting and revision, see the editor&#8217;s introduction to <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II.</note> The eagles you will find mentioned p. 359 as borne on Madocs shield. the
                    fact is that <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> bears them, as the lineal descendant of Rodri,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rhodri ab Owain Gwynedd (d. 1195; <title>DNB</title>), son of Owain Gwynedd (d. 1170;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and brother of Dafydd (d. 1203; <title>DNB</title>), is a character in <title>Madoc</title>.</note>
                    &amp; I have only transferred them from one brother to another. the cross <del>xxx xxx xxxxxx</del> the Cross of Cadwallader.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn claimed as a more distant ancestor the semi-mythical Cadwaladr ap Cadwallon, King of
                        Gwynedd (reigned c. 655&#8211;682), supposed to have visited Rome. Cadwallader&#8217;s cross was a Celtic one.</note> &#8211; Pocock spoilt my
                    ship by relying on his own knowledge instead of mine.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Pocock (1740&#8211;1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the marine painter of Bristol, had been asked to provide an illustration of Madoc&#8217;s ship for
                        Southey&#8217;s poem. It was omitted because Southey was displeased with the vessel&#8217;s anachronistic modernity.</note> I sent him a
                    copy from the Bayeux tapestry<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bayeux tapestry, commissioned by Bishop Odo (d. 1097),
                        the half-brother of William I, the Conqueror (1027/8&#8211;1087; reigned 1066&#8211;1087; <title>DNB</title>), completed c. 1077.</note> &#8211;
                    such a ship as was used in the Conquerors days, near enough Madocs age to have done well. he asked what the poem was about, &amp;
                    being told the discovery of America by Madoc &#8211; thought proper to draw a ship of the age of Columbus, &#8211; which I never saw till it
                    was engraved. the only vignette which pleases me is that emblem of the Cross &amp; the Palm &amp; the living stream.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> An engraving of the palm tree and cross appears above the exordial lines of <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805).</note> that in the title is very pretty,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The titlepage has a <hi rend="ital">troph&#233;e</hi> of the shield of Southey&#8217;s patron and friend <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams
                            Wynn</ref>, a harp and an unidentified stringed instrument, a sword, a bow with arrows, an Indian bonnet, and an opened
                        book of music.</note> &amp; the title itself would have been perfect if all the letters above had been the same pattern as
                    Madoc, &amp; that vile line of Roman letters had not occurred in the imprint.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The book &amp; letter which you mention have not reached me. It will probably find its way in the next parcel,
                    &amp; so I hope will the newest new version of the Psalms.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Cottle, <title>A New
                            Version of the Psalms of David</title> (1801).</note> the only way in which such a version could be made to answer the
                    cost of publication, is, by getting it if possible into use in the chapels. By this means any dissenting minister could
                    essentially serve you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I myself have many things in head &amp; some in hand. the great history still continues my main &amp; favourite
                        employment.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> I
                    think of yet another great poem but waver about the subject, sometimes thinking of Pelayo, the restorer of the Xtian monarchy in
                        Spain,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;story of Pelayo&#8217; would become the subject-matter of Southey&#8217;s poem
                            <title>Roderick, The Last of the Goths</title> published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in
                        1814.</note> sometimes of the Deluge.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> A plan that was never fulfilled.</note> by the
                    spring when my yearly batch of criticism is over I shall perhaps have determined. &#8211; I wish Madoc could pass thro such friendly
                    hands as <del>xxxxx</del> yours. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be kindly remembered to you &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">your good mother &amp; your sister</ref>. remember me also kindly &#8211; how time runs by! I
                    have known you &amp; <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">your family</ref> now a full third of my life! &amp; may sign myself
                    truly your old as well as your affectionate friend. &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>