<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1325</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2447</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Dr
                        Williams's Library, London, Crabb Robinson MSS.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 90&#8211;94 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1325" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1325" type="letter">
        <head>1325. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard Duppa</ref>, <date when="1807-05-23">23 May
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Richard Duppa Esqr/ 51. Great Marlborough Street/
                        London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MY 26/ 1807<lb />Endorsed: x 23 May 1807/ Southey to Duppa<lb />MS: Dr
                        Williams's Library, London, Crabb Robinson MSS<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 90&#8211;94 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-05-23">May 23. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Duppa</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti,
                            with His Poetry and Letters</title> (1806).</note> &amp; your letter reached me at the same time. I have cut the leaves,
                    collated the prints, &amp; observe many valuable additions, &amp; some great typographical improvements. It was accompanied by a
                    note from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Mr. Murray</ref>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Murray was the
                        publisher of Duppa&#8217;s <title>Michael Angelo</title>.</note> of a very complimentary kind. I like to be complimented in my
                    authorial character, &amp; best of all <del>xx</del> by booksellers, because their good opinion gets purchasers, &amp; so praise
                    leads to pudding, which I consider to be the solid end of praise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott&#8217;s</ref> promise to do what he can for M. Angelo in the
                    Edinburgh, &#8211; with this sort of salvo, &#8211; that <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> is not a very practicable [MS
                    torn], but he would do his best with him. My acquaintance with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> is merely an <hi rend="ital">acquaintance</hi>; but I had occasion <hi rend="ital">once</hi> to write to him respecting the <del>purchase</del>
                    sale of a MS. entrusted to me, &amp; bought by him for the Advocate&#8217;s Library, &amp; in that letter I introduced the subject.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey requested Scott to obtain a favourable notice in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>
                        in his letter to him of 4 February 1806 (Letter 1152).</note> I was greatly in hopes, &amp; indeed
                    expected, that <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> would have done as much in the Critical, by means of
                    his brother who writes the red hot orthodoxy there, he being, if you know, the man who believes in <hi rend="ital">40</hi>
                    articles, nine &amp; thirty not being enough for his capacious conscience.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review of Duppa&#8217;s book, cavilling at the author&#8217;s neglect of orthodox
                        grammatical rules, appeared in the <title>Critical</title>, 10 (1807), 385&#8211;399. Christopher Wordsworth (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>) reviewed for the <title>Critical Review</title>.</note> Had it not been for this, I
                    might perhaps have done something by applying to Fellowes, the Anti-Calvinist,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert
                        Fellowes (1770&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>) took orders but never held a position within the Anglican Church, though he published
                        several books on religious topics, such as <title>A Picture of Christian Philosophy</title> (1799) and <title>Religion without
                            Cant</title> (1801). He was the editor of the <title>Critical Review</title> from 1804 to 1811.</note> &#8211; a very
                    interesting man, &#8211; such a one, indeed, that, tho I never met him but once, I <del>should</del> could without scruple have written
                    to him. Wonderful to tell, he bears a part in that Review, tho his opinions are as opposite to <hi rend="ital">Hunt&#8217;s</hi>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Higgs Hunt (1780&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>) was joint-editor of the <title>Critical
                            Review</title> from 1805&#8211;1807.</note> &amp; all his other steeple-hunting whippers-in, as light is <del>xx</del> to
                    darkness. The hostile article I have not seen, &#8211; one of the advantages of living here is, that I never see these things till their
                    season is over, &#8211; &amp; then, like wasps in winter, their power of stinging is <del>over</del> &lt;at an end&gt;. I should have
                    been angry at seeing your book abused when the abuse could do any <del>xxx</del> hurt, &amp; should &lt;have&gt; felt that sort of
                    heat in my cheek, which denotes the moral temperature of the minute to be above temperate. Now, whenever it falls in my way,
                    which, very likely, never may be the case, it will come as a matter of literary history, &#8211; as what was said by some malevolent
                    &amp; ignorant person when <del>the</del> &lt;a good&gt; book first appeared, &amp; so it will furnish me an anecdote to relate
                    when I speak of the book, or if I should ever live to old age, &amp; have leisure to leave behind me that sort of transcript from
                    recollections, which would make such excellent materials for the literary history of my own times.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are mistaken about <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry White</ref>; the fact is briefly this. At
                    the age of seventeen he published a little volume of poems of very great merit; &amp; sent with them to the different Reviews, a
                    letter stating that his hope was to raise money by them to pursue his studies &amp; get to College. Hamilton,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Hamilton (dates unknown), owner of the <title>Critical Review</title> 1799&#8211;1804.</note>
                    (then of the Critical), showed me this letter, &#8211; I asked him to let me <del>xxx</del> review the book &#8211; which he promised &#8211; but he
                    sent me no books after the promise &#8211; which was lucky as when he failed he was in my debt. Well, the M Review noticed this little
                    volume in the most cruel &amp; insulting manner.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had favourably reviewed Henry
                        Kirke White, <title>Clifton Grove, a Sketch in Verse, with other Poems</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1803</title>, 2 (1804), pp. 552&#8211;554. He included the unfavourable review published in the <title>Monthly Review</title>
                        for February 1804 in the &#8216;Account of the Life of H. K. White&#8217; that prefaced the <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White, of
                            Nottingham</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807). He also included a letter vindicating Kirke White published in the March number
                        of the <title>Monthly</title>.</note> I was provoked, &amp; wrote to encourage the boy, &#8211; offering to aid him in a
                    subscription for a costlier publication, &#8211; I spoke of him in London, &amp; had assurances of assistance from Sotheby, &amp;, by
                    way of <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, from Ld Carysfort<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Joshua
                        Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), judge, diplomat, Whig politician and poet; the author of
                            <title>Dramatic and Narrative Poems</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; his second letter to me, however, said he was going to
                    Cambridge, under <hi rend="ital">Simeons</hi>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Simeon (1756&#8211;1824), MP for
                        Reading.</note> protection. I plainly saw the Evangelicals had caught him, &amp; and as he did not want what little help I
                    could have procured, &amp; I had no leisure for new correspondences &#8211; ceased to write to him, but did him what good I could in the
                    way of reviewing, &amp; getting him friends at Cambridge. He died last fall; &amp; I received a letter informing me of it. It gave
                    me a sort of shock, because, in spite of his Evangelicism, I always expected great things &#8211; from the proof he had given of very
                    superior powers, &#8211; &amp;, in replying to this letter, I asked if there were any intention of publishing any thing which he might
                    have left, &amp; offered to give an opinion upon his papers &#8211; &amp; and look them over. Down came <del>a</del> a box-full, the
                    sight of which literally made my heart ache, &amp; my eyes overflow, for never did I behold such proofs of human industry. To make
                    short, I took the matter up with interest, collected his letters, &amp; have, at the expense of more time than such a poor fellow
                    as myself can very &lt;well&gt; afford, done what his family are very grateful for, &amp; what I think the world will thank me for
                    too. Of course I have done it gratuitously. &#8211; His life will affect you, for he fairly died of intense application, Cambridge
                    finished him, &#8211; when his nerves were <del>almost</del> &lt;already&gt; so over-strained that his nights were utter misery, they
                    gave him medicines to enable &lt;him&gt; to hold out during examination for a prize! The horse won, &#8211; but he died after the race!
                    &#8211; Among his letters there is a great deal of Methodism &#8211; if this procures for the book, as it very likely may, a sale among the
                    righteous over-much, I shall rejoice for the sake of his family &#8211; for whom I am very much interested. I have, however, in justice
                    to myself, stated, in the shortest &amp; most decorous manner, that my own views of religion differ widely from his.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), I, p.
                        58.</note> Still, that I &lt;should&gt; become &#8211; &amp; and that, too, voluntarily &#8211; an editor of methodistical and Calvinistic
                    letters, is a thing which, when I think of it, excites the same sort of smile that the thoughts of my pension does, &#8211; &amp; I
                    wonder, like the sailor &#8211; what is to be done next. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Want of room has obliged me to reserve most of your letters, &#8211; which I meant for the latter end of Espriella&#8217;s
                        remarks<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from
                            the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; but when I came to the latter end &#8211; the printing had got beyond my calculation of
                    pages so much, that I was fain to stop.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Letters from England</title>, Duppa
                        contributed to the description of the monuments in Westminster Abbey (in Letter 23) and the discussion of shopping in London
                        (in Letters 7 and 11). Though it was not used, he also contributed a letter discussing an exhibition of pictures at the Royal
                        Academy and material on the Literary Fund; see Southey to Richard Duppa, 5 August 1806 (Letter 1206) and 17 August 1806
                        (Letter 1212).</note> I have good hope of such a sale as may induce my friend to travel again<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> There was no sequel to <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> &#8211; my own stock of matter not being half
                    exhausted, &#8211; nor, indeed, my design half compleated. <del>Xxxx xxxxxxxx xxx xxxxx xx xxxx xxxxxxx</del> the book ought to be
                    published in a month &#8211; Palmerin will appear nearly at the same time, &amp;, perhaps, tend to remove suspicion, if any should
                        subsist.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert
                            Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807). Southey wanted to preserve his anonymity as the author of
                            <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> The reception of this book will determine whether it is to be followed up or
                    not, &#8211; but if it be, be assured that you shall have ample revenge upon Fuseli.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Fuseli (1741&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), the history painter and admirer of Michelangelo, whom Duppa suspected of writing a
                        hostile review of his book on the painter.</note> I will tell you a criticism of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my
                        daughter</ref> upon him &#8211; I showed her the print of the creation of Eve &#8211; in Darwins Temple of Nature &amp; the little one
                    looked up to me &amp; said, why does she show her bottom so?<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">See Erasmus Darwin (1731&#8211;1802;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Temple of Nature; or, The Origin of Society</title> (London, 1803), between pp. 54&#8211;55; the
                        engraving was taken from a painting by Fuseli.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know nothing of botany, &amp; every day regret that I do not. It is a settled purpose of my heart, if my children
                    live, to make them good naturalists. If you come either into Yorkshire or Northumberland, you must not return to the south without
                    touching at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, &amp; seeing me in <del>xx</del> &lt;my&gt; glory. We have
                    papered the parlour this very day. It is not so fine a room as yours, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Duppa &#8211; but it is very beautiful, I
                    assure you, &#8211; &amp; the masons are at this time making a cieling to my study, &#8211; &amp; I have got curtains for it, the colour of
                    nankeen, &#8211; &amp; there is to be a carpet, &amp; a new fender, &amp; all sorts of things that are proper. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> tells me she has seen you &#8211; I am in good hope of persuading her to come down
                    this summer, &amp; if she comes, she shall not go till I have a set of drawings for the parlour. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want to hear, in spite of great trouble, &amp; little profit, that you have fixed upon <del>some</del> a new
                    subject, &amp; are again at work. There is no being happy without having some worthy <del>xxx</del> occupation in hand. &#8211;
                    Wordsworths poems I have not yet seen, they will appear I suppose in a parcel of which I am in daily expectation &#8211; <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> (1807).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>