<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1489</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2611</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 160&#8211;162.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1489" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1489" type="letter">
        <head>1489. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">John Adamson</ref>, <date when="1808-08-12">12 August 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 160&#8211;162.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-08-12">Aug. 12. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your translation, and will, by the first carrier, send off the plays of Ferreira and Quita, and the
                        Saudades.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Adamson was the translator of <title>Donna Ignez de Castro, a Tragedy, from
                            the Portuguese of Nicola Luiz, with Remarks on the History of that Unfortunate Lady</title> (1808). Antonio Ferreira
                        (1528&#8211;1569), <title>In&#234;s de Castro</title> (c. 1557); Domingos dos Reis Quita (1728&#8211;1770), <title>In&#234;s de Castro</title>;
                        Manoel de Azevedo Morato (dates unknown), <title>Saudades de D. Ignez de Castro. Das ne convertida em, Loureiro. Glojsa a hum
                            Soneto de Camoes</title> (1716).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have mistaken the meaning of <hi rend="ital">Xarifalte</hi>. Portuguese orthography is very loose in any but
                    modern authors, and it is sometimes necessary to hunt a word through every possible mutation of labial or guttural letters. Under
                    g&#233;rafalte it is to be found, which is the ger-falcon of our ancestors.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The story of I&#241;ez is, in any point of view, sufficiently atrocious, but the poets have not been true to history. It
                    is expressly asserted by Fernan Lopez,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3829 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library was Fernam Lopes/Fern&#227;o Lopes (c. 1385&#8211;1459), <title>Cronica Del Rei Dom Fernando O Noveno Rei De Portugal</title>, &#8216;a
                        fine old MS., but stained and wormed in the margin, russia, gilt leaves&#8217;.</note> that Pedro denied his marriage during his
                    father&#8217;s life, and never affirmed it till some years afterwards: what is still worse, that Alfonso repeatedly asked him if she
                    were his wife, and said that if she were he would acknowledge her as such.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In&#234;s Peres de
                        Castro (1325&#8211;1355), the murdered lover of Prince Pedro (1320&#8211;1367). When, after the death of his father King Afonso IV
                        (1291&#8211;1357), Pedro became king of Portugal in 1357, In&#234;s was declared to have been his wife and crowned queen as a
                        corpse.</note> I am myself decidedly of opinion that she was not. The arguments against the fact of the marriage which Joam
                    das Regas used at the election of King Joam I.,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jo&#227;o das Regras (13??-1404) was a
                        Portuguese jurist who in 1385 provided arguments against the rival claimants to the throne of Jo&#227;o (1358&#8211;1433), the
                        illegitimate son of Pedro I by Teresa Louren&#231;o. Jo&#227;o was then chosen by the nobles as king, becoming Jo&#227;o I. The new king
                        rewarded Jo&#227;o das Regras with titles and lands.</note> are to me as satisfactory as those which he brought against its
                    legality, if the fact had been proved, would have been in these days. I am sorry, also, to disbelieve the coronation of the dead
                    body: there is not a word of it in the Chronicler, though he fully describes its removal from Coimbra, and the Portuguese nobles
                    were not men who would have submitted to such a ceremony.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If your play be of modern date, Nicola Luiz<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author remains obscure to
                        literary historians: he has been identified as Nicolau Luis da Silva (1723&#8211;1787), author of chapbook comedies.</note> is
                    probably a modern author, and that removes all difficulty concerning him. There was a tragedy upon the same subject, published by
                    Dr. Simmonds<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Symmons (1749&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Inez, a
                            Tragedy</title> (1796).</note> about ten years ago, which obtained considerable praise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your translation, I dare say, does justice to the original; had it been still unprinted, I would have noticed a few
                    instances in which the proper names are mis-accented. What pleases me best in the play, is to perceive that the author has avoided
                    the fault of Camoens,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vaz de Cam&#245;es (1524&#8211;1580), the author of <title>Os Lus&#237;adas</title>,
                        or the <title>Lusiads</title> (1572).</note> and not made his heroine talk about Hyrcanian tigers, and such other commonplaces
                    which pass current for passion and for poetry.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have seen the Fonte das Lagrimas;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Fonte das L&#225;grimas&#8217;, which,
                        according to the legend, originated from the tears shed by In&#234;s de Castro when she was killed, is located close to a spring on
                        the Quinta das L&#225;grimas estate in Coimbra.</note> Link omits to mention that two beautiful cedars brush its surface with their
                    boughs. I have also seen the tombs of I&#241;ez and Pedro; they are covered with bas-relief, which ought to be accurately copied and
                    engraved.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Heinrich Friedrich Link (1767&#8211;1850), <title>Travels in Portugal: and through
                        France and Spain</title> (London, 1801), p. 302. The tombs are at the Monastery of Santa Maria, Alcobaca.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a shocking story of one of the children of I&#241;ez, &#8211; the Infant D. Joam, who murdered his wife;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Infante Dom John of Portugal (1349&#8211;1387) killed his wife Dona Maria Telles de Menezes (c.
                        1338&#8211;1379), suspecting her of adultery.</note> it is a worse story than even the murder of his mother. If at any time chance
                    should bring you this way, I shall have great pleasure in showing you all those facts of Portuguese history relating to your
                    subject, which have occurred to me in the course of long and laborious employment upon the history and literature of Portugal.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> I am, Sir,</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours respectfully,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>