<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1016</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2138</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    305&#8211;308.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1016" type="letter">
        <head>1016. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1805-01-10">10
                        January [1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M. P/ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    305&#8211;308.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-01-10">Jan<del>y</del>. 10</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have letters from my brother this evening. He is appointed first lieutenant to poor Lord Proby&#8217;s ship.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby (1779&#8211;1804), eldest son of Sir John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of
                        Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>). Proby was the captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, who, having been sent to
                        the disease-ridden Leeward Islands station, died on 6 August 1804 at Surinam, from yellow fever.</note> &#8211; I am sorry to add
                    that the vessel is in the most dreadful state. In the last 24 hours before he wrote they had buried four, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> himself had experienced some alarming symptoms the evening before <del>he
                        wrote</del>, which however had left him. As he has had one attack of the fever before I hope he is in less danger of a second.
                    Were it not for this new danger the affair of the Court Martial might be considered as very fortunate for him.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey was court-martialled for neglect of duty, disobedience of orders and contempt in
                        contradicting his captain, Sir Henry Heathcote (1777&#8211;1851), in command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, 1803&#8211;1805. The
                        last charge only was proven, but he was dismissed from his ship, the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>. However the commander of
                        the fleet in which Thomas served, Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>),
                        appointed him lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class frigate of the French navy captured in 1796,
                        and a finer ship than his previous one. On taking up his appointment on the <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, Thomas found the
                        ship&#8217;s crew struck down by fever.</note> The Commodore<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral)
                        Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), who was in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey
                        served.</note> to whom it was the means of introducing him speaks of him in very high terms &amp; has even said that he was
                    fitter to command the Galatea than his Captain.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 2.</note> It seems too that he
                    has got some credit for his defence which is very likely as he had not prepared one, <del>till</del> till <del>when</del> he was
                        <hi rend="ital">called</hi> upon for it &amp; allowed half an hour. On subjects which have affected him I have known him write
                    very affectingly, &amp; this short time <del>xxx</del> would be <del>xx</del> advantageous as it gave him no leisure to think of
                        <hi rend="ital">how</hi> he should say what he had to say, which would have puzzled him &amp; made him curse his stars for not
                    being able to write like Robert. He tells me there are hardly officers to make in the West Indies, &amp; asks if I have not
                    interest enough to get his name mentioned at the Admiralty. If the combined forces should defeat <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the Colonel</ref> &amp; the Doctor<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Doctor&#8217; was the
                        nickname of Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), whose father had been a physician. Prime
                        Minister from 1801 to 1804, Addington was removed from office by the &#8216;combined forces&#8217; of William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806, <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James
                            Fox</ref> and <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>. Southey hoped that the new
                        government would bring him useful connections in the Admiralty through Wynn, who was Grenville&#8217;s nephew, and William Dickinson
                        (1771&#8211;1837), a fellow pupil with Southey at Westminster School, Civil Lord of the Admiralty, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> I shall have in
                    more ways than one.</p>
        <p rend="indent6"> 3&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;2&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;1&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;4</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For this story telling business &#8211; <hi rend="ital">copia me inopem fecit</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;abundance makes me speechless&#8217;.</note> I have ten thousand stories &#8211; but it is ten to one that
                    whatever I send may come to you like a twice told tale, &#8211; &amp; to take a story out of its fit place is like tooth drawing or like
                    putting a picture in a bad light. Richest I am in stories of Catholic Mythology. I could tell you how when Adam fell sick he sent
                    Shem to the gate of Paradise to beg a branch of the Tree of Life &#8211; in hopes thereby to escape the penalty of death. That Shem got
                    the bough &#8211; but returned with it too late &#8211; that he planted it upon the grave of Adam, where it took root. That Noah took the tree
                    with Adam&#8217;s bones into the Ark. That Adam was buried at Golgotha so called in consequence. That the Tree which was a Trinitarian
                    tree being at once a palm, a cypress &amp; a cedar, was cut down for Solomon&#8217;s temple, but being by accident or rather especial
                    Providence not used in the building was the actual Cross, which was planted upon Adams skull &#8211; so that as it had at first grown
                    upon his grave, it <del>xxx</del> attracted his whole nature.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For these stories see the
                        Latin edition (Cologne, 1700) of the compendium of lives of the saints, <title>Flos Sanctorum</title> by Pedro de Ribadeneyra,
                        vol. I, pp. 19&#8211;20.</note> Much too I could tell you of the Virgin Mary &#8211; how she must be bodily in heaven &#8211; because no
                    reliques of her have ever been found on earth &#8211; which whatever you may think of it is sound logic to a papist. I could tell you
                    how St Peter had a daughter called Petronilla who was very ill; that one evening when he had company he said to her get up &amp;
                    wait upon my friends, when her disease left her &amp; she arose in health; &amp; that when they were gone he said now Petronilla
                    go to bed &amp; be sick again. &amp; so he let her die.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Petronilla is discussed in the
                        Latin edition (Cologne, 1700) of the compendium of lives of the saints, <title>Flos Sanctorum</title> by Pedro de Ribadeneyra,
                        vol. I, pp. 252&#8211;253.</note> But these are no tales for a Xmas fireside. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some such as these might make Ballads &#8211; if they do not find a worthier occupation. St Eucherius Bishop of Orleans
                    being rapt in a vision to the other world saw Charles Martel tormented bodily for the sin of sacrilege. When he recovered from his
                    trance he called to St Boniface King Pepins chaplain &amp; told him what he had seen, requesting that the <del>grave</del>
                    &lt;tomb&gt; of Charles Martel might be opened to verify what he affirmed. They opened it accordingly &amp; out came a huge
                    dragon. There was no body to be found &amp; the inside of the tomb was black &#8211; as if a fire had been burning there.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hincmar (806&#8211;882), Archbishop of Reims, reported this story to a Council of Quierzy in 858. It
                        concerns Saint Eucherius, Archbishop of Orl&#233;ans (c. 687&#8211;743), his enemy Charles Martel (c. 688&#8211;741) the Frankish ruler, St
                        Boniface (672&#8211;754), and Pepin (714&#8211;768), King of the Franks from 752 to 768&#8212;the son of Charles Martel. In <title>Acta
                            Sanctorum</title> (Antwerp and Brussels, 1643&#8211;1794). t. IV (January), &#8216;De S. Rigoberto Remensi Archepiscopo&#8217;, chapter IV
                        &#8216;Caroli Martelli sacrilegia damnatio&#8217;.</note> &#8211; When St John the Almsgiver was in his last illness a woman came to him for
                    absolution, but so overpowered was she with shame for her sinfulness that she could not articulate the confession. He therefore
                    bade her write it down, &amp; promised that none should ever see the writing. Before she could return to take back the paper &amp;
                    be forgiven, he was dead &amp; buried &amp; her confession with him. She went to his grave &amp; complained fearing that her
                    secrets would now be known, &amp; for three days &amp; nights continued to weep by the tomb &amp; to upbraid the dead [MS torn].
                    At length all the inhabitants of the grave arose with St John [MS torn] for foreman, who told her that she disturbed the dead
                    &amp; wetted them with her tears: however he gave her her confession sealed. Her own writing was obliterated, &amp; in its place
                    these words appeared &#8211; &#8216;Thy great sin forgiven thee because of my servant John&#8217;.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> This
                        story of St John the Almsgiver (d. c. 1616/1620 ) is contained in a contemporary biography by Leontios, 7th century Bishop of
                        Neapolis, <title>Vita Sancti Joannis Eleemosynarii</title>, p. 93, col. 1623; <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, t. II (January),
                        p. 501b.</note> &#8211; True stories these &#8211; the next is equally true &amp; more comprehensive. Fray Antonio de Santarem once
                    knocked a Devils eye out (Martin Luther once did the same thing with an inkstand<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Coleridge relates this story in <title>The Friend</title>, 8 (5 October 1809). See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>,
                        ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton, 1969), II, pp. 118&#8211;120.</note>) a poor rogue of a shepherd by name
                    Domingos fell in with this one eyed Devil &amp; made a bargain with him that he would make him pass for a Saint. Accordingly
                    Domingos began to work miracles with great success. The affair however was managed clumsily. They stole a cross containing certain
                    relics, burnt it &amp; then made a miraculous discovery of the treasure. The Knight to whom it had belonged claimed it, but the
                    mob hooted &amp; fell upon him &amp; Domingos went on triumphantly till Brother Antonio who had darkened one of the Devils
                    daylights fell upon him, got him into his church &amp; exorcised him; upon which he confessed all his tricks &amp; laid them all
                    to the Devils account. This being a first offence &amp; Domingos having given up his accomplice he was forgiven. But it was not
                    long before he drove certain cows to Badajoz for sale, where they were unluckily claimed by the owner. Domingos peached again,
                    &amp; said that his friend the Devil had met him in disguise &amp; desired him to sell the cows on his account, promising to pay
                    him well: No doubt was entertained of the truth of this story, &amp; that the latter part might be fulfilled to the letter, they
                    hung Domingos.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> This story is to be found in Boaventura Maciel Aranha (dates unknown),
                            <title>Cuidados da Morte, e Descuidos da Vida</title> (Lisbon, 1761), pp. 557&#8211;8.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Father, said a Franciscan to Frey Gil,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A brief life of Frey Gil de
                        Santarem (d. 1265), the well-known Portuguese Dominican, about whom there are numerous legends including the story that he
                        made a pact with the devil, is contained in <title>Cuidados da Morte, e Descuidos da Vida</title> (Lisbon, 1761), pp.
                        458&#8211;64.</note> I have overcome a terrible temptation. A woman was behind me in the street &amp; the Devil assaulted me
                    furiously, the nearer she came the stronger the temptation grew. At last I stood still &amp; determined to look her full in
                    &lt;the&gt; face &amp; brave the old Enemy. And so I conquered. &#8211; What sort of a woman was she said Gil. He replied very old &amp;
                    abominably ugly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The story of St Magnus&#8217;s dance is in Matthew of Westminster<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the
                        fourteenth-century manuscript chronicle <title>Flores Historiarum</title> (first printed 1567), the author (the so-called
                        &#8216;Matthew of Westminster&#8217;) records a story from the town of Colewiz in Saxony, where, in the year 1012, the priest of the
                        church of Magnus Martyr cursed a group of revellers so that they were compelled to continue singing and dancing without pause
                        for a year. For a translation, see Matthew of Westminster, <title>The Flowers of History</title>, 2 vols (London, 1853), I, p.
                        502.</note> who hath sundry good stories &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> which are much curtailed &amp; mutilated in the Nuremberg
                        Chronicle.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Nuremberg Chronicle, or <title>Liber Chronicarum</title> (1493) by
                        Hartmann Schedel (1440&#8211;1514) contains stories derived from many earlier chronicles, including the <title>Flores
                            Historiarum</title>.</note> Matthew Paris too is very rich in these things.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Matthew Paris (c. 1200&#8211;1259; <title>DNB</title>) was a Benedictine monk, English author of the <title>Chronica
                        Majora</title>.</note> I have got scent of a <del>xxx</del> tremendous story about K Arthur to be found in Gervase of Tilbury
                    &#8211; concerning his <hi rend="ital">family of apparitions</hi>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Volume one of
                            <title>Scriptores rerum Brunsvicensium</title> (Hanover, 1710), ed. Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz (1646&#8211;1716), contains
                        Gervase of Tilbury (c.1150&#8211;c. 1228), <title>Otia Imperialia</title>, in which Gervase reports the tradition that Arthur and
                        his knights were seen in the form of ghostly huntsmen.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>