<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.968</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2090</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="968" type="letter">
        <head>968. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-07-22">22 July
                        [1804]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Mr Danvers/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: E/ JUL 25/ 1804<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1804-07-22">July 22.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your way will be either to Manchester or Liverpool as you like best. the most expeditious is by the former place in
                    the mails, but it is the most expensive &amp; is too fatiguing. you had better make for Liverpool from thence in the long coach to
                    Kendal &#8211; &amp; there the coaches turn off &amp; you must pursue your route by some other means. Kendal is 30 miles from <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> but 20 of that distance lie thro the Lake country. In what trim are you for
                    walking? &#8211; suppose you take chaise for Bowness, (ten miles) &#8211; this place is on the shores of Windermere, &amp; from thence walk
                    about ten more to <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>, where I will meet you. there is a little inn there where
                    we can have decent beds, &amp; Wordsworth will show us all the best walks in that neighbourhood. <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> is 13 miles from us, a most delightful road. from hence we can accomplish
                    every thing else within a days distance by riding, except <ref target="places.html#Ullswater">Ullswater</ref>, which must be left
                    for your way back. Now then as to calculation of time &#8211; &amp; here you will find I fear an inconvenient delay at Birmingham. the
                    long coach from thence to Liverpool <del>goes</del> sets out at five or six, &amp; gets in in about 20 hours. the next morning you
                    start at six or seven for Kendal &amp; arrive about 10 that night. the fare will be 5 or 8 &amp; 20 shillings this last stage,
                    &amp; about 30 from Birmingham. do you therefore let me know when you mean to be at Kendal (there is always room in the long
                    coaches) &amp; on the following day I will be at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> &#8211; or perhaps (if the
                    weather be fine) at Bowness to meet you. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This plan you see is calculated for you if come alone. Should the <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">Smiths</ref> come with you the house at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> will not have room. you must
                    then go from Kendal to <del>Lowood</del>
          <ref target="places.html#LowoodInn">Low-Wood</ref>, &amp; <del>I will meet</del> thence to
                        <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> seeing <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> in the way. they
                    should go to the Royal Oak here at first, &amp; then if they stay as long as I hope &#8211; &amp; as they should do to see the country,
                    take lodgings, if good ones are to be had. I wish they may come while you are here, &#8211; we shall have some delightful days on the
                    Lake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bring with you some hypercarbonated kali<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sodium bicarbonate, used to
                        regulate acidity in food and create effervescence in soda water.</note> &#8211; for what we get by that name will not effervesce at
                    all. &amp; also some East India Sugar &#8211; a few pounds for your own consumption. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> will have some little thing to send by you. &amp; (to finish the paragraph of business) have the goodness to pay
                    ten pounds to <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Mrs Fricker</ref> in <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs
                        Coleridges</ref> name.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your intelligence about <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> alarmed me, tho I conclude from the tone of
                    what followed &amp; the tense, that all danger was over when you wrote. <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> has been
                    here, he appeared to less advantage than he had done in London. Yesterday young Roscoe called, &amp; dined with me &#8211; we thought
                    his manners remarkably pleasant. he is said to be a cleverer man than <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">his
                        father</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Stanley Roscoe (1782&#8211;1843): poet, who was close to his father,
                        William Roscoe, in outlook and tastes. Educated at Peterhouse, Cambridge, he became a partner in his father&#8217;s bank, and was
                        also a student of Italian literature. He published a book of poems in 1834. He married Hannah Eliza Caldwell (d. 1853) on 10
                        September 1818 and their son William Caldwell Roscoe was also a poet and essayist.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> arrived about three weeks ago, a good deal mannified both in person &amp;
                    manners since I had last seen him, &amp; of course a more suitable companion. he knows a great deal, seems to have chosen his
                    society well at Edinburgh, &amp; is certainly a young man with whom any body would be pleased &#8211; I have at last got a birth for
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Scapegrace</ref>. he is to go to Plymouth immediately, &amp; Admiral Colpoy<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Colpoys (c. 1742&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), British naval officer who achieved notoriety for
                        inciting the mutiny at Spithead in 1797. He was promoted to full Admiral in 1801 and appointed as Commander-in-Chief at
                        Plymouth in 1803. In 1804 he gave up his command to take a seat in the Admiralty.</note> will ship him off for a foreign
                    station. this good I have got by the change of ministry.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have corrected five proofs of Madoc.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which
                        Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and since then had been intermittently revising. It was completed in October 1804 and
                        published in 1805.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> prints with such excellent accuracy that I
                    never have any occasion to alter except for the sake of correcting the text itself or altering my own punctuation. I have nearly
                    compleated all the new parts of the poem &#8211; a week, if no visitors come in, will bring me to the first introduction of Thalala<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A character in <title>Madoc</title>.</note> &#8211; Book 8 in your copy, &amp; then, except one
                    section to be introduced in the old eleventh book, I shall have only to amend &amp; ornament the old story. the labour will be
                    over. it will be a relief to me when I have fairly done with it &#8211; after having for so many years considered it as a thing which
                    was to <del>be</del> do<del>ne</del>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It grows late &#8211; another proof in which I had a new passage to interpolate has detained me, &amp; I will not delay
                    the letter another day, that [MS torn] may have the more time to make your arrangements. How glad we shall be to see you! to
                    introduce you to <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>,
                    &amp; my dog &#8211; Dapper, who is as great a favourite as ever <del>Dapper</del> Cupid was!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Danvers&#8217;s dog, formerly Southey&#8217;s.</note> &#8211; if there be any new number of the Missionaries or the Baptists bring them
                        down.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to <title>The Transactions of the Missionary Society</title>,
                        which were first issued as separate numbers, each dealing with a specific mission, from 1798 onwards. They were gathered into
                        volumes, the first including the transactions for the years 1795&#8211;1802 in the Pacific and South Africa, the second (London,
                        1804) beginning with further South African transactions. The <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> were published as a periodical beginning in 1793, but then as bound volumes from 1800.</note> the first
                    from Barry,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown), a Bristol bookseller and stationer.</note>
                    the latter from James.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac James (b. 1759) was the son of Samuel James (1716&#8211;1773),
                        Baptist minister at Hitchin. He came to Bristol in 1773 as a student at the Baptist Academy During the late 1790s and early
                        1800s, James collaborated with <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref> in selling numerous works, mostly by
                        dissenters. As an associate of members of the Baptist Missionary Society Committee, James was well placed to supply the
                            <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, 6 vols (1800&#8211;1817), which Southey reviewed
                        in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title> (1803), 207&#8211;218.</note> I am grievously in want of a bookseller here, &amp; also
                    of a Juniper.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A &#8216;Juniper&#8217; was Southey&#8217;s term for a bookbinder, and &#8216;juniperize&#8217; meant to add a gold
                        border and lettering to the bindings of his books. The allusion was to Friar Juniper (d.1258), disciple of St Francis of
                        Assisi (Giovanni Francesco di Bernardone; 1181/1182&#8211;1226), who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to
                        give to a poor woman begging alms.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>