<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1409</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2531</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1409" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1409" type="letter">
        <head>1409. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-01-02">2 January
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ <del>Ludlow</del>/
                        [deletion and the remainder of the address in another hand] No. 9 Saville Row/ London <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark:
                        [partial] 1808<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-01-02">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 2. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Uncle,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may suppose that the news from Lisbon<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> That, on 29 November 1807, the
                        British navy had aided the Portuguese Prince Regent and the Queen, his mother, in escaping Napoleon&#8217;s invasion of their
                        country by escorting them across the Atlantic to Brazil.</note> has spurred as well as interested me. The books which <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref> had loaded down to me for reviewing (tho I had formally desired to have
                    none but such as I myself should specify) &#8211; have been shifted off to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>,
                    &amp; those of weightier matter to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 27 December [1807] (Letter 1405) and Southey to William
                        Taylor, [December 1807] (Letter 1408).</note> I have nothing to impede me except the introduction to the Cid,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> &amp; that has for
                    the main part has been done these four years &#8211; it requires only to be new-modelled with the new matter which will be found at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were all my documents at hand I could go to press in a month.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, with
                        the <title>History of Brazil</title>.</note> If they are to be found in London I will find them, but <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has in vain sent round to the booksellers with a list of French books not one
                    of which was to be found. I am now trying the provincial booksellers. The <ref target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">Bp
                        of Llandaff</ref> offers me a letter to Lord Spencer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George, Lord Spencer-Churchill,
                        5th Duke of Marlborough (1766&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), politician and book collector, who had his library at his house near
                        Reading.</note> &#8211; I shall take his letter conditionally, <del>which is</del> &#8211; that if his Lordships books are only to be
                    looked at I will not flatter him &amp; tantalize myself by looking at them. If they are to be used, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> shall take me to him, &amp; I will carry the Bishops letter. Thevet &amp; Claude
                    d&#8217;Abbeville are the &lt;French&gt; books wanted for the first volume &#8211; probably neither of them of much value, &amp; yet they
                    ought to be examined.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet (1516?-1592), <title>Singularitez de la France
                            antarctique</title> (1557); Claude d&#8217;Abbeville (dates unknown), a French Franciscan missionary to Brazil, and author of
                            <title>Histoire de la mission des p&#232;res Capucins en l&#8217;isle de Maragnan et terres circonvoisins</title> (1614).</note> Some
                    histories of Paraguay are more essential &amp; here I am utterly at a loss &#8211; for Charlevoix is good for nothing, &amp; I have
                    nobody but Charlevoix after Schmidel breaks off.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre Francois-Xavier de Charlevoix
                        (1682&#8211;1761), <title>Histoire de Paraguay</title> (1756); Ulrich Schmiedel (?1510&#8211;1579?), a German mercenary in the service of
                        Spanish conquistadors who travelled up the river Plate from Buenos Aires into the interior of Peru and Bolivia. Schmiedel was
                        the author of <title>Viaje al R&#237;o de la Plata</title> (1534&#8211;1554).</note> Herreras Hist. of Philip 2 in which he promises to
                    continue his greater work contains nothing to my purpose except the expedition of Orsua &amp; that wretch Lope de Aguirre.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625), <title>Historia general del mundo del tiempo
                            del rey Felipe II, desde 1559 haste su muerte</title> (1601&#8211;1612). Southey took from Herrera the story of the ill-fated
                        Amazon expedition of exploration conducted by Pedro de Urs&#250;a (1526&#8211;1561) and Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510&#8211;1561), but omitted it
                        from his <title>History of Brazil</title> and instead published it separately as <title>The Expedition of Orsua: and the
                            Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You did not send me Brito Freire,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Brito Freyre (1625&#8211;1692),
                            <title>Nova Lusitania, Historia da Guerra Brasilica</title> (1675).</note> I shall wait for him, having got as far as the
                    capture of Olinda,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Olinda, in Pernambuco, Brazil, was held by the Dutch in the late
                        1630s.</note> &#8211; &amp; bring up the affairs of Maraham to that time as they are to be found in Bernardo Pereira,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernardo Pereira de Berredo e Castro (d. 1748), governor of Maranh&#227;o 1718&#8211;1722, author of
                            <title>Annaes Historicos do Estado do Maranha&#333; de sey Descivrunebtim, at&#232; 1718</title> (1749).</note> to be collated with
                    Claude d&#8217;Abbeville whenever he comes to hand. My first volume will probably end with the final expulsion of the Dutch, &#8211;
                        <del>x</del> for all this remaining part there will be neither <del>ma</del> lack of materials, nor difficulty in arranging
                    them. There is a difficulty in the former part &#8211; I am now transcribing it, fitting in notes, &amp; filling up chasms. If I can
                    find any old historian of Paraguay the book may go to press <del>as in</del> immediately on my return from town. But the mode of
                    publishing it is worth some consideration; there is no possible risk of loss, &amp; it is hard to pay half the profits as interest
                    for a nominal advance of capital to publish with.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I can borrow the Spanish Chronicles anterior to Alonso XI,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Among the
                        many chronicles written in medieval Spain are the <title>Chronica Adefonsi Imperatoris</title>, <title>Historia
                            compostelana</title>, the <title>Cr&#243;nica najerense</title> and the <title>Cr&#243;nica silence</title>. Alonzo XI (1311&#8211;1350)
                        was King of Castile and Leon.</note> I shall also be ready with the European branch of the history. It is written down to the
                    death of Joam 3, &amp; from the death of Sebastian to the final overthrow of Antonios projects.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John III (1502&#8211;1557), King of Portugal, and his grandson Sebastian, also King of Portugal (1554&#8211;1578). After
                        Sebastian&#8217;s disappearance on an expedition to Africa, Antonio (1531&#8211;1595), though thought by some to be illegitimate, claimed
                        the throne. He was ousted by the Spanish invasion of 1580. Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was originally part of
                        larger work, which remained incomplete, his History of Portugal.</note> Lord Bute<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute (1744&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), son of the 3rd Earl of Bute (1713&#8211;1792, Prime Minister
                        1762&#8211;1763; <title>DNB</title>) a literary patron, whose library the Marquess inherited.</note> or <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> will be likely to have what I want. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> also tells me that Thomas Grenville<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Grenville (1755&#8211;1846), Wynn&#8217;s cousin, First Lord of the Admiralty from 1806 to 1807.</note> has some Spanish books
                    which he will show me. I was not wrong in working chronologically, but it has turned out unluckily, as Portuguese Asia must now be
                    the last in order of publication, &amp; there is at least a quarto &amp; half of it on my shelf.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Barl&#339;us<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caspar Barlaeus (1584&#8211;1648), <title>Rerum per octennium in
                            Brasilia et alibi nuper gestarum sub praefectura</title> (1647), a work containing many maps and charts. Southey&#8217;s
                        library, on his death, contained an edition of 1660.</note> is not here for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to
                    copy. I have only the small Cleves edition &amp; my Mauritias<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Franciscus Plante
                        (1613&#8211;1690), authored <title>Mauritias</title> in 1647, a work containing many of the same engravings as Barlaeus.</note>
                    contains a fine print of Bahia but no charts whatever. Of what value are those in Giov. Giuseppes work?<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Giuseppe di Santa Teresa (1658&#8211;1735), <title>Historia delle Guerre del Regno del Brasile</title>
                        (1689).</note> if their accuracy be not better than their beauty they are good for nothing, &#8211; tho there is the manifest notion
                    of a panorama in one of them. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> present plan is to leave this place with me, part
                    from me at <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward Littletons</ref> in Staffordshire, &amp; strike for Bristol &#8211;
                    to put himself under a good surgeon there with whom I am intimate. His complaint is a prolapsus ani<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A prolapsed rectum.</note> &#8211; &amp; God knows whether he will ever be rid of it. He is now at Ambleside with
                    his friend <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>, whither I go <del>x</del> Wednesday to meet <ref target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">the Bishop</ref> at dinner the next day. He has worked hard at Spanish &amp;
                    Portugueze, &amp; made good progress since he has been here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Prince Joam<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Manuel, Prince of Portugal (1537&#8211;1554).</note> has
                    furnished me with as compleat an end to both histories as a tragedian could desire. He might have made it as fine a one &#8211; had the
                    thing been done solemnly. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>x</del> I do not wonder at the expectation there is of your papers. They will surely contain much which cannot be given in a
                    historical form, &amp; which will turn to equal account in some supplementary shape. I wish it were possible for you to pass the
                    whole summer here &#8211; But I shall see you &amp; talk with you in February. &#8211; My affairs are going on promisingly. there is every
                    reason to believe that Espriella<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> will fetch up
                    all my lea way in the <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Row</ref>, &amp; that what I have already done will supply ways
                    &amp; means for this new year, &amp; leave <del>the</del> &lt;my&gt; whole time at my own disposal.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>