<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1534</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2656</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add
                        MS 30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 106&#8211;108.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1534" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1534" type="letter">
        <head>1534. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-11-12">12 November
                    1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth Dock Torbay/
                        Single<lb />Endorsements: Correction made to address [in another hand]. <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add
                        MS 30927<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 106&#8211;108.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The intelligence which I have to communicate will surprize you, if you have not already heard it from some other
                    quarter. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is married. The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperial Colonel</ref>  told me this was to be the case, some eight or nine weeks ago, adding that he had seen the
                        <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">Lady</ref>, but there are so many Hills in the world that I utterly
                    disbelieved his reported rumours. Married however he is to the fourth daughter of Lovelace Bigg Wither, a gentleman of great
                    weight in the county of Hampshire, &amp; of the very ancient &amp; good family of my old friend George Wither the poet. It seems
                    however that he must have taken the name for an estate, for his daughters name was Bigg.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lovelace Bigg (1741&#8211;1813) inherited the estate of Manydown, Hampshire, in 1789. He then took the name Bigg-Withers and
                        brought up his children there. George Wither (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, was a distantly-related
                        ancestor.</note> I learn from <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> that her fortune is said to be about 4000&#163;. &#8211;
                    with the expectation of something more at her fathers death. Of her age or of any thing else I know nothing,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine was thirty-three.</note> except that she hopes to see <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; me when we visit &#8216;the more enclosed parts of England&#8217; &#8211; <del>xx</del> is
                    not this <hi rend="ital">eempraunce</hi> in any body who lives by the Black Mountains<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        range of rough hills, scarcely inhabited, on the Welsh side of the river Wye near Hay-on-Wye, and a few miles from Hill&#8217;s
                        parish of Staunton.</note> to call <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> uncivilized?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am heartily glad of this, for it frequently made me uneasy to think how solitary the remainder of my Uncles life
                    was likely to be. He has none of those inveterate habits which often render late marriages uncomfortable, &#8211; all his habits have
                    been plucked up by the roots, &amp; he had new ones to acquire. The evil is that if he should have children there is no hope of
                    his living to see them grow up. That however is a remote evil. There will be enough for their education, &amp; if I am living
                    there will be somebody to superintend it. Cousin Robert will not do for a play fellow, when the age of riding <hi rend="ital">pocko</hi> is over,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A name for Southey when his son, Herbert was riding on his
                        back.</note> but he will do for something better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And so Tom we have got another Aunt by the Lord! &#8211; How will this be relished in the College Green?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, at the Bristol residence of Southey&#8217;s aunt <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Elizabeth Tyler</ref>.</note> &#8211; I am very curious to see this new relation, with whom, in case of a family, it is likely
                    that one day I must have be so nearly concerned. My Uncle may be trusted for chusing well. Aunt I shall not call her, being too
                    old to consider her as such. It seems more as if a brother had married, than a kinsman of another generation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now after this Gazette Extraordinary, comes the flat part of the newspaper, filled up how it can. It is time
                    that another Letter should arrive from you, &amp; I am daily looking for it. Two proofs of Thalaba have reached me, the notes are
                    in a very beautiful type, &amp; this edition will greatly x excel the former in its appearance.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> was published in 1809.</note> Kehama is just now
                    in great glory &#8211; he has won the Swerga, &amp; Kalyal is riding abroad in the huge chariot of Jagerenaut, as the Idols bride:<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 14.</note> I have got on to 2500 lines,
                    &#8211; probably half the poem.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A few days ago came a letter from <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, communicating to
                    me the as yet secret intelligence, that it is thought expedient to set on foot a Review for counteracting the base &amp; cowardly
                    politicks of the Edinburgh. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> it seems was the suggestor, to some of the
                    men in power. &#8211; <del>xx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &#8211; (the Baviad &amp; Massinger Gifford) is to be Editor, &amp; he
                    commissioned Bedford to apply to me. The pay will be as high as the Edinburgh, &#8211; &amp; such political information as is necessary
                    will be official communicated from official sources, &#8211; for in plain English the ministers set it up. But they wish it not to wear
                    a party appearance, &#8211; only to breathe at this time the right English at-him-Trojan spirit. Would I write about Spain was asked. I
                    have asked in return if they can bear to have the principle avowed of no peace while Bonaparte lives, &#8211; &amp; if I may damn Sir
                    Hew Dalrymple,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s exasperation was caused by the Convention of Cintra, signed on
                        30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under
                        Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed
                        to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command
                        by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which
                        Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> &#8211; sine-qua-nons upon the subject with me. And I have offered to take
                    those departments for which I conceive myself sufficiently qualified.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see
                        Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 9 November 1808 (Letter 1530) and 11 November 1808 (Letter 1532).</note> Next week will
                    probably bring in tidings how this is settled, &#8211; &amp; by the time these Annuals are off my hands, &#8211; a parcel on the new account
                    may be expected to arrive. They require no pledge to any party or set of opinions &#8211; I [have] [MS torn] taken care that there shall
                    be no mistakes about mine, &#8211; explicitly informing <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> that I am an enemy to
                    peace-mongers, an enemy of Catholic emancipation, a friend of the Church Establishment because I am a heretick requiring
                    toleration, an almost Quaker, &#8211; a damner of Sir Hew Dalrymple &amp; C<hi rend="sup">o</hi> &#8211; &amp; a friend to reform as being the
                    only thing which can prevent revolution. All fair &amp; above-board. The articles which are in fashion will most likely weigh down
                    those that are not. But is it not amusing that such an application should be made to me from such a quarter!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Little <ref target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> De Quincey</ref> is at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> &#8211; he was here last week, &amp; is coming again &#8211; I wish he was not so little,
                    &amp; I wish he would not leave his great coat always behind upon the road. But he is a very able man, with a head brimful of
                    information.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing can be done in the way of a County meeting against <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Ld
                        Lonsdale</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> therefore is now writing a pamphlet about the
                        Convention,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Concerning the Concerning the Relations of Great
                            Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the
                            Convention of Cintra</title> was published in 1809.</note> which doubtless will do your heart good. Curwen<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), Whig MP for Carlisle, Workington
                        landowner.</note> called here the day after we met him at Calverts<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert
                        (1771&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), who was at school with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at
                        Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death of his father, Calvert became a man of independent means,
                        inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east shore of Bassenthwaite, near Keswick, where he lived with
                        his family.</note> &#8211; pressing me to visit him at Workington. If I go it will be with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref> &#8211; for the sake of tracing the Derwent the whole way.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The river Derwent, after passing by Southey&#8217;s home <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>,
                        flows north and west to meet the sea at Workington.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-11-12">Nov. 12. 1808</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>