<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1313</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2435</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS
                        4812D.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 74&#8211;77 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1313" type="letter">
        <head>1313. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-04">[April
                        1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: April 1807<lb />MS: National Library of Wales MS
                        4812D<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 74&#8211;77 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> And so I am a court-pensioner!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn succeeded, before he left office, in
                        arranging that the pension he paid Southey from his personal funds was replaced by a government pension.</note> It is well
                    that I have not to kiss hands upon the occasion or upon my soul I do not think I could help laughing at the changes &amp; chances
                    of this world. O dear dear Wynn when you &amp; I used to hold debates with poor <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury</ref> over a pot of porter, how easily could your way of life have been predicted. &amp; how would his &amp; mine
                    have mocked all foresight. And yet mine has been a straight onward path. Nothing more has taken place in me than the ordinary
                    process of beer or wine &#8211; of fermenting, &amp; settling, &amp; ripening.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If Snowdon will come to <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> in the summer, Skiddaw will <del>come</del>
                    go to Snowdon at the fall of the leaf. I shall work hard to get the Cid<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition
                        of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> ready for publication &amp; must <del>x</del> go with it to London,
                    for the sake of getting at a few books in the Museum<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> &amp; some
                    perhaps at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> To take advantage
                        of the library of Spanish books assembled by <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Henry Richard Vassall-Fox</ref>.</note>
                    which I have not myself. In that case my intention is to go first to Bristol &#8211; &amp; perhaps to Taunton, &#8211; &amp; Wales will not be
                    out of my way. &#8211; but I wish to show you those parts of this country which you have not seen, which I have since you were here:
                    &amp; to introduce you to the top of <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, which is an easy mornings walk.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Specimens<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), co-edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, and published, to Southey&#8217;s dismay, with numerous errors.</note> shall be sent you when
                    the cancels are compleated &#8211; &amp; I am glad it has not been done sooner for this reason. They call upon me for a supplement<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was not issued.</note> &#8211; to supply the numerous omissions which were none of them my
                    making. <del>xx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Dapple</ref> has made wild work with his mutilations, interpolations, &amp;
                    alterations &#8211; &amp; whether the charitable world of book buyers will ever give me an opportunity of setting all this to rights is
                    very doubtful.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), which was jointly edited with Bedford and to Southey&#8217;s dismay
                        contained numerous errors. A second edition was not called for.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The mystery of this wonderful history of the change in administration is certainly explained;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of All the Talents, in which Wynn had served as Under Secretary of State
                        in the Home Office, had broken up because the King would not accede to its plan to introduce an act emancipating Catholics
                        from the civil penalties and restrictions placed upon them.</note> but who are the Kings advisers? Are they his hopeful sons &#8211;
                    or old Lord Liverpool?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Banks Jenkinson, 2nd Earl of Liverpool (1770&#8211;1828;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; Mr. Simeons<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Simeon (1756&#8211;1824), MP for
                        Reading.</note> wise remark that the new ministry was better than no ministry at all &#8211; put me in mind of a story which might
                    well have been quoted in reply. One of the German Electors when an Englishman was introduced to him thought <del>to hit his
                        national</del> the best thing he could say to him was to remark that it was <del>very</del> bad weather &#8211; upon which the
                    Englishman shrugged up his shoulder &amp; replied yes &#8211; but it was <hi rend="ital">better than none</hi>. &#8211; Would not this have
                        <hi rend="ital">told</hi> in the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You do not shake my opinion concerning the Catholicks. Their religion regards no national distinctions &#8211; it teaches
                    them to look at Christendom &#8211; &amp; on the Pope as the head thereof, &#8211; &amp; the interests of that religion will always be
                    preferred to any thing else.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey objected to the emancipation of Catholics as it
                        would allow into public office men who were loyal to the Pope rather than to the King.</note> Bonaparte is aware of this,
                    &amp; is aiming to be the head of a Catholick party in Germany &#8211; the scheme is curious. They propagate the nonsense of Jacob
                        Behmen<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jakob B&#246;hme (1575&#8211;1624), the German mystic, shoemaker and author of
                            <title>Aurora</title> (1612), admired by German intellectuals and Catholic converts including Karl Wilhelm Friedrich
                        Schlegel (1772&#8211;1829) and Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph Schelling (1775&#8211;1854).</note> first &#8211; which has already put
                    Kant &amp; Fichte<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Immanuel Kant (1724&#8211;1804) and Johann Gottlieb Fichte
                        (1762&#8211;1814).</note> out of fashion there, &#8211; &amp; then when they have prostrated the understanding of the people, the conquest
                    is easy. The main movers of this new propaganda are at Rome, where <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    knew some of them, &amp; obtained distinct information upon the <del>xx</del> subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So sure as the Catholicks were admitted into the navy so surely would you have a Catholick Chaplain on every ship,
                    &#8211; &amp; I would stake my salvation that some of them would be carried into Brest to serve the Anointed Emperor.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, Napoleon.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These people have been increasing in England of late years, owing to the number of seminaries established during
                    the French Revolution. It is worth your while to get their Almanack the Lay Directory it is called &amp; published by Brown &amp;
                    Keating &#8211; Duke Street &#8211; Grosvenor Square.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Catholic Directory and Annual Register</title>.</note> They are at their old tricks of miracles here and every
                    where else. St Winifred<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miraculous cures were being claimed at the holy spring of St
                        Winifred at Holywell, north Wales, a site of pilgrimage since the medieval period, where, in the seventh century, St Beuno is
                        said to have restored his niece St Winifred to life after Caradoc, a rejected suitor, had cut off her head. In 1806 John Milner
                        (1752&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), the Catholic bishop, published <title>Authentic Documents Relative to the Miraculous Cure of
                            Winifred White, of the Town of Wolverhampton, at Holywell, in Flintshire, on the 28th of June, 1805</title> detailing many
                        cases of miraculous cures at the fountain. Southey and Milner became opponents in print in the 1820s.</note> has lately worked
                    a great one, &amp; is in as high odour as ever she was.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am for abolishing the test<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Test Act of 1673 required all persons
                        filling any office, civil or military, to take oaths of supremacy and allegiance to the King and the Church of England.</note>
                    with regard to every other sect &#8211; Jews &amp; all, &#8211; but not to the Catholics. They <hi rend="ital">will not tolerate</hi>; &#8211; the
                    proof is in their whole history, in their whole system, &amp; in their present practice all over Catholick Europe. And it is the
                    nature of their principles <hi rend="ital">now</hi> to spread in this country. Methodism &amp; the still wilder sects preparing
                    the way for it. The old remedies have been proved efficient, &amp; should again be enforced. You have no conception of the zeal
                    with which they seek for proselytes, nor the power they have over weak minds, for their system is as well the greatest work of
                    human wisdom as it is of human wickedness. It is curious that the Jesuits exist in England as a body, &amp; have possessions here
                    &#8211; a Catholick told me this, &amp; pointed out one in the streets of Norwich &#8211; but he could tell me nothing more, &amp; expressed
                    his surprize at it &amp; his curiosity to learn more. Having been abolished by the Pope, they keep up their order secretly, and
                    expect their restoration, which if he be wise Bonaparte will effect. Were I a Catholick that should be the object to which my life
                    should be devoted &#8211; I would be the second Loyola.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ignatius of Loyola (1491&#8211;1556), founder
                        of the Jesuits.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Concessions &amp; conciliations will not satisfy the Catholicks like our Llewellyn<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Llywelyn ap Gruffydd (c. 1223&#8211;1282; <title>DNB</title>), the last prince of independent Wales before its
                        conquest by Edward I. Llywelyn several times proved willing to come to terms with the English crown.</note> &#8211; vengeance &amp;
                    the throne <del>xxx xx</del> are what they want. If Ireland were far enough from our shores to be lost without danger to our own
                    security I would say establish the Catholick religion there &#8211; as the easiest way of civilizing it, &#8211; but Catholic Ireland would
                    always be at the command of the Pope, &amp; the Pope is now at the command of France. It is dismal to think of the state of
                    Ireland. Nothing can redeem that country, <del>xxxx</del> but such measures as none of our statesmen &#8211; except perhaps Marquis
                        Wellesley<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Colley Wellesley, 1st Marquess Wellesley (1760&#8211;1842;
                            <title>DNB</title>): Anglo-Irish politician and bellicose Governor-General of the British colonies in India between 1798
                        and 1805.</note> &#8211; would be hardy enough to adopt &#8211; nothing but a system of Roman conquest &amp; colonization &#8211; &amp; shipping
                    off the refractory savages to the colonies &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> England condescends too much to the Catholick religion, &amp; does not hold up her own to sufficient respect in her
                    foreign possessions: &amp; the Catholicks instead of feeling this as an act of indulgence to their <del>xxxxxxx</del>
                    &lt;opinions&gt;, interpret it as an acknowledgment of their superior claims, &amp; insult us in consequence. This is the case of
                    Malta. In India the want of an established Church is a crying <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> evil. Nothing but Missionaries can secure in
                    that country what we have won. The converts &lt;would&gt; immediately become English in their feelings &#8211; for like Mahomet we ought
                    to make our language go with our religion &#8211; A better policy this than <del>xx</del> that of introducing pig tails after our own
                    home plans of princely reforms &#8211; for which Ld W. Bentinck<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant-General Lord William
                        Henry Cavendish-Bentinck (1774&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). When Governor General of British India from 1828, Bentinck
                        introduced a policy of Westernisation &#8211; making English the language of government rather than Persian and attacking Hindu
                        practices such as sati.</note> &#8211;with all due respect to him, &#8211; or whoever else was the agent in this inconceivable act of
                    folly &#8211; ought to be gibbetted upon the top of the highest pagoda in Hindostan.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>Xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx xxx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Devil &amp; his Dam will be a terrible cry to have raised against you. As for me you will not suspect me of any
                    undue bias in favour of our Church Establishment: &#8211; a very little alteration would make it <del>xx</del> as good as any
                    Establishment can be, &amp; it is the best extant &#8211; but in my own opinions I am as to all essential points so very nearly a
                    Quaker, that if it were not for their non-essential peculiarities I should quietly enter their fold, &amp; no longer be a stray
                    sheep in the land. But just as they, who hold all wars to be forbidden by Christ, think the British navy exceedingly useful &#8211; just
                    so do I regard the Church Establishment; &#8211; it is our protection against the intolerance of Romish bigotry, or Calvinistic
                    fanaticism.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I suppose I shall receive an official confirmation from the Treasury.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            See note 1.</note> &#8211; in what manner are these things paid? &#8211; do they remit, &#8211; or do I draw &#8211; as thanks to Lord
                            Melville<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>),
                            Secretary of State for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806.</note> &#8211; navy officers are now permitted
                        to do from abroad.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>