<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1550</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2672</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Oxford, MS Don. c.
                        79.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1550" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1550" type="letter">
        <head>1550. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">Thomas Smith</ref>, <date when="1808-12-05">5 December
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ Thomas
                        Smith Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ <del>Bownham House/ Stroud/ Gloucestershire./ Single Sheet</del> [MS illegible] to/ Gone To/
                        Eason/ Grey/ nr Tetbury<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; MINCHINHAMPTON/ 104<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Oxford, MS Don. c.
                        79<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-12-05">Dec. 5. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should send you this prospectus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prospectus for Coleridge&#8217;s
                        self-published journal <title>The Friend</title>, which he produced in 1809 and 1810. For the text see <title>The
                            Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton, 1969).</note> with great pleasure, were it not for
                    certain doubts &amp; fears as to the regularity &amp; perseverance with which the work will be carried on. Ability there is an
                    abundance, but for <hi rend="ital">sta</hi>bility I dare not be a voucher. That <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> head is full every body knows. &amp; I know that his common place books are full also; &#8211; if he has but the
                    resolution to arrange them &amp; put his scattered <del>materials</del> &lt;fragments&gt; in order. there will be no lack of
                    materials, [MS torn]atever he will do, will be of the <del>best</del> very best order, &#8211; no man living is so capable of
                    instructing [MS torn]blic, &amp; if he puts his design in execution it will be doing great food at a seasonable time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will wish me to say something about that country of which we are all thinking, &amp; for which so many are
                    fearing &amp; desponding. I have no fears for Spain. Great reverses we must hear of, Bonaparte at Madrid,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph-Napol&#233;on Bonaparte (1768&#8211;1844) was the elder brother of Napoleon, who made him King of Naples and
                        Sicily (1806&#8211;1808), and, in August 1808, King of Spain and the Indies as Joseph I of Spain (1808&#8211;1813). Joseph was forced by a
                        revolt to abandon Madrid and did not return until January 1809, after French reinforcements retook the city.</note> probably
                    at Lisbon, &#8211; but not master of Spain, &#8211; never &#8211; never &#8211; never. If there is any nation under heaven whose spirit is unconquerable
                    it is the Spanish nation. No people are so proud of their ancestors &amp; of their country, &#8211; no people have such reason to be
                    proud. They have done greater things there ever way other people atchieved, &amp; we have already witnessed what that remembrance
                    has enabled them to <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;do&gt; in their present contest. Bad as their religion is it is a mighty ally in times
                    like these: xx they are as sincere in it as ever, &amp; probably more attached to it because the higher clergy have long been men
                    of most exemplary lives. &#8211; Bad as their government is, it has never <hi rend="ital">corrupted</hi> the people as ours has done. &#8211;
                    they are <hi rend="ital">patriots</hi>, &#8211; we alas, are whigs &amp; tories, outs &amp; ins. &#8211; <hi rend="ital">tantararara</hi>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s parlance, derived from popular song, for the the noise and hot air produced by
                        party spirit on the benches of the House of Commons. <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by
                        John O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Dramatic Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London,
                        1798), III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All Fools All&#8217; was also a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754;
                            <title>DNB</title>) play <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> or rogues all &#8211; is the burthen of the song.
                    Manufactures have not vitiated the lower class. Commerce has not given the middle one an interest distinct from that of the
                    country. &#8211; there will be no clamourers for peace because their looms are stopt, &amp; their cotton pieces on hand. Of all men
                    under heaven the Spaniards can best bear the privations &amp; hardships of actual service. &#8211; they will starve out the French. &#8211;
                    absolutely hunger &amp; watch them to death. Then they have no Duke of York,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince
                        Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. York had commanded troops
                        in the disastrous Flanders expedition in 1793&#8211;1794. In 1809 rumours over corruption erupted into a full-blown scandal in which
                        York&#8217;s mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), a former courtesan, was shown to have preferred officers
                        for promotion in return for payment.</note> no royal family, &amp; no rotten Boroughs. &#8211; When I look at the proceedings of the
                    Court of Inquiry, &amp; see King, Ministers &amp; Lord-Mayor endeavoring to stifle the only generous cry that it has been my lot
                    to hear from the depth of England,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s exasperation was caused by the Court of
                        Inquiry set up to investigate the conduct of the generals at the Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French
                        army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the
                        1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its
                        weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals,
                        just arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew
                        Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). The inquiry failed to punish Burrard and Dalrymple, but they never afterwards took
                        command.</note> I get ashamed of my country, &amp; am obliged to think of such men as Sidney &amp; Hutchinson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Algernon Sidney (1623&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>). A republican executed for involvement in the Rye
                        House plot to assassinate the monarch. Colonel John Hutchinson (1615&#8211;1664; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan commander in the
                        English civil war and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I, as revealed in a posthumously published memoir by
                        his widow, Lucy Hutchinson (1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>): <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806).
                        In the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 361&#8211;378, Southey extolled the conduct and morality of
                        Hutchinson.</note> &amp; Milton, &#8211; least I should wish to renounce my birth place, &amp; talk Spanish for the rest of my
                    life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yet there is hope at home as well as abroad. That cry which was heard against the cursed Cintra convention came
                    from the heart of England. &amp; there is a stirring among the bones which seems to indicate that the Day of
                        <del>xxxxxxxxxxx</del> Resurrection &lt;&amp; of Judgement&gt; is at hand. at public meetings men do as they are bid. because
                    their votes are bought &amp; sold like any other dirty commodity. &#8211; but in private you hear but one opinion, &#8211; one sense of
                    national degradation. &#8211; one feeling &#8216;that it is not &amp; it cannot come to good&#8217;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act I, scene ii, line 158.</note> &#8211; which is a sure presage that good is
                    coming.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have reason to expect our excellent good friend <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> here at
                    midsummer. He is to conduct his wards to Liverpool, &amp; will bring <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David</ref> on to the
                    Lakes. This last summer is the only one that we have past without some abiding guest. My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> was called off in June by the Admiralty, &amp; is now I trust lying snug at anchor
                    in Torbay. that shocking system of keeping up the blockade thro all weather, having happily been given up, to the salvation of
                    ships &amp; seamen. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> is officiating at Durham, with fair prospect of
                    soon halving the practice of the place. &#8211; but I look at the Magazine Obituaries, &amp; do not find any such increase of mortality
                    there as should induce me to think he has much to do. He would grin at me with anger if he heard that sentence. As I
                        <del>not</del> have not seen him since his return from Lisbon, I purpose paying him a visit early in the new year. We are but
                    fourscore miles asunder, &amp; it is good fortune that our lots have not been more distant.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of myself the news is that I am weary of waiting for any reduction in the price of paper, &amp; so my History of
                    Brazil will set off this week to the press.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History
                            of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> And that the Hindoo romance,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> the beginning of which <del>xxxxx</del> you heard at Bownham,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Smith&#8217;s home in Stroud, Gloucestershire.</note> has been only now resumed, &amp; is now
                    three parts done. Early in the spring I hope to have it compleated.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> begs to be remembered to <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith</ref> &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> believe me yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I have mislaid your present address &amp; must direct to Bownham.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>