<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1250</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2372</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add
                        MS 30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1250" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1250" type="letter">
        <head>1250. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-12-28">28 December
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol/
                        Single<lb />Endorsement: Alvarez Pereyra<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ DEC 31/ 1806<lb />MS: British Library, Add
                        MS 30928<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you got the &#8216;&#8220;Academy of Compliments&#8217;&#8221;?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Academy of Compliments: Being the Rarest and Most Exact Way of Wooing a Maid or a Widow ... With Passionate Love
                            Letters, ... Together With a Choice Collection of Songs</title> (1750?).</note> I am afraid not. But if you can borrow it,
                    look for all the best &amp; most approved forms of apologies &amp; excuses, &amp; multiply &#8216;ten thousand pardons&#8217; ten fold, &amp;
                    suppose all these ten times ten thousand excuses to be addressed to yourself by me, as the fit preamble to what I am about to
                    say.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> More books, &#8211; but hear <hi rend="ital">why</hi> &amp; judge if I can keep troubling you, &#8211; luckily too it will not
                    be any difficulty to find them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> writes to urge me to hasten with all possible expedition the portion of
                    my work which relates to Brazil, the times being as he truly says South America mad.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        prospective flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil (occurred 29 November 1807) prompted Southey, at his uncle Herbert Hill&#8217;s
                        request, to begin a history of Brazil, using papers sent him by Hill and stored by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>; see Southey to John Rickman, 23 December 1806, Letter 1247.</note> That box which you received from Mr
                    Murdoch,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A friend of Southey&#8217;s uncle Herbert Hill in Lisbon, who had arranged the removal of Hill&#8217;s papers to London. His first name and dates are unknown.</note> &amp; which is now in London was half full of MS.S. relating
                    to that country, &#8211; of such importance that by his desire I have offered the information they contain first to Government. <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>
          <del>xxx</del> replies that it relates to the wrong side of S. America for their immediate views, &#8211; but that so far from wishing
                    to keep any such information private Government would rather encourage me to publish it, &amp; strongly advise me to lay every
                    thing else aside, &amp; come out with my History of Brazil while the state of the public mind &amp; the political circumstance of
                    the world will secure me so great a sale. About this you will say nothing. But it is obvious that I have no time to lose, &#8211; &amp;
                    my reason for troubling you is for the few books relating to the subject at Bristol.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They will easily be found, being these. All the MSS. &#8211; there are I believe five volumes all in small folio &#8211; two of
                    these lettered Memorias Antigas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A collection of manuscripts concerning Portuguese history;
                        including, to judge by the endorsement of this letter, Ferna&#771;o Lopes (c. 1385-after 1459),<title>Cr&#243;nica do Condest&#225;vel de
                            Portugal</title> (first printed 1526) concerning the national hero Nuno Alvares Pereira, &#8216;the Holy Constable&#8217; (1360&#8211;1431).</note> &#8211; the
                    others single volumes &#8211; in leather binding. Vida do P. Ancheita.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos
                        (1596&#8211;1671), <title>Vida do Vener. Padre Joseph de Anchieta, &#8230; Taumaturgo do Novo Mundo, na Provincia do Brasil</title>
                        (1672). This book was no. 3798 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library after his death. Anchieta (1534&#8211;1597), was a
                        missionary to Brazil.</note> Vida do P. Antonio Vieyra.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; de Barros (1675&#8211;1754),
                            <title>Vida do Apostolico Padre Antonio Vieyra da Companhia de Jesus, Chamado por Grande</title> (1746). This book was no.
                        3313 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> each in folio, both lettered &amp; in dirtyish leather
                    binding. The Novus Orbis of J. de Laet,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Novus Orbis
                            seu Descriptionis Indi&#230; Occidentalis</title> (1633). It was no. 1670 in Southey&#8217;s sale catalogue.</note> a well bound
                    folio &#8211; better than my folios usually are; lettered I think Laete Novue Orbis &#8211; it is in plain calf &#8211; &amp; you may perhaps
                    remember my buying it of Emery &amp; Lansdowne<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Bristol bookselling and printing
                        business.</note> for half a guinea, a year after they had asked me thrice as much for it. Lastly a folio in parchment which
                    has been made square by inlaying the leaves &#8211; lettered if my memory fails me not by poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> in black letter Mauritias<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Franciscus Plante (1613&#8211;1690), <title>Mauritiados
                            Libri XII</title> (1647). No. 2159 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; you will instantly recognise it by
                    its size &#8211; it is a Latin poem with prints &amp; maps &#8211; one of the finest books in my possession. Having <del>done this</del> found
                    these &amp; boxed them off by waggon, refer once more to the Academy of Compliments, &amp; apply all the thanks you can find there
                    to yourself &#8211; &amp; then be assured that I <hi rend="ital">do</hi> thank you in my heart more heartily than all those forms can
                    express.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> for all the materials in his hands, &amp;
                    have luckily a large cargo here also.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Rickman, 27 December [1806],
                        Letter 1249.</note> In a month Espriella<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &amp; the
                        Review<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was reviewing for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> will be
                    done &#8211; &amp; I shall begin &#8211; in another month Palmerin<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published an edition of
                            <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> will be off hand &#8211; &amp; then I shall
                    do nothing else till this is afloat &#8211; from which I may reasonably expect very considerable profits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You saw <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> I conclude on his way to Plymouth &#8211; as you may suppose I
                    miss him much. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> grows but suffers more from wind than ever child was known
                    to do &amp; hardly gets any rest day or night &#8211; still he thrives. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> is
                    my delight &#8211; &amp; would be yours if you were here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall beg <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> when <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> writes, to get some trusty person to wipe all the books from the mould. The price of labour for three or four
                    days will be well laid out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The extent of this work of mind I cannot well estimate &#8211; probably two quartos &#8211; honest ones they shall be. I have
                    materials for a far better map than has ever appeared &#8211; &amp; shall copy a few necessary prints of costume from the old
                    travellers. I have the plan of the work in my head &#8211; which is no little thing, the materials being of so disjointed a nature &#8211; but
                    a very curious book it will be, &amp; of great importance. There is but one person in Europe who has such materials,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The identity of this Frenchman is unclear. It is likely that he was Abb&#233; Francois Garnier
                        (1722&#8211;1804), the long-standing chaplain to the French factory in Lisbon. A less likely possibility is Abb&#233; Jean-Antoine Dubois
                        (1765&#8211;1848), a French Catholic missionary in India, whose long sojourn in the southern districts brought him into contact
                        with the legacy of Portuguese Catholic colonialism there. Dubois&#8217;s manuscript history of Indian religion was purchased by the
                        East India Company and published in English as <title>Description of the Character, Manners and Customs of the People of
                            India, and of their Institutions, Religious and Civil</title> (1816).</note> &amp; his are in great part copied from the
                    very papers of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> &#8211; which he has been twenty years collecting &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-12-28">Dec. 28. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>