<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1416</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2538</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    48&#8211;50.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1416" type="letter">
        <head>1416. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-01-14">14
                        January 1808.</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M
                        P./Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    48&#8211;50.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may rest assured that not one syllable of the abuse in the Courier has come from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This has not been
                            identified.</note> The origin of the report is obvious. He is very intimate with <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>, who is one of the proprietors (not the editor) &amp; to whom the house
                    belongs, &amp; his home in town is in consequence at the Courier-Office. I am a little suprized that you should have thought it
                    possible any thing so contemptible could have come from him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If it be possible for me to create time for the employment you will see me in the Courier during the course of the
                    winter, or spring. I am resolved to take <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> in hand, &amp; give him a few
                    letters there, every one of which shall operate as a most vigorous sudorific. The impertinence with which he alludes to my
                    residence at the Lakes after having been my guest there, fully entitles him to any discipline which I may be disposed to bestow. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The reviewals which this animalcule &amp; the British Critic have set forth upon the Specimens have proved that it
                    is possible to produce something worse than the book.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807) were reviewed in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11
                        (October 1807), 31&#8211;40, and in the <title>British Critic</title>, 29 (1807), 245&#8211;249.</note> &#8211; I shall take your word for
                    George Stevens&#8217;s poem, &amp; let him hear of it: In one of his first numbers he saw he could read Virgils second eclogue with as
                    much pleasure as if it had been addressed to a different subject &#8211; he shall hear of that too.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey implies that Jeffrey approves of sexual immorality: The <title>Edinburgh Review</title> (pp. 36&#8211;37)
                        had regretted the relative lack of poems in the <title>Specimens</title> by the Shakespearian editor George Steevens
                        (1736&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>) and recommended two love poems for inclusion, the second showing the middle-aged Stevens
                        imagining vicariously, through his &#8216;boys&#8217;, the pleasures of wooing his mistress&#8217;s &#8216;girls&#8217;. Virgil&#8217;s second Eclogue was thought
                        to reveal his homosexuality and paedophilia.</note> I will take him up as moralist, politician &amp;c &#8211; &amp; gibbet him to
                    public contempt &amp; indignation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am obliged to you for the newspapers. Scott Warings reasoning, if it can be so called, is thoroughly
                        despicable.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), MP and author
                        concerning Indian affairs; he opposed the campaign to encourage the East Indian Company to allow missionaries to proselytise
                        in its territories and in 1808 involved himself in a pamphlet war on the subject, publishing in 1808 <title>A Reply to a
                            Letter, addressed to John Scott Waring, Esq., in Refutation of the illiberal and unjust Observations and Strictures of the
                            anonymous Writer of that Letter</title>.</note> Something I had read upon the subject in reviewing Buchanans Travels,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 49&#8211;61,
                        Francis Buchanan (1762&#8211;1829), <title>A Journey from Madras through the Countries of Mysore, Canara, and Malabar: Performed
                            under the Orders of the Most Noble the Marquis Wellesley, Governor General of India, for the Express Purpose of
                            Investigating the State of Agriculture, Arts, and Commerce; the Religion, Manners, and Customs; the History Natural and
                            Civil, and Antiquities, in the Dominions of the Rajah of Mysore, and the Countries Acquired by the Honourable East India
                            Company</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; &amp; I am not without hopes that in consequence of what I said to him yesterday, the
                        <ref target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">Bp of Llandaff</ref> may take up the subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The removal of the Court to Brazil cannot be otherwise than most highly beneficial to that country &amp; to this,
                    as we shall now trade as freely with the colony as we did heretofore with Portugal. Any thing like enlightened policy is not to be
                    looked for: nor any thing beyond what cannot possibly be avoided. The Prince<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Portuguese Prince Regent, John VI (the Duke of Braganza) (1767&#8211;1826).</note> is almost an idiot, &#8211; but just as he was obliged
                    to run away from Bonaparte (who proved himself the greater idiot of the two in this business,) just so will he be obliged to open
                    a free trade with England &#8211; circumstances compel him to it. With respect to the natives, I am of opinion that it would require two
                    or three generations of civilization or taming, before intermarriages could be productive of good. The mixed breed or Mamalucos as
                    they were called were desperately bad, &#8211; even the Jesuits pronounced them irreclaimable. I have not yet learnt what proportion of
                    the Brazilian tribes still exist upon the sea coast, &#8211; probably a very small one. They must have been pretty well used up by a
                    villainous sort of slave trade, against which the Jesuits never could prevail, till it was too late. Nor can I tell you what is
                    the present state of the missions, &#8211; they have probably diminished since the dissolution of that wonderful Society which was
                    destroyd just when it had ceased to be mischievious, &amp; was doing nothing but good. Those Reductions<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The name of the village colonies established by the Jesuits around their missions to the Brazilian and
                        Paraguayan Indians. Southey was to publish a poem on this subject in 1825&#8211;<title>A Tale of Paraguay</title>.</note> may
                    however easily be restored; &#8211; &amp; the Jesuits meant this system to go no farther. &#8211; theirs was a sort of illuminism; &#8211; designed
                    to tame the savages, &amp; keep them always in a state of subjection founded upon ignorance. Yet such Reductions are good
                    preparatory schools &#8211; it requires two or three generations to domesticate the animal, &amp; get rid of the effects of
                    cannibal-diet-&amp; wild habits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That paper of D Luiz da Cunhas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey discusses the 1738 manuscript
                        report, <title>Carta ao Marco Antonio</title>, of the Portuguese ambassador to Paris, Luiz da Cunha, in his <title>History of
                            Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 265, 296. Da Cunha describes therein the advantages that would accrue from the removal of the
                        court from Portugal to Brazil.</note> is greatly abridged. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> permitted
                    Lady Shuldham<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Margaret Irene (c. 1772&#8211;1811), daughter of John Sarney of Somerset House,
                        London, and widow of John Harcourt of Ankerwyke, Buckinghamshire, married Admiral Molyneux Shuldham (1717/18?&#8211;1798;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in 1790. The couple resided at Lisbon.</note> to bring the original to England, &#8211; she left it with her
                    son <del>to be</del> Simon Harcourt,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lady Shuldham&#8217;s son by her first husband.</note> &#8211;
                    to whom I applied for it, &#8211; &amp; could get no answer to my application. I shall be ready almost immediately on my return from
                    London to put the first vol of Brazilian history to press &#8211; &amp; if I can borrow the very few Spanish Chronicles which I still
                    want, &#8211; the first of the European hist. also.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no poems, &#8211; &amp; long disuse begin to occasion something like an unwillingness to attempt any. <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> wrote to me the other day &#8211; &amp; abused me for having left off
                    poetry &#8211; I told him in reply that if the world would buy my poems they should have more, but that they must not expect another
                    Madoc for five &amp; twenty pounds. &#8211; that it was well we should be contented with posthumous fame, &#8211; but impossible to be
                        <del>xx</del> so with posthumous bread &amp; cheese. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You and I are looking for the same great family event about the same time.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Wynn&#8217;s wife gave birth to a daughter (first name unknown) in 1808. Southey&#8217;s letter congratulating Wynn is dated [March 1808],
                        Letter 1437. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref>, the Southeys&#8217; fifth child was born on 9 February 1808.</note>
                    This is a little unlucky &#8211; for had my journey taken place a few weeks sooner I could have touched at <ref target="places.html#Wynnstay">Wynnstay</ref>, &amp; seen more of you in a day there than in a month at London, where we shall
                    both be very busy &amp; move in such <del>opposite</del> different circles that we shall never meet </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-01-14">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> . 14.1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>