<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.921</idno><idno type="nines">rce2043</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4844 .  Previously  published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 493–498.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="921" type="letter"><head>921. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1804-04-08">8 April 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address:
                        To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Endorsement: 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 1804/ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 20 May<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4844 <lb/>Previously published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 493–498.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> I had allotted this evening to dissect old Barbablao – &amp; am sorry the second edition should have arrived before the first was so noticed. but I had no suspicion
                    that you designed to reprint it in the Iris.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had printed his poem on Bluebeard (‘Barbablao’) in the newspaper he edited,
                            <title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title>, on 17 March 1804. A revised edition appeared three weeks later. It was later published in the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 38 (1814), 437–440.</note> What you say of cheap editions is still more applicable to newspaper publication. for short poems it is the best
                    possible vehicle, &amp; those which stand the test may then safely be transferred to a more permanent paper.</p><p rend="indent1"> Lines 7 &amp; 8 in the old copy are well omitted – but I miss the following couplet, which pleasd my ear &amp; tallied well with the story as you have represented
                    it. for the future <hi rend="ital">number the lines</hi> of such poems for the benefit of us critics. – The You know he was brother &amp; – comes clumsily in like the <hi rend="ital">you-knows</hi> in the opening of our old plays which always are addrest to the audience &amp; mean you do not know. – his will was <hi rend="ital">withstood</hi>.
                    is that word accurately used? surely withstand &amp; disobey are not synonimes. – The one line of Sister Anne which follows is not pleasantly – in fact not well – expressed – &amp;
                    methinks you have made Sister Anne too cool at the discovery – the <hi rend="ital">blood</hi> upon the key should alarm her suddenly. the couplet rhyming tomb &amp; doom is in its
                    close cramped &amp; crowded. The tongue trips against it. ‘The key my loose powerless fingers forsook’ a lame &amp; expletive way of saying I dropt the key. Now come two words
                    coupled either of which, in that place, <del>xxx xxx</del> I should have feard to use – <hi rend="ital">shy stare</hi> – &amp; both together I believe will strike every reader as
                    very uncouth &amp; disagreable. ‘‘on a peg of black wood’’. needless for <hi rend="ital">hung up</hi> is enough, &amp; worse than merely expletive by presenting an image too
                    definite &amp; too trivial. the next lines are very good had they been related by the Poet – but <del>not</del> altogether undramatic. the word <hi rend="ital">clung</hi> I do not
                    understand – &amp; the exquisite <hi rend="ital">touch</hi> is too technical a phrase – nor could M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bluebeard be so little terrified as to recognize any
                    likeness to the statue. Of the Heads speech I object to nothing but the way in which she expresses her decollation, which is too roundabout. The two first lines of Annes next
                    speech very clumsy. indeed the whole paragraph appears to me incorrigible. The brothers speech is again too poetical for the occasion.</p><p rend="indent1"> I now come to some smooth sailing – <hi rend="ital">build remission</hi> being the next objectionable phrase. then they applaud the sound of the horn when they ought
                    to have dreaded it – &amp; to have turnd pale. And prattling <hi rend="ital">prolongs every gift of the fire</hi> – I can affix no meaning to this. <hi rend="ital">all</hi> – too
                    plainly for the rhyme – Bluebeard is also too loquacious &amp; too poetical in sudden passion. My decision has never been sympathys fool – this I do not like – it means he be not
                    mislead by <hi rend="ital">com</hi>passion when <hi rend="ital">passion</hi> is what the sentence requires. <hi rend="ital">framed to confine the couch</hi> – awkward. &amp; that
                    vile word <hi rend="ital">spar</hi>! which is damned <del>by</del> the slang of pugilists. Say <hi rend="ital">And</hi> Sion instead of <hi rend="ital">Even</hi> – for it more
                    rapidly combines the thought &amp; more flowingly fills the sentence. You have given too much attachment to the horse – it is impossible – you have raised him to the rank which the
                    Dog holds – &amp; I suspect there are many degrees of transmigration before the soul <del>xxxxx</del> ascends from one to the other. <hi rend="ital">parry</hi> is too <hi rend="ital">fencing</hi> a phrase. <hi rend="ital">scrape</hi> too slow a one. nor do I recollect any precedent for making them stamp like sheep who threaten – or for setting
                    the Knight swearing. His armour big gushes &amp;c – another line of lame expression.</p><p rend="indent1"> And now having culled the weeds I come to the story. you have hurt it by lessening the atrocity of Bluebeard, who seems, bating his dealings with the Devil, to have
                    been as good as Knight need be. There is too a most incongruous mixture of &lt;the&gt; modern <del>xxxxx</del> &amp; the legendary. Sister Anne we must have – but why Eliza – so
                    modern a name as not to be fifty years old in English? &amp; in her dress the language &amp; – also the looking glasses are all modern. This surprizes me in <del>xxx</del> you, who
                    struck the right key with so unerring a hand in Ellenore!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ellenore</title>, Taylor’s translation of Gottfried August Bürger
                        (1747–1794), <title>Lenore</title>, became popular and influential on its publication in 1796.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> In fine you will see that in spite of all the fine lines which are not particularized &amp; in spite of the general power which pervades it the poem does not please
                    me. In all legendary tales I require the absence of all ideas &amp; phraseology which are manifestly modern &amp; force upon me the anachronism. In all dramatic writing or dialogue
                    I require brevity &amp; the breaks of passion &amp; the plainness <del>of</del>, in all, narrative rapidity – &amp; that it be so perspicacious as to be instantaneously understood.
                    – If I had given you the more recondite &amp; metaphysical feelings which make me object to the passages here noted as faulty – you would form some judgement of the care with which
                    I reject in writing. for it is a bad symptom that I am now as solicitous to wound faults as I once was to produce beauties: But again of Bluebeard – I believe a shorter line is
                    better for narration – &amp; wish you had modelled the story upon the old metrical Romances, for which I have a true veneration. – Cinderella is far better <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor’s poetical version of ‘Cinderella’, which had initially appeared in the <title>Iris</title>, 21 January 1804, was also published in the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 35 (1813), 234–236.</note> – I lookd for faults &amp; found none worthy of notice.</p><p rend="indent1"> My Eclogue<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘The Alderman’s Funeral; An English Eclogue’ originated in a funeral witnessed in Bristol in 1803. The poem was
                        not published until 1810, in <title>The Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>; see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols
                        (London, 2004), V, pp. 427–432; see Southey to William Taylor, 22 March 1804, Letter 915.</note> still sticks unfinished. I will send you a rhymed story which was in the
                    Morning Post six months ago<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘King Ramiro’, published in the <title>Morning Post</title> on 9 September 1803, and on 12 May 1804 in the
                            <title>Iris</title> (edited by Taylor) and then, revised, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and with
                        revisions in <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837–1838).</note> – but has since that copy was sent there receivd more alterations than I found in two Bluebeards – <del>you
                        will</del> it shall come this week &amp; I will thank you to use the scalping knife as unmercifully as the example is here set. </p><p rend="indent1"> And now to your two last letters. to what you say of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>  I have [MS torn] express a sense of
                    obligation, which is not easily expressed. – I shall soon see <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; will consult with him in what manner Harry had better receive
                    your assistance – for it seems to me it had better come immediately from yourself. I dread his extravagance, &amp; cannot excuse it.</p><p rend="indent1"> My last crossed yours on the road. I reviewed Malthus for <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">A Aikin</ref><note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                        review of Thomas Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the future improvement of Society; with Remarks on the
                            Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292–301.</note> &amp; he has
                    blundered strangely in sending it to you, for it was settled that I should review it in consequence of a conversation at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>
                    table with him. however I hope yours may win the place as I shall be very glad to build upon the timbers of mine with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> aid; who
                    has for the book the same contempt &amp; indignation that I feel – I am sorry you have pleaded for Pinkerton against <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> - for Turner is certainly in the right – &amp; Pinkertons assertions were merely for the sake of contradiction. he is a rogue in private life – &amp; very often a pretender
                    in literature.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>): Scottish antiquarian and cartographer whose many publications earned him a
                        reputation for irreligious views, arrogant irritability and personal immorality. Pinkerton believed the Celts were incapable of rising to high levels of civilisation and sought
                        to prove that Scottish place names were not of Celtic origin: he wished to trace the Scottish people to the ancient Goths and to purge Scottish culture of Celticism. Pinkerton
                        criticised Sharon Turner for treating, in his <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title> (1799–1805), recently-published Welsh poems as historical documents detailing real
                        events of the sixth century. Pinkerton assumed them to be forgeries. Turner replied to Pinkerton’s critique in his <title>Vindication of the Genuineness of the Ancient British
                            poems of Aneurin, Taliessin, Llywarch Hen, and Myrddin</title> (1803).</note> his pretensions in Spanish knowledge are perfectly impudent. I catch him sometimes in the
                    Critical telling downright lies.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pinkerton worked for the <title>Critical Review</title> from about 1795 to 1802, when he went to live in
                        Paris (<title>DNB</title>).</note> You will do mischief by rendering the Welsh poems suspected – I have more to say but time presses – &amp; you shall have the rest in a few
                    days with King Ramiro.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 5.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-04-08">Sunday April 8. 1804</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>