<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1160</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2282</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery. Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
               (London, 1856), I, pp. 359&#8211;360.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1160" type="letter">
        <head>1160. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-02-25">25 February 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <ref type="m" target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">Mr Guthries</ref> &#8211; Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb />Postmark: [partial] FE/ 1806/ 2<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                  (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 359&#8211;360.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should not put you to the cost of a letter, nor myself to that of the paper whereon it is written, if I had not
               learnt that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> is in London, &amp; in consequence been uneasy respecting
               the MSS,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been sent a manuscript volume containing rare medieval metrical romances
                  belonging to a Mrs Sherbrook (first name and dates unknown), and had posted it to Scott, who had arranged its purchase by his friend
                  Thomas Thomson (1768&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), an Edinburgh advocate, record keeper and editor of medieval manuscripts; see Southey
                  to Walter Scott, 4 February 1806, Letter 1152.</note> lest if his house, more Scotico<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In
                  the Scottish manner&#8217;.</note> be shut up, it should be lost &#8211; in which case I must pay for it. Do make enquiry if it has been taken
               &lt;in&gt; at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref>, &amp; if not, look after it at the Coach Office.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written about your bedoctoring expences both to Lisbon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Where Southey&#8217;s
                  uncle <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref> resided. This letter has not survived.</note> &amp; to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John May, 10
                  February 1806, Letter 1154.</note> but the sooner you let me know what they may amount to the better, that I may mention the sum
               when next I write. It is very long since <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has written &lt;to&gt; me,
               &amp; therefore I daily look for a letter from him, &#8211; &amp; in general it is my custom to answer letters speedily, while what there is
               to say is uppermost</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter has answered this part of my enquiries. About the Highlands I can say nothing. It is not likely that I
               should be able to afford either the terms or the money, &#8211; my whole exertions will be necessary to set me even with the world this
               summer being now sadly behind hand. At present it is my serious intention, immediately on returning from London to set about a
                  play,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write a play.</note> sorely against the grain &#8211; in the hope of
               acquiring such a sum as may make me feel quite easy till better times. &#8211; The Critical I had neither seen nor heard of<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was negatively reviewed by Charles Valentine Le Grice (1773&#8211;1858)
                  in the <title>Critical Review</title>, ns 7 (1806), 72&#8211;83.</note> &#8211; from Cambridge abuse would come very naturally from the friends
               of Malthus or Clarke,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and James Stanier Clarke
                  (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). In the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), Southey reviewed Clarke&#8217;s <title>The
                     Progress of Maritime Discovery, from the Earliest Period to the Close of the Eighteenth Century, Forming an Extensive System of
                     Hydrography</title> (1803), 12&#8211;20, and Malthus&#8217;s <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future
                     Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), 292&#8211;301. He
                  also reviewed Clarke&#8217;s 1804 edition of William Falconer&#8217;s (1732&#8211;1769) poem <title>The Shipwreck</title> (1762) in the <title>Annual
                     Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 577&#8211;580 and Clarke&#8217;s <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (1805), in
                  the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 99&#8211;100.</note> &amp; also very honestly from a fellow who learnt his taste when
               he did his Catechism, &amp; sticks with the same fidelity to all the articles in both, &#8211; <del>which x</del> &lt;which&gt; I conceive
               the case with those who are honestly orthodox. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> had had his
               wits about him in time he might have reviewed me there, for it is in that Review that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">his brother</ref>, who believes in <hi rend="ital">40</hi> articles, writes in defence of the
               whole mythology which has been added to the system of Jesus Christ.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Wordsworth, who
                  reviewed for the <title>Critical Review</title>, was an apologist for the Church of England. The 39 Articles of Religion, which
                  Southey puns on here, established the basis of Anglican belief in 1563.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do&#8217;nt sleep in your flan<hi rend="ital">nel</hi> waistcoat Doctor. it excites a greater perspiration than you <del>are
                  aware</del> will perhaps believe. This is <ref type="m" target="people.html#KingJohn">King&#8217;s</ref> advice &amp; he thinks it of
               importance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very happily employed upon Espriella<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from
                     England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &amp; reading as relaxation the
               Italian Hist of Heresies by Bernini<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domenico Bernini (1657&#8211;1723), <title>Istoria, di Tutte
                     l&#8217;Heresie</title> (1705&#8211;1717).</note> which I bought in Edinburgh, a book highly useful to one who knows how to arrange what new
               ideas it presents, &amp; how to discriminate between truth &amp; falsehood. Beausobre<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac de
                  Beausobre (1659&#8211;1738), a French Protestant clergyman, who published a history of Manichaeism, entitled <title>Histoire Critique de
                     Manich&#233;e et du Manich&#233;isme</title> (1734&#8211;1739). Southey&#8217;s copy of this work was no. 185 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> for which I have been groaning these many years is on the road to me &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> has procured it from Paris &#8211; I had no notion that it was so scarce a book. Without this I felt myself very deficient
               in that part of religious history which relates to the connection between the superstitions of Europe &amp; the East.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The History of Heresies is in other words that of the corruptions of Xtianity, every addition to the system being
               opposed as it was introduced. This is a key to Church History. But among the earlier sects who sprung up before the Mythology was
               added, some <del>preferred</del> rejected Christ as an unfit nucleus to incrust with their fables, &amp; endeavoured to substitute
               Moses or Melchisedech<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> King of Salem, mentioned in Genesis 14.18&#8211;20, after whom a heretical
                  sect (the Melchisedechians) was established in Phrygia in the 9th Century.</note> as the Philosophers did Apollonius Tyaneus &amp;
                  Pythagoras.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Apollonius of Tyana, was a first century Greek philosopher who attempted to
                  revive the doctrines of Pythagorus (c. 570-c. 495 BC), the philosopher, mathematician and founder of the Pythagorean religious
                  movement.</note> Others more boldly <del>declar</del> set up for the Paraclete<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Some Muslim
                  theologians have argued that the paraclete, or &#8216;other counsellor&#8217; promised to the faithful by Jesus in John 14.15&#8211;15 and 16.7&#8211;8
                  refers to the Prophet Muhammad.</note> &#8211; in which as you know Mohammed followed them &amp; succeeded. The Church triumphed over all,
               sometimes by a silent absorption, <del>&amp; union with them xxx xxplex &amp;</del> thus Manicheism<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A dualist religious philosophy, in which good (God) and evil (Satan) are perceived to be in conflict, which
                  originated in Persia (Iran) in the 3rd century. Its founding prophet was Mani (or Manes in Latin).</note> is fairly <del>the</del>
               taken in with &lt;the&gt; faith &#8211; &amp; John Calvin &amp; John Wesley<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Calvin (1509&#8211;1564),
                  French Protestant theologian, active during the Reformation in the development of the Christian theology later known as Calvinism;
                  John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) Church of England clergyman, and founder of Methodism.</note> only repeated what they
               believed Manes was damned for <del>xxxx</del> bringing into Europe &#8211; the belief in Two Principles.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may perhaps remember a speculation of mine that Buddha is not older than the third Century of our era, which would
               if true destroy the whole fabric of Eastern chronology.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commonly known as Buddha, Siddhartha
                  Gautama, is believed to have lived in the northeastern Indian subcontinent some time during the 6th and 4th centuries BC.</note> I
               am confirmed in it by finding that the teacher of new sects branched off at the East as well as the West in those days, &amp; that the
               Adams Peak foot-mark<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam&#8217;s Peak is a mountain in central Sri Lanka which has a rock formation
                  near its summit, which in Muslim tradition is believed to be the &#8216;sacred footprint&#8217; of Adam.</note> venerated in Ceylon was one of
               the Twelve Masters instituted by Manes. &#8211; But you are hardly old enough to take an interest in these things. The great blessing of such
               pursuits as mine is &#8211; that the appetite for them heightens every day literally growing by what it feeds on. At your age I used to think
               of the Fathers as probably you do now &#8211; they now appear to me to be such men as modern Metaphysicians with this difference, &#8211; that they
               had tenfold the genius of any of the clan, &amp; that the subject on which they employed themselves being of infinitely greater
               imaginary importance, affords a better excuse for the possession of their powers of mind. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-02-25">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 25. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>