<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1324</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2446</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.lett.d.110.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1324" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1324" type="letter">
        <head>1324. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1807-05-18">[c. 18 May
                        1807]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend N. Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MAY 18/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: [Drawing of a foot on address sheet after
                        &#8216;Lightfoot&#8217;] <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.lett.d.110<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The story of my unhappy brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward Southey</ref> (his name is not
                    Tyler) is very different from what he has stated to it to me in his letter accompanying yours, &amp; doubtless from what he had
                    made it appear to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From the time he was capable of learning he was placed in the most favourable situations &#8211; first at the Grammar
                    School <del>at</del> &lt;in&gt; Bristol &#8211; then at the one <del>at</del> &lt;in&gt; Birmingham, &#8211; lastly under a Clergyman at
                    Bristol, &#8211; &amp; at every place it was absolutely impossible to make him attend to <del>xxx</del> any thing. In 1803 he determined
                    to go to sea. I was then at Bristol, &amp; strongly dissuaded him; no dissuasions were of any avail. go he would, &amp; he was
                    warned by me most earnestly that this step once taken was irrevocable, for he had no friends who could afford the expence of any
                    change of plan. &#8211; I could do little for him &#8211; as will appear in the sequel of this letter, &#8211; he however rigged for sea at the
                    eventual expence of his maternal <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncle M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hill</ref> of Lisbon &#8211;
                    the father of us all &#8211; a berth <del>xxx</del> found for him, the last time I saw him was in August of that year, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">my first child</ref> was then lying dead. &#8211; I gave him five guineas &amp; bade
                    him remember that if he did his duty I would do all that it was possible for me to do to serve him, but again bade him remember
                    that I would never rob myself of necessaries to support any folly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In October came a letter from him telling me that he had left his ship &#8211; &amp; was in a Gentlemans house at Exeter
                        (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Foster Barham<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Foster Barham (1763&#8211;1822).</note>) &#8211;
                    waiting my determination what he should do. The fault he laid upon his <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Aunt Miss
                        Tyler</ref> (of whom it would be necessary to make you understand her character to say more than a letter can hold, &#8211; suffice
                    it that the only excuse to be made for her is to suppose her &#8211; as I verily do &#8211; insane) &#8211; &amp; he expressed a readiness to obey
                    my advice. I wrote that nothing else was to be done but to return to sea, the expence of his fitting out having been incurred,
                    &amp; at the same &lt;time&gt; took measures for obtaining him another ship. His answer told me that all his uniforms &amp;c had
                    been sold to a travelling Jew. The same post which brought this provoking letter brought me a draft for about 15&#163; I think &#8211; for a
                    taylors bill at Exeter, &#8211; the next day came another from a Gun Smith, &#8211; &amp; <del>xxx xxx</del> a third from an alehouse &#8211; or
                    brothel at Plymouth. These I instantly returned. When I come to state <del>in such</del> my own circumstances you will perceive
                    that there was no alternative between involving myself in debt or leaving him to what he deserved, &#8211; &amp; you will already
                    perceive that had I begun answering such drafts there would <del>xxx</del> have been no end to them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Well he found his way from Exeter into Herefordshire to a friend of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref>, who took lodgings for him, got him &lt;a&gt; a mathematical teacher &amp; wrote to me to get him another ship.
                    Then his bills followed him &amp; were discharged by my Uncle, amounting with his expences there &amp; of a refitment for sea to
                    above 190&#163;. I procured an appointment for him (no easy thing in these times &#8211; especially for one who had left the service) &#8211; &amp;
                    to Plymouth he went. The next news was that he had left this situation also &#8211; had gone to Taunton <del>&amp; there</del> to my
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">fathers elder brother</ref>, a man of large fortune &amp; strange character, but
                    finding him in town had written to him &amp; receive an answer bidding him <del>xxx</del> go to his house &amp; stay till his
                    return &#8211; a wonderful act of kindness in him, &amp; certainly indicating a disposition to do more. But <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> immediately ordered in a new assortment of bills to this <del>xxx</del>
                    &lt;Uncle&gt;, which so irritated the old man that he turned him out of doors. He now went to Bristol to <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref>, &#8211; &amp; I heard nothing more till <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> informed me that he had reached Lisbon in a merchant ship from Bristol,
                    sent by her. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hill</ref> I mean by my Uncle &#8211; he being the only
                    relation who has ever demeaned himself as such towards us, &amp; &lt;he&gt; is in truth one of the most admirable of men. He spoke
                    of him with bitterness very unusual in him, &amp; added that if he <del>xxx xxx</del> could not be kept in the navy he would come
                    to the Gallows. I should tell you that in 1799 I predicted in the bitterness of my heart that he would turn strolling player, &#8211;
                    &amp; that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> having seen him in 1800 felt deeply convinced no good could
                    ever come of him. At Lisbon he was once more shipped in the Egyptienne,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A 40-gun frigate,
                        captured from the French in 1801, and commissioned into the Royal Navy.</note> &#8211; how or why he left <del>this xxx</del> the
                    service this time is what I have never heard, &#8211; but to Bristol he got once more &amp; then got an Ensigncy in the Militia.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There was <del>an</del> a Lady of some rank &amp; interest who he thought could push him in the army. She was a Roman Catholick, &#8211; what did he do to win her favour &#8211; but turn
                    Roman Catholick with all due forms. On the Good Friday of last year I know a person who saw him take the sacrament at the
                    Catholick altar! &#8211; My eye was never off him, &#8211; whatever he did at this time I knew: &amp; he left the regiment because <del>he
                        had</del> having charge of the French prisoners he had sold some of these &lt;prisoners&gt; provisions &amp; taken the money &#8211;
                    The Colonel very humanely permitted him to resign &#8211; He took horse from Bristol from a livery stable, &#8211; which horse was seized at
                    Taunton for an old debt contracted at the inn, &#8211; &amp; for this he is still liable to arrest: He went to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref> (who had now succeeded to his elder brother, that elder brother
                    having cut off all his nephews, &#8211; an action in some degree perhaps to be imputed to Edwards late misconduct.) &amp; was not xxxx
                    xxx by him &#8211; then he took to his present situation &amp;c I think you will <del>also</del> perceive that after thrice quitting the
                    navy, being expelled the army &#8211; for such xxx may <del>xxx</del> truly be said to be the case, &#8211; &amp; changing his religion upon
                    speculation, &#8211; it is the fittest situation for him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My sole income hitherto has been an annuity of 160&#163;. that annuity <del>xxx</del> has now just ceased because <del>I
                        have</del> a pension of 200&#163; has just been granted me<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Before he left office at the
                        fall of the so-called Ministry of All the Talents in 1807, Southey&#8217;s patron <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>
                        had succeeded in arranging that the pension he paid Southey from his personal funds was replaced by a government
                        pension.</note> &#8211; of which the net receipts will not exceed 144&#163;. No efforts of mine in literature have ever yet increased
                    this income to more than 300&#163;. I write as much as any clerk in an attorneys office, &#8211; but it is only half my time which I devote
                    to writing for bread, &#8211; the other is given for worthier pursuits, on which to build an everlasting reputation, &amp; by which to
                    do my duty in the world by contributing to the stock of knowledge therein. Hereafter this will prove the best worldly policy, &#8211; at
                    present all I have is as you may perceive little enough for a married man with a growing family. I have two other brothers &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">the one is at sea</ref>, &#8211; there is not a braver <del>nor a</del> &lt;or&gt; better officer,
                        <del>xxx xxx xxx</del> for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the other</ref> I have done much &#8211; even to
                    contracting debt for &#8211; &amp; having found friends for him who have done more, he has just graduated at Edinburgh in medicine,
                    &amp; is at this hour without any exception, one of the very finest &amp; most promising young men living. For both of these
                    brothers my house whenever they have been able to make it so has been a home, &#8211; &amp; for the last three years the younger has
                    annually spent five months with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now Lightfoot the sum of all this is that it is not <del>impossible</del> possible I can supply the money necessary
                    to place <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> in any situation whatever: &amp; <del>xxx</del> if I could assuredly
                    I would not, because it is my firm belief from the thorough knowledge I have of him, that the same misconduct would be repeated.
                    Dear Lightfoot there &lt;are&gt; insanities &amp; disorders <hi rend="ital">of heart</hi> &#8211; as well as of <hi rend="ital">intellect</hi>, &#8211; &amp; defects in our <hi rend="ital">moral</hi> being as well as in our <hi rend="ital">physical</hi>. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> was born without the sense of shame &#8211; from his childhood he has taken a
                    delight in deceiving others, &amp; the wonderful talents with which he has been gifted have unfortunately <del>have</del> been
                    applied to this purpose &#8211; the whole life, wherever he has been, has been one continuous deception, &#8211; &amp; he has always imposed
                    upon every body, first for sport, &amp; latterly for worse purposes. It is his own fault that he is not now at Oxford &#8211; whither
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> would have sent him, &#8211; that he is not in the navy &#8211; that he is not
                    in the army. He is now fit for nothing but what he is: nor would it be possible to place him in any office of trust, &#8211; after what
                    has past. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is no more able to assist him than I am, he being already
                    embarrassed by the expence so often incurred for him, &#8211; for he has cost his family more than either of his brothers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Any thing I could do would distress myself &amp; be thrown away. I know him too well to expect amendment. &#8211; It is a
                    grief to me &#8211; as you may well suppose &#8211; thank God it is the only one: <del>xxx</del> &amp; having always <del>xxx</del> foreseen
                    it I was prepared for it. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">His mother</ref> happily did not live to see these things but
                    she also had a forefeeling of what would come. &#8211; I shall answer his letter tomorrow<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This
                        has not survived.</note> &#8211; there is no time to do it by this post. He must be content with the lot to which he has reduced
                    himself, &#8211; &amp; in whatever lot he shall learn to demean himself honestly &amp; decently I shall ev[er] be ready to acknowledge
                    him as my brother &#8211; but help <del>xxx</del> him I cannot.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I have left myself no room to thank you for the interest you have taken in this affair, which is what I should have expected in
                        such a case from my old friend Lightfoot. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>