<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1350</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2472</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1350" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1350" type="letter">
        <head>1350. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-08-01">1
                        August [1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M. P./ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the Specimens I can only say that Hinchcliffes poem<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Hinchcliffe (1692&#8211;1742) was represented in the <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), I,
                        pp. 399&#8211;404, by &#8216;On Seeing Philesia at her Window, Viewing a Wedding&#8217;, &#8216;To Philesia, a Day Before Her Coming to Town&#8217;, and &#8216;A
                        Song of Thanksgiving&#8217;. If no substitution was made, then it is probably the first of these, with its voyeurism of a wedding
                        couple, to which Southey and Wynn objected.</note> is one of those which I ordered to be expunged, both viva voce to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> in London when I saw it in print: repeatedly afterwards before the
                    publication of the book &amp; after the publication also.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For these requests, see Southey
                        to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14 March 1807 (Letter 1286), 15 March 1807 (Letter 1288), [1 April 1807] (Letter 1303), and 21
                        April 1807 (Letter 1309).</note> If it still remains it must be because the book could not be found to supply the
                    omission.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I did not review Dutens.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Memoirs of a Traveller now in Retirement</title> (1805) was reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>,
                        5 (1807), 327&#8211;339.</note> Were I disposed to set much value upon my Annual labours your complaint of this volume would flatter
                    me, the truth being that there is not in it one half so much of mine as there is in the former volume. Besides what you
                    particularized there are only Barrows Cochin China Clarkes Naufragia &#8211;Report of the Bible Society. <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancasters</ref> Letter. Life of Dermody. <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> M. Angelo. Sir D Lindsays Works. Accounts of two attempts to civililize some Indian natives. Clarksons Quakerism
                    &amp; Jarrolds Dissertations on man.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to Cochin China, in the
                            Years 1792, and 1793: Containing a General View of the Productions, and Political Importance of this Kingdom; and also of
                            such European Settlements as were Visited on the Voyage, with Sketches of the Manners, Character, and Condition of their
                            Inhabitants</title> (1806), 2&#8211;16; James Burney, <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or
                            Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (Vol. 2; 1806), 16&#8211;30; James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (1805&#8211;1806), 71&#8211;72; <title>Report of
                            the British and Foreign Bible Society</title> (1805), 155&#8211;160; Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820), [Joseph Lancaster
                        (1778&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>)] <title>A New and Appropriate System of Education for the Labouring People</title> (1806),
                        278&#8211;282; John Wooll (bap. 1767&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of the late Revd. Joseph Warton, Master
                            of St. Mary Winton College; Prebendary of Winchester Cathedral; and Rector of the Parishes of Wickham and Upham, Hants: to
                            which are added, a Selection from his Works; and a Literary Correspondence Between Eminent Persons, Reserved by him for
                            Publication</title> (1806), 298&#8211;305; Lucy Hutchinson (n&#233;e Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson
                        (dates unknown), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806), 361&#8211;378; James Grant Raymond (1771&#8211;1817),
                            <title>The Life of Thomas Dermody</title> (1806), 383&#8211;397; Henry Richard Fox, 3rd Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the
                            Life and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1806), 397&#8211;411; Richard Duppa, <title>The Life and Literary Works
                            of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806), 411&#8211;425; George Chalmers, (bap. 1742&#8211;1825;
                            <title>DNB</title>), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Sir David Lyndsay</title> (1806), 482&#8211;494; Thomas Moore (1779&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epistles, Odes and Other Poems</title> (1806), 498&#8211;499; [Society of Friends of Pennsylvania],
                            <title>Accounts of Two Attempts Towards the Civilization of Some Indian Natives</title> (1806), 589&#8211;593; Thomas Clarkson,
                            <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar Customs, Religious
                            Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title> (1806), 594&#8211;607; Thomas Jarrold
                        (1770&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological and Political; in Answer to Mr.
                            Malthus&#8217;s &#8216;Essay on the Principle of Population&#8217;</title> (1806), 607&#8211;615.</note> But the year was barren of subjects &#8211; I
                    rejected many books that I might set upon South America, &amp; for the same reason did not volunteer another Missionary article
                    which else would have been written,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, for the sake of making progress towards his
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, Southey had turned down the chance to review the latest transactions of the missionary
                        societies. Southey reviewed the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1803</title>, 2 (1804), 189&#8211;201, and the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 621&#8211;634.</note> &#8211; &amp; a
                    thorough reviewal of Dante which I had else projected for the sake of studying him well &amp; being paid for it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say upon Bank notes has much good sense in it, &amp; I shall avail myself of it, as also of any
                        <del>thing</del> remarks you may make upon any other part of the work.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Letter 22 of
                            <title>Letters from England</title>, Southey discusses bank notes and their forgery.</note> Those letters which relate to
                    the state of fanaticism &amp; sectarianism in the country are the most valuable:<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Letter
                        70 of <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> they are matters of fact &amp; of history, &amp; if they teach the
                        <del>chu</del> high churchmen that their real danger is not from philosophy they will do some real good. By the by I learn
                    that a book has been written against my Anti-Methodistic review,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William
                        Myles (1756&#8211;1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People Called Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists
                            of the Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 201&#8211;213. Joseph Benson (1749&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>) published <title>Inspector of
                            Methodism Inspected</title> (1803), but its principal target was not Southey&#8217;s review but an article in the
                            <title>Christian Observer</title>.</note> besides letters in magazines wherein I am accused among other things of an
                    impure imagination for my picture of the consequences of confession. So I shall send for Mr. Bensons book &amp; at them again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Trumpet shall be restored if you desire it: but I must use the word tambor in the Cid for the <hi rend="ital">atambor</hi> of the Spaniards: it being evidently the same word, &amp; very probably a different instrument from the drum.
                    This book will speedily go to press. The parcel which I expected from Lisbon has reached Liverpool, &amp; as soon as it reaches
                    me, I shall make my bargain with the booksellers, with whom my reputation stands better than my cash account.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition, <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title>, was published by
                        Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica Particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from
                        the <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632).
                        Southey had been waiting for some books sent by his uncle, Herbert Hill; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 11 June
                        1807, Letter 1331.</note> The Specimens are of course too bad to sell: that sprat was my wicked pun &#8211; what could be said
                    better of such a minnow among the fry of Poets?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Sprat (1635&#8211;1713;
                            <title>DNB</title>), English divine. The headnote for Sprat reads: &#8216;Aptly named sprat, as being one of the least among the
                        Poets. &#8211; Exempli grati&#226;&#8217;, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), I, p.168.</note> &#8211; The
                    horse is <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> who has committed abominations out of number, &amp;
                    often delivered opinions diametrically the opposite of mine. I had 100&#163; when last in town for the first edition of Espriella
                    supposing it were to sell for 15/. What its price is they have not told me, if a guinea as I suppose, they will give me credit in
                    due proportion. Palmerin<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> is printed on our joint account &amp; I suspect I have done wrong, for it is sure to pay, &amp; not sure of any
                    thing beyond. I shall sell the first edition of the Cid, which will make a thirty shilling quarto: As my articles are the best in
                    the Annual except <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref> I think I shall raise my price,
                    &amp; no longer let my work be rated at the same per-sheet as our Well-Beloved Cousins &amp; Miss Lucy Aikins.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Contributors to the <title>Annual Review</title>: Charles Wellbeloved (1769&#8211;1858), Lucy Aikin
                        (1781&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>). Wellbeloved was a friend and Lucy Aikin the sister of the editor Arthur Aikin.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of your hopes.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn&#8217;s wife gave birth to a daughter (first
                        name unknown) in 1808. Southey&#8217;s letter congratulating him is dated [March 1808], Letter 1427.</note> I also have hopes of the
                    same kind,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref>, the Southeys&#8217; fifth child was born on 9 February 1808.</note> hopes they
                    truly are for let my family be ever so numerous I never feel a fear of their eventually doing well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My reason for doing so little in the new Madoc was that it might not be supposed I had done anything, otherwise the
                    remains of the quarto would be rendered unsaleable.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published in a smaller, duodecimo edition in 1807. For the changes, see <title>Robert Southey:
                            Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II.</note>
          <del>At present</del> As yet I have heard no other return of its profits than the 3&#8211;17&#8211;1. &amp; would have no expectation that ten
                    copies have told since. But as the poem strikes root, which ultimately it must &amp; will do, that edition will be chosen for its
                    size &amp; beauty, if it be not be superseded by a corrected one. Therefore I make no preliminaries or alterations [MS obscured]
                    it be sold. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For some time I have been expecting &amp; indeed almost hoping to hear of <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horaces</ref> death.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have well nigh got thro our indoor works. &amp; I expect early next week no less than eight &amp; twenty
                    packages from Bristol, 18 of which are books. You see I have fairly anchored myself for life, &amp; with an anchor too heavy ever
                    to be weighed again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tomorrow I go to <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> for a few days, &amp; am not without thoughts
                    of making a visit to Mrs Dixon.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Dixon (d.1820) and her husband Jeremiah Dixon, of
                        Fell Foot, Windermere (later of Balla Wray, Ambleside), were generous hosts to Wordsworth and Southey, and neighbours of <ref target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff</ref>. Mrs Dixon, daughter of the
                        engineer John Smeaton, was an amateur artist; she also established a school.</note> Did I ever tell you that I am in the good
                    graces of the Right Reverend the <ref target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">Lord Bishop of Llandaff</ref>?<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had done so; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 19 July 1806, Letter
                        1203.</note> who does me the honour of placing me under the shadow of his wing when I call upon him. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>
          <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Cobbett&#8217;s Political
                            Register</title>, 12.4 (25 July 1807), 115&#8211;116, William Cobbett ridiculed Wynn for defending the parliamentary privilege
                        that prevented MPs being arrested for debt.</note> I see has fallen foul upon Mr Charles Wynn &#8211; forgetting all his former
                    merits when serving for Old Sarum &#8211; I am a great admirer of Lord Cochrane,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> In parliament
                        the newly elected Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), became a radical MP and critic of
                        corruption and nepotism in the navy and in the government.</note> &amp; would wish no better fortune to my brother than to be
                    under a man who is so thoroughly &amp; deservedly beloved by all who have ever served under him &#8211; Your party seems to me likely to
                    split, if Whitbread<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician and
                        advocate of a negotiated peace with Napoleon.</note> speak the sense of his when he talks of peace, &#8211; the only thing which is
                    really to be dreaded. If you are consistent you will stand upon your own ground, &amp; in spite of taxes the nation <del>x</del>
                    will now be with you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Your godson</ref> is teething &amp; has just been weaned from necessity. he is a fine
                    fellow, &amp; makes what I call a legitimate noise. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith the younger</ref> is growing a
                    great girl, &amp; will soon with the help of grey hairs make me feel that I am no longer a young man. And yet by Gods blessing I
                    trust to carry with me a boys heart &amp; a boys spirits to the grave. I never yet saw any person whose spirits were so uniformly
                    joyous.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-08-01">August 1</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>