<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.980</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2102</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4811D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="980" type="letter">
        <head>980. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1804-10-05">5
                        October [1804]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esqr M. P./ Wynnstay/
                        Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The wet &amp; the cold remind me of Welsh stockings, &amp; they remind me of you, &#8211; We have been leading gay lives
                    since your departure, visiting at the Island<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Derwent Isle, Derwentwater, where <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel Peachy</ref> lived.</note> &amp;c, have had a subscription ball &#8211; &amp; a riot
                    at the theatre, not to mention that <del>an</del> a Paddy there on another night chose to quarrel with me, but as it went no
                    farther than words &amp; looks, &amp; I could look fiercest &amp; talk best <del>being</del> if I came off very well &amp; like
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Mellish<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps Joseph Charles Mellish (1769&#8211;1823);
                            <title>DNB</title>), translator of Schiller.</note> only pretty wellish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> is here &#8211; I delivered your message to him &amp; he I believe has sent it to
                        <ref target="people.html#EdridgePainter">Edridge</ref>, to whom however I shall have an opportunity of delivering it myself.
                    We have talked over the matter above the arms &amp; concluded that the best way of introducing the sheets will be in a vignette
                    group of all Welsh things, &#8211; the harp &#8211; the crwth<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Welsh name of a stringed instrument,
                        called in English &#8216;the crowd&#8217;.</note> &amp;c, &amp; to inscribe round its rim as on Iorwerths &#8211; Rodericus filius Ceni
                        Regis.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is arranging the elements of the image to be drawn and engraved for the
                        title page of <title>Madoc</title>, honouring <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, the poem&#8217;s dedicatee, by
                        displaying his family&#8217;s heraldic devices on a shield. Wynn claimed descent from Rhodri (1135?&#8211;1195), brother of Madoc and of
                        Iorwerth ab Owain Gwynedd or Iorwerth Drwyndwn (1145&#8211;1174) and son of Owain Gwynedd (c. 1100&#8211;1170; <title>DNB</title>). The
                            Latin inscription, which translates as &#8216;Rhodri son of the Welsh king&#8217;, explains this relationship.</note> &#8211; When you write describe me the bearings heraldically that the artist
                    may understand them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">The Printer</ref> goes on excellently &#8211; 38 sheets are done &#8211; &amp; I on my part see now
                    an end of my labour.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correcting proofs of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) even
                        while still revising the sections of the manuscript not yet sent to the printer.</note> three weeks will bring me to the
                    notes. of the preface so much is written as relates to the execution of the poem &#8211; I have related how slowly it was written, &amp;
                    at what distant intervals corrected or continued, for the purpose of thereby accounting for its main defects. Send me &#8211; if you can
                    &#8211; the legend round Iorwerths shield &#8211; or it will be too late to have it cut &#8211; indeed as it is, I fear the printing must stop for
                    it. &#8211; Tell me too whether M.P. simply <del>be to</del> should be affixed to your name, or any larger formula as Kt of the Shire
                    &amp;c &#8211; for I am inconveniently ignorant of these things. I have beblotted more paper than you could imagine in endeavouring to
                    shape what I would say in fitting terms, &amp; can find nothing better than thus &#8211; To CWWW &amp;c this poem which he will peruse
                    with a family as well as a national interest is &amp;c &#8211; inscribed by his friend &amp; school fellow &#8211;&#8211;. &amp; this is not well.
                    family is completely colloquialized into an adjective &#8211; but to say schoolfellow nakedly thus appears inaccurate. the word indeed
                    may be spared perhaps &#8211; as it occurs in the preface &#8211; And now I think of it it may be well to send you what I design to say of the
                    poem in general. All that is there said is very true &#8211; but as what is true may not always be prudent if you advise me to suppress
                    it &#8211; so be it &#8211; Yet I am myself inclined to let it pass. Return it to me for there is no other copy. An historical introduction to
                    the poem is to precede it, as brief as it may be, &amp; I think of <del>addin</del> partnering it with an acknowledgement of the
                    specific faults of the poem &#8211; if it be tried by epic laws, to which I shall protest it is not amenable. One dreams much about
                    prefaces before they come to be written, &amp; then the shortest always seems the best. At times I have dreamt of reviewing my own
                    previous poems in this, but it is quite unnecessary &#8211; &amp; therefore quite improper. &amp; even if it were not so I have had no
                    time for any supererogation of labour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If all <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord G.s</ref> letters in this intercepted correspondence be like
                    the one which I saw in the Herald, they will do him so much better honour in the general opinion that he will have no reason to
                    regret the rascally example we set the French of publishing private letters.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> During 1804
                        the French published correspondence that fell into their possession when they captured an East India Company ship, the
                            <title>Admiral Aplin</title>. The correspondence included letters written in 1803 by <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham, Baron Grenville</ref>, who had come into government in May 1804.
                        Published in both languages, the English title of the work was <title>Intercepted Letters. Intercepted on Board the Admiral
                            Aplin, Captured by the French and Inserted by the French Government in the Moniteur</title>. This propaganda publication
                        followed the British publication of <title>Copies of Original Letters from the Army of General Bonaparte in Egypt: Intercepted
                            by the Fleet under the Command of Admiral Lord Nelson, with an English Translation</title> (1798&#8211;1800).</note> &#8211; If you do
                    not preserve your <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref>
          <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Weekly Political Register</title> compiled and published by William Cobbett
                        from 1802&#8211;1835.</note> &#8211; I wish you would send them down to me &#8211; for I see no paper but a weekly one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> William Spencers poem is come down to me for trial <del>&amp; xxx</del> at the next jail delivery.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Robert Spencer (1770&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Year of Sorrow: A
                            Poem Written in the Spring of 1803</title> (1804) in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 574.</note> What
                    an excellent book is Barrows China!<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short
                            Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804).
                        Southey reviewed the book in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 69&#8211;83.</note> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> will leave me next week &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> in a fortnight &#8211; <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">our Island neighbour</ref> with whom we are now on most
                    neighbourly terms about the same time &#8211; I shall then be left to myself for the winter, &amp; to say the truth I look with as much
                    pleasure to its total quiet as ever any body did to the winter gaieties of London. I will write again soon. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref> grows well &amp; becomes a delightful play thing. We have a hare in
                    the house, by right of Dapper<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s dog.</note> as one of the towns peoples pack &#8211;
                    &amp; I have bought a jack ass, who is shortly to be made a Kt of the most ancient order of the thistle, &amp; thenceforth to be
                    Sir John for ever. thus have you all the news of the house on the hill at Keswick.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-10-05">Friday. October 5.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>