<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1624</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2746</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1624" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1624" type="letter">
        <head>1624. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-05-02">2 May
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whether Orsua&#8217;s expedition should or should not be written occasioned me a great deal of perplexity &amp;
                        indecision,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey took from Antonio de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625),
                            <title>Historia General del Mundo del Tiempo del Rey Felipe II, desde 1559 haste su Muerte</title> (1601&#8211;1612) the story
                        of the ill-fated Amazon expedition of exploration conducted by Pedro de Urs&#250;a (1526&#8211;1561) and Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510&#8211;1561).
                        However, he omitted it from his <title>History of Brazil</title> and instead published it in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812) and then separately as <title>The Expedition of Orsua: and the Crimes of
                            Aguirre</title> (1821).</note> &#8211; it does not cost me one minutes deliberation to determine upon omitting it as you advise.
                    Had I never written it I might have blamed myself for <del>xx</del> neglect. It will be sufficient just to mention it among the
                    many events to which the fables concerning El Dorado<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mythical city of gold, sought by
                        the explorer Francisco de Orellana (1511&#8211;1546), who died during a disastrous expedition, on which only 44 of 300 men survived,
                        navigating the Amazon.</note> gave rise. The next chapter as they are finished off shall be sent you by post thro <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; the Grand Parleur, as a Frenchman once called <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Abbot</ref>. This will save time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have has a good deal of anxiety of late. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> was seized last
                    week with the croop. he was bled in the jugular vein &amp; blistered on the neck, &amp; this God be thanked, has saved him. At
                    present he is suffering from the remedy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the list on the other leaf I have marked those books which I most wish for. The Verdadeiro Methado<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis Antonio Verney (1713&#8211;1792), <title>Verdadeiro Metodo de Estudar, para ser Util &#225; Republica,
                            e &#225; Igreja: Proporcionado ao Estilo e Necesidade de Portugal</title> (1746).</note> is a work whose importance I have
                    learnt from Fr. Gerundio,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Francisco de Isla (1703&#8211;1781), <title>Historia del Famoso
                            Predicador Fray Gerundio de Campazas, alias Zotes</title> (1758).</note> &#8211; you probably knew its history better than I do.
                        Lozano<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Lozano (1697&#8211;1752), <title>Historia de la Compan&#771;ia de Jesus en la
                            Provincia del Paraguay</title> (1754&#8211;1755).</note> or Montoya<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Ruiz de
                        Montoya (1585&#8211;1652), <title>Conquista Espiritual Hecha por los Religiosos de la Compan&#771;ia de Jesus, en las Provincias del
                            Paraguay, Parana, Uruguay, y Tape</title> (1639).</note> would be treasures to me, &#8211; for I am almost without a guide in
                    Paraguay. The 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter brings down the affairs of that country to the final establishment of B Ayres,
                    &amp; there I shall leave it till the second volume, &amp; then as soon as the Dutch War is over take up the History of the
                    Jesuits from their entrance &amp; the foundation of their system before I proceed to the insurrection against them in Brazil.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The increasing influence of the Jesuits in Brazil, the foundation of their system of
                        missions, and the campaign against it launched by colonists and other colonial clergy jealous of their power, is described in
                        the second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1817).</note> With the civil affairs of Paraguay I need have
                    nothing more to do now that the discovery of the country is completed, &#8211; except so far as they are connected with the P.
                        colonies.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese colonies.</note> This chapter <del>x</del> is transcribed
                    &amp; would have been sent off to night, if I had not some letters to finish which will go in the same inclosure. Make any
                    alteration you deem necessary, &#8211; I shall perceive it, &amp; <del>if I</del> can restore the passage if there existed any just
                    reason for it which you did not discover. When you have done return it under cover to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                        Rickman</ref>, &#8211; &amp; inclose the whole in a second cover to the <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Rt. Honble the
                        Speaker</ref> &amp;c &#8211; <del>xxx</del>. There is no conveyance so safe &amp; so speedy as the Post.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Was there ever so wretched a Book as Pinkertons!<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>), editor of <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in all
                            Parts of the World</title> (1808&#8211;1814).</note> By following political instead of natural arrangement his first edition
                    became obsolete before his second appeared, &amp; now the second is as obsolete as the first, &#8211; &amp; such a style no man ever
                    wrote but himself. And But Yet While are all synonyms with him in having no meaning at all.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I <del>have</del> should have had some of your MSS which are in my possession bound, if we had a binder on the
                    spot. Ribeiros Voyage to the Settlement on the R Negro<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had borrowed from Hill a
                        manuscript work by Francisco Xavier Ribeiro Sampaio (1741&#8211;1812?), <title>Di&#225;rio da uma Viagem que em Visita e Correci&#231;&#225;o das
                            Povoa&#231;&#243;es da Capitania de S&#227;o Jos&#233; do Rio Negro fez o Ouvidor</title> (1775).</note> has been of great use to me in
                    filling up Acunas account.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;1676?), <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento
                            del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title> (1641).</note> When the Dutch war is over my printed materials lie in a very narrow
                    compass, &#8211; only Vieyra,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Viera (1608&#8211;1697), the Brazilian-born Jesuit renowned for
                        his preaching and as the architect of the Jesuit missions (Reductions) there. In his <title>History of Brazil</title>, Southey
                        cites both Viera&#8217;s <title>Serm&#245;es</title> (1679&#8211;1748) and Andr&#233; de Barros (1675&#8211;1754), <title>Vida do Apostolico Padre Antonio
                            Vieyra da Companhia de Jesus, Chamado por Grande</title> (1746).</note> Berredo<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bernardo Pereira de Berredo e Castro (d. 1748), governor of Maranh&#227;o 1718&#8211;1722, author of <title>Annaes Historicos do Estado
                            do Maranha&#333; de sey Descivrunebtim, at&#232; 1718</title> (1749).</note> &amp; the wretched R Pitta.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebasti&#227;o da Rocha Pita (1660&#8211;1738), <title>Historia da America Portugeza, desde o anno 1500 ate o de
                            1724</title> (1730).</note> I shall not be long in transcribing the remainder of the volume, &amp; the omission of this
                    long chapter about Aguirre<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 1.</note> will give me room to insert a critical
                    account of my authorities, &#8211; which ought to accompany every historical work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As soon as <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has finished the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter he
                    shall send you the sheets that you may examine them at leisure &#8211; &amp; tell me what explanations are necessary in the additional
                    notes (which will extend from 50 to 100 pages) &amp; what amendments should be noticed in a list of errors. I am glad to find that
                    the narration proves more interesting than I had expected &#8211; It is so much less so than the history of the mother country &#8211; &amp;
                    than part of the Asiatic history, that I sometimes feared it would be found heavy, &#8211; but this does not appear to be the case.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not very likely that Falkner<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English
                        Jesuit whose papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the Adjoining Parts of South America</title>
                        (1774).</note> left any papers behind him, &#8211; if he had they might perhaps be traced. The last book which appeared about
                    Paraguay I suspect to be a fabrication, &amp; have made enquiries which will speedily ascertain the truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My fragment of Pombals Life<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebasti&#227;o Jos&#233; de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Count
                        of Oeiras, 1st Marquess of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782; <title>DNB</title>), Minister of the Kingdom of Portugal from 1750 to 1777.
                        Southey narrates his period of government in the third volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>.</note> goes in the
                    Frank-royal tomorrow.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My political news is that <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lds Grenville</ref> &amp; Grey<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1830&#8211;1834 and leading Whig.</note> are trying to get
                    into power by reestablishing the D of York in defiance of common decency &amp; of the people,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He
                        held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by allowing his
                        mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for which
                        promotion was arranged. Nevertheless, in May 1811 the Prince Regent reinstated his brother as Commander-in-Chief of the army,
                        a post which he held for the rest of his life.</note> &#8211; &amp; that for this purpose a second <del>xx xxxx</del> Coalition of
                    All the Talents is in agitation. The rascality &amp; the folly of such a design does not make it a whit the less likely,
                    considering the persons in question, but I do not believe it, because <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has taken
                    so conspicuous a part in the whole proceedings. I wish <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Ld</ref> or rather <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady H.</ref> were in power because I believe she would not forget you: &#8211; that
                        <del>done xx</del> justice done. I have no other <del>xx</del> wish about both parties, than that hemp enough may be found for
                    the public service, &#8211; notwithstanding our war with Russia&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">L.</ref> about your parcel<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Which contained the proofs of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810). This
                        letter has not survived. For further details, see Southey to John Rickman, [c. 1 May 1809], Letter 1623.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> May 2. 1809.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <table cols="3" rows="56" width="740">
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Fr. Paulo do Rosario. Relacam</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">da Victoria que honue a Capitan</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">mor de Paraiba. 1632.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Father Paulo do Rosario (dates unknown),
                                        <title>Relacam Breve e Verdadeira da Memoravel Victoria, que ouve o Capitao mor da Capitania da Paraiua
                                        Antonio de Albuquerque, dos rebeldes de Olanda</title> (1632).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Pedro de Magalhaens. Hist. de</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Province de Santa Cruz.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Magalhaens de Gandavo (1550-d.
                                    late 16th century), <title>Historia da Provincia de Santa Cruz do Brazil</title> (1579).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Fr. Pedro Monteiro. Hist. da</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">S Inquisicam do Reyno de Portugal.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Father Pedro Monteiro (dates
                                    unknown), <title>Historia da Santa Inquisi&#231;&#227;o do Reyno de Portugal, e suas Conquistas</title>
                                (1749&#8211;1750).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Ruy da Pina. Compendio das</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">cousas que ha outr&#233; Douro</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">e Minho<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Martins Ferreira (dates unknown), <title>Compendio
                                        e Summario das grandezas e cousas not&#225;veis que ha entre Douro e Minho</title> (1608), with a frontispiece by
                                    Rui de Pina (1440&#8211;1521).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Vida do P. Joam de Almeida</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">por Vasconcellos<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos (1596&#8211;1671),
                                        <title>Vida do Padre Joam d&#8217;Almeida da Companhia de Jesu, na Provincia do Brazil</title> (1658).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Verdadeir<del>x</del> Methodo de esti-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">-dar &#8211; proporcion ado ao estylo</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">e necessidade da Portugal<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis Antonio Verney (1713&#8211;1792),
                                        <title>Verdadeiro Metodo de Estudar, para ser Util &#225; Republica, e &#225; Igreja: Proporcionado ao Estilo e
                                        Necesidade de Portugal</title> (1746).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Jeronymo Lopez. Cronica do</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Infante Santo D Henrique<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jer&#243;nimo L&#243;pez (16th century),
                                        <title>Cr&#243;nica do infante Santo Don Henrique</title> (1529).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Montoya. Conquista Espe</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">-ritual de Paraguay<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Ruiz de Montoya (1585&#8211;1652),
                                        <title>Conquista Espiritual Hecha por los Religiosos de la Compan&#771;ia de Jesus, en las Provincias del Paraguay,
                                        Parana, Uruguay, y Tape</title> (1639).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Lozano. Hist. de Paraguay.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Lozano (1697&#8211;1752),
                                        <title>Historia de la Compan&#771;ia de Jesus en la Provincia del Paraguay</title> (1754&#8211;1755).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">x</cell>
              <cell width="680">Piedrahita Hist. del Nuevo</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Reyno de Granada<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> D. Lucas Fern&#225;ndez Piedrahita (1624&#8211;1688),
                                        <title>Historia General de las Conquistas del Nuevo Reyno de Granada</title> (1688).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Duarte de Alboquerque Coelho</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Memorias Diarias de la Guerra</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">del Brazil<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duarte de Albuquerque Coelho (1591&#8211;1658),
                                        <title>Memorias Diarias de la Guerra del Brazil</title> (1654).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Santuario Mariano<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> Agostinho de Santa Maria (1642&#8211;1728),
                                        <title>Santu&#225;rio Mariano</title> (1707&#8211;1723).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Fr. Antonio das Chagas. Cartas</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Esperituaes. Escola de Penitencia.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Obras Espirit. a Sermoeus.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio da Fonseca Soares
                                    (1631&#8211;1682), a soldier who became a Franciscan friar under the name Antonio das Chagas. Southey later acquired a
                                    seven volume edition of his <title>Obras</title> (or works) of 1763, no. 3257 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                                    library.</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Braz Luiz D&#8217; Abreu. Portugal</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Medico ou Monarchio Medico-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Lusitana.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bras Luis de Abreu (1692&#8211;1756), <title>Portugal
                                        Medico ou Monarchia Medico-Lusitana, Historica, Practica, Symbolica, Ethica</title> (1726).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">X</cell>
              <cell width="680">Comentarios de Ruy Freire</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">de Andrade<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paulo Craesbeeck (c. 1552&#8211;1632), <title>Coment&#225;rios
                                        do Grande Capit&#227;o Rui Freire de Andrada</title> (1647).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell>Foral de Abrantes</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Foral do Porto<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charters of the towns, Abrantes, published in
                                    1732, and Porto, published as <title>Foral da Cidade do Porto, de 20 de Junho de 1517</title> in
                                1788.</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Franc. de Almeida Jorda&#333;</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Rele&#231;am da Serra de Cintra<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Almeida Jord&#227;o (dates
                                    unknown), <title>Rela&#231;&#227;o do Castello, e Serra de Cintra</title> (1748).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Anno Historico.<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Santa Maria (dates unknown),
                                        <title>Anno Historico. Diario Portuguez. Noticia abbreviada de pessoas grandes, e cousas notaveis de
                                        Portugal</title> (1714&#8211;1744).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">X</cell>
              <cell width="680">Obras de Gil Vincente<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gil Vicente (c.1465 &#8211; c. 1536), the chief
                                    dramatist and lyric poet of Portugal. His <title>Works</title> were published first in 1561&#8211;1562.</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Ditos de Freira.<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joana da Gama (c. 1520&#8211;1585), <title>Ditos da
                                        Freira</title> (1555).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Joam Ferreira Roza. Tratado</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Unico da Constitua&#231;am</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">pestilencial de Pernambuco.<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jo&#227;o Ferreira da Rosa (dates
                                    unknown), <title>Tratado &#218;nico da Constitui&#231;&#227;o Pestilencial de Pernambuco</title> (1694).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Ethiopia Oriental<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacinto da Encarna&#231;am (dates unknown),
                                        <title>Summaria Rela&#231;ao do que obrarao os Religiosos da Ordem dos Pr&#233;gadore, na Conversao das almas, e
                                        prega&#231;ao do Santo Evangelho em todo o estado da India, e mais terras descubertas pelos Portuguezes na Afia, e
                                        Ethiopia Oriental, e das Miss&#245;es em que actualmente se exercita&#245; com todos os Conventos, e Casas, e numero de
                                        Religiosos, que de presente tem esta sua Congrega&#231;ao</title> (1679).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Agiologio Lusitano<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jorge Cardoso (1606&#8211;1669) and D. Ant&#243;nio
                                    Caetano de Sousa (1652 -1744), <title>Agiologio Lusitano dos Sanctos, e Varoens illustres em Virtude do reino de
                                        Portugal e suas Conquistas</title> (1652&#8211;1774).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Lopo de Sousa Coutinho</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Cerco de Dio.<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lopo de Sousa Coutinho (1515&#8211;1577), <title>Cerco
                                        de Dio</title> (1556&#8211;1574).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Luiz Felix da Cruz. Mani-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">-festo das hostilidades reste Reino</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">de Angola<note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luiz Felix da Cruz (dates unknown), <title>Manifesto
                                        das Hostilidades que a Gente que Serve a Companhia Occidental de Hollanda obrou Contra os Vassallos d&#8217; El R ei
                                        de Portugal no Reino de Angola</title> (1651).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30">X</cell>
              <cell width="680">O Valeroso Lucideno<note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors"> A work celebrating the Portuguese
                                    liberation from the Dutch of its colonies in Brazil by Frei Manuel Calado do Salvador (1584&#8211;1654), <title>O
                                        Valeroso Lucideno e Triunfo da Liberdade na Restaura&#231;&#227;o de Pernambuco</title> (1648).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Miguel de Castanhoso. Hist.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">das Cousas que D Christovam da</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Gama fez nor Reynos do Presto</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="30" />
              <cell width="680">Joam.<note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miguel de Castanhoso (d. c. 1565), <title>Hist&#243;ria das
                                        Cousas que o mui Esfor&#231;ado Capit&#227;o dom Crist&#243;v&#227;o da Gama f&#234;z nos Reinos do Preste Jo&#227;o</title>
                                (1564).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>