<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1603</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2725</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 505&#8211;507 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1603" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1603" type="letter">
        <head>1603. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1809-03-20">20 March
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MAR 23/ 1809 <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 505&#8211;507 [in
                        part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-03-20">March 20. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Charles</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If your eye has glanced upon the other leaf you will discover the cause of this letter so soon after my last. Two
                    Catalogues have just come to hand, &amp; the readiest way by which I can obtain what I want out of them is thro you, &#8211; as the
                    Bristol Bookseller will get the books from the Bath one. Then they may all come in a parcel come together by waggon, with any
                    thing <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> may have to send. I will pay you when you make your appearance, &#8211; or
                    send a draft for this &amp; the other disbursements, if you will let me know the sum total, &amp; make it worth sending. The
                    Voyage to Brazil<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Atkins (bap. 1685&#8211;1757), <title>A Voyage to Guinea, Brazil and the
                            West Indies in His Majesty&#8217;s Ships the Swallow and Weymouth</title> (1735).</note> is what I have been long &amp;
                    earnestly in search of.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What an infamous business is this acquittal of the D of York, after evidence more extraordinarily conclusive,
                    perhaps, than any that ever yet came before a Court of Justice!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of
                        York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798 to 1809, when it
                        was revealed that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept
                        money from army officers, in return for which promotion was arranged. After a parliamentary inquiry revealed his complicity, a
                        majority of MPs, not wishing to lose the favour of the crown and so jeopardise the ministry and their pensions and sinecures,
                        nevertheless voted for his continuance in office. However, the numbers against him were sufficient for his resignation to be
                        necessary.</note> The majority of the House of Commons stand now towards the people of England in the predicament of Jurors
                    who have given a false verdict, wilfully &amp; corruptly. They have betrayed their trust, &amp; a dismal thing it is to think with
                    what a dead-palsy it will strike all honest men, except those who are prepared to welcome the day of revolution come when &amp;
                    how it may, The parliament of Charles 2 &amp; James 2.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles II (1630&#8211;1685), King of
                        England, Scotland and Ireland 1660&#8211;1685; James II (1633&#8211;1701), King of England, Scotland (as James VII) and Ireland from
                        1685&#8211;1701.</note> never discovered a baser spirit, nor has England ever been insulted by the avowal of doctrines more
                    treasonable again her constitutional freedom than <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> has advanced. As for
                    that blind old man, who came forward to have himself recorded a sycophant &amp; a lyar, when he ought <del>rather</del> to have
                    been settling his account with Heaven for ol[d] crimes, rather than adding a new one to the list, &#8211; by the <del>xxx</del> living
                    God, old &amp; blind he is, he deserves to be hung in his Judges robes, &amp; with his wig about his neck.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Law, 1st Baron Ellenborough (1750&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), a notoriously pro-establishment judge who
                        had presided over the trial for treason of Southey&#8217;s radical associates in 1794.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> this dynasty of ours is in the way to destruction, &#8211; &amp; they who do not
                    understand how God could be said to have hardened Pharoahs heart,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Exodus 4: 21, 7:
                        4&#8211;5.</note> need not look far for a practical commentary.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is little of mine in this years Annual.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the
                        following in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809): <title>Tour Through Spain and Part of Portugal</title>,
                        Volume 3 of Richard Phillips, <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages and Travels</title>
                        (1805&#8211;1810), 56&#8211;57; Christian Augustus Fischer (1771&#8211;1829), <title>A Picture of Madrid: Taken on the Spot. Translated from the
                            German</title> (1808), 57&#8211;60; Thomas Clarkson, <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the
                            Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808), 127&#8211;148; <title>Report of the Committee of
                            the African Institution, Read to the General Meeting on the 15th July, 1807, Together with the Rules and Regulations which
                            were then Adopted for the Government of the Society</title> (1807); Thomas Zouch (1737&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224&#8211;235; Robert Drury (1687&#8211;1734?;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Adventures of Robert Drury, During Fifteen Years Captivity on the Island of Madagascar;
                            Containing a Description of that Island; an Account of its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; With an Account of the
                            Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion, and Civil Policy of the Inhabitants: to Which is Added, a Vocabulary of the
                            Madagascar Language. Written by Himself, and now Carefully Revised and Corrected from the Original</title> (1807),
                        253&#8211;263; John Finlay (1782&#8211;1810), <title>Scottish Historical and Romantic Ballads: Chiefly Ancient with Explanatory Notes and
                            a Glossary</title> (1808), 457&#8211;462; Charles Kirkpatrick Sharpe (1781?-1851), <title>Metrical Legends</title> (1807),
                        473&#8211;473; Francis Douce (1757&#8211;1834), <title>Illustrations of Shakespeare, and of Ancient Manners: with Dissertations on the
                            Clown and Fool of Shakespeare; on the Collection of Popular Tales entitled Gesta Romanorum; and on the English Morris
                            Dance</title> (1807), 554&#8211;562; Charles Lamb, <title>Specimens of English Dramatic Poets, who Lived about the Time of
                            Shakespeare</title> (1808), 562&#8211;570; [Howard Luke (1772&#8211;1864)], <title>A Brief Apology for Quakerism, Inscribed to the
                            Edinburgh Reviewers</title> (1808), 354&#8211;356.</note> The loss of the Aikins <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John</ref> and <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref>.</note> is a great
                    gain to the work, &#8211; Miss Lucys<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy Aikin (1781&#8211;1864).</note> critiques upon poetry were
                    absolutely nauseating. If the volume comes in your way, alter the word Colonists p. 151 to <hi rend="ital">Calvinists</hi>, &#8211; it
                    looks now as if I mean the Americans, instead of the worst blight in the country.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his
                        review of the <title>Report of the African Institution</title>.</note> P 145, I wrote <hi rend="ital">the King</hi> &amp; not
                        <hi rend="ital">a certain high personage</hi> &#8211; for it is my way to speak plain, &amp; in the same page they have printed
                    Kissareii for <hi rend="ital">Kissarsie</hi>, a well-deserved name, which needs no explanation to any who has read Tristram
                        Shandy.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life &amp;
                            Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759&#8211;1767), the name &#8216;Kysarcius&#8217;, pronounced &#8216;kiss-arse-ius&#8217; is used to
                        mock a sycophantic character. Southey uses a similar coinage in his review of Clarkson to designate the toadies of the
                        &#8216;establishment&#8217; who abandoned their support for slave trade abolition when it was accused of being jacobinical.</note> I do
                    not know who reviewed <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox&#8217;s</ref> history, but it is a very able article.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Mill (1773&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>) reviewed Charles James Fox (1749&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A History of the Early Part of the Reign of James the Second: with an Introductory
                            Chapter</title> (1808), in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 99&#8211;114.</note>
          <del>Sharon Turner did</del> The Cid was done by <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, &amp; undone by the
                    Printer who has placed that at the end which ought to have been in the middle.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon
                        Turner&#8217;s review of Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>,
                        7 (1809), 91&#8211;99.</note> Reviews are always hurried thro the Press, &amp; thence it is that no other books are ever so
                    incorrectly printed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> friend will go to Press as soon as the paper arrives from London
                    &#8211; it is to be printed at Penrith &amp; to circulate by the post like a newspaper. I suppose the first number will appear the first
                    week in April.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first number of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge&#8217;s</ref> new periodical <title>The Friend</title> was published on 1 June 1809.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is about soon to bring home <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">a wife</ref>, if <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has not misunderstood him, for it is by that
                    channel I have heard so. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Domine</ref> is not a very frequent correspondent,
                    &amp; I have so little time to spare, &amp; so many letters which must be written that I never urge him to write oftener, since if
                    he has found out the value of time a few years sooner than I did it so much the better. I shall go see him as soon as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is safely in bed,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Southeys&#8217;
                        daughter, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, was born 27 March 1809.</note> &#8211; if <del>xxx</del> it please
                    God that that should be the case, &#8211; Durham Cathedral is one of the things in England which I most wish to see. &#8211; when there
                    Newcastle is at so easy a distance that I shall make <del>a visit there for the sake of seeing James Losh</del> a visit there for
                    the sake of seeing <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">James Losh</ref>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you ever see a magazine called the Monthly Mirror? &#8211; I mention it because in one of the late numbers
                        <del>x</del> a gentleman therein declares that he <del>xxx</del>
          <hi rend="ital"> worships</hi> me.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Monthly Mirror</title> for November 1808, contained &#8216;An Invocation&#8217; by Y.G.N., the last line of which stated:
                        &#8216;&#8216;Mong modern bards, if thou canst give me scope, / I&#8217;ll be content; let bigot critics rot! / Spite of my awe for MILTON,
                        DRYDEN, POPE, / I dare to worship SOUTHEY, CRABBE and SCOTT&#8217; (307).</note> There&#8217;s honour for you! &#8211; to be sure he has put me
                    in a trinity with Crabbe<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), poet and Church
                        of England clergyman.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, &#8211; but I am the first person in that
                    Trinity by favour of the metre. This is a character in which I have never appeard before, &amp; if this gentleman should make any
                    proselytes to his new religion I shall be at a loss how to behave, <del>if</del> &lt;when&gt; any of these come &amp; say their
                    prayers to me.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> God bless you RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <table rows="4" cols="2" width="740">
            <row>
              <cell width="60" />
              <cell width="680">Bryans Catalogue<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Bryan (dates unknown), <title>A
                                        Catalogue of Books for 1809</title> (1809).</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">147.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Atkins Voyage to Brazil.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 1.</note> 5&#8211;6/</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">265.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Cooke&#8217;s Voyages.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Cook (1728&#8211;1779; <title>DNB</title>).
                                    Perhaps <title>An Account of a Voyage round the World ... in the years 1768, 1769, 1770, and 1771.A Voyage of
                                        Discovery to the Southern Hemisphere, etc. Captain J. Cook&#8217;s Third Voyage to the Pacific Ocean</title> in
                                    Robert Wilson (ed.), <title>Voyages of Discoveries round the World</title>, vols 2 and 3 (1806).</note> 14/. N.B.
                                if this copy be sold, the single vol. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 264 will <hi rend="ital">not</hi> do instead.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">314.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Frogers Voyage.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francois Froger (b. 1676), <title>A Relation of a Voyage made in the Years 1695, 1696, 1697 , on
                                        the Coasts of Africa, Streights of Magellan, Brasil, Cayenna, and the Antilles, by a Squadron of French Men of
                                        War, under the Command of M. de Gennes</title> (1698).</note> &#8211; 5/6</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p rend="indent2"> _____</p>
          <table rows="8" cols="2" width="740">
            <row>
              <cell width="60" />
              <cell width="680">Binns&#8217;s Catalogue<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Binns (c. 1781&#8211;1818), a bookseller of
                                    Bath, with premises in Cheap St.</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">&#10003;<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ticks against items in the letter are likely to
                                    have been added by the recipient.</note> 429.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Avicenna. 4/</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">440.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Paracelsus 7/ &#10003;</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">856.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Collins&#8217;s Miscellanies<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emanuel Collins (dates unknown),
                                        <title>Miscellanies: in Prose and Verse</title> (1762). Collins was a clergyman who kept a school in Shannon
                                    Court, Corn St, Bristol. Southey wrote of him &#8216;his school failed him, not because he was deficient in learning&#8212;of
                                    which he seems to have had a full share for his station&#8212;but because of his gross and scandalous miscouduct.&#8217;
                                    Later, he &#8216;kept something . . . like an alehouse&#8217; performing marriages there for the fee of a crown per couple.
                                    See George Price, &#8216;Emanuel Collins&#8217;, <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 3rd series VIII (9 September 1965),
                                    214.</note> 1/6 &#10003;</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">&#10003; 864.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Hoccleve.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library listed, as
                                    no. 1374, Thomas Hoccleve (c.1367&#8211;1426; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems, Never before Printed, with Notes and
                                        Glossary</title> (1796).</note> 4/.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">&#10003; 891.</cell>
              <cell width="680">King Arthur 5/</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">&#10003; 1151.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Backus&#8217;s Hist of the Baptists in N England<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Backus
                                    (1724&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Abridgement of the Church History of New England, 1602 to 1804</title>
                                    (1804), was no. 92 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> 7/</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="60">1660.</cell>
              <cell width="680">Mem. of Peter Henry Bruce<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  <title>Memoirs of Peter Henry Bruce, Esq., a Military Officer in the Services of Prussia, Russia &amp; Great
                                        Britain, Containing an Account of His Travels in Germany, Russia, Tartary, Turkey, the West Indies</title>
                                    (1783).</note> 2/ &#10003;</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p rend="indent2"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>