<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1245</idno><idno type="nines">rce2367</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850).  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                        60–63.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1245" type="letter"><head>1245. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1806-12-20">20 December
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850)<lb/>Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                        60–63.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1806-12-20">Dec. 20. 1806.</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your letter and parcel arrived yesterday, just as I had completed the examination of the former papers. I have now
                    examined the whole.</p><p rend="indent1"> What account of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">your brother</ref> shall be given it rests with you, sir,
                    and his other nearest friends, to determine. I advise and <hi rend="ital">entreat</hi> that it may be as full and as minute as
                    possible. The example of a young man winning his way against great difficulties, of such honourable ambition, such unexampled
                    industry, such a righteous and holy confidence of genius, ought not to be withheld. A full and faithful narrative of his
                    difficulties, his hopes, and his eventual success, till it pleased God to promote him to a higher state of existence, will be a
                    lasting encouragement to others who have the same uphill path to tread; – he will be to them what Chatterton<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bristol poet, Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770; <title>DNB</title>).</note> was to him, and he
                    will be a purer and better example. If it would wound the feelings of his family to let all and every particular of his honourable
                    and admirable life be known, those feelings are, of course, paramount to every other consideration. But I sincerely hope this may
                    not be the case. It will, I know, be a painful task to furnish me with materials for this, which is the most useful kind of
                        biography,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White: with an Account
                            of his Life</title> in 1807.</note> yet; when the effort of beginning such a task shall have been accomplished, the
                    consciousness that you are doing for him what he would have wished to be done, will bring with it a consolation and a comfort.</p><p rend="indent1"> Let me beg of you and of your family, when you can command heart for the task, to give me all your recollections of
                    his childhood and of every stage of his life. Do not fear you can be too minute; I will arrange them, insert such poems as will
                    best appear in that place, and add such remarks as grow out of the circumstances. The narrative itself cannot be told too plainly;
                    all ornament of style would be misplaced in it, – that which is meant to tickle the ear will never find its way either to the
                    understanding or the heart. </p><p rend="indent1"> Respecting the mode of publication, you had better consult Mr. _____.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> The booksellers will, beyond a doubt, undertake to
                    publish them on condition of halving the eventual profits, – which are the terms on which I publish. The profit, I fear, will not
                    be much, unless the public should be taken with some unusual fit of good feeling; and, indeed, this is not unlikely, for they are
                    more frequently just to the dead than to the living.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be glad to see all his magazine publications; possibly some of the pieces marked by me for transcription
                    may be found among them. There is one poem, printed in the Globe for Feb. 11. 1803, which I remember noticing when it appeared,
                    and which may be more easily copied from the newspaper than from the manuscript.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Globe</title> was founded by <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Richard Phillips</ref> in 1803, in
                        opposition to Daniel Stuart’s (1766–1846; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Courier</title>. The poem has not been identified.</note>
                    Whether any of his prose writings should be inserted, I shall better be able to judge after having seen the magazines. But the
                    most valuable materials which could be entrusted to me would be his letters, – the more that could be said of him in his own words
                    the better.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have been affected at seeing my own name among <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">your brother’s</ref>
                    papers; – there is a defence of Thalaba,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey included White’s praise of <title>Thalaba
                            the Destroyer</title> (1801) in <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White ...: with an Account of his Life</title>, 2 vols
                        (London, 1807), II, 284–285.</note> a part of which I regard as the most discriminating and appropriate praise which I have
                    received. It seems to have been published in some magazine.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> White’s comments on
                            <title>Thalaba</title> formed part of his article ‘Melancholy Hours, V’, in <title>The Monthly Mirror</title>, 16 (1803),
                        20–24.</note> These are the highest gratifications which a writer can receive; – for that class of readers who call themselves
                    the public I have as little respect as need be; but to interest and influence such a mind as <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry White’s</ref> is the best and worthiest object which any poet could propose to
                    himself – the fulfilment of his dearest hopes.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Yours truly,</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>