<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1582</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2704</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 135.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1582" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1582" type="letter">
        <head>1582. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1809-02-18">18 February
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsements: 18 Feb 1809; RS./ 18 Feb 1809; Paraguay &#8211; Dobrizhoffer de Abiponibus &#8211;/ Patagonia &#8211; Falkner an Eng.
                        Jesuit Missionary/ Archipelago of Chiloe &#8211; 1791 &#8211;/ part J R <lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 135<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-02-18">18 Feb. 1809</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Cintra Report,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Report of the Board of Inquiry&#8217; into
                        the events leading to the Convention of Cintra was published on 27 December 1808.</note> &#8211; <del>xx</del> the Portugueze is so
                    printed as actually in some instances to be compleatly unintelligible. This is too bad, &#8211; the Printer ought to have paid a clerk
                    in some Portugueze house for correcting the sheets. Thank you for the Memorial, &#8211; alas it is Hebrew-Greek to me! I am utterly
                    ignorant in all matters of science, &amp; in that state of ignorance I must remain. Yet I shall be able to give a better map of
                    Brazil than has yet appeared by correcting Aarons kakography,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among
                        Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map Exhibiting All the New Discoveries in the Interior Parts of North
                            America</title> (1795 rev. 1801, 1802, 1804), <title>Chart of the South Pacific</title> (1798), <title>A New Map of
                            Africa</title> (1802). The map was intended for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810&#8211;1819); see
                        Southey to John Rickman, 18 January 1809, Letter 1568.</note> &amp; by inserting such places as I <del>can</del> discover in
                    the course of my proceedings. Has the said Aaron ever seen the map of Paraguay in Dobrizhoffer de Abiponibus?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> borrow a copy for him from the
                        Advocates Library in Edinburgh, Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque
                            Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784). Southey eventually owned a copy of this work, no. 843 in the sale catalogue of his library.
                        It was translated by Sara Coleridge (with Southey&#8217;s encouragement), as <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People
                            of Paraguay</title> (1822).</note> &#8211; if not he should see it. I have not got the book, to my sorrow, but I have just spent
                    the best part of three weeks in getting at it, &amp; it is one of the best books I have met with. &lt;Has he seen a map of
                    Patagonia in an account of that country published by Falkner an English Jesuit Missionary <del>xxxxx xxxxx</del> &#8211; I am seeking
                    for the book.&gt;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose papers were
                        published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the Adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The history of the Review concerning which <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has
                    applied to you in his capacity of Jackal to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> the Editor, is this, &#8211; that it
                    is set up as an Anti-Edinburgh to counteract as far as possible the cursed, cowardly, peace-mongering politicians which would lay
                    this country prostrate at the feet of France.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Quarterly Review</title>, for
                        which Southey began writing from its first number in 1809. The <title>Edinburgh Review</title> advocated making peace with
                        France.</note> This is a good object, &amp; in this object I cooperate by writing my best upon other subjects. Interest in the
                    affair, except the regular per sheetage which is to be Edinburgh price whatever that may be! I have none, &#8211; but I shall be glad if
                    the work answers its purpose, &#8211; glad for two reasons, because I shall be well paid for what I do in it, &amp; well treated as to
                    what I do out of it. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> is the projector, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>, <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> &amp; that set of men are looked to for occasional assistance, &#8211; &amp;
                    Government for such political intelligence as they think fit to communicate. I stipulated for freedom of opinion, &amp; I dare say
                    most of the freedom that is found there will be mine. <del>Xx</del> As yet I have written but one article, which is a defence of
                    the Mission in Bengal, versus Scott Waring &amp; Sidney Smith.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Sydney Smith
                        (1771&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of and leading contributors to the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>
                        reviewed the activities of British missionaries in India negatively; Southey counteracted his views in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>. Smith&#8217;s review of &#8216;Ingram on Methodism&#8217; appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11 (January
                        1808), 341&#8211;362, and he reviewed &#8216;Indian Missions&#8217; in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 12 (April 1808), 151&#8211;181. Southey
                        reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John
                        Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius
                            Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical
                            Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity&#8230; By a
                            Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East
                            India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the
                            British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809), 193&#8211;226. In his turn, Smith responded in &#8216;Styles on Methodists and Missions&#8217;, in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 14 (April 1809), 40&#8211;50.</note> In my hatred to the Scotchmen (a little revenge being mingled therewith) I
                    wish the Quarterly to succeed. As one means of making it succeed I should rejoice if you reviewed the first books in your way
                    which may happen to appear, &#8211; &amp; if <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> as soon as a text shall turn up would
                    write an article concerning the poor.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Rickman did not contribute to the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title> until 1818, when he jointly authored with Southey a review of documents pertaining to the
                        poor laws. Thomas Poole did not write for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> Nothing more would be to be done than if you
                    saw a book advertised on a subject which you liked, to intimate it in a note to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">the Jackal</ref>, &#8211; the book would be sent you, &#8211; &amp; the per sheetage paid on the appearance of the articles. <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon</ref> it seems is reckoned on as a helper now &amp; then, &#8211; I tremble for his flowers
                    of speech. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> I believe has taken care of the Cid.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) was reviewed by Scott in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 117&#8211;134.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George I.</ref> has taken a great deal of pains which he might have spared for I know every
                    thing about Amerigo,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amerigo Vespucci (1454&#8211;1512), Italian explorer and navigator, who
                        participated in several voyages to South America between 1499 and 1502.</note> except what that Ptolomy<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Ptolom&#230;i Geographic&#230; Enarrationes</title> (1535), no. 2178 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> was said
                    to contain, &amp; which proves to be little or nothing. I am as much obliged to him as if all the trouble had not been
                    supererogatory. I believe it would take me equal pains were I to decypher the whole of his communications, but I have got at the
                    result in the way of skip &amp; go on, &amp; am rather thankful that they contain nothing which it is necessary <del>for</del> to
                    make quarto out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad you like the plain, downright straight-forward English of my History.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for an offer of hospitality in your former letter &#8211; but London is too far away for a yearly visit. I
                    propose passing a week or ten days at Edinburgh in the spring with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, for
                    the express purpose of profiting by the Advocates Library, when doubtless there will be something to be found. &#8211; What is become of
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dalrymples books?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Dalrymple (1737&#8211;1808;
                            <title>DNB</title>), hydrographer, writer on exploration.</note> will they be for sale? </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I rather like this Inquiry,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Perhaps <title>The
                    Proceedings of the Enquiry into the Armistice and Convention of Cintra, and into the Conduct of the Officers
                    Concerned</title> (1809), printed for John Joseph Stockdale (1776/7&#8211;1847).</note> &#8211; being swinishly inclined. It promiseth to accelerate the journey to Falmouth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I bespeak your daughter Ann for my own son <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, upon this
                    ground, that he being all for a boy which she is for a girl, they must have been made for each other. &#8211; I have another coming in
                    about six weeks.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref> was born on 27 March 1809.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you seem to think the Cintra Convention Book<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">See note 13.</note> to be of the nature of waste paper, I
                    will ask you for two copies &#8211; one for my Uncle R.<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>
          <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton upon Wye</ref> Hereford. One for <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>
                    Esq. Hale Downton Wilts. both these persons are interested enough in Portugal to value this collection of documents. If you can
                    lay hands on them, let J Mays copy go in my name, &amp; my Uncles in your own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yet more of map-making. I have a map of the Archipelago of Chiloe<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                    Chilo&#233; Archipelago consists of several islands lying off the coast of Chile. The map came from P. F. Pedro Gonzalez de Agueros
                    (dates untraced), <title>Descripcion Historial de la Provincia y Archipielago de Chile, y Obispado de la Concepcion</title>
                    (1791), no. 3480 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> published in 1791, &amp; probably upon a
                    larger scale than any other which has appeared of that out of the way part of the world. This I can send up if Aaron has not seen
                    it. And if Aaron will send me a proof of that part of his great map of England<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Arrowsmith&#8217;s <title>Map of England And Wales, The Result Of Fifteen Years Labour</title> was published in 1815.</note> which
                    includes this circle of mountains, I <del>will</del> can mark out the relative size &amp; situation of all the Lakes which it
                    contains, &#8211; a thing which in the selling maps of the Lake country is done with very great inaccuracy, &amp; which I am competent
                    to do, (having with only two exceptions) seen them all, &amp; most of them repeatedly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not whether the Brazil Pilot is yet published. the original is here, &amp; I had the translation sent down,
                    &#8211; the charts being now first added will make it a very useful book. <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s uncle
                        Herbert Hill had translated Manoel Pimentel (1650&#8211;1719), <title>The Brazil Pilot; or, a Description of the Coast of Brazil,
                            Translated from the Portuguese of Manoel Pimentel &#8230; to which are added, Charts, of some of its most Considerable
                            Ports</title> (1809). This was no. 2331 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I hope <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle&#8217;s</ref> next work will be a statistic Account of Brazil, but I suppose he will
                    wait till it be seen how much of <del>their</del> his materials can be inserted in the historical form</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1809-02-18">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 18. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>