<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.952</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2074</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.952" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="952" type="letter">
        <head>952. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-06-12">12 June
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol./
                        Single.<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK/ 2<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />Endorsements: [Keep Powels/<del> Oxalic</del>/ Salts
                        Tartare a [illegible word] to a Glass take effervescent; [various other illegible notes]<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1804-06-12">June 12. 1804.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You made a sad blunder about the manuscript. I sent for the single Chronicle which you have among the loose books,
                    that it might be bound, because it cannot be made use of in its present state without injury, the board covers fretting the leaves
                    as they open &amp; shut.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Danvers to send him &#8216;the great Portugueze
                        manuscript chronicle&#8217;; see Southey to Charles Danvers, [late May&#8211;before 1 June 1804], Letter 946. This was Fernao Lopes (c.
                        1385&#8211;after 1459), &#8216;Cronica del Rei Dom Fernando o Noveno Rei de Portugal&#8217;, no. 3829 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [April&#8211;May 1805], Letter 1063.</note> &amp; you sent off
                    instead of this a huge box for which I had no immediate need whatever &#8211; by the coach &#8211; which cost fourteen &amp; ninepence.
                    whereas what I wanted would have come for a couple of shillings.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was thoroughly wearied in London, indeed never <del>at any</del> before so compleatly jaded &amp; worn down to
                    the very bone. I had no time to look for the <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">Smiths</ref> &#8211; probably they will let me know
                    their approach that lodgings may be provided for them, &amp; you also will arrange this with them, that you may meet. September is
                    the best month, or even later, for beauty. If you come during the cloudless weather of full summer you lose the lights &amp;
                    shades, the scene shifting &amp; machinery of heaven which form so great a part of <del>the</del> mountain magnificence. Your
                    route should be by way of Brummejam<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Slang, based on the locals&#8217; unique accent, for the
                        city of Birmingham.</note> to Manchester. thence to Lancaster, &amp; from thence take the stage across the sands to
                    Ulverstone, by which means you enter the Lake country at the right end, &amp; see Connistone Lake first &#8211; then Windermere &#8211; &amp;
                    from thence take Rydal, <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> &amp; Wyborne-water in your direct line to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. But of this more particulars when they shall be needed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> are, on the
                    whole, both doing well, &amp; yet the young one has had some things against her. owing to the quantity of milk contained in her
                    breasts the one has gathered &amp; discharged, without however occasioning any apparent inconvenience to her. a more fretting evil
                    is the wind with which she is perpetually troubled, alike after the <del>xxxx</del> mothers milk &amp; after every other food with
                    which we have tried her. &#8211; Ask <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> by what likely means we can hope to alleviate this.
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> herself has not this complaint at present, nor has had it of late. the
                    young one struggles almost as if going into a fit, till it explodes with a loudness that sufficiently indicates the pain it must
                    have occasioned in her little stomach &amp; throat. Perhaps this may induce <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> to write.
                    &#8211; My eyes are again annoying me. it is an epidemic evil. many hundred of the soldiers &amp; volunteers at Manchester have been
                    discharged in consequence of this complaint, which it seems came from Egypt,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Keratoconjunctivitis or &#8216;Egyptian Opthalmia&#8217;, a contagious disease that spread in epidemic proportions across Western Europe
                        for the first time in the years 1798&#8211;1806, having been imported by the sailors and soldiers campaigning in, or against, the
                        armies of revolutionary France in Egypt.</note> &amp; is to be considered as one of our gains by the last war, &amp; the only
                    gains in which I have had a share. &#8211; What of the drawings? If they should be done while parliament are sitting inclose them to <hi rend="ital">
            <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>
          </hi> under cover to the Speaker asking him to inclose them to
                    me. you will know how to do this without any blundering. the inner cover must have only his name &#8211; no mention or hint of mine &#8211;
                    the outer one Rt Honbl the Speaker &amp;c &amp;c, Westminster. &amp; tell yon <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> that
                    the sooner these vignettes are in the Engravers hands the better.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had written to
                        King to request some illustrations for <title>Madoc</title> (1805), but none by him were included in the published work; see
                        Southey to John King, [1]&#8211;5 March 1804, Letter 904.</note> I wish to see them before they go to the Engravers that my
                    descriptions may be improved from &amp; fitted to the drawings. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> procures for
                    me some of the other designs from Pocock, Howard<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Pocock (1740&#8211;1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>): marine painter, formerly a merchant seaman. Pocock exhibited regularly at the Royal Academy from
                        1782&#8211;1815 and was a founder member of the Old Watercolour Society in 1804. Southey complained that Pocock spoilt the image of
                        Madoc&#8217;s ship that he had been commissioned to make, by drawing too modern a vessel. Henry Howard (1769&#8211;1847;
                            <title>DNB</title>): portrait and history painter, full member of the Royal Academy from 1808 and its Secretary from 1811.
                        Howard was also a book illustrator; besides <title>Madoc</title>, he was commissioned to provide designs for editions of
                            <title>The British Essayists</title> (1823) and Alexander Pope&#8217;s (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) translations of Homer in
                        1806 and 1813.</note> &amp;c &#8211; &amp; one or two will be done under my own eye &amp; to my own taste by <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had requested his friend to
                        provide designs for engravings to be placed in <title>Madoc</title>; see Southey to Mary Barker, 17 February 1804 (Letter
                        896), 3 March 1804 (Letter 906) and 29 December 18[04] (Letter 1009). In the event, the poem was published in 1805 with only
                        two engravings, one of which, of a giant snake, was misplaced.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Poem goes off on Thursday to Edinburgh to be printed there.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was printed by the Edinburgh firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James
                        Ballantyne</ref>.</note> this is <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> arrangement, &amp; will be so far
                    convenient as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> can correct the revises, the proofs will be sent to me. &#8211;
                    I am also likely to reprint in a separate volume my own best pieces from the Anthology &#8211; advertising them as so <hi rend="ital">re</hi>published to prevent all possibility of deceiving any purchaser.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        poems from the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) reappeared in his <title>Metrical Tales and Other Poems</title>
                        (1805).</note> from the disproportion of sale between those volumes &amp; my own acknowledged ones it is probable that 500 of
                    this old publication will sell off at once. It must not be calld Volume 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> as that would preclude
                        <del>xxx</del> a fourth volume &#8211; or it may be so calld, &amp; any after volume christened by some peculiar name which will
                    perhaps be the better plan. &#8211; The Amadis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation, <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title>, was published in 1803.</note> has sold well &#8211; that is nearly six hundred are gone. <del>it has sold</del>
                    more copies of this have gone off in one year, than of Thalaba<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> was published in 1801.</note> in three. If this be not flattering the chance of my
                    fifty pounds <del>at</del> the sale of the whole 1000 comes as a comfortable sweetener.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The box of lost goods came safe mirabile dictu!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;wonderful to
                        relate&#8217;.</note> for it came in half on the road, &amp; the waggoner secured it by cords. What Cardew<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> means by the other books I know not. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> gave me no reason to expect another, &amp; yet another it seems was sent, &amp; certainly never reached Bristol. &#8211;
                    This loss of the Don Quixote is very serious. do stick up a paper in the Custom House offering half a guinea to whoever has <hi rend="ital">found</hi> an odd volume of D Quixote, bound in red morocco, stating that it spoils a set. it may thus be possibly
                    recovered &#8211; otherwise a set worth &#163;3&#8211;12&#8211; in Portugal is utterly valueless.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Apparently the
                        missing volume was not recovered, for no. 3191 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra
                        (1547&#8211;1616), <title>Don Quixote de la Mancha</title> (1798), is described as &#8216;wanting vol. 6&#8217;.</note> Have you received the
                    books from Cork which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> was foolish enough to send?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked his brother to buy a number of books for him; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 1 February
                        1804 (Letter 892) and Southey to John Rickman, 30 June 1804 (Letter 957).</note> &#8211; I am uneasy at not receiving any letters
                    from him of late. We are in hourly expectation of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>. &#8211; But all the <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> are just arrived &amp; I must therefore conclude. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you Charles!</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>remember me to Betty.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers&#8217;s servant.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> how is Cupid? how is Joe.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cupid was originally Southey&#8217;s dog; Danvers
                        had inherited him; Joe was Thomas Southey&#8217;s dog and was being looked after by Danvers.</note> I have a dog Dapper.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>