<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1327</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2449</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 113.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 94&#8211;96 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1327" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1327" type="letter">
        <head>1327. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-05-27">27 May
                        1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ St Stephens
                        Court/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Endorsement: RS./ 27 May 1807.<lb />Stamped [partial]: CK<lb />Postmark
                        [partial]: MAY 30/ 1807<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 113<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 94&#8211;96 [in
                    part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The pleasantest season in the country for one who lives in it is undoubtedly this month of blossoms &amp; of
                    beauty, when we have not only immediate enjoyment, but summer before us. The best season for <hi rend="ital">seeing</hi> a
                    country, &amp; especially this country, is during the turn of the leaf. September &amp; October are our best months, we have
                    usually long &amp; delightful autumns, extending farther into winter than they do in the south of England. Our harvests such as
                    they are &#8211; are sometimes not in till the end of October, Every thing with us being proportionately late. If the Tantara-raras<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s disparaging term for the noisy MPs in the House of Commons. <title>Tantara-rara,
                            Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by John O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Dramatic
                            Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1798), III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All Fools All&#8217; was also
                        a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>) play <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> release
                    you, as for their own sake they will before the campaign opens against the partridges, you will be in good time for the Lakes, tho
                    not for the Highlands. &#8211; &amp; it is not amiss that the Highlands should be left for another year, when, if you want a companion I
                    will certainly accompany you.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had hoped to accompany Rickman if he travelled to
                        Scotland on government business; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 30 January 1807, Letter 1268.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref> has seen all that water colours can
                    do for our Lakes, in seeing them as delineated by Glover,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Glover (1767&#8211;1849;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the watercolour painter who owned Blowick Farm in Patterdale, on <ref target="places.html#Ullswater">Ullswater</ref>.</note> who is of all our artists the truest to nature. But I will show her sights beyond all reach of
                    human colouring, &#8211; such work as nature &lt;herself&gt; makes with <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> travelling clouds, &amp; columns of misty
                    light &lt;sunshine&gt;, falling as if from an eye of light in Heaven, &#8211; like that upon Guy Faux in his prayer book. <hi rend="ital">Every</hi> point of sight is beautiful &amp; Derwentwater can only be <del>guessed at</del> &lt;judged&gt;. by a
                    panorama, such as you will have from our boat, which the painter is at this very time decorating. Do not wait for another year,
                    for the sake of including your Scotch journey &#8211; God knows what another year may produce, either of good or evil, to both of us.
                    there is always so much chance of being summoned off on the grand tour of the universe, that a man ought not without good reason,
                    to postpone any little trip he may wish to take first upon our <del>xxxxx</del> microcosm.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for forwarding the chest &amp;c &#8211; on this day week I shall look for their arrival, with much pleasurable
                    impatience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of breeding up a boy to understand the Keltic language has often been in my mind. Have you seen a good
                    book in reply to Malthus by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jarrold?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Jarrold (1770&#8211;1853;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological, and Political; In Answer to Mr. Malthus&#8217;s
                            &#8216;Essay on the Principle of Population&#8217;</title> (1806).</note> &#8211; this disjointed question comes in, because he shows how
                    animals that are the most highly finished are most apt &#8211; like large looking glasses &#8211; to break in the making &amp; I have always
                    the fear of too much sensorial power in my children, <del>before</del> so before my eyes, as <del>not</del> never willingly to
                    shape any plans about them, which might <del>xxx up</del> &lt;occasion&gt; more cause for disappointment. &#8211; How easy would it be
                    for the London Institution, or any Society, to look out promising lads, <del>xx</del> &amp; breed <del>up</del> them up for
                    specific literary purposes. Should <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> live I should more incline (as more
                    connected with my own pursuits) to let him pass two or three years in Biscay, &amp; <del>xxx</del> so procure all that is thus to
                    be gained of Cantabrian<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The people of the region of Cantabria, on the south, Spanish,
                        coast of the Bay of Biscay.</note> antiquity, &#8211; a distinct stock I <del>believe</del> &lt;learn&gt; from the Keltic, but I
                        <del>xxxxxxx think</del> &lt;believe&gt; that one wave of our population came from those shores, of which the prevalence of
                        <del>black</del> dark hair &amp; rank complection is to <del>xx</del> me physical proof. Nothing can be so little calculated
                    to advance our stock of knowledge as our inveterate modes of education, whereby we all spend so many years in learning so little.
                    I was from the age of 6 till that of 20 learning Greek &amp; Latin, or to speak more truly learning nothing else, &#8211; the little
                    Greek I ever had sleepeth, if it be not dead, &amp; can hardly wake without a miracle, &amp; my Latin, tho abundantly enough for
                    all useful purposes, would be held in great contempt by those people who regard the classics as the Scriptures of taste.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Acu&#241;a<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey eventually possessed both the English and French versions of
                        the voyage narrative of Crist&#243;bal Diatrist&#225;n de Acu&#241;a (1597-c.1676), <title>Voyages and Discoveries in South America</title>
                        (1698), <title>Relation de la Riviere des Amazones</title> (1682). Southey had previously asked Rickman to look for this; see
                        Southey to John Rickman, 13 February 1807, Letter 1274.</note> will perhaps turn up among the books from <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref>, &amp; the other book may possibly be at Bristol. The sum of Acu&#241;a
                    seems to be given in his own words in the Mara&#241;on of Amazonas.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel Rodriguez
                        (1633&#8211;1701), <title>El Mara&#241;on y Amazonas Historia de los Descubrimientos, Entradas y Reduccion de Naciones</title>
                        (1684).</note> which came in your last cargo. I have however the history of many years to write before his voyage occurs.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have promised Artaxerxes<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s nickname for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, after the Persian emperor Artaxerxes I (also named Longimanus) who
                        reigned 465&#8211;424 BC.</note> to review <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharons</ref> new edition,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of Turner&#8217;s <title>History of the Anglo Saxons</title> was published by Longmans in
                        1807.</note> &#8211; not foreseeing when the promise was made that he would leave any metaphors to stick in the throat of my
                    conscience. However I will spare him, by making my attack upon modern style in general &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have a dirty &amp; deranged house &#8211; the masons have ejected me out of my study, &amp; it will be probably a full
                    fortnight before I am reinstated &#8211; meantime I have the discomfort of having my books in a heap. &amp; of course, am sure ten times
                    in the course of the day to want some book which proves to be in the least accessible part of it. These last two days have been
                    given to prefacing Palmerin,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected
                            by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> [MS torn] said preface is, in great part thereof,
                    very bibliographical &amp; dull. It will however establish the point that T. de Moraes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Francisco de Moraes Cabral (1500?-1572), author of <title>Libro del Muy esforzado caballero Palmerin de Inglaterra</title>
                        (1547).</note> was the author of the book, &amp; also show that there was the same sort of book manufactory carried on in
                    Elizabeths days as in our <del>x</del> own, &amp; that Anthony Monday<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anthony Munday
                        (1560?-1633; <title>DNB</title>), a miscellaneous writer for booksellers&#8217; commissions, who translated de Moraes as <title>The
                            [First-] Seconde Part, of the ... Historie, of the ... Princes Palmerin of England, and Florian du Desart his brother ...
                            Translated out of French, by A. M</title>. (1596).</note> made the same sort of use of his name as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Mavor<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr William Fordyce Mavor (1758&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), a miscellaneous
                        writer who gave his name to a number of educational publications, including <title>Mavor&#8217;s English Spelling Book</title> (many
                        editions from 1801).</note> does. This will be finished tonight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I find privies at Valencia eight hundred years ago. The proofs of the Cid<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> must pass thro your hands that you may find out in
                    them what has escaped me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Just at this time I am greatly in want of Thevet,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet
                        (1516?&#8211;1592), <title>Singularitez de la France antarctique</title> (1557).</note> &#8211; &amp; have no chance of meeting with it
                    till I get to London, unless peradventure it should be in the convoy from Lisbon, by which supplies are promised me. I have found
                    out the titles of several French books relating to my side (not <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld Gs</ref> &#8211;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wyndham Grenville, 1st Baron Grenville (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister
                        from 1806 to 1807. Grenville had informed Southey that the government did not wish him to prepare a briefing report about
                        Brazil, but had encouraged him to publish on the subject for the benefit of the public.</note>) of S. America; &#8211; by &amp; by
                    my best way will be to <del>some</del> &lt;put&gt; the list into some booksellers hands &amp; let him send to Paris for them</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your stories of <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> are truly Irish. he told these
                    himself with no very material alteration, &#8211; only laying fault in the first instance on Bingley.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rev. William Bingley (1774&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), the naturalist, traveller and local historian, was a
                        neighbour of Biddlecombe&#8217;s as a curate of Christchurch Priory, Hampshire, from 1802 to 1816.</note> In about a fortnight, if I
                    do not hear from him that the books are dispatched according to his promise I shall jog his memory with a letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You call <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> a generous man. I dislike him for two reasons.
                    first because I cannot like any body who has ever been connected with that wretch Pitt;<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> &amp; secondly because I abominate
                    the way in which he took up the Catholick question, &#8211; <del>xxxxx</del> the greedy manner in which he would have snavelled the
                    sinecure &amp; the impudence of his accepting a post for which he is so utterly unfit. The Duke of Portland<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The new Prime Minister was William Henry Cavendish Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> can only be locum tenens for M. Wellesley<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Colley Wellesley, 1st Marquess Wellesley (1760&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>): Anglo-Irish politician and bellicose
                        Governor-General of the British colonies in India between 1798 and 1805. Wellesley did not become head of the new ministry,
                        and declined a cabinet position while his conduct as Governor-General was under investigation.</note> or for Ld Melville,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State
                        for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. From 1802&#8211;1805 Melville&#8217;s use of public monies when Treasurer of
                        the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800), was investigated by a Royal Commission on suspicion that he had allowed the diversion of government
                        funds to his personal accounts. On 9 April 1805 Melville was censured in the House of Commons for the misuse of public funds.
                        He resigned and impeachment proceedings were commenced against him, but he was cleared of nearly all the charges in June
                        1806.</note> &#8211; if they can dare set up the latter, &#8211; or risque the impeachment of the former, for his cursed conduct in India.
                    What a pity it is that the proper <del>appl</del> use of hemp should be so little understood in this country! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref> &amp; make
                    your preparation to start as soon as the session closes.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-05-27">May. 27. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>