<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1526</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2648</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 116&#8211;118 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1526" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1526" type="letter">
        <head>1526. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-10-30">30 October
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey./ H. M. S. Dreadnought./ Plymouth
                        Dock &#8211; <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 116&#8211;118 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-10-30">Sunday Oct. 30. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must I think ere this have received a letter, the parcel, &amp; another book of Kehama.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was sending his brother drafts of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810) in instalments.</note> I
                    thought to have filled one more to day, but the weather was so tempting that it was not possible to keep indoors, &amp; I lounged
                    about the garden &amp; grounds, &amp; played with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> all the morning. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> probably keeps Kehama a few days, &#8211; it goes up in a treble cover &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> to whom the middle one is directed, may not have an opportunity of
                    delivering it to him immediately, &#8211; &amp; on the other hand when Bedford has read his fill &#8211; he may not be able readily to return
                    it to Herries, for the purpose of getting it refranked. If they reach you in right sequence they come right.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You enquire about <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> just as if you supposed that a man in
                    England was likely to get any thing because he had good claim to it &#8211; I have not heard that the Dean of Hereford is dead, &#8211; &amp;
                    I am sure that my Uncle has <del>no little</del> &lt;no&gt; expectation of obtaining any thing. He has made up his mind to pass
                    the remainder of his days at <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is some satisfaction to me that I shall be able to leave upon record my opinion upon this infamous
                        convention,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s exasperation was caused by the Convention of Cintra, signed on
                        30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under
                        Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed
                        to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command
                        by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which
                        Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> &#8211; in the History of Portugal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s never-completed history, of which his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) was an offshoot.</note> There is
                    a talk of an address from this county, &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> will do all he can to
                    prevent a meeting, or oppose any thing that may be done at one. he &amp; the ministry (all ministries alike) &#8211; never wish the
                    people to come before the King with any thing except professions that they are ready to kiss his Majesty&#8217;s <del>xx</del> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;. this
                    his Majesty is not yet tired of hearing, &amp; would go on creating knights, &amp; giving gracious replies to the end of the
                    chapter. I rejoice to see the spirited manner in which the Common Council has resented his most improper answer to their petition.
                    If any thing is done in Cumberland here it will originate with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, &#8211; he
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> will set the business in its true light in the country
                    newspapers, &#8211; &amp; frame the revolutions, to be brought forward by some weighty persons, &#8211; &amp; Wordsworth will speak at the
                    meeting, he being a freeholder. We are all to meet Curwen<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen
                        (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), Whig MP for Carlisle, Workington landowner.</note> (by his special desire) at Calverts<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert (1771&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), who was at school with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death
                        of his father, Calvert became a man of independent means, inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east
                        shore of Bassenthwaite, near Keswick, where he lived with his family.</note> on Friday next; &#8211; &amp; there I suppose the plan
                    of operations will be settled. It was wished not to make this a party matter, &amp; therefore Lord Lonsdale was applied to thro
                        <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">H. Senhouse</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to
                        Humphrey Senhouse, 19 October [1808], Letter 1523.</note> &#8211; but it seems he &#8216;views the Convention in a very different light!&#8217;
                    &#8211; God help poor England! well might <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref> forefeelingly call our Rulers </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent7"> a venal band</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Who are to judge of danger which they fear,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And honour which they do not understand.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The last lines of Wordsworth&#8217;s
                            sonnet &#8216;November, 1803&#8217;, from his <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> (1807).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you know any thing of Capt. Philip Beaver? &#8211; he has I believe the Acasta at this time in the W. Indies. &#8211; If you
                    were in the way of falling in with him, I would have a copy of the Cid<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition
                        of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> sent you, that you might give it to him as a mark of respect. &#8211; I
                    have been reading, &#8211; indeed have bought &#8211; his African Memordana, &#8211; the Journal of the Colony which he attempted to found on the
                    Island of Bulama, &amp; from which only himself &amp; one adventurer returned!<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip
                        Beaver (1766&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, who in 1791 participated in a scheme for colonizing the island of
                        Bulama, near Sierra Leone. The scheme failed and he returned in 1794, publishing his Bulama experiences in <title>African
                            Memoranda</title> (1805). In 1806 he was appointed to the 40-gun frigate <hi rend="ital">Acasta</hi> and in her went to
                        the West Indies, where he remained until after the capture of Martinique in February 1809 (<title>DNB</title>).</note> But
                    never did I read a book which gave me so high an idea of the infinite resources, activity &amp; genius of any one man, as that
                    plain, manly right English book has given me of its author.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> section of Kehama &#8211; 2345 lines &#8211; probably about half the poem. K has stormed
                    the Swerga, Ladurlad &amp; Kalyal are once more upon earth, &amp; Arvalan will soon be laid neck &amp; <del>xx</del> heels in
                        Padalon,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book 13.</note> &#8211; I see my way before me, &amp; shall soon begin to work with the
                    encouraging prospect of getting to the end.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> grows stout &amp; continues short. What does Pappa call you Herby? (which
                    is what he calls himself) &#8211; &#8216;Mine Dog.&#8217; &#8211; &amp; then laughs. And what does <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mamma</ref> call
                    you? &#8211; Bright eyes.&#8217; &#8211; You would laugh to see the faces he makes when he says of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">his
                        sisters</ref> name &#8211; not Ed<hi rend="ital">aw</hi>, but Ed<hi rend="ital">is</hi>. &#8211; Ed<hi rend="ital">aw</hi> he used to call
                    her. He says every thing, &#8211; rides <hi rend="ital">pocko</hi>, rides towel, rides foot, <del>xx</del> &lt;makes me give him&gt;
                    three tosses, &#8211; &amp; has no mercy upon either <hi rend="ital">pocko</hi>, towel, foot or father. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your niece</ref> wants sadly to know when you are coming home, &amp; is surprized that
                    you have not killed all the French yet. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I verily believe Lord Chatham<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham
                        (1708&#8211;1778; <title>DNB</title>), the minister whose policies were creditied with bringing victories during the Seven Years&#8217;
                        War.</note> would have finished the war by this time. Twenty thousand men landed at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Andero four months
                    ago would have exterminated all the French in Spain, &amp; 100,000 Spaniards would have been beyond the Pyrenees, spreading fire
                    sword &amp; manifestoes, more formidable than either before them. &#8211; I am glad to see they are infesting the towns upon the coast
                    from Catalonia. With Ld Cochranes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald, 1st Marquess
                        of Maranh&#227;o (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>). At this point in his remarkable career, Cochrane was a naval captain harassing,
                        by a series of daring coastal raids, French troop movements into Spain.</note> help, they will find employment for a great
                    many troops in defending their own shores. &#8211; But at home here all is delay, blunder, jobs &amp; rascality, &amp; so it will
                    continue to be till things are thoroughly altered. No strength of mind, no rectitude of heart, no feeling of honour, no sense of
                    shame, among our trading politicians. If it were not for the indignation which the people have discovered upon this cursed
                    occasion, one <del>should</del> might be ashamed of ones country &amp; tempted to wish oneself a Spaniard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall make use of your stories of the hand<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey explained in his
                    letter of 6 November 1808 to Walter Scott (Letter 1528), &#8216;In one of the Frenchmans knapsacks, among other articles of that property which they bargained to take away with them, was a delicate female hand with rings upon the fingers&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; of Junot,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Jean-Andoche Junot, 1st Duc d&#8217;Abrant&#232;s (1771&#8211;1813), the French general in command of the invasion of Portugal in 1807. Junot
                        was made Governor of Portugal after taking Lisbon at the end of 1807.</note> &#8211; &amp; good use. Do not let any stories of this
                    kind &#8211; or any thing which I can make use of escape you. you know how these things, even after the lapse of many years always turn
                    to account at last.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>