<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1003</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2125</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York
                        Public Library .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 366&#8211;369.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1003" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1003" type="letter">
        <head>1003. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1804-12-16">16 December
                        1804</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ Portland Square/
                        Bristol<lb />Postmark: [partial] 1804<lb />Endorsements: <del>173</del>
            <hi rend="ital">71</hi>
            <lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York
                        Public Library <lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 366&#8211;369.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have &lt;not&gt; written to you since your friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Porter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably the Reverend Joseph Porter (dates unknown), a clergyman based in Bristol.</note> was here in July &#8211;
                    to whom I will beg you when you see him to make my remembrances, for he seems to be a worthy man, thinking well upon many subjects
                    &amp; meaning well upon all. Since that time I have been <del>xxxxxx</del> busied with idle company &#8211; for this place swarms in
                    summer, or hard at work to make up for the time so lost, or expended in mountaineering. Madoc I trust will find his way to you in
                    about six weeks or two months.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in
                        1805.</note> the whole of the poem is printed, &amp; <del>the</del> notes will occupy no very long time. you will see a very
                    handsome book &amp; find a full third of the volume altogether new. So that I have something to show for my time notwithstanding
                    so <del> man</del> large a portion of it was spent abroad.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For this month past have I been thinking to write this letter, in the hope of persuading you to make a book about
                    Bristol, your native place &amp; mine. how worthless a book Barratts<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Barrett
                        (1727&#8211;1789), <title>The History and Antiquities of Bristol</title> (1789).</note> is every body knows, &amp; indeed all such
                    books as his are by their very nature unreadable what I would urge you to collect is not a <hi rend="ital"> History</hi> of
                    Bristol, but <hi rend="ital">Anecdotes</hi> of Bristol to relate just so much of its History as would make a not-tiresome chapter
                    &#8211; to preserve all the strange occurrencies which have happened there &amp; which can still be recovered from the memory of old
                    persons, &#8722; the biographies of all the remarkable persons born there or living there &#8211; an account of what is beautiful or
                    remarkable in or near it &amp;c &amp;c. such a book published with good views &amp; portraits would infallibly sell &#8211; I would have
                    related as far as possible what Bristol was &#8722; &amp; what it now is &#8211; such a book in short of the city <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, as
                    if had been written a century ago would have delighted you &amp; every body else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let us look closer into this matter. to begin with the history. ask <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">your
                        good Mother</ref> what Bristol was when she first saw it, or can remember it: when it ended at the College Green, &amp; at the
                    Barton, when the old bridge was standing, &amp; the old shambles, &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t </hi> Leonards Church, before Bridge
                    Street &#8211; Union Street &#8211; Clare Street were built &#8211; or Park Street &#8211; College Street &amp; all your end of the city &#8211; when Kingsdown
                    &amp; Clifton were villages &amp;c &amp;c. Changes such as these interest every body who know the places: we take a sort of family
                    interest in topographical anecdotes, &amp; it would be no difficult matter to show why this is the case, &amp; how we are the
                    better for it. For the ornamental illustrations of this part see next what can be recovered. Barrets view of the old bridge<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barrett&#8217;s view of the old bridge is a plain architectural drawing in <title>The History and
                            Antiquities of Bristol</title>, opposite page 96.</note> may be made picturesque, &amp; perhaps drawings exist of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Leonards,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Leonard&#8217;s church, Redfield, Bristol.</note> as they
                    must of the Cross when it stood in the College Green.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bristol High Cross, a monument
                        commemorating British monarchs, was removed from College Green, the area in central Bristol adjacent to the cathedral, in the
                        mid-eighteenth century.</note> &#8211; Next for the remarkables of Bristol &#8211; there is that strange tale of Mr Loves death,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Reverend Samuel Love, a canon of Bristol cathedral, died aged 29 in 1773, and a
                        monument was placed in the cathedral to his memory. Love was a poet who described in verse a remarkable occurrence that took
                        place shortly before his death: a robin took to settling on one of the pinnacles of the cathedral organ and singing while it
                        played during services. He was the subject of a poem by Hannah More (1745&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;On the Rev. Mr. Love. In
                        the Cathedral at Bristol&#8217;, in <title>The Works of Hannah More</title>, 6 vols (London, 1834), VI, pp. 13&#8211;14.</note> &#8722; the poor
                    man at Penpark hole<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 17 March 1775, Reverend Thomas Newman (dates unknown), a canon of
                        Bristol cathedral, fell to his death into Pen Park Hole, near Filton, north Bristol, while trying to plumb its depths. Pen
                        Park Hole is a deep cave, with an underground lake, discovered in the seventeenth century.</note> Gooderes murder<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In January 1741 Sir John Dineley Goodere (c. 1680&#8211;1741) was murdered, in a dispute over an
                        inheritance, on board HMS <hi rend="ital">Ruby</hi>, at its moorings in the King Road, at the confluence of the rivers Avon
                        and Severn, outside Bristol, by his brother Samuel Goodere (1687&#8211;1741) and two sailors under his command. Samuel was executed
                        at the Hot Wells, near Bristol.</note> some fifty years ago. John the Painter.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        the Painter (1752&#8211;1777), also known as James Aitken or John Aitkin, was an arsonist who, sympathising with the American
                        colonists in their war with Britain, set fires in naval dockyards in Portsmouth and Bristol in 1776 and 1777. He was hung from
                        the mast of a ship with a reported 20,000 people witnessing the execution.</note> Pedleys escapes from <del>xxx</del>
                        newgate.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1780 Joseph George Pedley (dates unknown), faced with the
                        seizure of papers which would have revealed his fraudulent financial dealings, burnt down his own house in Bristol. Imprisoned
                        in the city&#8217;s jail &#8211; Newgate, so-called after the London prison of that name &#8211; Pedley escaped, on 1 April 1781, but was caught
                        in Newcastle.</note> The Lawfords gate witches.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to Eleanor Keate (dates
                        unknown), reports that a previous occupant haunted the house that she and her husband owned outside Lawfords Gate, Bristol,
                        rendered it unsaleable for three years. See Keate&#8217;s <title>The Unfortunate Wife</title> (Bristol, 1779), p. 5. Henry Durbin
                        reported the events which occurred at the Lamb Inn, near Lawfords Gate, Bristol, in 1761. The daughters of Giles, the inn&#8217;s
                        landlord, found &#8216;fairies&#8217;&#8211; a poltergeist &#8211; moving objects supernaturally in their bedroom. See <title>A Narrative of Some
                            Extraordinary Things that Happened to Mr Richard Giles&#8217;s Children</title> (Bristol, 1800), p. 11.</note> the
                        story<del>es</del> of the fairies at Mangotsfield.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poltergeist at the Lamb Inn,
                        communicating by a series of knocks in answer to investigators&#8217; questions, declared it had been summoned by a witch of
                        Mangotsfield, a nearby village. Giles&#8217;s death in an accident the following year was attributed to witchcraft.</note> George
                        Lukins,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Lukins (b. 1734) was, on Friday, 13 June 1778, exorcised by seven
                        clergymen, having, he believed, been possessed by demons who made him speak in voices not his own. The<title> Narrative of the
                            Extraordinary Case of George Lukins, of Yatton, Somersetshire, who was Possessed of Evil Spirits for 18 Years: Also, an
                            Account of his Remarkable Deliverance, in the Vestry-Room of Temple Church</title> (Bristol, 1788) was supervised by John
                        Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>). The Methodist interpretation that Lukins was possessed by evil spirits was contested
                        by John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), who viewed Lukins as an imposter, and his symptoms were attributed to
                        epilepsy and St Vitus&#8217; Dance in the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>, 58, part 2 (July, 1778), 609&#8211;610.</note> of whom
                    there should be a portrait if possible &#8722; &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; once look for such things &amp; enough will be found. &#8211; I can help you to
                    a bloody murder &amp; a Ghost both excellent ingredients. The Bristol papers which are probably filed at the printers would of
                    course preserve a<del>n</del> great number of interesting circumstances. For biography John Henderson<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Henderson (1757&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>), a Bristol child prodigy, who by the age of eight was teaching
                        at Kingswood school. Henderson was educated as a Methodist, and became a brilliant classical scholar at Oxford, where he
                        became interested in magic, alchemy and the occult. Returning to Bristol, he helped patients in his father&#8217;s establishment &#8211;
                        now changed from a school to an asylum &#8211; including, in 1788, Southey&#8217;s acquaintance the poet William Gilbert (1763&#8211;1825).
                        Henderson died young, without publishing the great works expected of him, his constitution destroyed by drink. Southey owned a
                        treatise by Henderson and quoted from it in his 1797 <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and
                            Portugal</title>. See letter 214 of this edition.</note> would come within your reach &#8722; &amp; there are some of our old
                    navigators who sailed from Bristol &#8211; for it was once an adventurous place. the establishment of the different sectaries there,
                    their growth &amp; present state. discipline of the Moravians.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Moravian congregation
                        in Bristol dates from 1746, the first British Moravian community having been established in London in 1740.</note> public
                    amusements when established. manufactories &lt;each&gt; when first introduced &#8211; &amp; in an Appendix a catalogue of all books
                    published at Bristol, which would be a very curious document of the progress of provincial literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Such a book would sell best in numbers or parts with plenty of prints, views of the city &amp; in the city of which
                    latter description many, &amp; very interesting ones might be found. in fact the best way of proceeding would be if such an artist
                    as Holmes<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Holmes (d. 1852), an Irish artist resident in Bristol from about 1802,
                        had published <title>Sketches of Some of the Southern Counties of Ireland, Collected during a Tour in 1797</title> in
                        1801.</note> would combine with you, he furnish the drawings &#8211; you the work. calculations of expence you can make better than
                    I can &#8211; the prints would cost from 8 to ten pounds each &#8722; &amp; the plates remain a more substantial property than copyright. I am
                    supposing them of octavo size in the manner of Brittons book.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Britton (1771&#8211;1857;
                            <title>DNB</title>), an antiquary who, with his friend Edward Wedlake Brayley (1773&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), produced a
                        series, county by county, of lavishly-illustrated accounts of the historical features of Britain, entitled <title>The Beauties
                            of England and Wales</title> (1801&#8211;1818).</note> &#8211; Now if such a scheme should hit your fancy I have said enough &#8722; &amp;
                    if it should not, it would be useless to say more. Only that I think you would do it exceedingly well &amp; that you would find
                    much amusement in collecting materials, as so much would be to be gathered by personal enquiries from old people. if you think of
                    it at all seriously I will hunt out all the corners of my memory for you. had my poor mother been alive she would have been a mine
                    of information.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Like a great jack ass I began this upon a sheet which had the beginning of another letter on the other side &#8211; so
                    you see it is pieced &amp; will still pass muster as a single sheet for single it is. How are you going on &amp; your family? what
                    are you about? the Psalms you must ere this have done with.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cottle&#8217;s revised edition of
                        his <title>New Version of the Psalms of David</title> was published in 1805.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Your
                        sisters? your mother? Robert?</ref> are they all going on well?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am hard at my Annual work of reviewing which is I trust more than half done.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of Travels into the Interior of Southern Africa, in the years 1797 and 1798,
                            including Observations on the Geology &amp; Geography, the Natural History ... and Sketches of the Various Tribes
                            Surrounding the Cape of Good Hope</title>, Vol. II (1804), 22&#8211;33; Robert Percival (1765&#8211;1826), <title>An Account of the
                            Cape of Good Hope</title> (1804), 34&#8211;41; Daniel Mackinnen (1767&#8211;1830), <title>A Tour Through the British West Indies, in
                            the years 1802 and 1803 giving a Particular Account of the Bahama Islands</title> (1804), 50&#8211;56; John Barrow,
                            <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short
                            Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804), 69&#8211;83;
                            <title>Sir John Froissart&#8217;s Chronicles of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign
                            of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans. Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804), 189&#8211;194;
                        George Heriot (1766&#8211;1844), <title>The History of Canada, From its First Discovery: Comprehending an Account of the Original
                            Establishment of the Colony of Louisiana</title>, 194&#8211;197; <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the
                            Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility
                            and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 225&#8211;231; Edward Ledwich (1738&#8211;1823),
                            <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398&#8211;413; <title>Original Correspondence of Jean Jacques Rousseau, with
                            Mad. La Tour de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title> (1804), 485&#8211;488; Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr.
                            Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804), 488&#8211;93; David Irving
                            (1778&#8211;1850),<title> The Lives of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary Dissertations on the Literary History of Scotland and
                            the Early Scotish Drama</title> (1804), 493&#8211;499; Walter Scott, <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of
                            Ercildoune</title> (1804), 555&#8211;563; Charles Abraham Elton (1778&#8211;1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804), 564&#8211;565; William Day
                        (dates unknown), <title>The Shepherd&#8217;s Boy: being Pastoral Tales</title> (1804), 567&#8211;568; E. Warren (dates unknown),
                            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Day, or, Imagination&#8217;s Ramble</title> (1804), 568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a Series of Prints,
                            Designed by her Royal Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with Poetical Illustrations
                            by T. P</title> [Thomas Park (1758/9&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>)] (1804), 568&#8211;580; Thomas Green Fessenden (1771&#8211;1837),
                            <title>Original Poems</title> (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777&#8211;1805), <title>The Powers of Genius</title> (1801), 571;
                        Thomas Clio Rickman (1761&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in Celebration of the Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint
                            Domingo, November 29, 1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield, <title>Good Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert
                        Spencer (1770&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of Sorrow</title> (1804), 574&#8211;575; <title>British Purity: or, the
                            World we Live in. A Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries&#8230;By Lory Lucian and Jerry Juvenal, &#8230; Assisted by S. Scriblerus,
                            etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804), 575; William Falconer (1732&#8211;1769), <title>The Shipwreck</title>, (1804), ed., James Stanier
                        Clarke (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), 577&#8211;580; William Tooke (1777&#8211;1863), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles
                            Churchill: with Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his Life</title>, (1804), 580&#8211;585; J. Amphlett (dates
                        unknown), <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title> (1804), 585; Joseph Jefferson (1766&#8211;1824), <title>Horae
                            Poetic&#230;. Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586&#8211;587; Alexander Campbell (1764&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804), 587&#8211;591; William Crowe (bap. 1745, d. 1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593&#8211;594; John Finlay (1782&#8211;1810), <title>Wallace, or, The Vale
                            of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594&#8211;596; Jessie Stewart (dates unknown), <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas
                            Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768&#8211;1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected with Literature. Imitated from
                            the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597&#8211;598; <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (1804),
                        621&#8211;634; Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language,
                            of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive Society</title> (1804), 634&#8211;644; [Anon.] <title>No
                            Slaves - No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour of the African Trade by a Liverpool
                            Merchant</title> (1804), 644&#8211;648; William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813), <title>Indian Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures
                            on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title> (1803), 658&#8211;670; John Gardiner (fl. 1758&#8211;1792),
                            <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670&#8211;674; Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the Fresco
                            Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918&#8211;923.</note> dull work which takes me from better things. My
                        history<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note>
                    has had a long stand &#8211; yet have I since we removed to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> written a quarto volume of
                    it. In another month I hope to return to it fresh &amp; hungry. What my plans are of settling, or how long we may remain where we
                    are it would not be easy to say or even guess. This dreadful pestilence in the South of Europe deranges all my plans.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Yellow fever was epidemic in Iberia in 1804, and killed an estimated 60% of Gibraltar&#8217;s
                        population.</note> I cannot go to Lisbon while it is in such danger, &amp; yet am unwilling to chuse an abiding place till I
                    have been there. even if it were conveniently in my power to chuse &amp; fix. I saw our letter in the Gentlemans Magazine,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, which explains the uses to which the income from the edition of Thomas
                        Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>) had been put; see Southey and Joseph Cottle to the editor of <title>Gentleman&#8217;s
                            Magazine</title>, 6 August 1804, Letter 974.</note> &#8722; &amp; suppose you saw the Review of the work in the Edinburgh which
                    was exceedingly civil.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The notice of the Chatterton edition appeared in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (April 1804), 214&#8211;230.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> past the summer with me &#8211; he is a very fine young man
                    &amp; has just been elected President of the Medical Society at Edinburgh, being the youngest President ever chosen. he is also
                    President of the Speculative Society there. From <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> it is long since I have heard so
                    that I look very anxiously for a letter. It was said in a provincial paper that he was killed, but on enquiry at the Admiralty it
                    appeared that it was one of the other Lieutenants.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate, had, on 14 August 1804, made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the
                        French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at
                        the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission, 65 were killed or wounded. Southey suspected that his brother
                        was among them because the first lieutenant had been reported as dead, but he was absent from the raid because he had been
                        placed under arrest. Charles Hayman (d. 1804) was made first lieutenant in his stead and died in the attack.</note> I have
                    been very uneasy about him, &amp; am not yet comfortable. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> will come to the
                    gallows. a <del>fate</del> thing which I have so long foreseen &amp; so made up my mind to, that I only wish it was over. I begged
                        <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> to caution you against him, as he goes about taking up money in my
                    name. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My little Edith</ref> is just inoculated with the Cow Pock.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">To provide inoculation from smallpox in the light of the publication of the experiments of Edward
                        Jenner (1749&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>) on vaccinating against smallpox using cowpox serum in <title>An Inquiry Into the Causes
                            and Effects of the Variol&#230; Vaccin&#230;</title> (1798).</note> she is a sweet child &#8211; but so prematurely quick that I do not in
                    my heart expect to rear her.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be remembered to you &amp; all your good
                        family &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you Cottle &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-12-16">Dec. 16. 1804. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>