<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1488</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2610</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 480&#8211;483.Dating note: Internal evidence as to the arrival of a letter from John Adamson (Letter 1487) suggests that this letter was begun on the evening of 6 August.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1488" type="letter">
        <head>1488. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-08-06">6&#8211;9 August
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/298<lb />Postmarks: [illegible]<lb />Seal: [illegible]<lb />MS: Keswick Museum<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 480&#8211;483.<lb />Dating note: Internal evidence as to the arrival of a letter from John Adamson (Letter 1487) suggests that this letter was begun on the evening of 6 August.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere&#8217;s</ref> translations are in the Printers hands, they form an appendix which will
                    soon be printed, &amp; in the course of three weeks I hope you will receive the volume.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Three of Frere&#8217;s translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle
                            of the Cid</title>. Frere had been Britain&#8217;s ambassador to Portugal while Southey&#8217;s uncle had lived there; from 1808&#8211;1809
                        he was ambassador to Spain.</note> A portion of MS. is now lying at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> to
                    be forwarded with it. You will perhaps think the affairs of the Plata &amp; Paraguay are given too much at length.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to the manuscript of the first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title>
                        (1810).</note> I was puzzled what to do about them, especially as when I began the Plata was the great object of public
                    curiosity. But the discovery of the country, &amp; whatever relates to its original inhabitants, will form a much more interesting
                    part of the book than its mere civil history which is meagre, &amp; barren of all beauty. Of Paraguay there will be very little
                    more to say, except when the Jesuits appear, for after Yralas<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domingo Mart&#237;nez de Irala
                        (c. 1509-c. 1556), a Spanish conquistador who explored the Paran&#225; and Paraguay Rivers and later became governor of
                        Paraguay.</note> expedition to Peru, the Spaniards then turned their attention towards Tucuman, &amp; we have nothing to do on
                    that side of the Plata, &#8211; whereas the course of the Paraguay approaches so near to Mato grosso, that every &lt;step of&gt;
                    discovery in that neighbourhood becomes curious, &amp; to the purpose. The history of H Stadt<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hans Staden (c. 1525-c. 1579) was a German adventurer shipwrecked off South America and captured by the
                        Tupinamb&#225; people of Brazil. In his <title>True History</title>, first published in German and then, in Latin in the collection
                        of voyages edited by Johan Theodor and Johann Israel De Bry, <title>Peregrinationes</title> (1598&#8211;1613) (where Southey found
                        it), he claimed to have witnessed cannibal feasts.</note> seemed to me to paint so much of savage manners, &amp; to show so
                    much of the state of the Port. &amp; French in those parts, that more would be gained than lost by making him the hero of the
                    chapter. It is easily struck out if you think otherwise, &amp; the essential parts arranged in another place. The chapter which
                    immediately follows will compleat all that is to be said of this first race of savages, for the Aymures<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Aymures or Guaymures were reputed by Portuguese writers to be fierce savages who ate their own children.
                        Southey discusses them in chapter 8 of the first volume of his <title>History</title>.</note> who were a far more terrible
                    people did not come from the interior till a later period, &amp; the Tapuyas will be spoken of in connection with the French.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This tribe of Indians is discussed in chapter 13 of the first volume of his
                            <title>History</title>.</note> The Relaco&#275;s Annuaes<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit Relations of their
                        missions in South America, published annually from 1632 in Latin, French and Italian.</note> have a great deal of curious
                    matter about the former, &amp; about the latter Maurice supplied Joz Laet with much information which he inserted in <del>xx</del>
                    editing Maragraves posthumous papers.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Georg Marcgrave/Georg Marggraf (1610&#8211;1648). Born in
                        Saxony, Marggraf went to Brazil in 1638 in the expedition of the Dutch led by John Maurice/Johan Maurits of Nassau
                        (1604&#8211;1679). Marggraf&#8217;s papers on natural history were published, after his death, with editorial input from Joannes de Laet
                        (1581&#8211;1649) as part of the work of the expedition&#8217;s physician Willem Piso/Willem Pies (1611&#8211;1678) in the <title>Historia
                            Naturalium Brasiliae</title> (1648).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now about Texeira&#8217;s voyage.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Teixeira (d. 1641) was a Portuguese
                        explorer who became, in 1637, the first European to travel up the entire length of the Amazon, an expedition which helped
                        extend Portuguese colonial possessions there at the expense of Spain.</note> The story of the suppression of Acun&#257;s book<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;1676?), a member of Texeira&#8217;s expedition, published <title>Nuevo
                            descubrimiento del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title> (1641), translated into French as <title>Relation de la Riviere des
                            Amazones. Avec un dissertation sur la riviere des Amazones pour servir de Preface</title> (1682). The translator, Marin le
                        Roy de Gomberville (1600&#8211;1674), claimed that King Philip IV of Spain (1605&#8211;1665), to whom Acu&#241;a presented the work, wanted it
                        suppressed because its geographic information might aid the recently-independent Portuguese in taking the Amazon basin as
                        their colony. The English translation was <title>Voyages and Discoveries in South America</title> (1698).</note> comes from
                    Gomberville, the Frenchman who translated it. I do not give any credit to it. Manuel Rodriguez says the book was become scarce
                    because few copies were printed, &#8211; a sufficient reason. The information obtained by that voyage was of most consequence at Para,
                    &amp; it was of no consequence there whether the book was suppressed or not, while any of Texeiras party were alive or any of
                    their papers preserved. As this is an authentic &lt;account&gt; of the Great River, &amp; not like Orellanas half-fable,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Orellana (1511&#8211;1546) died during a disastrous expedition, on which only 44 of
                        300 men survived, navigating the Amazon. His exploits were described in Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de Oviedo (1478&#8211;1557),
                            <title>Historia general y natural de las Indias</title> (1542).</note> it will be proper to weave into it whatever
                    additional circumstances can be found, &#8211; except such as relate to <del>xxx</del> a later period. Condamine<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Marie de La Condamine (1701&#8211;1774), a French mathematician involved in an expedition to
                        South America who, in 1543, completed a four month raft journey down the Amazon. He published a narrative of the expedition:
                            <title>Journal du voyage fait par ordre du roi a l&#8217;&#233;quateur</title> (1751).</note> supplies something, &amp; your Diaries
                    of Fr. Xavier Ribeiro<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Xavier Ribeiro Sampaio (1741&#8211;1812?), colonial official,
                        wrote a manuscript <title>Di&#225;rio da uma Viagem que em visita e correci&#231;&#225;o das povoa&#231;&#243;es da Capitania de S&#227;o Jos&#233; do Rio Negro
                            fez o Ouvidor</title> (1775).</note> more. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A letter has reached me this evening from <ref target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">John Adamson</ref> of Gateshead,
                    Durham, asking me if I can give him any account of Nicola Luiz,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author remains
                        obscure to literary historians: he has been identified as Nicolau Luis da Silva (1723&#8211;1787), author of chapbook
                        comedies.</note> whose tragedy of In&#275;z de Castro he bought at Lisbon, &amp; has lately translated.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Adamson was the translator of <title>Donna Ignez de Castro, a Tragedy, from the Portuguese of Nicola Luiz,
                            with Remarks on the History of that Unfortunate Lady</title> (1808).</note> I can find this name nowhere except in
                        Murphy<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Cavanah Murphy (1760&#8211;1814), <title>Travels in Portugal; Through the
                            Provinces of Entre Douro e Minho, Beira, Entremadura, and Alem-Tejo, in the Years 1789 and 1790. Consisting of
                            Observations on the Manners, ... Trade, Public Buildings, Arts, Antiquities &amp;c. of that Kingdom</title> (1795). In
                        this work Murphy credits Nicola Luiz as the only author of a Portuguese tragedy on the story of In&#234;s Peres de Castro
                        (1325&#8211;1355), the murdered lover of Prince Pedro (1320&#8211;1367), who, when he became king of Portugal in 1357, was declared to
                        have been his wife and crowned queen as a corpse.</note> who calls him the P. Plautus.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning the &#8216;Portugueze Plautus&#8217;, an allusion to the Roman playwright, Titus Maccius Plautus (c. 254 BC&#8211;184 BC).</note>
                    Where he learnt this I cannot by any means discover, &#8211; &amp; am half inclined to suppose that Antonio Ferreiras<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Ferreira (1528&#8211;1569), <title>In&#234;s de Castro</title> (c. 1557).</note> play may have been
                    published under this fictitious name, &#8211; for if it were a real name it would surely be found either in Nic. Antonio, the Mappa de
                    Portugal or the Academys Catalogue.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Adamson, 6 August 1808, Letter
                        1487. Southey refers to Nicol&#225;s Antonio (1617&#8211;1684), <title>Bibliotheca Hispana Vetus</title> (1696); Jo&#227;o Baptista de Castro
                        (1700&#8211;1785), <title>Mappa de Portugal</title> (1745).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> H.K Whites Remains<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title> (1807), which were edited by Southey.</note> were to be sent
                    you with the large paper poems &amp; Anthology. <note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The new 1808 edition of Southey&#8217;s 1797
                            <title>Poems</title> and the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800).</note> The second edition of this book has sold
                    off in two months, &amp; a third is &lt;now&gt; printing as fast as two presses can supply it. What a strange beast is the Public!
                    This poor boy published a little volume of poems, <del>xx</del> nobody bought them, &amp; he might have drudged away the rest of
                    his life in an Attorneys Office if Simeon &amp; Wilberforce had not given him 30 &#163; a year,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Simeon (1759&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>) and William Wilberforce (1759&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>) had been recorded in
                            <title>Remains</title> as having contributed &#163;20 and &#163;30 per annum respectively to <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Kirke White&#8217;s</ref> education.</note> because he was running mad with
                    Calvinism. He works &amp; prays himself fairly to death, &#8211; &amp; now all the world are crying out what a prodigy, &#8211; tho they had
                    neither eyes to see, nor understandings to comprehend, nor hearts to acknowledge this while it could do him any good! &#8211; They serve
                    geniuses just as they do venison, &#8211; hunt it down while it is living, &amp; then offer it up with all due honour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Three of your MSS here would make a good &amp; saleable volume as Travels in the heart of S America &#8211; the voyage in
                    the Madeira &#8211; the Rio Negro &#8211; &amp; to the Lago de Xarayes.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey came to own these
                        manuscripts himself: the sale catalogue of his library lists as no. 3849 &#8216;Miscellaneous: &#8211; Voyage up the Madeira in 1749, <hi rend="ital">with a MS. map &#8211;</hi> Relaciaon da Guerre e Successos de Mato Grosso desde 1759 ate 1764 &#8211; Noticias do Lago
                        Xarayes &#8211; Memoria de Observa&#231;oens Physico Economicas acerca da Extraccaon do Oiro das Minas do Brazil, por Man. Ferreira da
                        Camara; in 1 vol. half bound calf , 4to&#8217;. No. 3859 was a copy of Francisco Xavier Ribeiro Sampaio&#8217;s <title>Di&#225;rio da uma
                            Viagem que em visita e correci&#231;&#225;o das povoa&#231;&#243;es da Capitania de S&#227;o Jos&#233; do Rio Negro fez o Ouvidor</title> (1775).</note>
                    They supply great materials for improving the map. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> I think might
                    translate them, &amp; get a good sum for so doing; with a map to each voyage which you could enable Arrowsmith<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of Soho Square, London, renowned
                        for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map Exhibiting All the New
                            Discoveries in the Interior Parts of North America</title> (1795 rev. 1801, 1802, 1804), <title>Chart of the South
                            Pacific</title> (1798), <title>A New Map of Africa</title> (1802).</note> to make, such a quarto volume as this, at this
                    time might be sold for 150 &#8211; or 200 pounds &#8211; &amp; it would in no way forestall my work, or prevent the use which I make of these
                    materials.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hervas says strange things of the language of the Araucans, as being more artificially constructed than any other,
                    &amp; yet bearing greater marks of being a primitive tongue.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lorenzo Herv&#225;s y Panduro
                        (1735&#8211;1809), <title>Catalogo de las Lenguas de las Naciones Conocidas</title> (1800&#8211;1805). The Araucans were the Indian
                        nations that dominated what is now the central part of Chile. They fought successfully against conquest by the Spanish in the
                        sixteenth century and against subjugation within independent Chile for much of the nineteenth century. Southey praised them in
                        his &#8216;Song of the Araucans During a Thunder Storm&#8217;, published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 1799. See <title>Robert
                            Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, <title>Selected Shorter
                            Poems</title>, ed. Lynda Pratt, pp. 372&#8211;374.</note> I should like to see Falkners<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the
                            adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note> grammar, for if one half of what Hervas affirms may be believed
                    the history of this language is as inexplicable as that of the Greek: In Chiloe a new language has grown up of which the words are
                    all Spanish, &amp; the <del>grammar</del> syntax Araucan. The Guarani &amp; Tupi<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Indian
                        tribes of the Amazon in Paraguay and Brazil.</note> grammars would be of very great service if it were possible to procure
                    them. The languages of N America seem to be far more barbarous, than the Southern ones. the polyglot grammar &amp; vocabulary
                    which Hervas promises would afford materials for thoroughly investigating the history of languages, if they should ever be
                    executed, however imperfect the execution in many instances must needs be: but I dare say his work will never be compleated &#8211;
                    Spain has a long war upon her hands, &amp; literature &amp; every thing else must be at a stand till that is terminated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a change in the Annual Review. <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> is deposed &amp;
                    Thomas Rees<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">Thomas Rees</ref>, Unitarian minister and writer on theological history, brother of <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Owen Rees</ref>, partner with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>,
                        publisher of the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> (the brother, whom you saw at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>) reigneth in his stead: a fitter man, for <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthurs</ref> mineralogy &amp;
                    botany which he understands thoroughly, were of little use in such a department, &amp; he wanted method &amp; every thing else &#8211; I
                    have told <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> to send me nothing except books of travels, &amp; those I shall take for
                    the sake of reading them. &#8211; I have begun to put together my own memoranda made in Portugal; &#8211; with your corrections &amp;
                    amendments they will make a good book. I should like to append to it a brief history of the Factory;<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British factory in Lisbon, where British merchants carried on their businesses.</note> this would be
                    interesting to all persons who have been connected with it. When the papers have grown to bulk sufficient for a parcel they shall
                    travel to you, &#8211; if we should not meet before that time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have lost time in assisting the Portugueze, &amp; Wellesley<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arthur
                        Wellesley, later to become Field Marshall and 1st Duke of Wellington (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), sailed in July with an
                        expeditionary force to Portugal. He would spend the next six years fighting Napoleon&#8217;s armies in Iberia.</note> will be in
                    more danger than Junot.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Andoche Junot, 1st Duc d&#8217;Abrant&#232;s (1771&#8211;1813), the French
                        general in command of the invasion of Portugal in 1807. Junot was made Governor of Portugal after taking Lisbon at the end of
                        1807.</note> Yet I think the P. will fight well <del>fight well</del> in English company &#8211; &amp; it is not impossible that a
                    second battle may be won in the neighbourhood of Aljubarrota,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of Aljubarrota
                        (1385), fought between Portugal and Castile, and resulting in a decisive victory for the Portuguese.</note> not less glorious
                    than the first.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-08-09">Aug. 9. 1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>