<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1482</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2604</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1482" type="letter">
        <head>1482. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-07-19">19
                    July 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Durham./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-07-19">Wednesday. July 19. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It seems to me that the eventual removal of <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> from
                    Norwich takes away the main reason for preferring it to any other place, &#8211; &amp; that the competition of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Reeve,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Reeve (1780&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), physician and traveller, who
                        after a European tour on which he met many leading men of science, settled in Norwich, marrying in 1807 Susan Taylor
                        (1788&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>) of whom Henry had been enamoured.</note> married into the very connection by which you would
                    have been supported, would take away a main part of the practise to be scrambled for. The nearer distance between London &amp;
                    Norwich, is I think less desirable than the easy journey from <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> to Newcastle &#8211;
                    especially as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has set his heart upon setting up here, if ever he be enabled to
                    settle any where. In point of country you are better off than in Norfolk, &#8211; in point of expence better, in point of climate not
                    worse. And it is pleasant that you are able to ride here in two days when your patients can spare you, &#8211; &amp; that I can walk to
                    you in three, when I can spare time, &amp; muster up resolution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Peacheys</ref> are not coming this year. This has been long determined
                    on. They have taken Combe Flory,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A village in Somerset, Emma Peachey&#8217;s native county,
                        of which her maternal grandfather was rector.</note> &amp; <del>xxx</del> &lt;<ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P.</ref>&gt; is said to be pretty well. The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperial</ref> took a hyper-imperial freak into his head some months ago; &#8211; he thought Europe could not be delivered without his
                    exertions, &amp; negociated an exchange into some regiment on service. Just when every thing was concluded, some difficulties were
                    started at the War-Office, which broke off the business, &amp; he remains therefore in inglorious inactivity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For one day I should <del>be</del> hardly be glad to see you. Make it something longer, &amp; <del>come</del> the
                    sooner <del>come</del> you come the better: the old boat is in good order, the old stones at the marooning-point in the same
                    place, &#8211; &amp; we will make the most of the time you can spare.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey</ref>  it is plain that
                    we must disinherit him for an undutiful Uncle. There must be something very like craziness both in that man &amp; his <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">elder brother</ref>, or they never would have acted so unreasonably &#8211; It is
                    well the breed is mended</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Cid<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        (1808).</note> will be published in three or four weeks, &#8211; &amp; you will find it a book after your own heart. I have begun to
                    put in order my Travels in Portugal, which the books I have around me, &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref>  corrections &amp; additions will enable me to render very compleat.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not produce this projected book; but his 1797 <title>Letters written during a Short Residence
                            in Spain and Portugal</title> were reprinted in an expanded form in 1808 as <title>Letters written during a Journey in
                            Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> The first portion of &#8216;Brazil<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> published in three volumes from 1810&#8211;1819.</note> &#8216;is just
                    going off to him for his revision. Heaven knows when the price of paper will fall, &#8211; a few weeks ago there appeared no possibility
                    of such a change, &#8211; at present the political prospect is very different. I am confident the Spaniards will succeed in their
                    struggle, &#8211; &amp; it is likely that the North of Europe will make some effort to deliver itself, whenever the French armies are
                    employed elsewhere; &#8211; then the ports of the continent will be open &#8211; rags will come over once more, &amp; my book go to press.
                    Heaven help us that such an earthquake should be necessary for the birth of a mouse!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Annual has not yet reached me, &#8211; there is a parcel on the way, in which it ought to be contained. You will see
                    in it what I said of Spain twelvemonths ago,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey&#8217;s review of Robert Semple
                        (1777&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Observations on a Journey through Spain and Italy to Naples; and thence to Smyrna and
                            Constantinople</title> (1807), in the <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 118&#8211;130.</note> &#8211; &amp; I shall
                    look with some curiosity for your articles. Those in the Medical Review<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>London Medical Record</title>, to which Henry Southey was contributing articles.</note> please me well &amp;
                    promise well, &amp; this reminds me of one of the <del>medical</del> things which you may or may not know, <del>but</del> which it
                    is not amiss to mention upon the chance. A practitioner somewhere in the middle of England has started a new theory respecting
                    small-pox: that the cold treatment by not suffering the disease to exhaust itself in eruption, leaves behind a leaven in the
                    system, &#8211; which is the cause of the increased ravages of consumption. &#8211; You will disbelieve this as I do, &#8211; but such things may
                    serve <del>for reference in</del> to be referred to in some of your reviewals &#8211; Some physician or surgeon at Birmingham gives
                    great relief in inveterate asthmas, by having the chest rubbed with spirits every morning &#8211; In the last Vol. of the Asiatic
                    Researches is a paper upon &#8216;the Remarkable Effects of Sol-Lunar influence upon the Fevers of India&#8217;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Balfour, &#8216;Observations Respecting the Remarkable Effects of Sol-Lunar Influence in the Fevers of
                        India: with the Scheme of an Astronomical Ephemeris for the Purposes of Medicine and Meteorology&#8217;, <title>Asiatick
                            Researches</title>, 8 (1808), 1&#8211;34.</note> &#8211; in which an unaccountable correspondence with the Tides is asserted; &#8211; a
                    strong testimony in favour of this opinion is to be found in Piso&#8217;s treatise de Medicin&#226; Brasiliensi. P. 13.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Willem Piso (in Dutch Willem Pies, in Latin Guilielmus Piso, in Portuguese Guilherme Piso)
                        (1611&#8211;1678), a Dutch physician and author of <title>Historia Naturalis Brasili&#230;</title> (1648), in which the Dissertation on
                        the Medicine of Brazil forms the first section.</note> Should you have occasion for it I will transcribe the passage. The
                    connection seems imaginary, &amp; the paper is by no means satisfactory, yet unless <del>the</del> it had been thought so in
                    India, it would not have been inserted in such a work. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You had better trouble <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref> with a line. &#8211; We are going on
                    well, &#8211; except that I have one of my obstinate colds, now almost a month old, &#8211; &amp; every return of hot-weather as usual
                    freshens it. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> have
                    just been vaccinated &#8211; the former was very ill in a bilious fever about five weeks ago; &#8211; the disease went thro the place, &#8211;
                    scarcely any children escaped it. Rhodes lost his eldest &amp; this was the only death, &#8211; but it went very hard with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> &amp; reduced him very much.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211; a kiss from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>
                    , &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> desires to be gratefully
                    remembered, I having taken care to remind her that you saved her life three times.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>