<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1531</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2653</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 488&#8211;490.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1531" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1531" type="letter">
        <head>1531. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-11-10">10 November
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye./
                        Hereford/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 488&#8211;490.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Few circumstances have ever given me so much pleasure, as the tidings contained in your letter.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s uncle had recently married <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">Catherine</ref>,
                        daughter of Loveless Bigg-Wither (1741&#8211;1813), a Hampshire landowner.</note> The only thing which made me feel not perfectly
                    happy in my present abode, was the thought that you were living alone in a country parsonage, &amp; that thought frequently came
                    across me. I had heard some six or eight weeks ago a rumour to this effect, from <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel
                        Peachy</ref>, &lt;but there are so many Hills in the world that I rather wished than believed it likely to be you when he
                    spoke&gt; &#8211; whether he was right in the name I cannot recollect, <del>for</del> &amp; the last fragment of his epistle served for
                    shaving paper this morning, &#8211; if he was, he had seen my <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">new relation</ref>, who must be
                    some how connected with the family of a Major Audrey,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844) married, in
                        1795, Catherine&#8217;s sister, Jane Bigg (1770&#8211;1846).</note> once the Colonels Guest in his Island here.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Peachy and his family spent their summers on Derwent Isle, near the Keswick shore of Derwentwater.</note> The
                    blood of old George Wither<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Wither (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, a
                        favourite of Southey&#8217;s.</note> is good blood, &#8211; &amp; none of his own family can think of him with more love &amp; respect
                    than I do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thought I had told you that my latter peregrinations in Portugal, &amp; the knowledge which my books have
                    supplied me with concerning that country would form matter for a seperate work, &#8211; which will be sent you before it goes to the
                    press, for additions &amp; corrections, &amp; which bids fair to be a curious work.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey did not publish a new book of this description but a new edition of <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in
                            Spain and Portugal</title> did appear in 1808.</note> Your letters of the Catholick Priests are here, but I do not
                    remember that they contained any thing which could be brought to bear in D Luisas life.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                            <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, I, pp. 259&#8211;302, Southey included a<title>
                            Life of Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title>, taken from <title>Vida y Virtudes de la Venerable Virgen Do&#241;a Luisa de
                            Carvajal y Mendoza, su Jornada a Inglaterra y Sucessos&#8217; en aquel Reyno. Por el Licenciado Luis Mu&#241;oz</title>
                        (1632).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will never be convinced that Cumberland is a more civilized country than Herefordshire, till you have seen it.
                    I have now better hopes of persuading you to visit us in the summer, for if <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill</ref> has seen the Lakes she cannot but wish to see them again, &amp; if she has not,
                        <del>xx</del> she must know that every body is expected to see them in these times. All summer &amp; autumn long they come to
                    us in thicker flocks than the wild-fowl who migrate here in winter, &amp; we have more high ton <del>xx</del> in one week at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> than Staunton sees in seven years.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Staunton
                        is a small village over ten miles from the nearest rural town, Hereford.</note> Here is a great deal which you would delight
                    in seeing, &amp; I am one of the best guides in the country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not likely that I shall visit the South before 1810, &amp; it is likely that then <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, perhaps both Ediths <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, Southey&#8217;s wife, and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                            May</ref>, his daughter.</note> will accompany me. <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref>
                    wishes to see her, &amp; she wishes to see M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne, who is young <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref> godmother. We have also halting places at Liverpool, Lichfield &amp; Birmingham. So that I think of travelling
                    like Queen Elizabeth in her progresses, &amp; being feasted all the way. &#8211; Curwen<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), Whig MP for Carlisle, Workington landowner.</note> has been pressing me to
                    visit him at Workington Hall, where I shall probably go with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> sometime
                    before Xmas, &amp; sometime after it I think of making a pilgrimage to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cuthberts shrine at Durham,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The shrine of St Cuthbert (c. 634&#8211;687) in Durham Cathedral.</note> &amp; passing a week
                    with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We expect <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> to be our Guest, either on his way to London or
                    on his return. He has seceded from the Edinburgh Review, alledging their cowardly politicks as the reason of his secession. This
                    was probably first occasioned by the manner in which I refused to bear a part in it, for that among other <del>xxxx</del> causes,
                    &amp; perhaps a little by the critique on Marmion.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s poem <title>Marmion</title>
                        (1808) was negatively reviewed by <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 12 (April 1808), 1&#8211;13.</note> I have learnt this evening that another Review<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> of the same form &amp; character (saving its rascality) is projected,
                    with the view of counteracting these base politicks which could make us betray Spain &amp; Portugal, &amp; lay us at the feet of
                    Bonaparte. My information is confidential &amp; official, <del>xx xxx xxxx</del> some of the men in power are setting this on foot
                    &#8211; <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is to be the Editor, &amp; he applies to me to bear a part in it. My
                        reply<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 9 November 1808 (Letter
                        1530) and 11 November 1808 (Letter 1532).</note> states the principles upon which I am ready to <del>consider</del> do this,
                    which upon the two main points of no peace, &amp; no Catholick emancipation sufficiently coincide with theirs for minor
                    differences to pass unnoticed. I offer to begin with an article upon the Hindoo question, concerning the Missionaries.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> The pay is to be the Edinburgh price, not less than
                    ten guineas per sheet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By a provoking blunder <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> omitted to send the MS. in his last
                    parcel. Will you let me have the account of the falls of the Parana to insert before it goes to the printer.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Material wanted for the first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am truly glad at this change in your way of life, &#8211; it has relieved me from the only thought that ever lay heavy
                    upon my heart. The morning &amp; the noon may well be past in solitariness, but, for the latter part of the day it is an evil
                    &amp; a sore evil to be alone. And in your case the single objection, which is sometimes a valid one, does not hold good, for
                    having been torn up by the roots from the <del>xxxxx in</del> society in which all your habits had grown, you had necessarily new
                    ones to acquire. God grant you health &amp; long life, &#8211; this is wishing <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill</ref> happiness. I am too old to be thought of &lt;hereafter&gt; as cousin Robert, &#8211; but not too young for
                    her to consider me &lt;as something in the light of&gt; <del>xxx xx</del> your brother</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you both.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-10">Nov. 10. 1808. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>