<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1082.1</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2204.1</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS has not
                        survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 20.2 (September 1805), 100 [from where the text is
                        taken]Dating note: Dated from the reference in Southey to John Rickman, [mid-July 1805], Letter 1082.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1082.1" type="letter">
        <head>Letter 1082.1. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Editor of the Monthly Magazine</ref>, [<date when="1805-07-15">mid-July 1805</date>] <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not
                        survived<lb />Previously published: <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 20.2 (September 1805), 100 [from where the text is
                        taken]<lb />Dating note: Dated from the reference in Southey to John Rickman, [mid-July 1805], Letter 1082.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent1">SIR,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>I HAVE asserted that Vasco Lobeira <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vasco de Lobeira (d. 1403), a Portuguese author.</note>
                    is the author of &#8216;Amadis of Gaul&#8217;. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Preface to his translation, <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title> (1803).</note> &#8211; As this is a curious point of literary history, and some of the Reviews have contradicted
                    the assertion, <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott had done so in his reviews in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1803</title>, 2 (1804), 600&#8211;603, and the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, October (1803), 109&#8211;136.</note> allow me as
                    briefly as possible to state the proofs by which it is supported.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">1. The Portuguese have always ascribed the romance to this author.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">2. It was evidently written when the Court of Windsor <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1386 the Treaty of
                        Windsor united the English and Portuguese courts via the marriage of King Joam I of Portugal (1358&#8211;1433) with Philippa of
                        Lancaster (1359&#8211;1415).</note> was the most splendid of the Courts of Christendom; therefore it is not older than the time of
                    Lobeira.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">3. The names Oriana, Lisuarte, Grimanesa, and Briolania, are Portugueze.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">4. The Spanish version, the oldest which is known to be extant, refers to a Portugueze original, and says, that an
                    Infanta of Portugal had objected to a certain part of the story. There exists a sonnet, in old Portugueze, attributed to a
                    Portugueze Infante, addressed to Vasco Lobeira, as author of &#8216;Amadis,&#8217; and objecting to this very part. <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had discussed the uncertain location of this sonnet in the Preface to <title>Amadis</title>, 4 vols.
                        (London, 1803), I, p. ix: &#8216;In the reign of Joam I. says Manuel de Faria y Sousa, &#8220;the Infante Don Pedro wrote the Sonnets
                            <title>Bom Vasco &amp;c. Vinha Amor &amp;c.</title> in praise of Vasco Lobeyra, the inventor of the Books of Chivalry by
                        that of Amadis.&#8221; I know not where the second of these Sonnets is to be found, neither of them are among the Infante Dom
                        Pedro&#8217;s Poems published by Joseph Scares da Sylva at the end of his <title>Memorias para a Historia del Rey Dom Joam
                        1</title>. as copied from the Cancioneiro of Resende; nor do I recollect them in that very rare and valuable Collection, to
                        which I cannot now refer.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">5. Gomes Eannes de Zurara, librarian to the King of Portugal, and keeper of the archives, in a chronicle written
                    1463, sixty years after Lobeira&#8217;s death, has this decisive passage: &#8212; &#8216;Many authors, being desirous to lengthen their works, fill
                    up their books by relating how princes passed their time in banquettings and games and revels, from which nothing followed except
                    their own diversion; as in the ancient feats of England, which is called Great Britain, and in the book of &#8220;Amadis,&#8221; though that
                    was made wholly at the pleasure of a man called Vasco Lobeira, in the time of King D. Fernando, all the things in the said book
                    being feigned by the author.&#8217; <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Gomes Eanes de Zurara (c. 1410&#8211;1474),
                            <title>Chronica del Rei D. Joam I de Boa Mem&#243;ria. Terceira Parte em que se Cont&#233;m a Tomada de Ceuta</title> (Lisbon,
                        1644).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">In reply to these arguments and this testimony, it is said that D&#8217;Herberay and Tressan speak of certain originals in
                    the Picard language. Neither of these authors speak decisively. The one says, &#8216;he remembered such manuscripts which he <hi rend="ital">thought</hi> might be the originals;&#8217; the other, that &#8216;he <hi rend="ital">thought</hi> he had seen such among
                    Queen Christina&#8217;s collection in the Vatican.&#8217; <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey rehearses the discussion he
                        had published in the Preface to his translation of <title>Amadis</title> (4 vols. (London, 1803), I, pp. 3&#8211;4. He refers to
                        Nicolas de Herberay des Essarts (d. ca. 1557), a Picardy-born translator of<title> Amadis</title> into French (1540&#8211;1548);
                        Louis-&#201;lisabeth de la Vergne de Tressan (1705&#8211;1783), also a translator of <title>Amadis</title> into French (1779). Both
                        French translators claimed an earlier, Picard original for the romance. The possible location of the manuscript was in the
                        collection in the Vatican archives assembled by Christina (1626&#8211;1689), Queen regnant of Sweden from 1633 to 1654, who
                        converted to Catholicism, abdicated and lived in Rome.</note> These authorities are of little weight. Such manuscripts,
                    however, may probably have existed, and are easily accounted for. The daughter of Joam I. who knighted Vasco Lobeira, married
                    Philip the Good of Burgundy. <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isabella of Portugal (139 7&#8211;1471), daughter of King Joam I
                        of Portugal (1358&#8211;1433), married, in 1429, Philip the Good, also Philip III, Duke of Burgundy (1396&#8211;1467).</note> What more
                    probable than that this Infanta (for all the family were learned and were patrons of learning) should have taken to her husband&#8217;s
                    court the romance which was the delight of her father&#8217;s, and that it should have been translated to please her? The Picard
                    version, therefore, if it could be produced, would not invalidate Lobeira&#8217;s claim.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">On these grounds I shall think myself justified in asserting, in the literary History of Portugal, that Vasco
                    Lobeira is the author of &#8216;Amadis of Gaul,&#8217; the most celebrated of the prose romances, and the best.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have thus defended my opinion, because, unless I mistake, one of the Reviews in question was written by a
                    gentleman for whose talents I have the highest respect, whose knowledge of chivalrous literature exceeds mine, and with whom I
                    would not venture to break a spear any where except on my own ground. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>; see note 3.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>