<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.886</idno><idno type="nines">rce2008</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 49.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 250–252 [in
                    part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="886" type="letter"><head>886. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-01-20">20 January
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS/ Jan. 20./ 1804<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 49<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 250–252 [in
                    part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1804-01-20">Friday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 20. 1804.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is curious enough that I should form a juster opinion of the Polynesians than <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capt Burney</ref> who has been among them<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed James Burney’s <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated
                            with Charts</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 3–12.</note> – but so it is – the
                    Friendly Islanders are no friends of mine &amp; if he will look at the Missionary Transactions<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had read about the first mission to the Pacific islands in the course of reviewing <title>Transactions
                            of the Missionary Society</title> (1803) for the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 189–201.</note> they
                    will lose his good word, for he will see that at Tongataboo<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tonga, chief island of the
                        archipelago, named, after the welcome accorded to Captain James Cook (1728–1779; <title>DNB</title>) in 1773, the Friendly
                        Isles.</note> they are not only cannibals but have an ugly trick of cutting up people alive to eat them. I well remember his
                    mention of the sacred language &amp; of the words which he took down from Omai’s mouth.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Burney had made a glossary of Polynesian words that he had collected from the Pacific Island traveller Mai (Omai)
                        (c.1751–1780). Burney was a lieutenant on the ship that brought Mai to Britain in 1774, and in 1776 he accompanied Mai on his
                        return journey.</note> he should by all means show them to Wilkins<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles Wilkins
                        (bap. 1749–1836; <title>DNB</title>): linguist whose grammar and translations of Sanskrit pioneered study of the language in
                        Europe.</note> – whom I take to be a man of more true worth than Sir W Jones.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir
                        William Jones (1746–1794; <title>DNB</title>): orientalist and friend of Wilkins, whose studies of Persian and Sanskrit led
                        him to suggest that European languages descended from India.</note> it is also the case in the Friendly Islands as Sir Harry
                        Englefield<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Charles Englefield, 7th Baronet (c.1752–1822; <title>DNB</title>):
                        antiquary and man of science.</note> told me on Vancouvers<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Vancouver
                        (1757–1798; <title>DNB</title>): a midshipman on Captain Cook’s third voyage of discovery that returned Mai to Tahiti. In
                        1791–1795, Vancouver commanded an expedition to survey America’s northwest coast, wintering at Hawaii.</note> authority, for
                    Vancouver designed a second work upon the manners &amp;c of their people.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> This work never
                        appeared. Vancouver’s untimely death prevented his finishing even his first narrative, <title>A Voyage of Discovery to the
                            North Pacific Ocean and Round the World, 1791–1795</title> (1798), which was completed by his brother, John Vancouver
                        (bap. 1756–1829).</note> – I have met Haslam.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Haslam (bap. 1764–1844;
                            <title>DNB</title>): resident apothecary at Bethlem Hospital (‘Bedlam madhouse’), London, who published
                            <title>Illustrations of Madness: Exhibiting a Singular Case of Insanity, and a No Less Remarkable Difference in Medical
                            Opinions</title> (1810).</note> he is too <hi rend="ital">material</hi> a moralist &amp; metaphysician like all surgeons
                    for that practise does harden the heart &amp; deaden the feelings. but he has a strong head. he told me that most Bedlamites were
                    Methodists, &amp; made mad by Methodism, a fact on which I have laid some stress in an article for the next Annual – the best by
                    far that I have ever written – upon the History of Methodism.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William
                        Myles (1756–1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People called Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists
                            of the Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 201–213.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Last week I was two days at Sir Wilfred Lawsons,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wilfrid Lawson, 10th
                        Baronet of Isell, Cumberland (c. 1764–1806).</note> &amp; there laying hold of Astleys Collection of Voyages<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A New General Collection of Voyages and Travels</title> (1745–1747) was published by Thomas Astley (fl.
                        1728–1737).</note> detected Alcaforado &amp; found all my suspicions confirmed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Alcoforado, <title>An Historical Relation of the First Discovery of the Isle of Madeira. Written Originally in
                            Portugueze. Translated into French, and Now Made English</title> (1675).</note> Green (the compiler)<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Green (d. 1757) compiled the voyage narratives for Astley’s work.</note> suspected the
                    authenticity, but was not enough versed in Portugueze literature to ascertain it – but luckily the original is in your keeping,
                    &amp; I will beg you to send it in the parcel. It is one of the small quartos, in parchment &amp; in bad condition, lettered in
                    the venerable way of the country at length – its title Epanaphoras Tragicas by Dom Francisco Manoel.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A part of Dom Francisco Manuel de Mello (1608–1666), <title>Epanaphoras de Varia Historia Portugueza... em
                            Cinco Relaçoens de Sucessos Pertencentes a Este Reyno</title>. Southey’s copy of this work, published in Lisbon, 1675, was
                        included in the sale catalogue of his library as no. 3515.</note> It will turn out to be neither more nor less than a
                        novel.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Epanaphoras de Varia Historia Portugueza</title> contains fictionalised history, relating legends of runaway English
                        lovers found in Madeira, as well as naval disasters and the history of the restoration of Portuguese sovereignty in the state
                        of Pernambuco.</note> I must have blundered in describing Camoens, well remembering that I brought it from <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> keeping to your house, when last in town. five volumes the common
                    duodecimo size. light spotted binding, lettered but not gilt on the back.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis Vaz de
                        Camoes (1524–1580), <title>Obras</title>, 5 vols (Lisbon, 1782), was no. 3185 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> If you can find this I will still trouble you to send it with Mickles translation<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis Vaz de Camoes, <title>The Lusiad, or the Discovery of India, a Poem</title> (1778), trans. William Julius
                        Mickle (1734/5–1788) This work was no. 440 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note><hi rend="ital">by coach</hi>, for as Lord Strangford (who has got an appointment which I should have liked)<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Percy Clinton Sydney Smythe, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780–1855; <title>DNB</title>), was
                        appointed secretary of the British legation at Lisbon in 1802.</note> has been like Mickle, passing off his own verses for
                        Camoens’s,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Strangford’s <title>Poems from the Portuguese of Luis de
                            Camoens</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 569–577.</note> it will give me a fair
                    opportunity of lengthening my account with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> on the Creditor side by giving
                    each his due. If you cannot find this edition, there is one in three small volumes,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly the three-volume <title>Obras de Luiz de Camoens Principe dos Poetas Portuguezes</title>, published in Lisbon, in
                        1772.</note> in marble paper covers, (Dutch marble) but in that case it will be useless to send Mickle, as the critical
                    Portugueze preface is not contained there, which will abridge all labour of hunting for interpolations thro a long poem – I have
                    some remorse of conscience at troubling you.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref> writes me that 1200 of the Annual Review have sold, of 2000 which were
                    printed, &amp; that the demand continues unabated. he is in high spirits at its success, &amp; wishes me to come near London –
                    looking upon me I suppose as one of his staff officers – as in fact <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>
                    &amp; I constitute his main strength. it is clear enough that if, like him, I regarded pen-&amp;-ink-manship solely as a trade I
                    might soon give in an income of double the &lt;present&gt; amount, but I am looking forward to something better &amp; will not be
                    tempted from the pursuit in which I have so long so steadily persevered. You are right about <del>xxxxx</del> subscriptions<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey is abandoning an earlier plan to publish <title>Madoc</title> (1805) by
                        subscription.</note> – &amp; I was right also – the bare shadow of an attempt will convince <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &amp; the few others who advised &amp; prest the mode, that it must be
                    according to my constant opinion, ineffectual. I shall therefore content myself with sharing <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> profit letting him incur all risque.</p><p rend="indent1"> This vile reviewing still bird limes me. I do it slower than any thing else yawning over tiresome work, &amp;
                    parcel comes down after parcel, so that I have already twice whoopd – before I was out of the wood. yesterday Malthus received – I
                    trust in Gods mercy – a mortal wound from my hand.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Malthus
                        (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the future improvement of
                            Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292–301.</note> today I am at the Asiatic Researches.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Asiatic Researches; or Transactions of the Society Instituted in Bengal for Enquiring
                            into the History and Antiquities, the Arts, Science and Literature of Asia</title>, vol. III, in the <title>Annual
                            Review</title>, 2 (1803), 898–908.</note><ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwins</ref> Life of Chaucer is on the road to me.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Godwin’s <title>Chaucer ... Including Memoirs of ... John of Gaunt, Duke of
                            Lancaster; with Sketches of the Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in the Fourteenth Century</title> (1803)
                        in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 462–473.</note> – by the by the Philosopher came in for a hard rap
                    over <del>xx</del> the knuckles with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Malthus. These things keep me from better employment, but they whet
                    the desire for it, &amp; I shall return to my Portugueze society with doubled zest.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s ‘History of Portugal’, which he was working on but never completed.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> In the dark ages medicine was in the hand of the Jews. why was this? am I right in supposing it was because they
                    travelled &amp; brought with them the wisdom &amp; experience – as well as folly – of the East? Xtians could not travel safely.
                    but Hebrew like Arabic was a passport, for synagogue &amp; mosque were everywhere. A decree of the Lateran Council<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of the five ecumenical councils of the Roman Catholic Church held in the Lateran Palace in
                        Rome.</note> that the sacrament should be <hi rend="ital">first presented</hi> to the sick seems levelled against Jew
                    physicians. another which forbade all unchristian remedies I interpret not against fornication, but against such remedies as human
                    blood &amp;c., a list of which will elucidate not the history of medical science, but the growth of superstition &amp; the
                    inevitable effects of ignorance.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of what could the Malabar<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> A region of Southern India, which at this time
                        was owned by the British East India Company.</note> cannon be made – of 13 taken by the Portugueze four were of metal – were
                    the rest leather – stone – or wood?</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you read the Institutes of Menu translated by Sir W Jones?<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Jones , <title>Institutes of Hindu Law, or, The Ordinances of Menu, according to the Gloss of Culluca</title> (1796).</note> I
                    should be very glad to see your corollaries from that book. Hindostan – indeed the whole of civilized Asia puzzles me, &amp;
                    provokes me that we should have so few documents to reason from. As far as their history can be unravelled from fable, nothing is
                    discoverable but the war of <hi rend="ital">sects</hi>, not of religions, &amp; how so ridiculous a religion should have been so
                    blended with astronomy, how allegory should put on so cursedly ugly a mask is a puzzle.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is on his way to London, if indeed he be not there. Of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> no news since my introductory letter. he is I suppose with his precious <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Aunt</ref> – &amp; as I cannot check the chariot wheels of destiny, all I can do is to
                    keep out of their way. Poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is on his way to the West-Indies<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s brother Thomas served as a lieutenant in the fleet sent to transport troops to defend
                        the Windward and Leeward islands against the forces of Napoleon Bonaparte. They were decimated by yellow fever.</note> – damn
                    the West-Indies. I have set him to make queries about the interior of Africa from the negroes – &amp; to bring me home live
                    land-crabs that I may have a breed of beauties here – &amp; a live alligator for <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> remember me to him – to <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LambMaryAnne">Mary Lamb</ref>. I am well – but have an ominous dimness of sight at times which makes me
                    think of <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref>.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Tobin began to lose
                        his eyesight in 1793–1794.</note> that would indeed be a sore visitation! but I will feed while the summer lasts – that my
                    paws may be fat enough to last licking thro the dark winter – if it must come.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Vale!</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>