<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1661</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2783</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 152&#8211;155 [with
                        omissions].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1661" type="letter">
        <head>1661. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-07-30">30 July
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 152&#8211;155 [with
                        omissions].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-07-30">July 30. 1809</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that my lease was signed yesterday, &#8211; so that I am now master of this place for 7, 14 or
                    24 years at my own option. &#8211; &amp; having taken poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jacksons</ref> part as well as my
                    own, there will <del>xxx</del> room enough for us all, let us grow as we may.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had news of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>. how he got out of the Northampton God
                    knows, but over to Lisbon he went as a private in the ranks, &#8211; there a Major Chamberlin<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably Thomas Chamberlin (d. 1828), Major in the 24th Foot Regiment, April 1809 to May 1811.</note> took him by the hand
                    finding he was my brother (tho he did not know me) &amp; wrote to me saying he would try to get him a Commission in a Portugueze
                    regiment which he was raising, &amp; Lord John Fitzroy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord John Fitzroy (1785&#8211;1857),
                        attach&#233; at the British Embassy in Lisbon and son of Augustus, 3rd Duke of Grafton (1735&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Prime
                        Minister 1768&#8211;1770.</note> insisted on being at the whole expence of his equipment. The Colonel of the Regiment<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant Colonel George Duncan Drummond (d. 1811), commander of the 2nd 24th Foot Regiment in
                        the Peninsular war, from April to November 1809.</note> also exerted himself on his behalf. &#8211; Well &#8211; the next day brought in a
                    letter from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Scapegrace</ref> himself dated Abrantes, telling me he was made Lieut. &amp;
                    Adjatant in a Portugueze Regiment, with permanent rank in the British army, &amp; 10s a day, that he was &lt;the&gt; avowed
                    protege of Marshal Beresford,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809 and 1810 the Anglo-Irish officer William Carr
                        Beresford, Viscount Beresford (1768&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>) had achieved great success in applying British training methods
                        to the Portuguese army, to which he had been appointed Marshal.</note> &amp; that if I asked him to whom he was indebted for
                    this good fortune, he replied to his own good conduct! And not a word does he mention of Chamberlin, his Colonel or Lord J
                    Fitzroy, kindly &amp; generously as they had all behaved to him. I confess this want of material gratitude has given me even a
                    worse opinion of him than I had before.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> left me on Monday last. My summer cold prevented me from going about with
                    him as much as I wished, &#8211; partly also I was prevented by being in daily expectation of <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Bethams</ref> arrival, &#8211; for as she knew nobody in the house except myself, it behoved me to be here when she arrived. I
                    went out however for those days which were thus employed, &#8211; by way of Materdale &amp; Paterdale &#8211; then when we arrived poor <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles</ref> had one of his bilious head aches &amp; was obliged to go to bed. James
                        Rickards<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Rickards (d. 1812) visited the Lakes at the same time as Danvers in
                        summer 1809. He was probably a friend from Southey&#8217;s days in Bristol.</note> was of our party, &amp; he &amp; I guided by a
                    boy whom Luff<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Charles Luff (d. 1815): a friend of the <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> and the <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>,
                        who lived at Patterdale, at the head of <ref target="places.html#Ullswater">Ullswater</ref>, and later took an official post
                        at Mauritius.</note> lent us for the service, went a ten mile walk to Angle Tarn &amp; Hays Water, following the stream from
                    the latter down to Brothers water &amp; so home. By that time Danvers was recovered &amp; we drank tea in Luffs garden, where <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> &amp; a very pleasant man of the right sort by name Tilbrooke<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Revd Samuel Tillbrook (1784&#8211;1835), evangelical cleric, a fellow of Peterhouse, Cambridge and
                        later also rector of Freckenham, Suffolk. Tillbrook was acquainted with Wordsworth, near whose home at Rydal he purchased a
                        cottage.</note> joined us. Next day up Helvellin along the whole top &amp; down to Grasmere. on the third into Langdale &amp;
                    home over the Stake. a noble expedition, glorious weather all the way, &#8211; &amp; for farther particulars I shall refer you to Don
                    Manuels next volume.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey intended to publish a fourth volume of his three-volume work
                            <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title> (1st edn 1807, 2nd edn 1808), but this never
                        appeared.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing more has been heard about Rhadamanthus<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey intended to start a
                        new periodical which would review literary works by dead authors; see Southey to Thomas Southey, [16 May 1809], Letter 1630.
                        It was named after the Greek mythological figure Rhadamanthus, a wise king, who was one of the judges of the dead. Southey&#8217;s
                        plans for this periodical were never fulfilled.</note> &#8211; the business doubtless stands over till my visit to Edinburgh, which
                    will take place early in the winter. I am at present hard at work upon Lord Valentias Travels,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of George Annesley, Viscount Valentia (1770&#8211;1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India,
                            Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809), in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 88&#8211;126.</note> &#8211; for <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles&#8217;s</ref> company has thrown me behind hand. This third Quarterly will have three articles of mine &#8211; I corrected last
                    night a proof for it about the South Sea Missions, &amp; they expect Ld Valentia for the same number.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title> appeared in
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61, but his review of Abiel Holmes (1763&#8211;1837), <title>American
                            Annals; or, a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> appeared in the next number of
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319&#8211;337.</note> in about three days I shall finish it. It seems likely
                    that as they feel the weight of my Reviewals, they will call upon me for more of them. Joel Barlowes poem of Columbus is coming
                    for the fourth,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The American writer and politician, Joel Barlow (1754&#8211;1812) published
                            <title>The Columbiad. A Poem</title> in England in 1809. It was a revised version of his <title>Vision of
                        Columbus</title>, published in 1787. Southey did not review this work for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> &amp; I am to
                    write about the Methodists,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of [James Sedgwick (1775&#8211;1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching.
                            By a Barrister</title> (1809), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514.</note> which I shall do
                    with a good will. For two guineas a sheet one can afford to write carefully &amp; take two copies, if the subject be such as to
                    require it. Books of travels which supply both matter &amp; arrangement take less trouble, &amp; the first writing serves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> arrived a few hours after <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> departed. I am sitting to her again, &amp; she has begun a picture of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, which promises to be a very happy likeness. We meditate a cart-expedition to Buttermere, or rather to Scale
                    Hill, wishing to escape <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Marys</ref> bad dinners, &#8211; &amp; so home thro Newlands. Would that
                    you were with us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not know which most surprized me &#8211; the former <del>xxx</del> victory of the Austrians, or the utter folly
                    &amp; pusillanimity which has now laid them prostrate at Bonapartes feet.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain and
                        Austria were in alliance against France in 1809, but Napoleon advanced into Austria where he suffered a significant defeat at
                        the battle of Aspern-Essling (22 May 1809). The Austrians failed to follow up this victory, which allowed Napoleon to seize
                        the capital, Vienna, in early July. The Austrians were then defeated by the French at the battle of Wagram on 5&#8211;6 July
                        1809.</note> Henceforth there neither can, nor deserves to be, any redemption for that vile dynasty. The baseness with which
                    they have sacrificed the Tyrolese by their armistice cuts them off from all hope &amp; all compassion. No man will again lift his
                    arm in their cause, &amp; the <del>xxx</del> salvation of Germany whenever it does come (&amp; it will come at last) will owe it
                    to a better principle than loyalty to the Imperial Crown Meantime the immediate effect will be as bad as possible. It will pour
                    again into Spain, &amp; we shall have let the opportunity of securing that country pass by. Of one expedition the result will
                    probably reach you as soon as the letter can do.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren expedition was an
                        unsuccessful British attempt to open another front in the Netherlands in support of the Austrian Empire&#8217;s struggle with
                        France. Approximately 40,000 soldiers with supporting horses and artillery landed at Walcheren on 30 July 1809. There was
                        little fighting but the army sustained heavy losses from sickness, and in December 1809 the rest withdrew.</note> I suppose it
                    is intended to keep the Island of Walcheren as well as to take it. &#8211; if so the thing is worth doing, not so much for any
                    additional security it can give us, as for the credit of the thing, &amp; the better annoyance it will be to the enemy, whose
                    pride will be <del>xxx</del> more wounded by it than by any thing else that we could possibly do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> who has just had another daughter born, comes in the autumn &#8211; I shall go with
                    him to Irton,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southwest of Wastwater in Eskdale, Cumbria. Irton Hall, designed around a
                        fourteenth-century Pele tower, was the seat of the Irton family, Lords of the Manor of Irton and Melthwaite since medieval
                        times.</note> &amp; ascend Scafell,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Though there are two mountains of this name in
                        the Lake District, Southey probably refers to Scafell Pike, the highest mountain in England, east of Wastwater.</note>
                    thus compleating my knowledge of this country. &#8211; Kehama<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse
                            of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> is in status-quo, but my cold seems now about to take its leave, &amp; I shall resume my
                    early rising, the moment it can be done with comfort. &#8211; I have sent <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref>
                    Queen Oraca,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem was first published as &#8216;Queen Urraia and the Five Martyrs of
                        Morocco&#8217; in the <title>Morning Post</title> in early September 1803, and in the <title>Iris</title>, 3 November 1804. It was
                        published as &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors;
                            with some Original Pieces Hitherto Unpublished</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), I, pp. 269&#8211;280. It was also published in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838). Both these works were published by the house of Ballantyne.</note> &amp; the
                    Aldermans Funeral<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem &#8216;The Alderman&#8217;s Funeral, an English Eclogue&#8217; was not
                        included in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with some Original
                            Pieces Hitherto Unpublished</title> (1810), but it was published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                        1808</title>, 1.2 (1810).</note> for a miscellaneous collection which he is making. The mode of printing &amp; publishing
                    Kehama will ere long be settled &#8211; but I must clear off the reviewing, &amp; get a good start of <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> before there be leisure to write the necessary letters about it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The long expected tidings of <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachys</ref> release is
                    arrived. I had always foreseen it, &amp; can truly say that I have felt a deeper sorrow in looking at her in the midst of mirth
                    &amp; festivity than when the tidings reached me that she was at rest. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I could not go on to Edinburgh from Durham, because <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> was
                    coming here &#8211; &amp; because <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> was delayed in London so much beyond the time which
                    he had appointed for his return, &amp; which would have suited me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry to say that there is not yet another number of Kehama ready for you &#8211; but this also shall be done as
                    soon as it can be. The truth is tho I do much I yet have to be idle when there is an excuse for it, &amp; notwithstanding this
                    propensity so many things crowd upon me that if some of my Hindoo Gods would accommodate me with a few of their supernumerary
                    hands &amp; arms,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810) includes
                        characterisations of the Hindu gods.</note> I could find good employment for as many as they could spare.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> All well. Love from all</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>