<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1487</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2609</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 158&#8211;160.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1487" type="letter">
        <head>1487. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">John Adamson</ref>, <date when="1808-08-06">6 August 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 158&#8211;160.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-08-06">Aug. 6. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Sir.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have never seen the name of Nicola Luiz,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Adamson was the translator of
                            <title>Donna Ignez de Castro, a Tragedy, from the Portuguese of Nicola Luiz, with Remarks on the History of that
                            Unfortunate Lady</title> (1808).</note> except in Murphy;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Cavanah Murphy
                        (1760&#8211;1814), <title>Travels in Portugal; Through the Provinces of Entre Douro e Minho, Beira, Entremadura, and Alem-Tejo, in
                            the Years 1789 and 1790. Consisting of Observations on the Manners, ... Trade, Public Buildings, Arts, Antiquities &amp;c.
                            of that Kingdom</title> (1795). In this work Murphy credits Nicola Luiz as the only author of a Portuguese tragedy on the
                        story of In&#234;s Peres de Castro (1325&#8211;1355), the murdered lover of Prince Pedro (1320&#8211;1367), who, when he became king of
                        Portugal in 1357, was declared to have been his wife and crowned queen as a corpse. The author remains obscure to literary
                        historians: he has been identified as Nicolau Luis da Silva (1723&#8211;1787), author of chapbook comedies.</note> and the title of
                    the Portuguese Plautus<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Titus Maccius Plautus (c. 254 BC&#8211;184 BC), Roman
                        playwright.</note> which he gives him, being generally applied to Gil Vicente,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gil
                        Vicente (c.1465-c. 1536), called the Troubadour, is considered the chief dramatist of Portugal and called the Portuguese
                        Plautus.</note> thought it not unlikely that he might have written Richard for Robert, as he is apt to do so. Barbosa&#8217;s great
                        Bibliotheca<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Diogo Barbosa Machado (1682&#8211;1772), <title>Bibliotheca Lusitana</title>
                        (1741&#8211;1759).</note> is not in my possession, and I have referred in vain to Nicolas Antonio,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicol&#225;s Antonio (1617&#8211;1684), the Spanish bibliographer, author of <title>Bibliotheca Hispana Vetus</title>
                        (1696).</note> to the Mappa de Portugal,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jo&#227;o Baptista de Castro (1700&#8211;1785),
                            <title>Mappa de Portugal</title> (1745).</note> which contains a copious list of poets, and to the Catalogue of Authors
                    which the Academy printed as the sources from which their dictionary was to be compiled. How it should be that this name is not to
                    be found in either, is to me altogether unaccountable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is possible that Antonio Ferreira&#8217;s play<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Ferreira
                        (1528&#8211;1569), <title>In&#234;s de Castro</title> (c. 1557).</note> may have been originally published under this fictitious name. I
                    have no other reason for supposing so than that it seems almost certain if the name of Nicola Luiz were a real one, it would have
                    been included in one or all of the works which I have consulted; and Ferreira did in one instance practise an artifice of this
                    kind, yet I think you must have seen his play. It begins: &#8211; </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Colhey, colhey alegres,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Donzellas minhas, mil cheirosas flores.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Pluck, gaily pluck./ Young
                            companions, a thousand perfumed flowers&#8217;. See Ferreira, <title>The Tragedy of Ines de Castro</title>, trans. John R. C.
                            Martyn (Coimbra, 1987), p. 243.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">Should this be the tragedy in question, I will, with great pleasure, transmit you an account of the author, or send
                    you my copy of his works (should that be more agreeable), which, when you have completely done with it, may be returned through my
                    brother Dr. Southey, of Durham.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The tragedy of Domingos dos Reis Quita,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domingos dos Reis Quita
                        (1728&#8211;1770), <title>In&#234;s de Castro</title>.</note> upon the same story, has been Englished by Benjamin Thompson.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Benjamin Thompson (1774&#8211;1816), <title>Inez de Castro, a Tragedy, Translated from the
                            Portuguese of Don Domingo Quita</title> (1800).</note> There are two Spanish ones by Geronimo Bermudez (published
                    originally under the name of Antonio de Silva), in the sixth volume of the Parnaso.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Geronimo Bermudez (1530&#8211;1599), authored, using the penname of Antonio de Silva, <title>Nise Lastimosa</title> and <title>Nise
                            Laureado</title> (1577) on the subject of In&#234;s de Castro. These were included in <title>El Parnaso Espanol</title>
                        (1768&#8211;1778), the collection of Spanish poems made by Juan Jos&#233; L&#243;pez de Sedano (1729&#8211;1801).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry K. White</ref> had merely begun the first scene of his projected play, and that,
                    as was evident from the handwriting, at a very early age.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> As Southey noted in the
                        Preface to <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White of Nottingham</title> (London, 1807), I, p. 52, Kirke White had begun a
                        play on the subject of In&#234;s de Castro.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Portuguese have two poems upon the same story, the Penasco de las Lagrimas, written in Spanish by Francisco de
                    Fran&#231;a da Costa,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Francia y Acosta (17th-century), a native of Porto,
                        wrote &#8216;Penasco de las Lagrimas&#8217; in ottava rima; he is chiefly known for his collection <title>Jard&#237;n de Apolo</title>
                        (1658).</note> and the Saudades de D. Ignes de Castro, by Manoel de Azevedo.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Listed in Barbosa&#8217;s<title> Bibliotheca Lusitana</title> as Manoel de Azevedo Morato (dates unknown), <title>Saudades de D.
                            Ignez de Castro. Das ne convertida em, Loureiro. Glojsa a hum Soneto de Camoes</title> (1716).</note> This latter I have
                    myself planned a play upon, The Revenge of Pedro: whether it will ever be executed, is very doubtful,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was not.</note> but this part of the story is far fitter for dramatic poetry than the foregoing.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> I am, Sir,</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours with respect,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>