<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1247</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2369</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                        95.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 55&#8211;57 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1247" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1247" type="letter">
        <head>1247. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1806-12-23">23 December
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 23 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1806.<lb />Seal: [fragment] red wax<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                        95<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 55&#8211;57 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now that the <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Emperor or Imperial Abbot</ref> is fairly reinstated upon his
                    throne, I know once more how to direct, &amp; having just finished off the Capitaneus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey is referring to Captain James Burney&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific
                            Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (Vol. 2; 1806) he reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5
                        (1807), 16&#8211;30.</note> proceed to tell you of my goings on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is gone to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> in Leicestershire<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Over the winter of 1806&#8211;1807 Wordsworth and his
                        family were living in a farmhouse owned by <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref> near his new
                        house at Coleorton, Leicestershire.</note> on his way to London, where he will <hi rend="ital">perhaps</hi> give the Lectures
                    which have been advertised.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to a letter to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, Coleridge was to &#8216;lecture at the Royal Institution upon the
                        Principles common to the Fine Arts&#8217;; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 18 October 1806, Letter 1229. He did not in fact lecture
                        there until 1808, on the subjects of the Principles of Poetry, Shakespeare and Milton.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> left me on Friday, having been appointed to the Pallas,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, launched in 1804, was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was Thomas
                        Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the capture of many French
                        and Spanish warships.</note> &#8211; I have some hope of his promotion, for <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has
                    mentioned him to <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">his Uncle</ref>. So I am left alone to my winter occupations, &amp; truly
                    they are quite sufficient to employ me. Two months however, if no unlucky interruption prevent, will be sufficient to clear all
                    off, &amp; send Espriella &amp; Palmerin into the world.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published his
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> and an English
                        translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> I have an additional &amp;
                    weighty motive for dispatch. The times being South-America mad my account of Brazil, instead of being the last work in the series
                    must be the first.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The prospective flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil (29 November
                        1807) prompted Southey, at his uncle <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill&#8217;s</ref> request, to begin a
                        history of Brazil, using papers sent him by Hill and stored by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>; See
                        Southey to John Rickman, 23 December 1806, Letter 1247. Southey wished <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to
                        use his position as Under Secretary of State in the Home Office to ascertain whether the government might provide him support
                        during the preparation of a work likely to provide it with useful information in the new political situation.</note> There are
                    in the bookcase downstairs at your house<del>x</del> sixteen bundles of sealed papers. Those papers contain more information
                    concerning South America than his Majestys Agents have been able to obtain at Lisbon &#8211; more in all probability than any other
                    person in Europe possesses except one Frenchman, now returned to Paris.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The identity of
                        this Frenchman is unclear. It is likely that he was Abb&#233; Francois Garnier (1722&#8211;1804), the long-standing chaplain to the
                        French factory in Lisbon. A less likely possibility is Abb&#233; Jean-Antoine Dubois (1765&#8211;1848), a French Catholic missionary
                        in India, whose long sojourn in the southern districts brought him into contact with the legacy of Portuguese Catholic
                        colonialism there. Dubois&#8217;s manuscript history of Indian religion was purchased by the East India Company and published in
                        English as <title>Description of the Character, Manners and Customs of the People of India, and of their Institutions,
                            Religious and Civil</title> (1816).</note> he has seen them, &amp; is very likely to get the start of me: &#8211; unless, which
                    is not improbable, Bonaparte should chuse to withold from the world information which would be of specific use to England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Concerning these papers, of whose contents I was till last week ignorant, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has written to me, urging me to make all possible speed with this part of
                    the work, &amp; desiring me to offer the information to government. I inclosed the letters up to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &amp; it may be that he will advise me to come up to London upon this business.
                    I hope not. I should rather wash my hands of all other business first, &amp; then can certainly in half a year accomplish a large
                    volume, &#8211; for on this subject there is no collateral information to hunt for. A very few books contain all the printed history,
                    &amp; there will be more difficulty in planning the work well than in executing it. &#8211; There will be business of some consequence
                    in the way of map making <del>xxx</del> which will delight Arrowsmith,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith
                        (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer and map publisher.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> having very valuable materials for a map of Brazil.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is of so much consequence that it will perhaps be advisable to let the Palmerin sleep &amp; so save a months
                    time, which may be better spared for it when I get the book fairly in the press &#8211; but this we shall see. I have the first
                    materials here &amp; can advance some way with them. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> letter will instruct me
                    whether to set to work for myself, or for the government &#8211; giving them information is God knows throwing pearls you know to whom &#8211;
                    but so the pearls be paid for, &#8211; well. The best thing they could do for me, &amp; for themselves if they really want information
                    respecting South America &#8211; is to send me to Lisbon for that specific purpose &#8211; without any ostensible charge.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you may suppose we were all here as staunch Paullites<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Paull
                        (1770&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), Indian trader (1790&#8211;1805) and radical politician, who stood for Westminster in the general
                        election of November 1806, against Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) for the Whigs and Sir Samuel Hood
                        (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>) for the Tories.</note> as the son of the Mermaid himself. There is nothing in the world like
                    resolute &#8211; straightforward honesty. &amp; is sure to conquer in the long run. I have been reading Quaker-history, which is worth
                    reading because it proves this, &amp; proves also that institutions can compleatly new mould our nature, &#8211; for if the instinct of
                    self defence can be subdued, nothing else is so powerful. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox&#8217;s</ref> death is a loss
                    to me &#8211; who had a promise from him &#8211; but I will not affect to think it a loss to the country. he lived a year too long. England
                    cannot fall yet, blessed be God, because its inhabitants are Englishmen &#8211; but if any thing could destroy a country it would be the
                    incurable folly of such governors, &amp; the utter hopelessness there is of getting better ones with such a representation. My
                    plan for reform is to sow Hounslow Heath with hemp &amp; inclose it with gibbets.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Hounslow Heath, London, was crossed by major routes to the West country and became a notorious haunt of highwaymen and
                        robbers. Southey suggests growing &#8216;hemp&#8217; for rope, and building devices to hang them.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How is <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>? &#8211; a question of more
                    consequence than where is the key of Prussia &#8211; or if the Russians have cut off a regiment of French. We go on tolerably well. Poor
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> indeed rests neither day nor night for flatulence &#8211; yet he grows &#8211;
                    &amp; is uncommonly lazy for his age. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> goes on excellently well &#8211; if
                    his brain be but as capable as hers, much as I should hope &#8211; my hopes would be satisfied.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you seen the Memoirs of Colonel Hutchinson?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy Hutchinson (n&#233;e
                        Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel
                            Hutchinson</title> (1806). Southey reviewed this work in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807),
                        361&#8211;378.</note> If not by all means read it &#8211; it is the history of a right Englishman, &#8211; &amp; the sketch of English history
                    which it contains from the time of the Reformation is so admirable that it ought to make even Scotchmen ashamed to mention the
                    rascally name of Hume.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Scottish philosopher and historian, David Hume (1711&#8211;1776;
                            <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>The History of England</title>, 6 vols (1754&#8211;1762) was the best-selling general history
                        of the age.</note> I have seldom been so deeply interested by any book as by this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Inclosed is some verbal criticism for <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to [Richard Duppa], fragment [December 1806], Letter 1248.</note> which
                    because of its duplicity profits by the <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Imperial Abbots</ref> privilege &#8211; a better title
                    that than Lord Bishop &#8211; God bless you. &#8211; Can you by means of any Almanack vade-mecum<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        &#8216;go-with-me&#8217; or handbook.</note> or memorabilia tell me the <hi rend="ital">dates</hi> of the Kings message which led to the
                        war,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The King&#8217;s message is discussed in Letter 61 of <title>Letters from England by
                            Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807).</note> of Despards
                        Execution<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Marcus Despard (1751&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), a revolutionary hung
                        for treason on 21 February 1803. He is discussed in <title>Letters from England</title>, letter 48.</note> &#8211; &amp; of Emmets
                        insurrection<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Emmet (1778&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), executed on 20 September
                            1803 for his part in a rebellion, discussed in letter 61 of <title>Letters from England</title>. Southey published an elegy on
                        Emmet in the <title>Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title> on 12 November 1803. See <title>Robert Southey:
                            Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, pp. 420&#8211;423.</note> &#8211; things necessary
                    to be touched upon by any friend from Spain?</p>
        <closer rend="indent1"> RS.</closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-12-23">Tuesday. Dec. 23. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>