<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1362</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2484</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 117.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1362" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1362" type="letter">
        <head>1362. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-09-22">22 September
                        1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 22 Sept. 1807<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 117<lb />Unpublished</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is unusually long since you have heard from me,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had last written
                        to Rickman at the beginning of August; see Southey to John Rickman, 8 August 1807, Letter 1351.</note> &amp; during that
                    interval I have been passing something like a grass-hoppers summer, &#8211; boating &amp; mountaineering with various droppers-in.
                    Bathing in the lake, &#8211; painting book-shelves, arranging &amp; re-arranging the books upon them, &amp; rather enjoying the sight of
                    them than making much use of them. There are something more than two thousand volumes in the room, &amp; I shall find place for
                    about 500 more when they arrive. The rest must be lodged in another apartment. You will be well pleased to see their comely array,
                    &amp; the oeconomical manner in which we have contrived to save binding &amp; yet give the unbound books a respectable
                    appearance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My idlest season however is not wholly unproductive. On the arrival of the expected parcel from Lisbon I lost no
                    time in preparing a portion of the Cid for the printer, &amp; have already received two proofs from them: <del>which</del> I am
                    sorry they did not pass thro your hands.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the
                            Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica particular del
                            Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and
                            <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632). The printer was <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">William
                            Pople</ref>.</note> But as my plan is to add the essential notes <hi rend="ital">in loco</hi>, &#8211; &amp; reserve the
                    discursive &amp; supererogatory for the end, the sheet shall be sent to you by &amp; by for your perusal &amp; annotation before
                    their after-crop of remarks be sent off. Section by section the references are placed in the margin, after the goodly fashion of
                    old times, at the end of each, &#8211; &amp; at the beginning in like manner the argument, or contents &#8211; The notes are numbered 1, 2, 3
                    &amp;c in every book. I do not think any thing which can facilitate the readers progress has been overlooked.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> provokes me with his tedious delays. Whenever the wind blows with a
                    wintry sound I think of my books &amp; am tempted to let fly an execration at him for having detained them till the summer is
                    over, &amp; then doubled or trebled the risque of their voyage.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having decided to stay at
                            <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, Southey was arranging for his books and other belongings which he
                        had left with friends to be sent to him.</note> Not to mention that there are many of which I am in want. &#8211; There are the
                    little quartos in the cup-board below stairs <del>xxxxx</del> of the Jesuits letters from their various missions which contain
                    matter to my purpose. Whether these little be Cartas Annuaes<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Annual Reports made by
                        Jesuit missionaries were a valuable source of information on the countries of Japan, and Southeast Asia. Here he is thinking
                        of Portuguese volumes, perhaps from what was listed in the sale catalogue of his library as &#8216;Relacaon da Republica, que os
                        Religiosos Jesuitas das Provincias de Portugal, e Hispana, &amp;c. 2 vol. <hi rend="ital">n. d.</hi> &#8211; Regulae, &amp;c. Soc.
                        Jesu, <hi rend="ital">Antv.</hi> 1635, and others on the Jesuits <hi rend="ital">together 7 vol.</hi>&#8217;. None of the Cartas
                        Annuaes is listed as such.</note> I am not certain. They are thinnish volumes, &amp; rather in better binding than usual.
                    Upstairs there is also a thick duodecimo entitled Vieira Lusitano,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>O Insignie Pintor e Leal Esposo Vieira Lusitano, Historia Verdadeira, que elle Escreve em Cantos Lyricos</title> (1780)
                        by Portuguese painter Francisco Vieira (1765&#8211;1805).</note> bound, &amp; so lettered, if I forget not. I made when abroad an
                    abstract of this singular poem, (the most interesting in the language, tho wholly neglected) which would produce five or six
                    guineas in the Athen&#230;um,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>.</note> but in transcribing it, the book
                    ought to be at hand. When you have convenient opportunity consign these three books to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, for conveyance here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A very pretty concluding chapter our wise Generals have cut out for the History of the River Plata! &#8211; I am glad of
                    the evacuation of a country which none but fools would ever have dreamt of keeping &amp; am consoled for the disgrace by
                    recollecting how much of it rests upon the shoulders of Crauford whom I abhominate for his babbling about fortifications &amp; his
                    admiration of Mack.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In June 1806, with Spain, the colonial master of South America, under
                        French sway and Britain&#8217;s enemy, a force under Admiral Sir Home Riggs Popham (1762&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) and William Carr
                        Beresford (1768&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), occupied Buenos Aires and held it until 14 August. On 3 February 1807 the attack
                        was renewed when the British took Montevideo from the sea. In July a British attempt to retake Buenos Aires was repulsed with
                        great loss of life. Brigadier-General Robert Crauford (1764&#8211;1812), participated in the failed attack. Karl Mack, Baron von Leiberich (1752&#8211;1828), Austrian soldier, commander of the forces defeated by Napoleonic France at
                        Ulm and Austerlitz.</note> There is also a great fitness in his being defeated &amp; taken by a volunteer force. What is to
                    become of Portugal? what of Brazil? &#8211; Beyond all question our policy should be to induce the Court to remove there. There is a
                    danger that France may get possession of Lisbon, &amp; send French troops to protect Brazil.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably by this time received Palmerin.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> I doubt whether, having read Amadis,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of the
                        Spanish romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> you will have patience to read it; &#8211; if you have, the progress of morals from
                    the days of the one romance to the other will shock you as something curious.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>. I shall see her
                    before the winter is expired, &amp; rely upon her coming here next summer.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1807-09-22">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 22. 1807</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I am glad to read of <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobins</ref> marriage.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 7 September Tobin had married Jane Mallet (d. 1837) in London.</note> My God &#8211; cried <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George II</ref> when I read the paragraph to him a second time (he never hears anything
                        the first) &#8211; why I thought to have had her myself! &#8211; Yet it appears that he never saw the Lady, &#8211; &amp; if he had certes she
                        is better off with a<del>n eyeless</del> &lt;blind&gt; husband than a brainless one.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>