<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1125</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2247</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1125" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1125" type="letter">
        <head>1125. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1805-11-24">24
                        November 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
                        M. P./ Lincolns Inn/ London<lb />Postmark: FREE/ NOV 28/ 1805<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: Southey has dated the letter incorrectly as &#8216;&#8216;Monday&#8217;&#8217; as 24 November 1805 was a
                        Sunday. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I beg leave to present you with all my right &amp; title to a turtle &#8211; but you must look sharp after it. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has shipped one on board the Aberdeen, Capt Cummings<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> &#8211; for London in this present convoy &amp; some Gentleman passenger has undertaken to
                        <del>take</del> see it on board the coach for <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. &#8211; I have been laughing this
                    half hour at the excellent &amp; seaman like absurdity of sending me a turtle, &#8211; till it occurred to me that it might be worth
                    your looking after, if it be not eat by the way.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The turtle died in quarantine; see
                        Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806, Letter 1140.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor Lord Proby&#8217;s common place book has been gutted of what little it contained &amp; given to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> &#8211; who I believe you know is in the Amelia.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby (1779&#8211;1804) was the eldest son of Sir John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort
                        (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>). Proby was the captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, who, having been sent to the
                        disease-ridden Leeward Islands station, died on 6 August 1804 at Surinam, from yellow fever. Wynn had asked Southey if his
                        brother, who was currently serving on the <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, could recover any of Proby&#8217;s papers for his family and
                        friends; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 7 December 1805, Letter 1130.</note> It contained some remarks concerning Surinam
                    &amp; its government, anecdotes of cruelty towards the slaves there, &amp; an attempt to disprove one of the propositions in
                        Euclid.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Euclid (fl. 300 BC) the Greek mathematician who established the principles of
                        geometry.</note> The purser cut these out &amp; gave <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> the blank book. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> says of him that he was a very different man in the Amelia from what he had
                    been in the Danae, &amp; that the recollection of his former severities disturbed him <del>in his dying</del> on his death
                        bed.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Proby had been captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Danae</hi> (formerly the French
                        frigate, <hi rend="ital">Vaillante</hi>, which was captured in 1798). In March 1800, under Proby&#8217;s command, her crew mutinied,
                        took control of the ship and handed it over to the French.</note> He was made too young, but had ripened into what a man &amp;
                    a Sea Captain should be. &#8211; I thought this worth telling you, in case you might wish to get these papers for Lord Carysfort if they
                    have not been destroyed, tho for my own part I would rather destroy such freshening remembrances of grief than seek for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> enquires your direction as if he had a design upon you with another turtle. Poor
                    fellow he has been very unlucky in the Amelia doing nothing for eight months, &amp; catching nothing but the yellow fever.
                    Government ought to augment the pay upon foreign stations for, in the West Indies it is not equal to the rest: I can learn nothing
                    satisfactory about the disputed prize money.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804, the naval ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas Southey was a lieutenant, had captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and
                        cargo captured in armed conflict, but in this case the prize money was contested because the ships were captured before war
                        was officially declared.</note> He hears that he is to have two thirds. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>
                    hears that it is to be only one sixth &#8211; &amp; the Courier silenced me by a positive affirmation that the sailors <del>were</del>
                    to have the whole as usual.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey took up his brother&#8217;s cause to have his share of the
                        prize money reinstated and <title>The Courier</title> published a paragraph supporting the sailors&#8217; claim to the prize-money
                        on Saturday 24 August 1805. This was followed by a longer defence of their position in <title>The Courier</title> on 31 August
                        1805 under the title &#8216;Indemnification to the Spanish Merchants&#8217;. A &#8216;reply from a
                        Spanish merchant&#8217; appeared in <title>The Courier</title> for 6 September 1805. Southey&#8217;s response, that the prize money was
                        being withheld from the sailors in a measure that was &#8216;impolitic, ungenerous and unjust&#8217; was published in <title>The
                            Courier</title> of 25 September 1805, p. 2. This was refuted by an editorial article in <title>The Courier</title> of 28
                        September 1805, where it was stated that there was no truth in Southey&#8217;s assertion.</note> If this was a lie &#8211; which is very likely, it was a lie by authority; &amp; ministry are ashamed to avow
                        <del>x</del> a measure so unpopular</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I mean to tell the Cids story more at length &amp; publish it in a little volume with erudite notes some of the
                    Ballads about him &amp;c.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in
                        1808.</note> Twill bring me fifty pounds by the sale of an edition, &amp; some credit, &amp; be better alone than in the
                    Introduction &#8211; for my History<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected, but never completed, &#8216;History of
                        Portugal&#8217;.</note> must be cleared of extraneous matter for the sake of reducing its bulk.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Specimens can only make two volumes I conceive.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and
                        Bedford&#8217;s jointly edited anthology, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> was published in three volumes by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> delay has been very provoking. It has cost me much vexation &amp;
                    the loss of a years sale &#8211; but it serves me right. One fortnight of my own labour in London would have done what he has been
                    eighteen months &lt;about&gt; &amp; not done yet. &amp; after all I see plainly that I must be at the expence &amp; trouble of a
                    journey to town to finish it myself. I did not put it into his hand one tenth part so much for my own convenience as for the sake
                    of giving him some employment in the hope of curing his uncomfortable disease of having nothing to do.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-11-24">Nov. 24. Monday.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>