<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1411</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2533</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1411" type="letter">
        <head>1411. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-01-03">3
                        January 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 11 Craven
                        Street/ Strand/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ JAN 6/ 1808<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is no harm done in having sent you the books as what you cannot do at once you can take with you &#8211; only <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> Poland &amp; the Sermon should be done without delay.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Harry was reviewing books, in Southey&#8217;s stead, for the <title>Annual Review</title>; see Southey
                        to Henry Herbert Southey, 27 December 1807, Letter 1405. Henry&#8217;s review of Burnett&#8217;s <title>View of the Present State of
                            Poland</title> (1807) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 110&#8211;113; his review of Joseph Cooke
                        (1775&#8211;1811), <title>Methodism condemned by Methodist Preachers: or a Vindication of the Doctrines contained in Two Sermons on
                            Justification by Faith, and the Witness of the Spirit; for Which the Author was expelled from the Methodist
                            Connection</title> (1807) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 169.</note> As soon as you
                    inform me of your Durham direction, or that you do not go there, I will forward Joinville to you &amp; also <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> specimens.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Memoirs of John Lord de Joinville, Grand Seneschal of Champagne Written by Himself</title> (1807). The book was
                        reviewed by Southey himself, not Henry, in the <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 215&#8211;219. Southey also wrote
                        the review of Burnett&#8217;s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers</title> (1807) that appeared in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1807</title>, 6 (1808), 618&#8211;631.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you wrote verse I could easily put you in the way of turning it to account in the newspapers, &#8211; as it is &#8211; the
                    ways by which you can make money seem to be these. A little by reviewing, &#8211; if <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King
                        Arthur</ref> has the civility to send you any books, which may be doubted, &#8211; for that family are civil to me against the
                    grain. Rather more by the Athen&#1237;um,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The magazine edited by John Aikin, <title>The
                            Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, to which Southey was a contributor.</note> &#8211; your
                    Scotch tour may go there; &#8211; you may write an account of Lisbon &amp; of <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>, &#8211; &amp; you
                    may write biography for it; &#8211; they are in want of this article, &amp; it is likely that the Cathedral Library may supply books of
                    materials. Do you understand Spanish &amp; Portugueze enough to do some thing for Pinkertons Voyages &amp; Travels?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), compiler of <title>A General Collection of the
                            Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in All Parts of the World</title> (1808&#8211;1814).</note> at least if you do not
                    you can easily acquire it, &amp; it is very likely that I can secure this employment for you, &amp; also furnish you with the
                    materials. Could you english Esplandian<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Las Sergas de Esplandi&#225;n</title>, (1510) one of a series of Spanish chivalric romances by Garci Rodr&#237;guez de Montalvo
                        (1450&#8211;1504) of which <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, which Southey translated in 1803, is the first.</note> so as to go on with
                    the romances of the Amadis family? &#8211; the Spanish of the romances is remarkably easy, the construction straight forward, the
                    vocabulary scanty, and the more antiquated it is the greater is its semblance to Portugueze. I can borrow for you the originals
                    from <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, &amp; engage <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to
                    publish it on the same terms as he does for myself &#8211; that is sharing the eventual profits. Your name should not appear as that
                    might professionally hurt you. This plan appears to me very feasible, <del>xx</del> easy of execution; &#8211; &amp; likely to afford
                    you employment quite as long as you can want it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is unlucky that you cannot <del>xxxxxxxx</del> live at free quarters till <del>next</del> the next winter, &amp;
                    get this work enough in the mean time to set off with a little more stock of <del>xxxxx</del> cash in hand. I am bare at this
                    time, &#8211; Espriella is fetching up my lea-way, &amp; in all likelihood will fetch it up completely, but it will take a second
                    edition to do this.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). A second edition was
                        published in 1808.</note> Could you have returned with me you would have earned something for the winter, &amp; I should have
                    been better able to have lent you a helping hand. Your matrimonial plans prevent this &#8211; I regret nothing but the ultime dicto
                    <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;previously mentioned&#8217;. Harry married Mary Sealy (1784&#8211;1811), the daughter of a wealthy Lisbon merchant, in 1809.</note>
          <del>xx</del> inconvenience. &amp; that is hardly worth regretting. the attachment began well &amp; I shall be disappointed if it
                    does not end well. When I get to London I will endeavour to send you what I can &#8211; &lt;if possible&gt; &#8211; little it must needs be &#8211;
                    By the years end I expect to be better off. My lea way has been occasioned by the system of not selling copyrights, &amp; the
                    total failure of any produce from Madoc &#8211; which has as yet brought me only 25&#163;. But if Espriella rights me in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> books &#8211; which there is every reason to think it will, I have the sale of the
                    small edition,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second, duodecimo edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; of
                        Palmerin,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> &amp; of the Cid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title> (1808).</note> to look to for the ensuing years ways &amp; means; &#8211; so that tho more behind hand than I have
                    ever been before, I may yet consider myself on the whole as in a fairer way than has ever &lt;yet&gt; been my lot
                        <del>before</del>. The first volume of Brazil which I am preparing for the Press<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> published in three volumes from 1810&#8211;1819.</note> will discharge my debt to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, &amp; I shall, besides this, get thro work enough in the coming year, for the
                    calls of the year after. And every year the labour of the last will bring in something.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> to see if he can provide you with any
                    Durham introductions. About fifteen years ago I fell in with a Durham man at Cambridge, to whom, should you by any accident meet
                    him, you may mention my name &amp; <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa&#8217;s</ref>. He was an intimate friend of poor D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sewards.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr John Seward, physician brother of Southey&#8217;s college
                            friend, <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>. John was &#8216;poor&#8217; because he died young of heart disease. Southey discusses John in his letter to Anna Seward, 10 December 1807, Letter 1394.</note> his name Hugh Salvin,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Hugh Salvin (1773&#8211;1852).</note> &amp; a very clever man he is wherever he
                        <del>be</del> may be, or whatever is become of him; - but from that time to this I have never seen or heard of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is well that you are able to take my reviewing off my hands, which would else have a good deal delayed me with
                    Brazil. I shall be ready for the press with the first volume soon after my return from London, - if the books still wanting are to
                    be found in London I will find them, - there being few private libraries to which I could not get access.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I forgot to observe to you that it would have been better if those Spanish plays (which are written in verse) had
                    been translated with familiar blank verse, - such as &lt;that of&gt; our old dramatists, which had succeeded so admirably in
                    Thorntons Plautus<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bonnell Thornton (1725&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Comedies
                            of Plautus, Translated into Familiar Blank Verse</title> (1767&#8211;1774).</note> &#8211; &amp; I believe in Colemans Terence<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Colman (bap 1732&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Comedies of Terence</title>
                        (1765).</note> also, tho this latter book has never fallen in my way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Le Moynes poem<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre Le Moyne (1602&#8211;1671), <title>Saint Louys, ou, La
                            Sainte Coronne Reconquise: Poeme Heroique</title> (1666).</note> would make a good analysis for the Athen&#230;um &#8211; but [MS
                    torn] extracts ought to be translated. Make your analysis, - return me the book with the passages marked on a slip of paper that
                    you would have done, &amp; I will lick them into blank verse presently for you. This of course at your leisure &amp; not till
                    reviewing is done. &#8211; The descent in the Pyramids is noted by Hayley in his notes to the Essay on Epic Poetry<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on Epic Poetry</title> (1781), pp.
                        127&#8211;128.</note> &#8211; &amp; has been pronounced the best that is anywhere to be found. But better use has been made of the
                    Pyramids by the Abbe Terrasson in Sethos,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean Terrasson (1670&#8211;1750), <title>Life of
                            Sethos, Taken from Private Memoirs of the Ancient Egyptians</title> (1731).</note> &#8211; which is without exception the best
                    book of its kind, &amp; <del>xxx</del> of a higher moral character than any French work that I ever yet met with.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> I am sorry you leave town before I get there</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-01-03">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 3. 1808.</date>
          </p>
          <p>Have you got paid for the last Annual<del>s?</del>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>