<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1137</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2259</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1137" type="letter">
        <head>1137. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard Duppa</ref>, <date when="1805-12-29">[29-]30 December
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Richard Duppa Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 51. Great
                        Malborough Street/ Oxford Street/ London./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />Endorsement:
                        CXXI.<lb />Watermark: T BOTFIELD<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: Southey
                        states that the letter was &#8216;begun yester-&#8217;evening&#8217;.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Duppa</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> For this last fortnight I have been exceedingly unwell &amp; incapacitated from doing anything, first by a bilious
                    diarrh&#339;a, &amp; now by the regular influenza, which chuses to make me in the fashion. I am still taking James&#8217;s powders,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> James&#8217;s fever powder, containing phosphate of lime and oxide of antimony as sweating
                        agents, was the invention of the physician and medical writer, Robert James (bap. 1703&#8211;1776).</note> &amp; hope tomorrow to be
                    so far recovered as to begin with bark<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Fever Bark&#8217; was a popular treatment for illnesses
                        such as influenza.</note> but I am still very weak, head bad &#8211; throat still sore &#8211; nights restless &amp;c &amp;c. It is even
                    some effort to write &#8211; but I am writing to say that if it were not for this utter disability I should have hammered all day at the
                    M. Angelo<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> After Duppa&#8217;s visit to the Lakes in the summer of 1804, both Wordsworth and
                        Southey translated poems for Duppa&#8217;s <title>Life and Works of Michel Angelo Buonarroti, with his Poetry and Letters</title>,
                        which was published in 1806. Wordsworth translated one sonnet; Southey three sonnets and a madrigal. A further poem, &#8216;And
                        sweet it is to see in summer time&#8217;, was a joint effort, the first four stanzas by Wordsworth, the following five by Southey.
                        See Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Uncollected Translations of Michelangelo by Wordsworth and Southey&#8217;, <title>Review of English
                            Studies</title>, 14 (1938), 193&#8211;199.</note> &#8211; that I might not be the means of delaying you. You led me to expect longer
                    delay on your part &#8211; &amp; I on mine, willingly procrastinated a very difficult job in the hope that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> would arrive, of whom we are in daily expectation.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge, who was returning across Europe from Malta, did not arrive back in Britain until
                        August 1806.</note> However the very first thing which I shall do when sufficiently recovered to do any thing, shall be to go
                    thorough-stitch with the translations as well as I can.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letters are in tune to a miracle.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa wrote several passages of
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). The description
                        of the monuments in Westminster Abbey, in Letter 23, is an example of his contribution.</note> I like them exceedingly &amp;
                    do not see that they stand in any need of transcription, except in compassion to the Printer, for it must be confessed your
                    handwriting is the very perfection of unintelligibility. The first must come in about 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> or 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in the series. the other a little farther on. I wish you also to show him the Exhibition for 1802. There was a
                    picture of Opies<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The painter, John Opie (1761&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>). The picture,
                            <title>The Unfortunate Traveller</title>, was probably that which, under the title <title>The Dead Traveller and his
                            Faithful Dog</title>, sold for 10 guineas after Opie&#8217;s death in 1807.</note> of a dog watching the body of his Master,
                    worthy of much praise if he had not ridiculously ruined it by making the dog a fine fat combed-&amp;-washed parlour spaniel! <ref target="people.html#OpieAmelia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> O.</ref> actually borrowing the handsomest dog she saw in the streets
                    &#8211; to sit for the occasion. I saw this picture when first sketched, &amp; thought it one of the finest I had ever seen &#8211; so did
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &#8211; when finished it was spoilt by this folly. But I should like
                    just to say something civil of <ref target="people.html#OpieAmelia">Opie</ref> which may truly enough be done &lt;upon this
                    picture&gt; &#8722; tho I do not &amp; cannot like the man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your travelled Englishman will be a fit person to show him the Exhibition<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey refers to the fictional host (Mr. J.) of his Spanish traveller, Espriella, in <title>Letters from
                        England</title>.</note> &#8722; &amp; you may say what is to be said about Somerset House.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        On its institution in 1771 the Royal Academy was permitted to use seven large state apartments in Somerset House. The Royal
                        Academy moved to the new Somerset House, built by Sir William Chambers (1722&#8211;1796) in 1779. According to Kenneth Curry
                        (<title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, p. 403) Southey contributed the following entries to volumes VI (1807), VII (1808) and VIII (1813): Volume VI: &#8216;Vasco Lobeira&#8217;, 314&#8211;317; &#8216;Francisco Rodrigues Lobo&#8217;, 318; &#8216;Fernam Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Gregorio Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Francisco de Losa&#8217;, 344&#8211;345; &#8216;Joam de Lucena&#8217;, 371&#8211;372; &#8216;Miguel de Luna&#8217;, 388; &#8216;Fr. Francisco de Santo Agostinho Macedo&#8217;, 434&#8211;435, &#8216;El Enamorado Macias&#8217;, 437&#8211;438; &#8216;P. Fr. Pedro Malon de Chaide&#8217;, 506; &#8216;D. Jorge Manrique&#8217;, 523&#8211;524; &#8216;Don Juan Manuel&#8217;, 529&#8211;530; &#8216;Ausias March&#8217;, 542&#8211;543; &#8216;Juan de Mariana&#8217;, 555&#8211;557; &#8216;Vicente Mariner&#8217;, 558; &#8216;Luis de Marmol Carvajal&#8217;, 569; &#8216;P. M. Fr. Juan Marquez&#8217;, 574&#8211;575. Volume VII: &#8216;Juan de Mena&#8217;, 28&#8211;30; &#8216;Don Inigo Lopez de Mendoza&#8217;, 37&#8211;38; &#8216;D. Diego Hurtado de Mendoza&#8217;, 38&#8211;39; &#8216;Menezes&#8217;, 41&#8211;42; &#8216;Christoval de Mesa&#8217;, 59&#8211;60; &#8216;George de Montemayor&#8217;, 174&#8211;175; &#8216;Ambrosio de Morales&#8217;, 194&#8211;198; &#8216;Alonso de Castro Nunez&#8217;, 466; &#8216;Antonio de Naxara&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Abraham Nehemias&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Florian de Ocampo&#8217;, 471&#8211;472; &#8216;Fr. Diego de Olarte&#8217;, 487; &#8216;Fr. Andres de Olmos&#8217;, 497; &#8216;Jerome Osorio&#8217; [with Thomas Morgan (1752&#8211;1821)], 530&#8211;533; &#8216;Alonso de Ovalle&#8217;, 548; &#8216;Andres de Oviedo&#8217;, 555&#8211;556; &#8216;Gonzalo Fernandez de Oviedo&#8217;, 556&#8211;557; &#8216;Lorenzo de Padilla&#8217;, 578; &#8216;Pedro Paez&#8217;, 578&#8211;580; &#8216;D. Juan de Palafox y Mendoza&#8217;, 585. Volume VIII: &#8216;Josef de Ossau, Salas y Pellicer&#8217;, 25&#8211;26; Bartholom&#233; Pereira&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Luys Pereyra&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Antonio Perez&#8217;, 46&#8211;47; &#8216;Ruy de Pina&#8217;, 173; &#8216;Juan de Pineda&#8217;, 175; &#8216;Fernam Mendes Pinto&#8217;, 178&#8211;179; &#8216;Thome Pires&#8217;, 182&#8211;184; &#8216;Fernando de Pulgar&#8217;, 385.</note> With architecture &amp; the
                    arts it would be very foolish for me to meddle when you are at hand. &#8722; I have a third cargo ready to send off &#8211; or nearly ready &#8211;
                    as soon as I think <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is returned to London <del>&amp; will xx</del> in the way
                    to receive it. &#8211; If any chance should lead you to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> &#8211; or by <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref> &#8211; I should be obliged to you to take some of these Letters in your
                    pocket &#8211; &amp; show them to Artaxerxes,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s nickname for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, after the Persian emperor Artaxerxes I (also named Longimanus) who
                        reigned 465&#8211;424 BC.</note> that he may determine in what shape to print them. there will be 300 such pages, &#8211; I like two
                    handleable volumes better than one <del>large</del> thick octavo &#8211; but he will know which is best, <del>accor</del> in the <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster-Row</ref> sense of the word <del>x</del> good &amp; its degrees of comparison.
                    I shall be in town &#8211; if no ill fortune prevent me &#8211; by the end of March &#8211; but these Letters may go to press the beginning of
                    February.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Receive this, which was begun yester-evening &#8211; as a letter of excuse for not immediately translating what remains
                    to be done &#8211; &amp; a promissory note to do it as soon as I am able. I should be very sorry to occasion any delay. Your book will
                    be too late for this years review but I will take care of it in the next,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed Duppa&#8217;s <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806)
                        in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 411&#8211;425.</note> either myself &#8211; or by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>. And I will see what can be done in the Critical thro
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> brother who writes the orthodoxy there &#8211; If his belief in the 9
                    &amp; thirty articles can be made useful to your Life of M. Angelo &#8211; there will be as odd an instance of cause &amp; effect as one
                    shall easily meet with &#8211;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Wordsworth (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>) was a
                        scholar and apologist in the <title>Critical Review</title> for the Church of England, of which the 39 Articles of Religion,
                        of 1563, established the basis of belief.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1805-12-30">Monday. Dec. 30. 1805 &#8211; </date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Your Tuscan<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni [Michelangelo]
                            (1475&#8211;1564) was born in Caprese, near Arezzo, in Tuscany.</note> seems to me to have very Opera-House sort of ideas of
                        poetry &amp; not to know what is good from what is bad. &#8211; I wish you could point out in your errata that the Cancion<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa&#8217;s edition of Michelangelo&#8217;s poems formed the appendix to his <title>Life and
                                Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806), of which Southey had seen an
                            early presentation copy. Duppa did correct the mistake in numbering in an errata slip at the end of the work.</note> &#8211; as
                        I formerly mentioned &#8211; has been erroneously printed &#8211; each stanza numbered as a seperate poem. How such a blunder could have
                        been made in the first edition is wonderful. Should it be detected by any reviewer he will say you printed the poems without
                        understanding them. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>