<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1616</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2738</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1616" type="letter">
        <head>1616. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1809-04-21">21 April [1809]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Endorsement: 21 April 1809<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ APR
                        24/ 1809<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written so that the other page may be torn off &amp; consigned to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &#8211; Have you heard that the Bishop of Durham <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Shute Barrington
                        (1734&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Durham from 1791 to 1826.</note> is writing an answer to that said defence of the
                        Mission.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication
                            of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in
                            his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the
                            Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity&#8230; By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the
                            Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to
                            India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> I suppose the good old
                    man smells heresy &amp; will take for his motto Non defensoribus istis &#8211; <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin
                        translates as &#8216;not such defenders&#8217;, and is from Virgil, <title>Aeneid</title>, II, V, 21.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The rejection of your Cidiana I rather impute to some implacable enemy against me than any other cause, &#8211; in whom,
                    or for what cause I know not, &#8211; but the M. Review has manifested it for the last ten years.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Bedford to write a review of his <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) for the <title>Monthly
                            Review</title>; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 28 February 1809, Letter 1590. The rejection mentioned here was
                        temporary: the book was reviewed in complimentary terms in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 63 (1810), 131&#8211;144.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tomorrow or Saturday at the latest, I expect to send off my Portugueze article,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez; com as Palavras Portuguezas Propriamente
                            Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo d&#8217;Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May,
                        1809), 268&#8211;292.</note> by post, as <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has instructed me. The American one a few
                    days afterwards.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763&#8211;1837), <title>American Annals; or, a
                            Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title>, in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2
                        (November 1809), 319&#8211;337.</note> My work necessarily takes up more time than ordinary reviewing, because in both cases it is
                    wholly without extracts to fill it out. I shall be glad to receive the Hesiod,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hesiod was
                        a Greek pastoral poet thought to have flourished between 750&#8211;650 BC. Charles Abraham Elton (1778&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>)
                        published <title>The Remains of Hesiod the Ascraean: Translated from the Greek into English</title> in 1809. Southey did not
                        review this work.</note> which I have an inclination to read carefully, but wish to be paid for so doing. About the desire of
                    limiting all articles to a single sheet I made no mistake, &amp; am glad to find that <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffard</ref> perceives the folly &amp; impracticability of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You, in common with all Sir J Moores friends must be sorry for the publication of their late documents, which so
                    incontestably prove him to have unequal to the situation in which he was placed.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        diplomatist <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">John Hookham Frere</ref> was sent to Spain as minister-plenipotentiary
                        to the Central Junta on 4 October 1808 and when the French marched on Madrid he urged Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), the Commander of the
                        British forces in northern Spain to also advance upon Madrid despite his inclination to retreat through Portugal. After the
                        disastrous retreat to Corunna, Frere was blamed for this advice and recalled by the British government. After some of Frere&#8217;s
                        and Moore&#8217;s correspondence was read out in the Commons on 27 April, Moore&#8217;s side of matters was presented in James Moore
                        (1763&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British Army in Spain, Commanded by His Excellency
                            Sir John Moore. Authenticated by Official Papers and Original Letters</title> (1809). Frere&#8217;s correspondence with Moore
                        was published in 1810 in a work entitled <title>To the British Nation is Presented by Colonel Venault de Charmilly, Knight of
                            the Royal and Military Order of St. Louis, the Narrative of his Transactions in Spain with the Rt. Hon. Hookham Frere, His
                            Britannic Majesty&#8217;s Minister Plenipotentiary, and Lt. Gen. Sir John Moore, K.B. Commander of the British Forces: with the
                            Suppressed Correspondence of Sir J. Moore: Being a Refutation of the Calumnies Invented Against Him, and Proving that He
                            was Never Acquainted with General Morla</title>.</note> And what madness to publish such an account of an army to which
                    Parliament had voted thanks! &#8211; I am much pleased with <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Freres</ref> part of the
                    correspondence, &#8211; &amp; not a little gratified to find him confirming every opinion which <hi rend="ital">I</hi> have constantly
                    confessed upon the subject of our campaign in Spain. Your last letter of politics is not quite in unison with my feelings &amp;
                    foreseeing &#8211; Things are come to this dilemma, &#8211; reform or ruin, &#8211; &amp; on one of these horns I pray to God that John Bull may
                    give his Damned [illegible word] a deadly toss. I M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford am a pensioner &#8211; so much the worse for me, &#8211; but
                    I am not the worse for the pension, &#8211; &amp; there is not a man in England who would &lt;more&gt; gladly see the D of Y.&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in
                        Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited
                        by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return
                        for which promotion was arranged. In May 1811 the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent</ref> reinstated
                        his brother as Commander-in-Chief of the army, a post which he held for the rest of his life.</note> &amp; his Majestys
                    precious ministers exalted according to their deserts than I RS. should do. As for a new ministry I have no expectation of a
                    better. &#8211; one set is as bad as the other, &amp; I rather hate the whigs the worst, because they pretend to some honesty, which I
                    must do the in-rogues the justice to say they do not. But a constitutional reform would save the country, &amp; nothing short of
                    that will be of any avail.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had the Mumps &amp; have been in the Dumps, by rhyme &amp; <del>by rea</del> by reason thereof. &#8211; Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Godson</ref> (my Moon I call him &#8211; but he insists upon it that he is not a Moon &#8211; his
                    answer this morning to the application ran thus &#8216;A son I am, &amp; a boy&#8217;, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert
                        Southey</ref> I <hi rend="ital">are</hi>, &amp; a good boy &amp; a nice boy) &#8211; that long parenthesis puts me to the expence of
                    another nomination case. Your Godson, then I say, would soon find the way to your heart, for never did the same number of <hi rend="ital">round</hi> inches contain more sweetness, more quaintness, &#8211; &amp; I might almost add beauty to the list. Frank
                    him down one of those <del>books</del> picture<del>s</del>-books which will go in a letter, &amp; I will tell him his Godfather
                    sent it Oh how his bright eyes widen &amp; sparkle! &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> yrs as ever.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-04-21">April 21 </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>