<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1133</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2255</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1133" type="letter">
        <head>1133. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1805-12-17">17 December
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ DEC 20/ 1805<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Inclosed is a draft on <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> for &#163;40.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We daily expect to hear of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> arrival.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had been acting as Public Secretary to the British Civil Commissioner in Malta. Though
                        due to return home, he did not arrive in England until August 1806, and never went back to live in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</note> He left Malta early in September. his own letters say that he was to go
                    to Naples &amp; that Sir A. Ball<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Alexander Ball (1757&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), the
                        Civil Commissioner and <hi rend="ital">de facto</hi> governor of Malta, from 1803 until his death.</note> was to use all his
                    influence to get him sent with dispatches overland by our Embassador there, &#8211; at any rate he was coming by land. Since this
                    letters have been received by <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> from Stoddart<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), writer and lawyer, who from 1803 to 1807 was an advocate
                        for the king and the admiralty at Malta, in which capacity he became an associate of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>.</note> saying that he had heard from Coleridge who had got as
                    far as Trieste on his way. I conceive he would be at Vienna about the time of Macks rascally surrender<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant Field Marshal Mack von Leiberich (1752&#8211;1828), commander of the Austrian forces defeated and
                        captured by the French army at the Battle of Ulm in October 1805.</note> &#8211; in time to get off, &#8211; &amp; that he will make a
                    sweep round thro Prussia. However, tho in good hope, I am somewhat more anxious than I chuse to say to <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> . </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Count<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s nickname for <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> after his employment with Count Zamoyski (dates unknown) as a tutor in Poland.</note> leaves us on
                    Friday for London. I have put him in the way of making a book which, if he can find means of subsisting, while it is in hand, will
                    certainly be productive to him. Specimens of the English Prose Writers &#8211; chronologically arranged, with brief biographical &amp;
                    critical notices.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett&#8217;s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Earliest
                            Times to the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title> was published in three volumes with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> in 1807. This compilation formed a companion work to George Ellis,
                            <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn 1801, 3rd edn 1803) and Southey&#8217;s own anthology,
                        jointly edited with Bedford, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> I have given him a list which
                    is as compleat as I can make it, &amp; marked for him as many Specimens from the old &amp; curious books here as will make at
                    least a quarter part of a volume. <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> will give him some help, &amp; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> some. He is in a fair way of making by these hearty
                    shoves a book of much respectability, &amp; of very likely sale, &#8211; &amp; of acquiring more knowledge during the operation than he
                    would ever have got by any other means. I take no small merit to myself for having discovered something which he can do, &#8211; a
                        <del>work</del> &lt;thing&gt; nearly as difficult as to double the cube. You will not say to any body what I say in this tone
                    of him. Poor fellow he wants &lt;about&gt; five hundred a year to make him in good health, good spirits, &amp; a favourite with
                    every body. However he is much better than when he arrived.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am ominously fearful that another batch of my criticism has been burnt at the Printers! &amp; dread every day to
                    see a letter from <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> beginning &#8216;I am sorry to say &amp;c.&#8217; Luckily the Review
                    can have been but just begun, &amp; I am in no danger of being a pecuniary sufferer, <del>except by</del> as &lt;eventually&gt; in
                    the former case, &#8211; except by loss of time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must go to London as soon as the reviewing season is over &#8211; which will be in March &#8211; Is there any chance of
                    seeing you there? If not I shall at any rate see you at Bristol either then or early in the Autumn. It is not possible to
                    determine any thing about taking <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> till we see what turn political affairs may
                    take. If a continental peace be patched up <del>x</del> most likely Bonaparte will then bully the Portugueze &#8211; But I not much
                    apprehensive of this. Prussia will either act as a mediator, or turn the scale against him, &#8211; the former the more probable, the
                    latter the more desirable event. If Prussia takes part against I expect to see an attempt made to reestablish Poland. it is not
                    likely to succeed, because all the peasantry are better off under their present Masters than they were under their former ones, &#8211;
                    their nobles have posts &amp; pensions, &amp; their men of enterprise are engaged in the service of their new countries. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has left me no wish for the reappearance of Poland as a separate state, tho
                    they are a noble race of men.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Little Edith</ref> has for these two nights been very unwell with incipient
                        <del>ja</del> jaundice. We have just given calomel<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The common name for mercury
                        chloride, which was taken for various ailments.</note> &amp; opium, &amp; she seems better &#8211; tho the remedy <del>has</del>
                    cannot have taken any effect. You would be surprized to see how forward she is in her tongue.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Espriella gets on well.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> I have told
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> it may go press by the first of February, by which time half will be
                    transcribed. &#8211; it is my <del>xxxx</del> leisure work, taken up at intervals, but a months set-to would compleat it. Both that
                    &amp; the Cid<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note>
                    will be published before the summer, if no ugly accident interfere. So that I have good reason to expect this next year will
                    better my finances materially. And from Lisbon I shall return rich with materials.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s projected visit to Portugal never took place.</note> If <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir
                        Domine&#8217;s</ref> love adventure do not stand in his way<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> While at the home of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> near Ambleside, Henry Southey had met Emma Noel (d. 1873). She was
                        the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of Exton Park, Rutland (1759&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel
                        in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple&#8217;s plans to
                        marry, the relationship soon ended; see letter 1117 of this edition.</note> I shall wish him to go over with me, or join me
                    there, &amp; be my travelling companion thro the whole of the northern provinces.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Basileus</ref>. it is
                    a great loss that he is not at hand to look over Espriella with a foreigners eye.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-12-17">Tuesday Dec. 17. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>