<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1237</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2359</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, ed.,
                        &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico e
                            Geografico Brasileiro, 178 (1943).  Previously  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, ed., &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey
                        a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro,
                        178 (1943), 35&#8211;37.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1237" type="letter">
        <head>1237. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">John Theodore Koster</ref>, <date when="1806-11-11">11
                    November 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, ed.,
                        &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e
                            Geografico Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943)<lb />Previously published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, ed., &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey
                        a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro</title>,
                        178 (1943), 35&#8211;37.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1806-11-11">Nov. 11. 1806.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are all truly rejoiced at the good tidings communicated in your letter. The newspapers had led me to expect a
                    different conclusion to the contest, it would have given me great pleasure to have seen General Tarleton ousted by any body, but
                    the election of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Mr. Roscoe</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Banastre Tarleton, 1st Baronet (1754&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and politician, was MP for Liverpool
                        between 1801 and 1806, when he was ousted at the election by William Roscoe.</note> is something more than a victory over this
                    fellow. It is a triumph of literature, of intellect, of humanity, of liberty: &#8211; of the good principle over the evil one. Your city
                    has in part redeemed itself from the infamy of its accursed slave trade, by sending such a representative to Parliament.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since you saw my brothers,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>.</note> a great family event
                    has happened here &#8211; I have had a son born, who is heir apparent to more Portuguese books perhaps than any one not a subject of
                    Portugal. We call him <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>. An infant&#8217;s life is so precarious that I do not
                    venture to form any hopes about him, but if it please God that he should live and take but half as much delight in these said
                    books as his father does, I think he will not be dissatisfied with his inheritance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref>  (I beg his pardon &#8211; the Doctor I should have said) will
                    have told you that I go on as usual in this delightful place. Nothing is so regular as I am, except the Church clock, and if there
                    is at any time a difference between us, I believe in my conscience it is the clock that is wrong. I have several things in hand of
                    more or less importance. One is a new edition of Palmerin of England,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was
                        preparing for the press, an English translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title>, published in 4
                        volumes in 1807.</note> corrected from the Portuguese, which I think I can prove to be the original. You have no taste for
                    such things, but you would enjoy Don Quixote more entirely after reading them.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miguel
                        de Cervantes Saavedra (1547&#8211;1616), <title>Don Quixote de la Mancha</title>.</note> Another is the Chronicle of the Cid<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> &#8211; which is
                    of higher character and claims. To this there will be some valuable preliminary and explanatory matter, and the book itself,
                    filled up from all the existing documents which Spanish literature supplies, is I believe, the most curious picture of manners
                    that has ever appeared. I shall here dispose of some of the materials which I had collected as preliminaries for my Portuguese
                        history,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected, but never completed, &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note>
                    relating to the state of society in that country after the Moorish conquest and before its establishment as a separate Christian
                    state, because I shall have no room there for anything which can with equal propriety be placed elsewhere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has been returned about a fortnight,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had travelled abroad to Malta for his health in 1804, taking up a temporary post there as Public
                        Secretary to the British Civil Commissioner. He arrived back in England in August 1806 but, though he returned to Keswick for
                        a short time, did not live there again.</note> still hypochondriacal but certainly in better health of body. He talks of
                    delivering Lectures at the Royal Institution upon the Principles common to the Fine Arts.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> He did not in fact lecture there until 1808, on the subject of Shakespeare and Milton.</note> His adventures in Italy
                    have been very interesting. The second Inquisitor at Rome, Piccolomini, brother to the Prince,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In March 1806 Napoleon put pressure on the Pope to remove English, Russian, Sardinian, and Swedish
                        subjects from his dominions, and to close his ports to the ships of those powers with which France was at war. Coleridge
                        elaborated several stories, some taller than others, dramatising his departure from Rome. In <title>Biographia
                            Literaria</title>, 2 vols (London and Princeton, 1983), I, p. 216, he wrote of having been &#8216;rescued&#8217; from arrest by &#8216;the
                        kindness of a noble Benedictine, and the gracious connivance of the good old man, the present Pope.&#8217; The Pope in question was
                        Pius VII (1742&#8211;1823), elected 1800; the noble Benedictine has not been traced. The Piccolomini family of Sienna, powerful in
                        Rome and the church from the twelfth to the seventeenth centuries, was less prominent by 1800. No inquisitor of that name has
                        been traced.</note> gave him timely notice that an order to serve the English had arrived, and obtained passports for him a
                    few hours before it was carried into execution. Lucien Bonaparte,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte
                        (1775&#8211;1840), brother of Napoleon.</note> advised him if he had ever written anything against his brother to take care of
                    himself, indeed, I have no doubt that had he been taken he would have been murdered like Palm<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Johann Philipp Palm (1768&#8211;1806), a bookseller from Nuremberg, Germany, who was executed by a French
                        firing squad on 26 August 1806 for publishing and distributing libellous pamphlets about France and Napoleon.</note> or
                    Captain Wright.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wesley Wright (1769&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer. In
                        May 1804 his ship, the <title>Vincejo</title> was captured off the coast of France by the French navy. Accused of having
                        landed royalist agents, he was imprisoned in Paris, where he died in solitary confinement. He was thought by the British to
                        have been murdered.</note> Lucien leads a wise and happy life; he is entirely a domestic man, passionately fond of his wife
                    and children, and it is believed a true lover of liberty. He is greatly beloved at Rome. The general feeling throughout Italy is
                    an utter dread and abhorrence of the French, but an utter contempt for every body else, which it must be confessed on our part, we
                    heartily deserve. In Naples and Sicily however all the intellect, talents and property of both countries are on the side of the
                    French, as they would be on the side of the Devil, to get rid of a more rascally King<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Ferdinand I (1751&#8211;1825), king variously of Naples, Sicily, and the Two Sicilies from 1759 until his death. His feudal reign
                        was opposed by liberals who allied themselves with the invading French forces which occupied Naples in 1799&#8211;1800 and
                        1806&#8211;1815. Ferdinand withdrew to Sicily, where his government was directed by the British.</note> and more rascally government
                    than the Devil himself could have the heart to establish among them. But conduct with respect to those countries has been, like
                    the whole conduct of the English government, stupid and senseless to the last degree. But this is a heart-sickening subject, for
                    things are so bad that they must be worse before they can be better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All our family desire their remembrances. I shall perhaps see you in the spring when I mean to go to Lisbon,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not return to Lisbon.</note> if it be not shut against the English, at any
                    rate to London.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours very truly,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>