<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1484</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2606</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D (undated
                        letters).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1484" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1484" type="letter">
        <head>1484. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-07">[July
                        1808]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. M. P./
                        Acton/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D (undated
                        letters)<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: From the internal evidence of Southey&#8217;s catarrh attack and his progress with the
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> which was published in 1808.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Colonel Shipleys Mort Arthur<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lt. Colonel William Shipley (1778&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a neighbour of Wynn&#8217;s in north Wales, married Wynn&#8217;s sister Charlotte in 1806. He owned a rare
                        printing of Sir Thomas Malory (1415/18&#8211;1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Morte d&#8217;Arthur,</title> probably through his father
                        William Davies Shipley (1745&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>).</note> never went out of my possession, &amp; hardly out of my sight.
                    The extract <del>which</del> I made from the Preface myself, &amp; positively certain I am that it could not possibly have
                    received any injury in <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> house. I have somewhere about half the Mort Arthur in
                    that same edition, &#8211; which was lent out long ago &amp; whether I shall ever be able to recover it is somewhat doubtful, &#8211; but if
                    that be the case, &amp; the leaf which is missing in Colonel Shipleys happens to be in it, I will very gladly supply the defect in
                    his, &#8211; my own fragment being fit for nothing else, but doing such a good office.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two causes will prevent me from falling into the fault against which you caution me. a conviction that I am in
                    danger of it, &#8211; &amp; the necessity there is for compressing as much as possible, <del>xxx</del> to gain room. Unluckily the
                    History of Brazil<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> published in three volumes
                        from 1810 to 1819.</note> with which I must begin gives me no opportunity of committing this fault &#8211; &lt;it does&gt; not
                    conmence till an age when all beauty of costume was over.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The claim of eleven copies is very oppressive, &amp; your plan for meeting it is the best possible. If it be
                    persisted in, move that the several libraries entitled to these copies be on their part bound to print catalogues &#8211; to one of
                    which every person paying his tax of these said copies, shall be entitled on demand, &#8211; this, &amp; some new regulations for making
                    the books there accessible, would be of service to literature.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is discussing
                        Wynn&#8217;s participation in parliamentary debates, during June 1808, concerning a <title>Bill for the further encouragement of
                            Learning in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, by securing to the Libraries of the Universities, and other
                            public libraries, copies of all newly-printed books, and books reprinted with additions, and by further securing the
                            copies and copyright of printed Books to the authors of such books, or their assigns, for a time to be
                        limited</title>.</note> &#8211; I do not see the force of your reasons against the entail of copy-right in the family of the author.
                    Annotators might always make their terms with the proprietors: &amp; if they could not the example of Warton Upton &amp;
                        Douce<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Three editors of other poets&#8217; works: Thomas Warton (1728&#8211;1790;
                            <title>DNB</title>) published <title>Observations on the Faerie Queene of Spenser</title> in 1754 and a <title>History of
                            English Poetry</title>, finishing three volumes (1774, 1777, 1781). The fragment of a fourth volume was issued in 1790. A
                        revised edition in four volumes was published in 1824, incorporating annotations and other material by Francis Douce
                        (1757&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). Douce published <title>Illustrations of Shakespeare, and of Ancient Manners</title> in 1807.
                        John Upton (1707&#8211;1760; <title>DNB</title>), Warton&#8217;s friend, edited and annotated Arrian&#8217;s Epictetus in two volumes
                        (1739&#8211;1741); and made a new edition, with glossary and notes, of Spenser&#8217;s <title>Faerie Queene</title> (1758)
                            (<title>DNB</title>).</note> might advantageously be followed. Is it not certain that those works which are known to be,
                    or estimated to be the best in the language, have <del>xxx</del> lain in obscurity for a longer time, than ever this enlarged term
                    which the new bill purposes to allow us? look for instance at Hartley on Man:<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> David
                        Hartley (1705&#8211;1757; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Observations on Man, His Frame, His Duty, and His Expectations</title>
                        (1749).</note> a book scarcely heard of till it had been published forty years. &#8211; As for myself I think I have devised a
                    method of eluding the laws of copyright, &#8211; so as to give my family the whole term which the law is pleased to allow, &#8211; &amp; that
                    is by the simple plan of never publishing another poem while I live, &#8211; but writing on as sedulously as I can, &amp; leaving them
                    for posthumous publication. They will then become valuable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have more hope from Spain than you seem to feel. You will see in the Review of Semples Travels what I said upon
                    that subject twelve months ago.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 118&#8211;130.</note> It has long been my opinion that if we ever lived to see the
                    deliverance of Europe, Spain was the country in which it would begin, &amp; this I thought, because in no other country does there
                    exist so strong a feeling of patrotism &amp; notional pride. As for our Ministry &#8211; &amp; especially as for our War Office, &#8211; oh my
                    dear Wynn what a lucky thing it was for the Spaniards that Bonaparte kidnapped their government for them! &#8211; Spain will deliver
                    herself by her own right arm, &#8211; the spirit of liberty has broken out; &#8211; nothing else could possibly check the power of France,
                    &amp; it is not alone the power of France that can extinguish it. &#8211; I lose all patience at hearing Whitbread talk of peace.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), brewer, Whig politician and advocate of a negotiated
                        peace with Napoleon.</note> That man has drank his own rascally porter so long, that there is not a drop of
                    &lt;unadulterated&gt; honest English blood left in his veins.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If your mountain &amp; mine could be bought a little nearer together, I should not have much scruple as to what
                    became of the flat country that seperates them. <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoes</ref> pamphlets have damned one
                    party in Liverpool &amp; the other party damned themselves for the love of General Tarleton &amp; the Slave Trade.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roscoe&#8217;s <title>Considerations on the Causes and Consequences of the Present War</title>
                        (February 1808) and <title>Remarks on the Proposals Made to Great Britain for Opening Negotiations for Peace in the Year
                            1807</title> (1808). These pamphlets were answered by <title>A Letter to W. Roscoe, Containing Strictures on His Late
                            Publication Entitled &#8216;Considerations on the Causes, Objects and Consequences of the Present War&#8217;</title> (1808) and
                            <title>A Review of Mr. Roscoe&#8217;s Considerations on the Causes of the Present War, and the Expediency of a Peace with
                            France</title> (1808). General Sir Banastre Tarleton, 1st Baronet (1754&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>) was MP for Liverpool
                        from 1790&#8211;1812 and an opponent of the campaign to abolish the slave trade.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You shall soon have Kehama<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> in sequence as it proceeds &#8211; It has been much altered since <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> sheets were transcribed, &#8211; &amp; a good deal of rhyme inserted, &#8211;
                    For this last fortnight I have been confined by a severe catarrh, &#8211; to call it a cold could not express the severity of this
                    disease with me. I am still suffering from it, &#8211; but hope it is abating. Yours has been a more serious attack &#8211; &amp; I hope you
                    have not travelled too soon after it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>The Cid will be ready in about three weeks &#8211; but I have not yet got the translations which <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> promised me.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Three of Frere&#8217;s
                            translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the
                                Cid</title>. Frere had been Britain&#8217;s ambassador to Portugal while Southey&#8217;s uncle had lived there; from 1808&#8211;1809 he
                            was ambassador to Spain.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>