<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1328</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2450</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS
                    Eng.lett.d.110.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1328" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1328" type="letter">
        <head>1328. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1807-05-28">28 May
                        1807</date>
          </head><p>MS: Bodleian Library, MS
                    Eng.lett.d.110<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-05-28">Thursday night. May 28. 1807. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">brother of mine</ref> is, as you may well suppose, a thorn in the
                    flesh. He writes me a penitent letter, &amp; a good one, in a hand like a stable boys: but his Priest has not taught him that
                    there can be no absolution without full confession. He denies the charge about the French prisoners &#8211; my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> heard it at Bristol, &amp; said to me &#8216;you may be sure I did not enquire into this
                    matter&#8217; &#8211; &#8211; it is certain that for some misconduct of this kind, involving a criminal charge, he was obliged to leave the
                    regiment, &#8211; &amp; it is very lucky for him the horse was stopt as it was, for he could have had no intention of returning with it
                    when he <del>xxx</del> hired it, &amp; it is better he should be liable to an arrest for debt, than make an appearance for
                    horse-stealing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He writes penitently now, &amp; one who did know him so thoroughly and from his youth up as I do, might easily give
                    credit to him. Hopeless however as I am from a deep conviction that he is destitute of any moral sense &amp; has been blind of
                    heart from his birth, &#8211; I am well aware that I must not shut my own against him, while there is any possibility, how faint soever,
                    of restoring him. In my last letter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, [c. 18 May 1807],
                        Letter 1324.</note> I stated fully to you what my circumstances were, &amp; that statement has shown you how utterly unable I
                    am to meet the heavy expence of fitting him out in life anew, were it practicable to get him a situation, which as yet while his
                    character is unreclaimed, it is not, &#8211; or were it prudent if practicable. My circumstances however by Gods blessing, will yearly
                        <del>xxx</del> improve, &amp;, as I told him, whenever he learns to demean himself decently &amp; to do his duty in any
                    situation let it be as humble as it may, he shall not find me deficient in brotherly offices.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing it is certain can reclaim him. but bitter suffering. Some experience of a vagabond life he has had, &amp;
                    he must have more, it is prudent for his sake, &amp; necessary for mine, &#8211; for now I cannot lend him a helping hand, nor would I
                    yet if I could. But I shall see you before the year closes, &#8211; &amp; then, if he lives respectfully meanwhile (<del>for</del>
                    &lt;as&gt; &#8211; in any situation a man may be respectable) I will look after him, <del>&amp; if xxx xxx xxx</del>. Do not tell him
                    this, lest he should think of making his way to me, which would be of all things the most unpleasant &amp; disquieting. Only let
                    him know that I have never lost sight of him, &amp; never shall, &#8211; that if he does his duty I will do mine, &#8211; that there are not
                    three more affectionate brothers living than his fathers sons, &#8211; it is his fault that they are not four, &amp; will be his fault
                    if they are not one day made so. But that he must be aware his promises of amendment are not lightly to be credited &amp; that
                    some apprenticeship to repentance is necessary for one who has so long set shame at defiance, &amp; been the shame &amp; sorrow of
                    his family. &#8211; Many &amp; many are the plans which I could build upon his talents, were their but a foundation of morality <del>for
                        them</del> to rest upon, &#8211; but when the heart is naught &#8211; &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present he is utterly ignorant of the common rudiments of learning; &#8211; still his extraordinary talents might soon
                    recover the time he has lost; &#8211; &amp; if he can be trusted when I come into Devonshire, &amp; will go thro two years severe study,
                    I will enable him to maintain himself after that time by literature as a profession, &#8211; which so far from disqualifying him from
                    any &lt;other&gt; means of support, will recommend him to it, but will support him if he has no other, &amp; give him a rank in
                    life which nothing else could do. But there must be proof of good behaviour first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will tell you what is in my mind, do not let him know it. <del>xxx</del> As for the army, were it practicable &#8211;
                    you know that for one with a lack of morals it is the direct road to the Devil. You <del>know</del> &lt;may perceive&gt; that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edwards</ref> talents are equal to any thing, &amp; will give me credit for knowing enough
                    of literature to be able to direct him. I would board him one year with a Welsh clergyman, &amp; one year with a Scotch one, to
                    learn the two Celtic dialects thoroughly. after which half a year in Ireland might suffice to acquire the third. He should then
                    come home to me, &#8211; I would procure all the <del>materials</del> &lt;remains&gt; which are preserved in the Welsh language, &amp;
                        <del>by xxx</del> &amp; with such help as I could give him by bringing my knowledge to bear upon the new materials which he
                    would then be able by mere translation to supply, &#8211; he should produce a work which would give him means to fit himself out for any
                    line of life which he might then prefer &#8211; if he should not by that time have acquired a love of letters. With my connections there
                    is no doubt of effecting this, &#8211; if he would only be his own friend, &#8211; but of that I confess that I despair. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will I dare say laugh at the <hi rend="ital">out-of-the-wayness</hi> of this scheme, &#8211; yet nothing is so
                    feasible, &amp; I am thus proposing for him what I should do with my own son, were he old enough. &#8211; Are you shaking your head
                    Lightfoot? So am I &#8211; not at the plan, but at <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edwards</ref> wretched want of principles,
                    which I verily believe, will frustrate every thing that can be done, as it has frustrated all that has been done, &amp; will make
                    him end as disagreeably as he has begun.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Excuse me for waiting till the season of franking returns, &#8211; the subject will plead my excuse.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s friend <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> was unable to frank
                        mail on Southey&#8217;s behalf if Parliament was not in session.</note> My book is not yet advertised &#8211; which I wonder at, &#8211; but
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has directions to send it you, together with Joan of Arc<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> New editions of <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1806) and <title>Madoc</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; I
                    look for a letter from you with some promised good news. Never regard franking, one item more will not perceptibly lengthen a
                    half-yearly bill for letters of half a yard long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> O Nicholas Wood you &amp; I are thirteen years older than we were when we parted &amp; I dare say you have lost the
                    dried piece of your thumb which was &lt;deposited&gt; <del>xxx</del> on the same shelf with Lactantius<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucius Caecilius Firmianus Lactantius (c. 240&#8211;320), the early Christian author of <title>The Divine
                            Institutions</title>.</note> &amp; in the same room with the Pot of Abomination. &#8211; I have preserved some college mementos,
                    &#8211; the four prints among them which I found in Radfords<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arundel Radford (d. 1824), a
                        student at Exeter College, Oxford, BA 1796.</note> rooms, &#8211; (one of which is that of Gaspar Poussin <del>xxx</del> which
                        <del>xxx</del> is the subject of one of my better <hi rend="ital">poemets</hi>:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        &#8216;Musings on a Landscape of Gaspar Poussin&#8217; was written in 1795 and published in Southey&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> (1797).</note>)
                    &#8211; my own breakfast cups, &amp; poor <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Sewards</ref> breakfast plates. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>