<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1064</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2186</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 72.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    319&#8211;322.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1064" type="letter">
        <head>1064. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1805-05-01">[1 May
                        1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ May 1st./ [ MS illegible]/ 1805<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 72<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    319&#8211;322.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> If my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> were not in the West Indies the French or the Devil
                    might go there without costing me a single oath, or a single uneasy thought. I hate the Planters &amp; the Creoles, &amp; have no
                    love for the Sugar &amp; Rum Merchants; and, moreover one good lesson is wanting to teach this country that as the main use of
                    going to war is to be securely in peace at last, nothing can be so absurd as the restitution of the enemy&#8217;s strongholds, when once
                    you have been at the trouble &amp; expense of conquering them. Damnation &#8211; at what a price were the French islands purchased last
                    war! thousands &amp; thousands of fine fellows thrown overboard to the sharks, or buried to be dug up by the land crabs. And at
                    what a waste of life have we kept this miserable squadron under Sir Samuel Hood<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore
                        (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), in command of the fleet in which Thomas
                        Southey served until he was superseded by Admiral Sir Alexander Forrester Inglis Cochrane (1758&#8211;1832) in 1805.</note> paid to
                    pick up prizes &amp; send them into harbour &#8211; for the French fleet to come &amp; take them out again. The Romans were the only
                    people who ever went wisely to work. &#8211; I am very uncomfortable about poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. it had
                    been so long my inclination to see him an Admiral at last, that I don&#8217;t like any of these cursed interruptions which are so likely
                    to put an end to his best prospects &#8211; &amp; to him too. &#8211; He had just sent prizes into S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincents which would
                    have paid him 1000&#163;,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Vincent was an island in the southern part of the Windward
                        Islands of the West Indies. It had been ceded to the British by the French in 1763. In December 1804 HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas Southey was a lieutenant, captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the
                        ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with
                        cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict,
                        but Southey was concerned that the arrival of the French Mediterranean Fleet in the West Indies, which had sailed from Toulon
                        in March 1805, would mean the loss of the vessels.</note> &#8211; &amp; these of course are gone with everything else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The grandest of all Parleurs has parleyed to some purpose for his own credit. but it is sickening to see how that
                    knot of boobies called the Administration are going thro thick &amp; thin to shelter an old rogue!<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Speaker (&#8216;Parleur&#8217;) of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>,
                        had given his casting vote in the House of Commons in support of a motion of censure of Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville
                        (1742&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. During
                        1802&#8211;1805 Dundas&#8217;s misuse of public funds when Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800) was being investigated by a Commission
                        of Inquiry; its report led to the motion of censure.</note> My hope is that they &lt;will&gt; so irretrievably implicate
                    themselves with him in the general odium as to damn themselves for ever &amp; ever Amen. Oh Se&#241;or Juan Manrique<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;John Rickman&#8217;.</note> there are a number of good heads in this island of ours &#8211; but
                    there are also a number of great men who would be a great deal better if they &lt;had&gt; a little brains in their heads &#8211; or else
                    no brains at all.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am correcting Joan of Arc for a third edition &#8211; merely weeding out a thousand mean &amp; miserable parts which
                    provoke me when I see them.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of Joan of Arc was published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> in 1806. For the alterations to the poem, see <title>Robert Southey:
                            Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), I.</note> but this is trouble &#8211; &amp; I
                    have nothing but my trouble for my pains &#8211; the copy right having been sold &#8211; when I had no other means of getting bread to eat.
                    However the book has paid me well in setting me up in the world &#8211; &amp; I owe it this amends. &#8211; My quarto it is to be feared will
                    not sell, because it is a quarto.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published in an expensive
                        quarto format, costing 2 guineas.</note> I am got into a good humour with it since it has been published. Yet if I did not
                    play the boy very often &amp; the fool quite often enough, that poem would make me think I had grown old before my time. it is in
                    so sober a tone of thought, &amp; thoughtful feeling, &#8211; &amp; its brightest parts have the colouring of an evening sunshine. &#8211; The
                    best omen I have heard of its well-doing is that Martin Burney<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Burney (c.
                        1788&#8211;1853) was the son of Southey&#8217;s friend <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">James Burney</ref>. He was afflicted with a
                        paralysis of one side of his face, as Southey observed to Coleridge in letter 952 of this edition. Martin Burney became a
                        barrister and a close friend of <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref> and <ref target="people.html#LambMaryAnne">his sister</ref>. </note> likes it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You were quite mistaken about the Abergavenny. there was no misconduct whatever &#8211; except in the pilot for running
                    her aground. I can positively &amp; undeniably convince you of this.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> After John Wordsworth
                        (1772&#8211;1805), captain of the East Indiaman, the <hi rend="ital">Earl of Abergavenny</hi>, went down with his ship on the
                        Shambles rocks off Portland Bill, on 5 February 1805, rumours circulated blaming him for negligence.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref> has sent me down a print of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to William
                        Say&#8217;s (1768&#8211;1834) 1805 mezzotint after James Northcote&#8217;s (1746&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>) portrait of Coleridge 1804.</note> &#8211;
                    which if it resembles any one has a distant likeness to <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count Burnetski</ref> &#8211; having
                    exactly his eyes &amp; hair.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A Frenchman&#8217;s prize-essay on the Reformation has come here to be reviewed. <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Charles Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay on the Spirit and Influence of the
                            Reformation of Luther</title>, tr. B Lambert (dates unknown) (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4
                        (1806), 177&#8211;187.</note> he has been schooled in Germany, &amp; has written better than I thought a Frenchman would have
                    written, or the French Institute have ventured to approve upon such a subject. These reviewals which have any bearing towards any
                    historical subjects I like well enough, &amp; regard them as a good way of getting at my own opinions, &amp; bringing them into
                    some order in a first sketch &#8211; &amp; being paid for it. Villars has not fairly stated the evils of the Reformation &#8211; he forgets
                    the death-stop which it put to the spread of Xtianity, which I regard as the greatest &amp; best means of civilizing the savage
                    world. I have also 1. a Life of Sir Walter <hi rend="ital">Ralegh</hi> as the name is spelt<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848), <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805) in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 477&#8211;483.</note> &#8211; which ought to be cut down from two quartos as thin as
                    myself, into an article for the Biog. Brit.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Biographia Britannica</title> (1st
                        edn, 6 vols, 1747&#8211;1766; 2nd edn, 5 vols, 1778&#8211;1793).</note> 2. Philips Present State of Peru,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The Present State of Peru, Comprising its Geography, Topography,
                            Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and Manners of its Inhabitants; Embellished by ... Engravings of
                            Costumes</title> (1805) was published by Richard Phillips (1767&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>). Southey reviewed this work in
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 49&#8211;60.</note> of which I knew the history before the book reached me. it
                    is exactly such as a Present state of England would be made up in Peru from a stray volume of the Monthly Magazine, &amp; a print
                    of the Kings procession [MS torn] S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls after his recovery, or of the Lord Mayors Show. 3. Lindley&#8217;s
                    narrative of his imprisonment at Bahia<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Lindley (dates unknown),
                            <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ... with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and
                            Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto Seguro</title> (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806),
                        27&#8211;32.</note> &#8211; not very much to the credit of <del>xx</del>my friends the Port. but Mr Lindley should not go smuggling. &#8211; In
                    my history<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> I am coming
                    to a splendid period &#8211; the great struggle with the Turks in India &#8211; at the siege of Dio, &#8211; one of the most extraordinary on
                        record.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Siege of Diu in Gujurat, India (1538) occurred when a combined fleet of
                        Turkey, Egypt, Venice, the Republic of Ragusa (now known as Dubrovnik) and the then Sultan of Gujarat, Mahmud Begada,
                        attempted to capture the city, then held by the Portuguese. The attempt failed.</note> D. Manuel gets on with his Letters<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; some of which are under transcription to be sent to you. If I be not very much deceived
                    this will be the most profitable of all my labours &#8211; which it well may be &amp; yet not be overpaid.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Ld Holland</ref> has, through <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, offered me the use of his Library, which as he has laid in an excellent store of books in Spain would be of
                    great <del>xxx</del> advantage to me, were I within reach of it. I am in want of sundry books, yet will not send for them for a
                    while &#8211; waiting to see what may turn up with regard to Portugal &amp; to my own destination.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am <del>xxx</del> as much obliged to <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> for his Lecture as
                    if I understood it, which I do sufficiently to see that he is going the right way to work.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Carlisle&#8217;s Croonian lecture &#8216;On Muscular Motion&#8217;, read to the Royal Society in November 1804 and published in its
                            <title>Philosophical Transactions</title> for 1805, dealt with &#8216;the combination, by means of nerves, between animated and
                        what may be deemed inanimate matter, as in the instances of bones, shells, teeth and other extravascular and insensible
                        substances, which, when completed, are no longer alterable by the animal functions&#8217;. See <title>Abstracts of the Papers
                            Printed in the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, from 1800 to 1830 Inclusive,</title> Vol. I,
                        1800&#8211;1814 (London, 1832), p. 165.</note> &#8211; does he or do you know that if any deformity happen to the human nails, it is
                    perpetuated? &#8211; or am I reasoning from my own individual experience too generally &#8211; for I have the proof at my <hi rend="ital">fingers end</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; The proofs are coming,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was in expectation of proofs from <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref> of their jointly edited anthology,
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> &amp; the pamphlet<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s pamphlet, <title>A Letter to the Right Hon. William Pitt on his Political
                            Experiments</title> (1804).</note> may be consigned to rest among my other books &#8211; as I have seen it. &#8211; there has been a
                    smart earthquake in Staffordshire &#8211; <note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> On Sunday, April 20, 1805, &#8216;a great shock of an
                        earthquake was felt at Alveton, and the places adjacent, about one o&#8217;clock in the morning. During the concussion several
                        chimneys were thrown down, particularly in the hamlet of Prestwood, but the inhabitants received no injury&#8217;, William Pitt,
                            <title>A Topographical History of Staffordshire</title> (Newcastle-under-Lyme, 1813), p. 228.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>