<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1215</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2337</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin,
                        Texas, 1976), pp. 109&#8211;110.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1215" type="letter">
        <head>1215. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1806-09-13">13 September 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: 10o&#8217;Clock/ SP.16/ 1806F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 121 1806/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Sep./ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />Seal: [partial, illegible] Red wax<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin,
                        Texas, 1976), pp. 109&#8211;110.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1806-09-13">Saturday Sept. 13. 1806.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I began to be somewhat uneasy at your long silence, &#8211; but in all such cases my consolation is that bad news always
                    travels fast, &amp; I knew your many avocations well enough to account for the gap in our correspondence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is here, &amp; now restored to health. He brought with him the seeds of an ague
                    caught no doubt at Deptford from the pestilential fens of Essex, &amp; also was very seriously afflicted with haemerrrhoids, so
                    that he was fairly laid up. This in some manner proved fortunate. I should first have told you that the Amelia<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey was serving on the ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class
                        frigate of the French navy captured in 1796 and commissioned into the navy.</note> having been paid off, he came down here not
                    upon leave, but as being on half-pay. While he was ill, an appointment came after him, naming him to a sloop of war, &amp; he was
                    of course obliged to send back an certificate of his inability to serve, adding that as soon as he was recovered he would
                    immediately apply to the Admiralty for employment. Now before he makes this application, may I request you once more to get him
                    mentioned to Admiral Markham,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Markham (1761&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>): naval officer
                        who was a member of the Board of Admiralty (1801&#8211;1804 and 1806&#8211;1807). For Markham&#8217;s answer, see Southey to Thomas Southey,
                        28&#8211;29 September 1806, Letter 1221. In the event, this attempt was unsuccessful; see Southey to John Rickman, 26 June 1807,
                        Letter 1336.</note> that he may be placed either in a frigate or a line of battle ship, &#8211; for in the small craft there is no
                    comfort, &amp; no chance of promotion, neither indeed is it respectable for so old an officer as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> to serve in them, &#8211; I may add for so good a one. As soon as I hear from you
                    that this has been done he will write up in form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There were two Bourkes at Westminster in my time, with neither of whom had I anything more than a mere sight
                    acquaintance. One went into the army &amp; had half his face shot away in Holland<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Bourke (1777&#8211;1855), army officer and colonial governor, who was educated at Westminster School between 1788 and 1793. The
                        other Bourke who went to Southey&#8217;s school has not been identified.</note> &#8211; I do not believe that either of them can ever have
                    been out of Europe, &amp; know no one else of the name. But it is no wonder that people claim acquaintance with me at so safe a
                    distance, when I have just been claimed face to face as an old friend by a gentleman of whom I have no more recollection than the
                    Man in the Moon has of me. He is a Swiss calling himself Capt Moncrieff<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note>
                    of the 36<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">mais autrefois Dugenie</hi>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning
                        &#8216;formerly Dugenie&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; says he knew me nine years ago at Lisbon, where he was intimate with Prior.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> Do you remember him? In Portugal he has certainly been, but I am equally certain
                    that he never was any acquaintance of mine, for he lived by his own account with Robarts &amp; Bouden<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> &amp; that set, with whom I never associated. He told me that I one day read him some
                    passages of my Jean d&#8217;Arc<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796; 2nd edn
                        1798).</note> &#8211; this I know to be a lie, &#8211; for in the first place I am not in the habit of reading my own verses to any but my
                    very nearest home friends, or to a man of letters from whom I expect &amp; require criticism, &#8211; &amp; in the next place if I had
                    been disposed so to have done it was impossible, for no copy of that book ever entered Portugal till after I had left it. I
                    suspect M. Dugenie has what we call sported a face upon me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am watching Portugal almost as anxiously as you yourself can be. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My
                        Uncle</ref> wishes me there, &amp; blames me for not being there at this time, without I think, sufficiently considering the
                    causes of my delay, &amp; that even independent of those reasons, my ways &amp; means are not quite so easily raised as Lord Henry
                        Petty&#8217;s.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess of Lansdowne (1780&#8211;1863), known as Lord
                        Henry Petty, was the Chancellor of the Exchequer (1806&#8211;1807).</note> I shall go in the spring with my family, if it be
                    prudent, from political views, to take them; if not I will go alone, should the country then be open.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not visit Portugal again. Herbert Hill returned to England in 1807 when it looked likely that the
                        country would be invaded by French forces.</note> If the court removes to Brasil I must own I shall feel very strongly tempted
                    to follow them.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having been warned of Napoleon&#8217;s intention to invade Portugal, on 27
                        November 1807, the Portuguese royal family left Lisbon for their colonial holdings in Brazil.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not worth your while to read the Missionary Transactions &#8211; my account of them comprises the important matter,
                    &amp; methodizes a very perplexed &amp; heterogeneous narration.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the
                            <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 189&#8211;201, and
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 621&#8211;634.</note> In the next years I shall two articles [sic] upon the
                    subject &#8211; one of the East Indian Mission &#8211; the other of the Methodist one &#8211; &amp; probably a third upon the far wiser system of
                    the Quakers in America.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Of these projects, Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts of
                            the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226. This review dealt
                        mostly with East Indian missions.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#MooreThomas">Moores</ref> Poems which occasioned the intended duel between him &amp; <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> the reviewer, have been sent to me by <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref>, it having long been determined that when next he infested the public with lewd verses I should take him
                    in hand,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Moore&#8217;s (1779&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Epistles, Odes and Other Poems</title> (1806) in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 498&#8211;499. In
                        the July 1806 number of the Edinburgh Review Moore&#8217;s work was attacked by <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis
                            Jeffrey</ref>, who denounced both the poet and his book, leading Moore to challenge him to a duel. The duel was
                        interrupted by police officers, who arrested both men, and the whole affair was ridiculed in the newspapers.</note> &#8211;
                        <del>xx</del> you may be assured <del>that</del> I shall not spare him from any dread of what he would establish as the <hi rend="ital">Ultima ratio Reviewerorum</hi>,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The last resort of the reviewed&#8217;.</note>
                    nor consider myself amenable to any false laws of honour for upholding the cause of morality.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Athen&#230;um will have me for a contributor at first.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807&#8211;1809), published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> I wish to serve <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, because I like him &amp; think him a kind hearted man &#8211; &amp; among my papers are many things which I
                    &lt;may&gt; as well get paid for now, &amp; methodize hereafter if occasion occur.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Little Edith</ref> has had the measles, &amp; thank God is well thro them &#8211; she grows
                    &amp; is in every respect a singularly forward child. In strength &amp; stature she nearly equals <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her cousin</ref>, who is sixteen months elder, &amp; very considerably exceeds
                    her in intellect. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> expects to be confined the beginning of next month.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, the Southeys&#8217; first son, was born 11 October 1806.</note> She joins me
                    in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope your next will contain better news of the books &#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>