<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1281</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2403</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 105.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1281" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1281" type="letter">
        <head>1281. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-03-03">3 March
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 3 March 1807<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 105<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Galvam<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duarte Galv&#227;o (1435&#8211;1517), <title>Chronica del D. Affonso Henriques
                            primero, D. Sancho, I &amp; II, D. Affonso II &amp; III, e Dom Diniz, Sexto Rey de Portugal</title> (1727&#8211;1729).</note>
                    &amp; Caramuru<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jose&#769; de Santa Rita Dura&#771;o (1722&#8211;1784),<title> Caramuru: Poema &#201;pico do
                            Descobrimento da Bahia</title> (1781).</note> may come at your leisure in a box with the M.S.S. which it would not be
                    prudent to hazard by sea in the general removal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was planning to have his books
                        shipped to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>; see Southey to John Rickman, 23 February [1807], Letter
                        1278.</note> There are the nine volumes on the shelf below stairs &#8211; two or three which I am not very well acquainted with in
                    the cupboards there, &#8211; &amp; one upstairs in the bookcase beyond the fireplace &#8211; a folio, bound but not lettered &#8211; which is very
                    stupid &amp; very unsightly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of books relating to South America I recollect a folio parchment Chronicle History of the Augustinians in Peru &#8211;
                    purporting to be a first volume.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de la Calancha (1584&#8211;1654), <title>Coronica
                            Moralizada del Orden de San Augustin en el Peru, con Sucesos Exemplares en Esta Monarquia</title> (1638). No. 3322 of the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> such books being usually printed volume by volume. Hist: of Peru by
                        &lt;Z&gt;<del>Garate</del> &lt;Carate&gt; 1 thin folio<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Augustin de &#199;arate (dates
                        unknown), <title>Historia del Descubrimiento y Conquista del Peru</title> (1577). No. 3326 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> &#8211; &amp; another by Diego Fernandez two thin ones<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Diego Fernandez (c.
                        1520-c. 1581), <title>Historia del Peru</title> (1571). No. 3381 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; they
                    stand side by side in the bookcase beyond the fireplace &#8211; &amp; another Hist. of the same country by Pedro Cie&#231;a &#8211; a small thick
                    volume bound in something more like dried lemon peel than any thing else &#8211; &amp; not lettered.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Cie&#231;a de Leon (c. 1520&#8211;1554), <title>La Chronica del Peru</title> (1554). No. 3196 of the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> this is probably down stairs. <del>Ther</del> I am in no hurry for any of these; &#8211; but
                    at your full leisure &#8211; (of which heaven knows you have little enough) they may as well come with the MSS. If they should not fill
                    the box put in any thing Spanish or Portugueze.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I did a good months work in February. My friend Hans<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hans Staden (c.
                        1525-c. 1579), a German member of a expedition up the de la Plata river, who in 1552 was captured by the Tupinamb&#225; people of
                        Brazil. Escaping to Europe in 1555, Staden published a German account of his travels in 1557, claiming to have witnessed
                        cannibalism. His narrative was translated into Latin and in 1593 was incorporated in Theodor de Bry (1528&#8211;1598),
                            <title>Collectiones Peregrinatiorum in Indiam Orientalem et Indiam Occidentalem</title> (1590&#8211;1634).</note> is got safe
                    home to his country, &#8211; I go next to the Paraguay with a lyar called Cabeza de Vaca, &#8211; who worked miracles in Florida &amp; brought
                    home that foolish story of there always being a race of hermanphrodites there who were the undertakers &#8211; I dare say you have seen
                    a picture of them &#8211; The man went governor to the Revis Plata (may I not call it the Plata at once &#8211; &amp; so drop the silver
                    etymology <del>&amp;</del> &#8211; the single word becomes a mere name as it should be without any meaning.) &amp; was sent back to
                    Spain by the soldiers. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#193;lvar N&#250;&#241;ez Cabeza de Vaca (c. 1488/1490-c. 1557/1559). A Spanish
                        adventurer who was part of an expedition intended to conquer Florida. Shipwrecked in 1528 off Texas and captured by Indians,
                        de Vaca eventually returned to Europe in 1537 and published an account of his adventures, <title>La Relaci&#243;n</title> in 1542,
                        in which he recorded seeing men dressed as women and performing women&#8217;s tasks, while living with men. He returned to America
                        in 1540 as governor of the Rio de la Plata, but was arrested and returned to Spain in 1545, where he published his
                            <title>Comentarios</title> (1555), criticising the colonists.</note> He wrote his own commentaries, &amp; there is a
                    German adventurer by name Hulderic Schmedel<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ulrich Schmiedel (?1510&#8211;1579?), a German
                        mercenary in the service of Spanish conquistadors who travelled up the river Plate from Buenos Aires into the interior of Peru
                        and Bolivia. Schmiedel was the author of <title>Viaje al R&#237;o de la Plata</title> (1534&#8211;1554).</note> who was there at the same
                    time &amp; writes on the other side &#8211; so the truth is to be got at between them. After his expulsion a party made their way to
                    Peru being the first march across the continent in that direction. I think my title must be Brazil &amp; Paraguay.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was published as the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> Here is a History of
                    Paraguay by the Jesuit Charlevoix<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre Francois-Xavier de Charlevoix (1682&#8211;1761),
                            <title>Histoire de Paraguay</title> (Paris, 1756).</note> which is of all lying books the most impudent. I know not where
                    to look for authority when Schmidel<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">See note 10.</note> leaves me. There is however one
                    comfort in historifying that no time needs be lost. While I wait for material for one part I can proceed with another.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will receive a book from Our Fathers which are in the Row<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, the
                        firm of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> in <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster
                            Row</ref>, sending a copy of Southey&#8217;s and Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807).</note> &#8211; which I dare say will put me in a cold sweat, &amp; cost me sundry of those interjections which are vulgarly
                    called oaths, before I have cut the leaves open; it being, by the few <del>pro</del> sheets which have sent me one of the very
                    worst printed books that ever was seen. You will observe that I have <del>xxx</del> given the merit of this in the preface to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">G CBedford</ref>, as being his due; As some of my books have been too good to
                    sell, I hope this will be more fortunate as the same objection certainly cannot apply to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a Spanish poem among my books which ought to have some Brazilian matter in it I forget its title &#8211; but it
                    one of the small quartos rather thicker than usual &#8211; in dark binding &#8211; &amp; relating the life of one whose name was Diaz or Dias
                    &#8211; &amp; I think &#8211; but am not sure &#8211; <hi rend="ital">Pedro</hi> Diaz.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Dias
                        (1548&#8211;1571) was a Jesuit killed by pirates on his way to Brazil in 1571.</note> A rude wooden cut upon the page represents him
                    having his throat cut or his brain knocked out by the French &#8211; for I believe he was one of the forty Jesuits whom they took on
                    their way to Brazil &amp; murdered them all. If the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> discovers this in his
                    search let it come in the box. Think what a delight it will be to me to have all my books about me at last &#8211; ranged round a better
                    study than I could ever afford to have elsewhere. A journey to London every other year will enable me to do all that needs to be
                    done there.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-03-03">[MS torn]rch 3. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>