<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1528</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2650</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3877.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 177&#8211;180.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1528" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1528" type="letter">
        <head>1528. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1808-11-06">6 November
                        1808</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Ashesteil/
                        Selkirk<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Watermark: JW &amp; BB/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1808<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3877<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 177&#8211;180.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Scott.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sometimes thought of publishing translations from the Spanish &amp; Portugueze, with the originals
                        annexed,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s suggestion that Southey might publish such translation was rapidly
                            superseded by his solicitation, with <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref>, of Southey to write on Spanish affairs for the new <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>.</note> &#8211; but there was no prospect of profit to tempt me, &amp; as certainly, if I live, it is my
                    intention to enter fully into the literary history of both countries, &#8211; that made me lay aside the thought of any thing on a
                    lesser scale. Another reason perhaps may have been this, that it is not more difficult to compose poetry than to translate it,
                    &amp; that, in my own opinion I can make as good as I can find. &#8211; Very very few of the Spanish ballads are good; &#8211; they are made
                    in general upon one receipt &amp; that a most inartificial one &#8211; they begin by describing the situation of somebody, who makes a
                    speech which is the end. <del>An</del> Nothing like the wildness or the character of our ballads is to be found among them. It is
                    curious &amp; at present inexplicable to me how their prose should be so exquisitely poetical as it is in the Cid,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was based on Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar
                        (c. 1043&#8211;1099), <title>Chronica de la Famoso Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593).</note> &#8211; &amp; their poetry so
                    completely prosaical as it is in almost all their narrative poems. &#8211; Nevertheless I <del>xxxx to be</del> &lt;might be&gt;
                    tempted. Some translations I have by me, &#8211; &amp; many of my books are marked for others. there are some high-toned odes in the
                    Spanish, &amp; a good many beautiful sonnets. Many of their epics would afford good extracts &#8211; &amp; I am competent to
                        give<del>x</del> critical <del>bio</del> sketches of biography, formed not <del>from</del> at second hand, but from full
                    perusal of the authors themselves. My name however is worth nothing in the market; &amp; the booksellers would not offer me any
                    thing to make it worth my while to interrupt occupations of greater importance. I thank you heartily for your offer of aid, &amp;
                    should the thing be carried into effect, would gladly avail myself of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am planning some thing of great importance, &#8211; a poem upon Pelayo the first Restorer of Spain; &#8211; it has long been
                    one of my chosen subjects &amp; these late events which have warmed every heart that has right British blood circulating thro it,
                    have revived &amp; strengthened old resolutions.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelagius/Pelayo (c. 685&#8211;737), founder of
                        the Kingdom of Asturias. Through his victory at the Battle of Covadonga, he is credited with beginning the Christian
                        reconquest of the Iberian peninsula from the Moors. The planned poem became <title>Roderick, Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> It will be in regular blank verse, &amp; the story will naturally take rather a higher tone than Madoc.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It gives me great pleasure to hear that you have done with the Edinburgh Review. Of their base article respecting
                        Spain<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In no. 24 (July 1808), 441 the <title>Edinburgh</title> was lukewarm about war
                        in the article &#8216;Mr Whitbread&#8217;s <title>Letter on Spain</title>;&#8217; in no. 25 (October 1808), 215 it also cast doubt on the worth
                        of supporting the Spanish in their war against French occupation: see &#8216;Exposition of the Practices and Machinations which led
                        to the Usurpation of the Crown of Spain, and the Means adopted by the Emperor of the French to carry it into
                        Execution&#8217;.</note> I heard from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, &#8211; that subject is the fair
                    touchstone whether a man has any generous sympathies in his nature. There is not in history such another instance of national
                    regeneration &amp; redemption. I have been a true prophet upon this subject, &amp; am not a little proud of the prophecy. Of the
                    eventual issue I have never felt a moments doubt. Such a nation, &#8211; such a spirit are invincible. But what a cruel business has
                    this curst convention of Cintra been!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s exasperation was caused by the Convention
                        of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by
                        Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at
                        Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the
                        Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace:
                        Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). Public outcry led to
                        an inquiry, after which Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> &#8211; Junot pretty clearly expressed his own
                    feelings of our Commander in chief<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dalrymple.</note> when he recommended him to take up
                    his <del>bo</del> quarters at Quintellas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Portuguese dealer in diamonds at whose Lisbon
                        palacio the French commander Junot took up his quarters.</note> house as he had done, &#8211; &#8216;the man, he said, kept a very good
                    table, &amp; he had <del>very</del> seldom had reason to find fault with it! &#8211; My blood boils to think that there should be an
                    English General to whom this rascal could venture to say this! &#8211; In one of the Frenchmans knapsacks, among other articles of that
                    property which they bargained to take away with them, was a delicate female hand with rings upon the fingers. &#8211; Our ministers do
                    not avail themselves as they might do of their strong cause. They should throw away the scabbard, &amp; publish a manifesto
                    stating why this country never will make peace with Bonaparte, &#8211; &amp; on what plain terms it will at any moment make peace with
                    France under any other ruler: I fully believe that it would be possible to overthrow his government by this means at this
                    time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A reviewal of my Cid by you<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed Southey, <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid Rodrigo Diaz de Bivar, the Campeador, from the Spanish</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (1809),
                        117&#8211;134.</note> will be the best aid that it can possibly receive. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">500 only were printed, &amp; in spite of the temporary feeling, &amp; the wonderful beauty of the book, I dare say
                    they will hang upon hand. If it sold well I should be very desirous of translating the chronicles of Fernam Lopez,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fernao Lopes (c. 1385&#8211;after 1459), chronicler of Portugal, wrote <title>Cr&#243;nica del-rei D.
                            Pedro</title> (1735); <title>Chronica del Rey D. Ioam I de Boa Memoria, e dos Reys de Portugal o Decimo, Primeira Parte,
                            em Que se contem A Defensam do Reyno at&#233; ser eleito Rey &amp; Segunda Parte, em que se continuam as guerras com Castella,
                            desde o Principio de seu reinado ate as pazes</title> (1644). Lopes&#8217;s manuscript &#8216;Cronica del Rei Dom Fernando o Noveno
                        Rei de Portugal&#8217; was listed as no. 3829 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library after his death.</note> which are in my
                    judgement far superior to all others.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will rejoice me to see you here, &amp; show you my treasures, &amp; talk of the days of the shield &amp; the
                    lance. We have a bed at your service, &amp; shall expect you to be our guest. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> who left me to day desires his re[MS torn]ances. He is about to write a pamphlet upon this preci[MS torn]
                        Convention,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Concerning the Relations of Great
                            Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the
                            Convention of Cintra</title> (1809).</note> which he will place in a more philosophical point of view than any body has
                    yet done. I go to press in a few weeks with my History of Brazil, &amp; have <del>at present</del> Thalaba at present in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> hands, that poem having just reached the end of its seven years
                        apprenticeship.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was
                        published in 1810; the second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> in 1809.</note> And I have got half way thro my
                    Hindoo poem,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> which it is to be hoped will please myself, inasmuch as it is not likely to
                    please any body else. It is too strange, too much beyond all human sympathies, but I shall go on, &amp; as in such cases I have
                    usually little but my labour for my pains, the certainty that it never can <del>never</del> be popular will not deter me from
                    gratifying my own fancy.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> joins me in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Scott</ref>.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> believe me yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-11-06">Nov. 6. 1808</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>