<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.997</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2119</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.997" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="997" type="letter">
        <head>997. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-12-07">[started before 7
                    December&#8211;]16 December 1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers/ Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ DEC 19<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: The reference to the lost &#8216;packet of notes&#8217; intended for <title>Madoc</title>,
                        indicates that this letter must have been started before Southey&#8217;s letter to Henry Herbert Southey, 7 December [1804], Letter
                        998.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I began in my turn to wonder at your silence, &amp; when your letter came it alarmed me both for your thumb &amp;
                    my books. the conclusion removed my apprehensions for you, but not for myself. your thumb will grow, but woe <del>th</del> to the
                    poor books if the rats have actually begun upon them. Shall I beg you to give a look at Horts<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764&#8211;1849), Unitarian minister and writer, who was one of many storers of books for
                        Southey.</note> &amp; see if they be safe there from damp &amp; vermin<del>s</del> &#8211; I never think of my books without
                    vexation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By good fortune the purchase of <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">our house</ref> is broken off.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s landlord, <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">William Jackson</ref>, had been
                        negotiating the sale of his house to Mr White (names and dates unknown) of Keswick.</note> Come you therefore in the summer,
                    &amp; send me off some wine with as little delay as may be convenient. four dozen port, three of bucellas or vidonia.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> White wines produced in Portugal and Tenerife respectively.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in trouble about Madoc. a packet of notes sent off a fortnight ago has not reached Edinburgh, &amp; should it
                    be lost no alternative remains but to publish the book without them, for it is impossible at this distance from my books to
                    replace them, nor would it be easy were they all at hand. the loss is not certain as yet &amp; so I will yet hope the best.
                    provoking! for the press stands still the while. the whole poem is printed off: a matter as you may suppose of no small
                    satisfaction to me, after so many years. Much of it will be new to you, enough to give it an interest of novelty. Of the old story
                    you will miss little, &amp; that little you will have no reason to regret.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since this letter was begun I have been in fear &amp; trouble about Tom, nor am I yet thoroughly easy. <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> had learnt at Lloyds Coffee House that the boats of the Galatea had severely
                    suffered in an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the Lilly; but he could learn no particulars. I wrote to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 4 December 1804, Letter 996.</note> whose <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">youngest brother</ref> is in
                    the Admiralty; he in consequence enquired there &amp; saw a private letter from a man who had been in the action, in which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> name was not mentioned, so that as the account was very particular we considered
                    all was well. No sooner was this over than the news of the hurricane arrived, &amp; in the first account it was said that a
                    frigate was lost at Dominica,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Dominica is an island in the Lesser Antilles group of islands
                        in the West Indies.</note> which &#8211; if true &#8211; must have been <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> ship. Well &#8211; this
                    was soon contradicted &#8211; but next appears a paragraph in the Whitehaven paper<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The
                            Cumberland Pacquet and Ware&#8217;s Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note> stating the death of Michael Bircbeck of that town,
                    master of Galatea, killed in attempting to cut out the Lydia, in which unfortunate attempt the First Lieutenant fell, the Surgeon,
                    &amp; the Lieutenant of Marines. &#8211; You know I always look if a thing be probable before I admit it to be true &#8211; no doubt would
                    have existed in my mind as to the truth of this had not the Surgeon been mentioned, who I was sure could not have gone on such an
                    attempt. I wrote off to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> again,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14 December 1804, Letter 1002.</note> by this time Commodore
                        Hoods<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814;
                            <title>DNB</title>), in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey served.</note> official letter was arrived, &amp; it
                    turned out there was a Lieutenant killed, whose name happily for me was not Southey, &#8211; &amp; not one of the persons mentioned in
                    the Whitehaven paper. Upon this I wrote off to the Editor requesting to know on what information he had inserted the paragraph,
                    stating to him what I knew, &amp; inferring a reasonable <del>xxxx</del> &lt;belief&gt; that Michael Bircbeck was safe as well as
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, which I wished him to communicate to the father.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter does not appear to have survived.</note> The Editors answer has just reached me: a private letter
                    from Antigua<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Antigua is one of the Leeward Islands of the West Indies.</note> brought the
                    tidings which so far as they concern me are evidently erroneous, but I fear not so decidedly so about Bircbeck for it should
                    rather seem that he is the Masters Mate than Master. I am exceedingly interested about him for the poor father was thrown almost
                    into agonies by my letter &#8211; it made him feel he said like one raised from the dead &#8211; &amp; it would be shocking if after all his
                    son should have been killed &#8211; &amp; <del>xxx</del> that he should have the shock to endure a second time &#8211; alas what a dreadful
                    aggregate of human wretchedness does human folly occasion!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate, had, on 14 August 1804, made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the
                        French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at
                        the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or wounded. Southey had suspected that his
                        brother was among them because the first lieutenant had been reported as dead, but he was absent from the raid because he had
                        been placed under arrest. Charles Hayman (d. 1804) was made first lieutenant in his stead and died in the attack. Michael
                        Birbeck (dates unknown) was indeed the Master and was killed in the action, according to William James (d. 1827), <title>The
                            Naval History of Great Britain</title>, 5 vols (London, 1822&#8211;1824), III, pp. 274&#8211;276.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The parcel of notes has at last found its way to Edinburgh, &amp; it is to be hoped no farther delay in the
                    printing will take place. Of the four vignettes I have seen two which are both very beautiful, the ship of Madoc in full sail from
                    a design of Pocockes, &amp; a groupe of Aztecan arms with a Welsh <del>xxx</del> harp &amp;c &amp; the shield of Madoc for the
                    title page. the two others will be a cross on a rock with a palm tree above &amp; a spring at its foot<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), has only three illustrations: the engraved titlepage with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn&#8217;s</ref> shield upon a <hi rend="ital">troph&#233;e</hi>; the palm and cross upon the
                        rock (after the Table of Contents); and the snake before the cave, engraved on the titlepage for the second part, &#8216;Madoc in
                        Aztlan&#8217; (bound incorrectly after 320 instead of after 184). It is probable that the image of the ship by Nicholas Pocock
                        (1740&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>) was omitted because Southey was displeased with the vessel&#8217;s anachronistic modernity;see
                        Southey to Joseph Cottle, 25 August 1805, Letter 1097).</note> &#8211; as an emblem to be upon the leaf with the exordial lines,
                    which run thus &#8211; Come listen to a tale of times of old,</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Come, for ye know me. I am he who sung</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The Maid of Arc, &amp; I am he who framed</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of Thalaba the wild &amp; wonderous song.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come listen to my lay &amp; ye shall hear</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> How Madoc from the shores of Britain spread</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The adventurous sail, explored the ocean ways,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And quelled barbarian power, &amp; over threw</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The bloody altars of Idolatry,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And planted in its fanes triumphantly</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The Cross of Christ. come listen to my lay!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Madoc</title> was
                            published in 1805 with this exordium. See <title>Robert Southey. Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5
                            vols (London, 2004), II, p. 8.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">The remaining vignette is for the second part. A huge snake to whom you are to have the pleasure of being
                    introduced, sunning himself at the entrance of a cavern. These four are all. If the books sell well I will have more to another
                    edition, &amp; it may be best to let <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> finish the waterspout for this, as under that
                    belief he may perhaps get it ready in time. If I had it some months ago it should have been engraved now. &#8211; You will find Madoc
                    more Catholic than you will like, but not more so than he must have been. the propriety of preventing any bloody ceremonies by
                    force &amp; christening one generation who know nothing of christianity for the sake of making the next really christians, is
                        <del>my</del> a thing of which I am well convinced &#8211; as you may have seen in the Annual Review,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title>
                        (1800&#8211;1801) in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207&#8211;218.</note> &amp; will see more fully in one of the
                    portions of my history<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never
                        completed.</note> whenever that shall appear. There is no danger that you should suspect me of believing in the Virgin Mary
                    tho Madoc does, tho very likely some foolish people may.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Call occasionally at Codys<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Cody (dates unknown), a Bristol
                        bookseller.</note> for me &amp; see what travels he has, &#8211; I hope to God it will not be very long before I shall be enabled to
                    chuse a settled dwelling place &amp; get my books together. This dreadful pestilence will most likely keep me from Lisbon<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Yellow fever was epidemic in Iberia in 1804, and killed an estimated 60% of Gibraltar&#8217;s
                        population.</note> &#8211; I have some thoughts as soon as my recovery is done of turning to &amp; writing our letters<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably an early reference to Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                            Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> to raise an immediate sum for the purpose of furnishing a
                    house, which I could get done in the course of the summer or autumn, &#8211; &amp; what will please you better seriously think of Bath
                    as a fit place. &#8211; We shall see how Madoc turns out, &amp; these Specimens<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The project
                        that Southey undertook with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note>
                    which are sadly delayed by <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &amp; but now just going to press,
                    whereas had I been on the spot they would have been three parts printed. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> was inoculated yesterday with the cow pock, the small
                    pox being in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Jenner (1749&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>) published his experiments on vaccinating against smallpox using cowpox serum in <title>An Inquiry Into
                            the Causes and Effects of the Variol&#230; Vaccin&#230;</title> in 1798.</note> She does well &amp; is a very sweet child, but so
                    prematurely quick that I much fear we shall not rear her. she has cut two teeth quite easily &#8211; this however is no proof that the
                    next will come so too &#8211; At first you would not think her pretty, but very soon she would win upon you &amp; you would call her
                    exceedingly interesting. I continue well &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> grows fat. Take care of yourself
                    this winter. How is Joe &amp; how is Cupid.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dogs in Danvers&#8217; care; formerly belonging to
                        the Southey and his brother Thomas.</note> I have got an Ass by name John; &amp; he is quite a pet.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-12-16">Sunday 16 Dec. 1804.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>