<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1584</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2706</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 131&#8211;133.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1584" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1584" type="letter">
        <head>1584. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1809-02-18">18 February
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 131&#8211;133.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-02-18">Feb. 18. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter required an earlier answer, because it asked me a question respecting Dr. Collyer&#8217;s book.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Bengo Collyer (1782&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), congregational minister and religious
                        writer, who published <title>Lectures on Scripture Prophecy</title> (1809).</note> I should have replied immediately, if it
                    had not arrived at a time of considerable anxiety.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If it gives you any satisfaction to see my name in the list of your friend&#8217;s subscribers, by all means place it
                        there.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s name was included in the list of subscribers.</note> The subject is a
                    very important one, if it be ably handled: the proofs from prophecy appear to me the best ground that can be taken to establish
                    the truth of revelation. I shall accept the book with pleasure; but do not you, on another occasion, scruple at asking me to
                    subscribe for myself. When you send it, it will save an unnecessary expense if you consign it to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman&#8217;s</ref> care; he is in the habit of sending me frequent parcels by the waggon, &#8211;
                    one in about six weeks, and these generally serve as deposits for all stray communications which may happen to be addressed to
                    me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are right in supposing it is the &#8216;Quarterly&#8217; for which I have been engaged. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> is the projector of the Review. He has long broken off all connection with
                    the &#8216;Edinburgh,&#8217; &#8211; before the reviewal of &#8216;Marmion&#8217; appeared<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Though Scott wrote for the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, its editor <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> published a highly
                        critical piece on his 1808 poem <title>Marmion</title> in volume 12 (April 1808), 1&#8211;35.</note> (which indeed would not have
                    influenced him), upon the ground of his disaccord with their principles of politics, and the system of criticism which they
                    adopted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bigland&#8217;s &#8216;Essays&#8217;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Essays on Various Subjects</title> (1805) by John Bigland (1750&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), schoolmaster and educational
                        writer.</note> I have not read; nor do I ever read books of that nature, unless they come to me to be reviewed, and I am paid
                    for reading them. Summaries of history are of no use to me, nor am I ever solicitous about the opinions of other men, except it
                    falls to my lot to deliver one of my own. Then, indeed, I make it a duty to read everything that has ever been written upon the
                    subject, as far as it is possible so to do. Warburton&#8217;s &#8216;Correspondence&#8217;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from a Late Eminent Prelate to One of His Friends</title> (1808), by William Warburton (1698&#8211;1779;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Gloucester and religious controversialist.</note> has not yet fallen in my way. He was a
                    powerful man, &#8211; so powerful that even when he was most in the wrong, he makes you respect him; and you almost pardon his arrogance
                    in deference to the feeling of superiority from which it springs. The new books which I most wish to see,&#8211;indeed, almost the only
                    ones that I feel any desire for, are those of voyages and travels: of these, if I could afford it, I should buy all that come out.
                    I take in Pinkerton&#8217;s publication of the contemporary ones,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>), editor of <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in all
                            Parts of the World</title> (1808&#8211;1814).</note> and I am thankful to him for publishing them, ill as they are translated,
                    and indiscriminately as they seem to be brought there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your views of the good which Bonaparte will do by his temporary triumph accord with mine. The good will be
                    permanent, the evil only for a time. It is to be hoped our ministry are not so wholly engrossed by the defence of the Duke of
                        York,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he
                        had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army
                        officers, in return for which promotion was arranged.</note> and their attempts to invalidate a very plain story by such petty
                    prevarications as a dirty lawyer uses to bring off a fellow for sheep stealing, as to forget the Spaniards.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made no bargain about the &#8216;Curse of Kehama,&#8217;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published by Longman in 1810.</note> nor have I any expectation of making a good
                    one. It will, however, be time enough to think of this when the poem is finished. We have had one sickness after another for the
                    last two months; my rest has thus been broken, and the poem has been at a stand. Of my History eighteen sheets are printed.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in
                        1810.</note> I am better pleased with it in print than before, and am working very hard in transcribing and filling up for the
                    press.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Duke of Kent<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Edward, Duke of Kent and Strathearn (1767&#8211;1820;
                    <title>DNB</title>),
                    the fourth son of King George III (1738&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> has manifested a disposition to serve your brother <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref> in one way. Perhaps if Dr. Collyer<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        note 1.</note> were to mention his situation to him, he might do it effectually in another, by placing him in a public
                    office. Remember me to him, and believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>