<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1683</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2805</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 251&#8211;253 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1683" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1683" type="letter">
        <head>1683. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, [started before and continued on] <date when="1809-09-19">19 September [1809]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/
                        H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; [partial] PLYMOUTH / 2<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 251&#8211;253 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have hunted two books of Heraldry, the French Dictionaries &amp; the Cyclop&#339;dia without finding any such term as
                    Humette or any thing like it. I cannot guess at its meaning.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See the postscript to this
                        letter.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your opinion respecting Ld Gambiers trial accords entirely with my own.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey is referring to the controversy surrounding the Battle of the Basque Roads in April 1809. Although the British fleet
                        achieved some success, it failed to destroy the French navy completely. Captain Thomas Cochrane, later 10th Earl of Dundonald
                        (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), who had led a highly effective fireship attack at the start of the battle, accused his
                        commanding officer, the evangelical Admiral James Gambier, Baron Gambier (1756&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>) of being reluctant to
                        pursue the attack and thus achieve a complete victory. Cochrane was also an MP with a reputation for exposing abuses of
                        office, and, in the weeks after the battle, he pursued his campaign against Gambier via parliamentary speeches. Gambier
                        demanded a court-martial at which he was exonerated and, by implication, Cochrane was blamed for libelling a superior officer.
                        Whilst Gambier received public thanks from parliament for his actions in the battle, Cochrane was not permitted to rejoin his
                        ship for a few months. When he received new orders to serve in the Mediterranean, Cochrane refused and went on half-pay,
                        devoting his time to exposing abuses in the Admiralty. For Southey&#8217;s account, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 364&#8211;379.</note> Wardle<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gwyllym Lloyd Wardle (c.
                        1761&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Okehampton 1807&#8211;1812, who played a central role in exposing Frederick, Duke of York
                        (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) and Mary Anne Clarke&#8217;s (1776?-1852; <title>DNB</title>) involvement in office
                        trafficking. However, his own reputation was quickly sullied by counter-allegations from Clarke, alleging corruption and
                        conspiracy. He was the author of <title>The Trial of Colonel Wardle</title> (1809).</note> I believe to be a worthless sort of
                    fellow, &#8211; he is the same man who ran his poney against the Exeter Mail,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In one of the more
                        bizarre sporting contests seen in Georgian England, a &#8216;Mr Wardel&#8217; had raced his pony against the mail-coach from London to
                        Exeter, the pony winning by 45 minutes. In addition, the pony &#8216;is accustomed to drink ale and beer, and frequently drank a
                        pint of port at a time&#8217;, <title>National Register</title>, 1 (1808), p. 565, reporting events on 3&#8211;4 September 1808.</note> &#8211;
                    for which any man ought to have been hung. As for the trial about the furniture there was no harm in his bargaining for the
                    evidence, but a good deal of meanness in his refusing to fulfill the bargain.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of
                        Clarke&#8217;s allegations against Wardle was that he bought her testimony against the Duke of York by promising to pay for
                        furnishing her house, but then failed to do so.</note> I would believe M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkes word implicitly; there
                    is a good deal of good in that woman, &amp; as <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> says I have a great respect for
                    her, saving her vocation. ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> More Inquiries &#8211; Ld Chatham must take his turn next.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitt, 2nd Earl of
                        Chatham (1756&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and younger brother of the former prime minister William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>). The <title>Commentary</title>
                        criticised his role in the ill-fated Walcheren expedition of 1809.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent2"> ___</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1809-09-19">Sept 19.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> is gone at last after a cruel illness. I followed him
                    to the grave to day. &#8211; a good man to whom the town of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; many of its
                    inhabitants are greatly beholden. He has left <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> 50 &#163; to be paid when
                    he comes of age; &#8211; had he thought of bequeathing him his books it would have been a more suitable <del>xxx</del> remembrance. By
                        <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilson</ref> he has not dealt as became him, &#8211; her legacy is a
                    poor 10 &#163; per year, in which he has considered the humbleness of her wishes rather than the greatness of his obligation. His
                    affected reason for this is that he could not properly leave her more than he has left to two of his sisters; a reason by no means
                    valid, for she was more to him than all his family. Never had man a more faithful, anxious &amp; indefatiguable nurse: &#8211; always
                    watchful &#8211; always willing, never uttering a complaint, never sparing herself; with the most disinterested affection, acting so
                    entirely from the feelings of a good heart, that I do not believe even the thought of <del>xxx</del> duty ever entered into it.
                    The night after his death we made her take a little spirit &amp; water, &#8211; it was not a tea cup full, &#8211; but upon her it acted as
                    medicine, &#8211; she told me the next day that for the first time during two years she had slept thro the night. He never turned in his
                    bed during that whole time that she did not hear, &#8211; nor did he make the slightest unusual sound or motion that she was not up to
                    know what could be done for him. &#8211; As you will readily suppose I have long since told her never to think of quitting this place,
                    but to remain here as long as she lives with people to whom she is attached (for she doats upon <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>) &amp; who can
                    understand her worth.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Busy as it is usually my fortune to be I was never so busy as now. My first chapter for <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> is written<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1809 to 1812
                        Southey contributed to the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for 1808&#8211;1810 in James Ballantyne&#8217;s <title>Edinburgh Annual
                        Register</title>.</note> &#8211; I expect something from you about America to inweave in the second. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has not sent me all my materials &amp; what he did send were delayed a
                    fortnight upon the road by the mismanagement of the Post Office. &#8211; but I am getting on. You will delight in the spirit of the
                    work, &#8211; in the plain straight forward kind of things which I relate, disdaining all petty &amp; all party considerations &amp;
                    looking <del>xxx</del> only to the public weal, &amp; those principles by which alone it can be upholden.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Three mornings more will finish my transcribing task for the first volume, including a long chapter which I fear
                    can hardly be got into the volume, tho I much wish to insert it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> Then come the notes-supplementary, &#8211; which might with
                    great pleasure to myself &amp; profit to my reader be extended to another volume as large, but I shall not allow them much more
                    than 50 pages. The book as a whole is more amusing than was to be expected. About a fortnights morning work will compleat my work
                    for it. 440 pages are printed, &#8211; the whole will not be less than 600.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that I am at Kehama again,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &amp; I trust in a fair way of soon reaching the end. There are not more
                    than 4000 lines done, &amp; I guess about 4500 will be its extent. I was gravelled at some of those rubs which must be met with
                    sometimes, &#8211; but have got afloat again (it was like being aground) &amp; am making way. I wish I could go on transcribing for you,
                    but in very truth I work at other transcriptions till my fingers ache, &amp; then have such a mass of reading to go thro, that a
                    single set of eyes &amp; hands is hardly sufficient for me. Nevertheless you shall have your copy finished before the book goes to
                    press. I began the printers copy in one spare half hour before supper, &amp; made improvements of great effect in the way of
                    finishing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> was here the other day for half an hour with Miss Hawker &amp; her sister,
                    &amp; some other Lady.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s visitors have not been traced.</note> I had not seen him
                    before for a long while. <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> will be <del>there</del> &lt;here&gt; for three days
                    at the end of the month. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> coming is I believe at an end owing to his fathers
                    death.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Last night we had a prodigious flood, higher in some places than can be remembered, &#8211; I say in some places, because
                    the Lake was previously low, the force of the waters was<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey has omitted to
                        write a word. C. C. Southey, in the published text, has interpolated &#8216;spent&#8217;. See Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 251&#8211;253.</note> before they found their
                    way to it. Do you know the little bridge over what is usually a dry ditch at the beginning of the Church Lane? The water was over
                    it, &amp; three feet deep in the lane. Half Slacks Bridge is gone. a chaise driver &amp; horses lost between this place &amp;
                        Wigton,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A small market town in Cumbria, north of Keswick.</note> &#8211; &amp; the corn
                    washed away to a heavy amount. It was a tremendous sight. Two large boughs were torn off the tree behind the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must not wish you to be paid off, unless you could be sure of a better appointment than you have at present, or
                    of not being appointed at all. If however you should be set adrift, &amp; are afraid of coming here (&#8211; I must not venture to say
                    what I would about it) &#8211; at any rate you had better make for Hereford, &#8211; that is not at a very costly distance, &#8211; &amp; you are so
                    far on the way &amp; only a little [MS illegible] of it. As for peace I see no hope of it. &#8211; no fear of it would be the better
                    phrase.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Junta<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish Supreme Central Junta, whose unwillingness to
                    organise supplies for the British Army while urging a policy of attack, led <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellesley</ref> (and Southey) to suspect some of the
                        Junta of co-operating with the French.</note> have mismanaged &amp; so have we &#8211; I know not whose mismanagement has been the
                    worst &#8211; The army which has been wasted at Flushing would have recovered Spain. The Spaniards will not be left to do it their own
                    way, by detail. What these changes at home will produce one cannot guess till it is known what is going out &amp; who is coming
                    in. If <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref> comes in we may expect something. If <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> goes out &#8211; the candle will be taken out of the dark lantern.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Another book of Heraldry which I have just lain my hand on explains Humet or Humetty &#8211; a Term made use of to denote an
                            Ordinary<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In heraldry, an ordinary is a simple geometrical figure that runs from
                            side to side or top to bottom of a shield.</note> which is <hi rend="ital">couped</hi> or cut off, &amp; no where reaches
                        to the edges of the Escutcheon,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A shield, or shield-shaped emblem, displaying a coat
                            of arms.</note> such as Crosses, Fesses<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fess is a horizontal band running
                            across a shield.</note> &amp;c.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The postscript is written at the top of the first
                            sheet.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>