<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1574</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2696</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 210&#8211;212 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1574" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1574" type="letter">
        <head>1574. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-02-03">3 February
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ [deletion
                        and addition in another hand] <del>Plymouth Dock</del>/ Torbay <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 210&#8211;212 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-02-03">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 3. 1809.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> [illegible large scrawl] &#8211; There Tom, &#8211; tell me what that hieroglyphic is if you can. the Devil himself must be a
                    good guesser if he finds it out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We want a Nelson in the army.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horatio, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of
                        Bront&#233; (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), who died at the Battle of Trafalgar on 21 October 1805.</note> Poor Sir John Moore was
                    too cautious a man.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and
                        varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna on 16 January 1809.</note> He waited in distrust of the Spaniards, to see what course the war would take, instead of being on the spot to
                    make it take the course he wished. When Hope<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Hope, 4th Earl of Hopetoun (1765&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>). During Moore&#8217;s advance into Spain, Hope commanded one of the army&#8217;s two divisions. He took part in
                        the retreat to Corunna and succeeded to overall command when Moore fell.</note> was at the passes of the Guadarrama mountain,
                    he &amp; the rest of the army should have been at Somosierra the other key to Madrid. There would have been reinforcements sent,
                    if he had not positively written to have empty transports <del>sent</del>, &#8211; &amp; the men been therefore disembarked. Good God
                    had there been twenty thousand fresh troops at Corunna, to have met the French what a victory should we have obtained, when even
                    with the wreck of an army foot-sore, broken-hearted, &amp; half starved, we defeated them so compleatly at the last!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of Corruna, fought 16 January 1809, resulted in a defensive victory for the retreating
                        British, if only in that they repelled the French and so gained time to embark for Britain.</note> &#8211; One thing results from
                    this <del>last</del> action, &#8211; the fear of invasion must be at rest for ever. We can beat the French, under every possible
                    disadvantage, &amp; with two, almost indeed three to one, against us. Come then Bonaparte! the sooner the better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ministers are jarring with each other. It is <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> who stands up
                    for Spain, &#8211; &amp; I learn from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> that they will stand by the Spaniards to
                    the last cost what it may &#8211; But they paralize one another, &amp; the rest of the Cabinet by meeting him half-way, &#8211; doing <hi rend="ital">half</hi> what he proposes, utterly undo everything. Still if we had a few such men as Cochrane<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and
                        formerly Thomas Southey&#8217;s captain. Cochrane gained renown through a campaign of daring and brilliantly executed raids
                        harassing and attacking settlements on the Spanish and French coasts.</note> in the army, &#8211; men who would <del>place</del>
                    &lt;have&gt; the same faith in British bottom by land as we have at sea, &#8211; that faith would redeem us. To be upon the defensive in
                    the field is ruin. Men never can win a battle unless they are determined to win it, &#8211; &amp; that cannot be the case when they wait
                    to be attacked. 100,000 men in Spain would overthrow &amp; destroy Bonaparte, &#8211; but we sent them in batches to be cut up. We
                    squander the strength of the country, we waste the blood of the country, we sacrifice the honour of the country &#8211; bring upon
                    ourselves a disgrace, which Bonaparte were he ten times more powerful than he is could never <del>bring</del> inflict upon us,
                    were there but true wisdom &amp; right courage in our rulers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written more letters than one since Dec. 12.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The only surviving
                        letter to Thomas Southey written after that of 12 December 1808 (Letter 1553) is dated 10 January 1809 (Letter 1563). The
                        letter mentioning Landor&#8217;s return from Spain appears not to have survived.</note> you have probably by this time received
                    them. In one I told you that <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> had returned to fight our Consul from
                        Coru&#241;a<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ever cantankerous and prickly Landor, in Spain to fight against the French,
                        had overheard a remark made by Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), British envoy to the
                        Spanish juntas in French-occupied Spain. Stuart said &#8216;He&#8217;s mad; he doesn&#8217;t have the money&#8217; and Landor, who had funded a small
                        group of soldiers during his own service with the Spanish military and was proposing to fund the Spanish, incorrectly thought
                        the remark was directed at him. See John Forster, <title>Walter Savage Landor</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                        135&#8211;141.</note> &#8211; (but this must have been before December) &#8211; the Consul has made peace with him by disowning words which <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> heard him utter, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">L.</ref> I believe will return to Spain to be in the forlorn hope. But tho Bonaparte may take the country, he cannot keep it.
                    He would not have done what he has, if the Spaniards had proclaimed <del>xxx</del> a Republic. &#8211; for &lt;which&gt; you may
                    remember I pointed out the peculiar fitness which their separate states afforded. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very busy. Some books of main importance to my history which I vainly attempted to buy, I have succeeded in
                    obtaining from a public library, by secret favour, &#8211; against rule.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> to borrow the following books for him from the Advocates Library in
                        Edinburgh, which he needed for writing his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819): Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791),
                            <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784); Jos&#233; Gumilla (1686&#8211;1750), <title>Histoire
                            Naturelle, Civile et Geographique de L&#8217;Orenoque</title> (1758), a French version of the original <title>Historia Natural,
                            Civil, &amp; Geografica de las Naciones situadas en las Riveras del Rio Orinoco</title> (1731); Giovanni Battista Ramusio
                        (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi et Viaggi</title> (1550&#8211;1559).</note> &amp; upon these I must work incessantly to get them
                    sent back again as speedily as possible, but this is very hard work, for like a woodcock all their guts are trail. Thirteen sheets
                    are printed, &#8211; &amp; probably <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> will soon be at a stand for copy before I can get
                    thro this indispensable labour. The volume will however most likely be sent in June.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The new review is to be called the Quarterly, &amp; will I suppose soon start. I fancy <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref> has taken care of the Cid there.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) was reviewed by Scott in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809), 117&#8211;134.</note> Of the new edition of Thalaba nine books are printed.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) was published in 1809.</note> &#8211; three weeks at farthest
                    will compleat it, &amp; a month more may be allowed before it be published, for [MS illegible] &amp;c &#8211; &amp; the journey from
                    Edinburgh by waggon, &#8211; or by sea. &#8211; Of late I have done little to Kehama,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note>
          <del>xxx</del> for these books now employ my morning time, &#8211; &amp; before they came restless nights occasioned by little illnesses
                    of the children made me lie till breakfast time. With my first possible leisure I shall hurry thro your transcription &#8211; It would
                    be convenient if I could borrow from my Hindoo Gods a few of their supernumerary heads &amp; hands,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem, <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, characterises the gods of the Hindu religion.</note> for I
                    find more employments than my present compliment can get thro.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Holding that my face will &#8216;carry off a drab&#8217; &#8211; I have a new coat of that complexion, just come home from Johnny
                    Cockbaines, the King of the Tailors.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Cockbain (dates unknown), a <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> tailor.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will conclude by copying part of a letter from <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> which you will
                    think very curious, &amp; will interest you more than any I could add of my own. &#8216;Of this motion against the Duke of York<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in
                        Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited
                        by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return
                        for which promotion was arranged.</note> strange fancies float in my mind. Two months ago a story went all over London, &#8211;
                    every body believes it, that the Duke of York threatened in Bond Street to horse whip an M. P. of the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince of Wales&#8217;s</ref> household, for endeavouring to get some of his letters from
                        M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarke. The Duke of Kent<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Edward, Duke of Kent and
                        Strathearn (1767&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), the fourth son of King George III (1738&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) was suspected of
                        manipulating the scandal because he coveted his brother, the Duke of York&#8217;s, position.</note> hates the D of Y. &amp; one of
                    the Secretaries of the former, Col. Dodd<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major Dodd (dates unknown), the Duke of Kent&#8217;s
                        private secretary, later accused in court of being instrumental in bringing the scandal to light by remunerating Clarke for
                        exposing the affair.</note> walks publicly arm in arm with Hague<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Hague (dates
                        unknown) wrote a series of pamphlets attacking the Duke of York&#8217;s conduct including <title>A Letter to . . . the Duke of York,
                            or an Exposition of the Circumstances that led to the late Appointment of Sir Hew Dalrymple</title> (1808),<title> An
                            Englishman&#8217;s Letter to his Majesty</title> (1808) and <title>Traits of all the Royal Dukes</title> (1808), following them
                        up with a handbill accusing the Duke of Sussex of trying to prevent their sale. For this he was convicted of libel on 23
                        February 1809.</note> the D Ys libeller<del>x</del>. <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbet</ref> is <hi rend="ital">certainly</hi> in the interest of the D Kent &amp; <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">P of Wales</ref>. I know a
                    person employed by the D Kent confidentially &amp; officially, for the Duke keeps an office! &#8211; who has also been deeply in the
                    confidence &amp; money concerns of Lord Moira,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Rawdon Hastings, 1st Marquess of
                        Hastings and 2nd Earl of Moira (1754&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and politician.</note> the P Wales&#8217;s friend; this
                    person was M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkes favourite &amp; confident while she lived with the D York. I <hi rend="ital">know</hi>
                    farther that Wardel sits in <hi rend="ital">that</hi> seat for Oakhampton,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gwyllym Lloyd
                        Wardle (c. 1761&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), elected M.P. for Okehampton in 1807, had played a central role in exposing the Duke
                        of York and Mary Anne Clarke&#8217;s involvement in office trafficking. However, his own reputation was quickly sullied when, in
                        July, it emerged that Wardle had bought Clarke&#8217;s testimony against the Duke of York with a promise to pay for the furnishing
                        of her house. It was alleged by Clarke that Wardle had been acting for the Duke of Kent.</note> to which P Wales nominated
                    Barham &amp; <hi rend="ital">paid the expences</hi> in the last Parliament.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph
                        Foster-Barham (1759&#8211;1832), MP for Stockbridge and also Okehampton, left parliament in 1807.</note> These are droll facts. I
                    have no doubt that every thing charged against the D York is true: but I fear the facts will not be brought home to him. The fact
                    however of his keeping a number of mistresses, all of them the most notorious strumpets in town in the highest stile, before he
                    had them, will however be proved &amp; admitted at the Bar of the H of Commons, &amp; that will blast his character (he a Prince
                        <del>of</del>, high in official station, &amp; a married man) with all the virtuous part of the community. He cannot come off
                    with honour, whatsoever may become of the actual motion against him.&#8217; &#8211; Is not this very curious? &#8211; I <del>will post</del> have
                    just room to add that half the newspapers are at this time under prosecution from the D York, &amp; that in <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuarts</ref> words he has nearly silenced the Newspaper press.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The hieroglyphic at the beginning of the letter is a facsimile of the <del>x</del> way in which you signed your
                    christian name at the end of your last.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>