<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1728</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2850</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 179&#8211;181.Dating note:
                        internal evidence of the performance of the melodrama of Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Mary the Maid of the Inn&#8217; from 27 December 1809.
                    </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1728" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1728" type="letter">
        <head>1728. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams-Wynn</ref>, <date when="1809-12-31">[late December 1809]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M P./Acton/
                        Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 179&#8211;181.<lb />Dating note:
                        internal evidence of the performance of the melodrama of Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Mary the Maid of the Inn&#8217; from 27 December 1809.
                    </p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> When is the Installation to take place? &#8211; If not till summer I will try to do something, tho with little
                    expectation of either pleasing myself, or any body else.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The service of installation of
                            <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>, as Chancellor of Oxford University took place in 1810.
                        Southey was asked by Wynn (Grenville&#8217;s nephew), to write a poem commemorating the event. It was published as &#8216;Verses. Spoken
                        in the Theatre at Oxford Upon the Installation of Lord Grenville&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2
                        (1811), 641&#8211;643.</note> Except a solitary sonnet to Lord Percy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hugh Percy, 3rd Duke of
                        Northumberland (1785&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), politician and landowner, whose &#8216;most dramatic, and puzzling, Commons
                        interventions came in 1807 when he first tried to turn the Slave Trade Abolition Bill into a Slavery Abolition Bill by moving
                        an amendment to emancipate every black child born after 1 January 1810&#8217;, <title>DNB</title>.</note> upon the Slave Trade,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem &#8216;Sonnet to Lord Percy, on his Late Motion for the Gradual Abolition of
                        Slavery in the West Indies&#8217; was published in the <title>Courier</title> in April 1807, under the signature &#8216;R. S.&#8217;</note>
          <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> I have not written a poem these seven years &#8211;never being idle enough to think of one. And for <del>making
                        goo</del> writing upon such an occasion I should almost as soon think of trying my hand at an Oxford sausage against an Oxford
                    cook, as <del>for</del> of making Oxford verses in competition with University poets. However it is so reasonable that you should
                    look to me, that this very morning I was casting about in my own mind to see whether any thing would be brought forth. &#8211; Upon your
                    triumph I can only say I am glad you have had reason to rejoice. &#8211; tho in my conscience I wish it had been any other reason. &#8211;
                        <del>xxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> himself is not a more determined No Popery Man than I am.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spencer Perceval was appointed Prime Minister in October 1809 and was strongly opposed to
                        Catholic emancipation.</note> This <del>xxxx</del> &lt;question&gt; however has now nothing to do with the matter, &amp; there
                    &lt;are&gt; other points in which I can as sincerely compliment Ld G. as I should condemn him upon this. But upon no point so
                    willingly as the belief that whether in power or not he will, as far as in him lies, save this country from the dangers, &#8211;
                        <del>xxx xxxx xxxx xx</del> &amp; worse, dishonour of peace with Buonaparte. Is there any objection to <del>xxx</del> touching
                    upon this?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Rogers came to Balliol a few months before I left it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cooke Rogers, a
                        student of Balliol college, who Southey knew briefly while he was there, his first name and dates are unknown.</note> He was a
                    wild Welshman just caught &#8211; a very honest good fellow, whom we used to call Cadwallader. He lived a good deal with us, &amp; had I
                    am sure at that time a very sincere regard for me. I have never seen him since &#8211; They tell me he is become a stiff disciplinarian,
                    &#8211; which is not much to his credit. &#8211; nevertheless for the memory of old times it would be a great <del>xx</del> joy to me to give
                    him a shake by the hands once more.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Much joy of your <del>daughter</del> &lt;child&gt;. The heathen name which you give her is in danger of being
                    shortened into Vic, &#8211; &amp; that is the diminution of Vixen, <del>xxxx</del> a name proper to female terriers, &amp; therefore
                    unseemly for your daughter. <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Presumably Wynn intended to call his daughter Victoria, but
                        there is no record of a child of that name. Charlotte his first daughter was born in 1807 and Mary was born in 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will not be long before you receive my first volume, there is but one sheet more to print, besides the
                    supplementary notes. Kehama is in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> hands &amp; I expect the first proof
                    this week.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> has sent me the Life of Nelson to review,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed several books about Nelson in his article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3
                        (February 1810), 218&#8211;262. These included John Charnock (1756&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord
                            Viscount Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.; with Observations, Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d.
                        1847), <title>The Life of Lord Nelson</title> (1806); T. O. Churchill (fl. 1800&#8211;1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount
                            Nelson, Duke of Bront&#233;, &amp;c</title> (1808); and James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John
                        McArthur (1755&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title>
                        (1809). Southey&#8217;s article was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> &amp; offers 20
                    guineas per sheet for doing it, &#8211; it is precisely that subject on which his expectations from me must necessarily be disappointed,
                    let me do what I can. The book is by no means so bad as might have been expected yet being almost wholly compilation it would have
                    been far better if the Compiler could have been contented to appear <del>in</del> as Editor only, &amp; have printed this document
                    under the title of the Nelson Papers, &#8211; giving the little else which they had to give in the form of notes &amp; <del>xxxxx</del>
                    headings. If they meant to make a book of reference this would have been the best form, &#8211; &amp; it is only as a book of reference
                    that what they have made can be considered, &#8211; for who will read it? &#8211; I mean to weigh the book &amp; calculate its faults (as
                    biography) by the stone.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Adm. Sotheby<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rear-Admiral Thomas Sotheby (1759&#8211;1831).</note> made <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> Acting Commander with the Lyra<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS
                            <hi rend="ital">Lyra</hi> was a Royal Navy Cherokee class 10-gun brig-sloop, launched in August 1808.</note> &#8211; &amp; I
                    have been trying to get him confirmed, &#8211; which most likely will not be done. However if <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> can do it for me, he will. My best hope for him is that Lord
                    Melville may go back to the Admiralty,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. From 1802&#8211;1805
                        Melville&#8217;s use of public funds when Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800), was investigated by a Royal Commission. On 9 April
                        1805 he was censured in the House of Commons for allowing the misuse of public funds. He resigned and impeachment proceedings
                        were commenced against him, but he was cleared of nearly all the charges in June 1806. However, Melville did not hold a
                        government position again before his death in 1811.</note> &#8211; when I am sure <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>
                    would get him promoted. Surely it is not possible that the present set of men can keep their ground. Yet I will rather support
                    even them than see the Foxites in power.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Whigs with a political allegiance to <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James Fox</ref>, Foreign Secretary and Leader of the House of Commons until
                        his death in September 1806.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> takes the living of <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>,
                    resigning for it his Christ Church preferment in Herefordshire. This will be likely to bring me more frequently to London. I shall
                    probably visit him then towards the fall of the leaf, &#8211; if one may look on so far. I hope to get the press of business off my
                    hands in time to be at Durham for the <hi rend="ital">Long Main</hi>,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> An annual cock
                        fight at Durham.</note> &#8211; a thing which it is highly proper that D. Manuel should see.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Manuel Espriella, the fictional tourist of Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England: By Don Manuel Espriella. Translated
                            from the Spanish</title> (1st edn, 1807; 2nd edn, 1808). Southey&#8217;s plans for Espriella to travel to further parts of the
                        country in an additional volume never materialised.</note> Heaven knows whether I shall ever see the other side of Snowdon.
                    The older I grow the more I have to do at home, the less inclination to leave it, &amp; yet the more calls abroad.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They have made a melodrama of Mary the Maid of the Inn at one of the Strand theatres.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Mary, the Maid of the Inn&#8217; was written in 1796 and published by Southey in <title>Poems</title> (1797), in
                            <title>The Oracle</title>, 11 February 1797 and, revised, in later editions of the 1797 <title>Poems, in Minor
                            Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and in <title>Poetical Works Collected by Himself</title> (1837&#8211;1838). It was still being
                        issued as a one penny broadside ballad in the mid-nineteenth century. Southey&#8217;s poem was adapted for the stage by the theatre
                        manager and actress, Jane Scott (married name Middleton; bap. 1779&#8211;1839) and it was presented at the Adelphi Theatre in London
                        between 27 December 1809 and 2 April 1810, and again in 1811 and 1816.</note> Did I ever tell you that the story is in Plotts
                        Staffordshire?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Plot (bap. 1640&#8211;1696; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Natural
                            History of Staffordshire</title> (1686).</note> The scene of it was the Black Moor of Skorridge, near Leek, <del>x</del>
                    the chief personage a man, &amp; the murder not <hi rend="ital">discovered</hi> but prevented. If you have the book you will find
                    it at P. 291.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s citation is correct. The passage appears in Plot&#8217;s <title>Natural
                            History of Staffordshire</title> (London, 1686), p. 291.</note> I verily believe that at least half my reputation is owing
                    to that paltry ballad, &#8211; which is bad enough to spoil a very fine story. The strolling players recite it here about the
                    country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has found on shipboard a copy of the American Madoc which is on its way to me.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc: A Poem</title> was published in Boston, Massachusetts, in 1806.</note> It was published in numbers. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has unluckily bound it without directions, &amp; so deprived me of the
                    criticisms upon the covers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>