<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1032</idno><idno type="nines">rce2154</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                    D3.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1032" type="letter"><head>1032. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-02-05">5
                    February 1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthries</ref> Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh –/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] FE/ 1805<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                    D3<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As Madoc is now finished,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805) was being printed
                        by the firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> in Edinburgh.</note> do you get for me the
                    remaining sheets beginning with Sheet 3.C. page 387. &amp; also the sheet with the preface &amp;c. &amp; pay the carriage for me
                    to Penrith – because the rascals charge me five shillings – whereas at Edinburgh they would not demand 1/6. – The copy thus
                    compleated will do to correct for a future edition &amp; save a better, &amp; I shall have the pleasure of seeing the whole
                    together at least six weeks [<del>earlier</del>] &lt;before&gt; the published book will reach <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> – which will be another pleasure.</p><p rend="indent1"> By this time you have received the 20 £ which <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> sent off on the
                        31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> – making the first quarters allowance. your remittance for the future will be sent either on a
                    regular quarter day – or at any other times &amp; proportions which you may chuse – you will let me know this in your next.</p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Calvert has something like a paralytic affection in one of her legs. she has lost all
                    feeling in it – tho she still has the use of the limb. If you were here I would advise Calvert<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert (1771–1829; <title>DNB</title>), who was at school with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death
                        of his father, Calvert became a man of independent means, inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east
                        shore of Bassenthwaite, near Keswick (<title>DNB</title>).</note> to get an apparatus &amp; give her the nitrous oxide, this
                    being precisely a case for it. – A great event has taken place in our own household – Mary the maid having this morning walked off
                    without ceremony to be married, – to the great discomposure of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridges</ref> schemes, who is on the eve of going to Liverpool to visit the tribe of Crampton.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Peter Crompton (dates unknown) of Eton House, Liverpool, a radical reformer who supported
                            <ref target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref> in the 1790s and who contested elections at Nottingham (1796,
                        1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Beef <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Philips</ref> is publishing a compendium of all modern travels in numbers.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillips published the compendium <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages &amp; Travels: Containing, I. Translations from Foreign Languages, of
                            Voyages and Travels Never Before Published. II. Original Voyages and Travels Never Before Published. III. Analyses of New
                            Voyages and Travels Published in England</title> (1805–1809).</note> I wish you would look at one of them &amp; tell me
                    whether the works are analized at any length – or if it be little more than a mere review – because if well done the book would be
                    useful to me. – I am getting on with history &amp; thinking about the Spaniards Letters<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> was published by
                            <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807.</note> – which my finances compel me to think about against
                    my inclinations.</p><p rend="indent1"> The title page to Madoc is exceedingly beautiful. Open Gothic letters, engraved after Tomkins’s writing,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Tomkins (1743–1816; <title>DNB</title>): writing-master and calligrapher, who took
                        commissions for decorative book titles of luxury publications.</note><del>on an</del> a graphic antiquarian &amp; amateur <del>q</del> who is quite unrivalled in his art. He has done this to oblige
                        <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>. – I would fain be finishing Kehama<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note> if I could afford <del>xxx</del> to write for
                    pleasure, without any regard for profit.</p><p rend="indent1"> All well. the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> stands half her time – walks along by the
                    window – &amp; says ‘take care’. Your friend John<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ass.</note> is in good
                    plight &amp; behaves better of late.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1805-02-05">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 5. 1805.</date></p><p rend="indent1"> Get the sheets soon – or they will be shipt off for London.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>