<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1353</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2475</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o
                        (ed.), &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico
                            e Geografico Brasileiro, 178 (1943).  Previously  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o (ed.), &#8216;Cartas de Robert
                        Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico
                            Brasileiro, 178 (1943), 37&#8211;39.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1353" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1353" type="letter">
        <head>1353. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">John Theodore Koster</ref>, <date when="1807-08-20">20
                        August 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o
                        (ed.), &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico
                            e Geografico Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943)<lb />Previously published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o (ed.), &#8216;Cartas de Robert
                        Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico
                            Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943), 37&#8211;39.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1807-08-20">Aug. 20. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have to thank you for the little box of books which I found here a few days ago on my return from a short visit
                    to <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. That it came thro you I learn by my Lisbon advices and also from <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Samuel Reid</ref>. The cargo is deficient in three volumes which I hope have been forgotten in
                    the first packing, and not lost on the way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will not be very long before I shall have it in my power to send you the first fruits of many years hard labour.
                    I am going to press with the Chronicle of the Cid, a book of which the history is briefly this.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in
                        1808.</note> In describing the state of society in the Spanish peninsula at time when Portugal first became an independent
                    state I had many years ago written an abstract of the Cid&#8217;s life, as exhibiting in a connected and highly curious narrative the
                    manners of the age; for this, however, short as it was the after growth of my papers convinced me that there would be no room. I
                    then thought of enlarging it and printing it separately; but in setting about this the original documents appeared to be every way
                    so interesting that I finally resolved upon setting seriously to work, and giving a Chronicle of the Cid at length and more fully
                    than it has ever yet been done even in his own country. Here are three documents which I have had before me, the Poema del Cid,
                    the oldest poem in the language and perhaps the oldest work having been written almost immediately after his death. The Chronica
                    del Cid, and the Chronica Geral compiled by order of Alonso el Sabio about the year 1250.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s edition included translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica Particular del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the
                            <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title>
                        (1632).</note> These two works are generally the same, that is the one has either been extracted from, or engrafted into the
                    other, each however, contains some circumstances which are not in the other. With these before me, I have combined all that is
                    contained in the three into one narration, which is every where translation, tho of course it differs from every one of the
                    separate originals. I have added whatever matter is to be found in other equally authentic authorities, given minute references to
                    these at the end of every section, and entered into every kind of critical investigation and elucidation which was necessary in
                    the notes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The whole will be preceded by an introduction concerning the state of Spain under the Goths and Moors, which will
                    sketch its history till the period when the Chronicle begins. I believe that this will be as curious a book as has ever yet
                    appeared in our language.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It has pleased his most gracious Majesty, or rather it pleased <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
                        Grenville</ref> for him just when he went out of office, to give me a pension of 200&#163;. I thank the royal bounty. It will
                    please his Majesty to deduct from this in the shape of taxes 56&#163;. I admire the royal conscience. Having thus premised that I am a
                    pensioner I may now say a word or two upon the state of affairs. Things appear to me to be hurrying towards a revolution and that
                    not from the efforts of any party to bring about one, but from the total lack of all talents among our governors, and the excess
                    of political profligacy. While Pitt<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime
                        Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> and <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> were living they who did not
                    credit the one believed in the other, this political faith is at an end. <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld.
                        Grenville</ref> is the only man left who has the character of a statesman. In that character he is greatly over-rated, and he
                    has let the time slip when he might have acquired the highest popularity by resigning those sinecures of which sooner or later he
                    must be stripped. The people begin to despise their rulers; every day they become more and more convinced of the extent of their
                    prodigality and peculation. External circumstances become daily worse and worse, and what is to save the state waggon, driven so
                    unskilfully and at such an unmerciful rate, down so steep a road, what is to save it from an overturn! <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis Burdett</ref> wants talents equal to his integrity and his popularity, but were there
                    an able man in his place, he might be the political Martin Luther of England. I was very very sorry, or rather very indignant at
                    your last election. Nothing could be more dishonourable to a city which I was wont to think one of the most liberal in the
                    kingdom; than thus to displace one of the best members to make room for one of the very worst.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William Roscoe</ref>, elected in 1806, offended many of his
                        constituents by speaking in favour of Catholic emancipation and against the slave trade. He lost his seat in the May 1807
                        election and the Tory George Canning (1770&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), who had satirised Southey&#8217;s poems in <title>The
                            Anti-Jacobin, or, Weekly Examiner</title> (1797&#8211;1798), became the city&#8217;s MP.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall take the liberty of directing a small box for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to
                    your care, consisting of jellies, etc., things very eatable at a custom house, but I believe not otherwise serviceable. My brother
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is with him. I have at length fixed my family here, and have just
                    received the main part of my own and <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncle&#8217;s</ref> library from Bristol. Remember us
                    all to <ref target="people.html#KosterMrs">Mrs. Koster</ref> &#8211; your son and your daughters. I shall see you in the course of the
                    winter.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>