<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.993</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2115</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 288&#8211;290 [with
                        slight omissions].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="993" type="letter">
        <head>993. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1804-11-27">27
                        November 1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ C
                        W Williams Wynn Esqr M. P./ <del>Lincolns Inn</del>/ <del>London</del>. Audley End/ Saffron Walden<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmarks: FREE/ NOV 30/ 1804; [partial] NO/ 30/ 804<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 288&#8211;290 [with
                        slight omissions].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-11-27">Tuesday. Nov. 27. 1804.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Returning last night from the neighbourhood of <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, where we have
                    been the guests of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> for the last fortnight, I found your letter &amp;
                    your three franks. The Church is beautifully situated, &amp; would by a good artist be made a most picturesque scene. I wish I had
                    seen it with my own eyes &#8211; it would certainly have supplied a good subject for description which, connected with the feeling of
                    the story, might have made that very ornamental which is now very bad.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Dapples</ref> pamphlet has pretty accurately answered my expectations.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s pamphlet, <title>A Letter to the Right Hon. William Pitt on his
                            Political Experiments</title> (1804) which had been sent to Southey by Wynn.</note> it is respectable, but unimpressive,
                    not general enough in its scope of thought to be of permanent value; not close or poignant enough upon its particular subject to
                    produce any immediate effect. it should have been more logical &amp; pithy, to convince; &#8211; more diffuse &amp; ornamented, &#8211; to
                    persuade. Still it is a respectable pamphlet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I looked into Herberts book<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Herbert (1772&#8211;1851;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>Antiquities of the Inns of Court and Chancery; Containing Historical and Descriptive Sketches
                            Relative to their Original Foundation, Customs, Ceremonies, Buildings, Government, &amp;c., &amp;c., with a Concise
                            History of the English Law</title> (1804).</note> for a few minutes at Hallums,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Henry Hallam (1777&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>): historian and reviewer.</note> &amp; formed a more favourable opinion than you
                    express who has read it thro.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc is now beyond the reach of accident. the whole poem is printed &amp; I daily expect the first proof of the
                    notes, which would have been far more amusing had I had my books about me &amp; access to sundry others. The exordium runs
                    thus</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Come listen to a tale of times of old,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come &#8211; for ye know me. I am he who sung</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The Maid of Arc, &amp; I am he who framed</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of Thalaba the wild &amp; wonderous song.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come listen to my lay &amp; ye shall hear</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> How Madoc from the shores of Britain spread</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The adventurous sail, explored the ocean ways,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And quelled barbarian power, &amp; overthrew</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The bloody altars of idolatry,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And on their ruins raised triumphantly</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The Cross of Christ. Come listen to my lay!</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">This was written in consequence of Lord Carysforts<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Joshua Proby, 1st
                        Earl of Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>): judge, diplomat, Whig politician and poet, and author of <title>Dramatic
                            and Narrative Poems</title> (1810).</note> advice. the plan of the lines is good, &amp; they have cost me more time than
                    the execution will give you cause to suspect. Uniformly the worst parts of the poem have cost me the most labour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been reading Lady Wortleys Letters<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letters of Lady Mary Wortley
                    Montagu (1689&#8211;1762; <title>DNB</title>), were pubished by James Dallaway (1763&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), in <title>The Works of the Right Hon. Lady Mary Wortley Montagu ... Published, by Permission, from
                            her Genuine Papers</title>, 5 vols (1803).</note> with great delight. they are a valuable acquisition to English literature &#8211; as much superior to M. Sevigne&#8217;s<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marie de Rabutin-Chantal, Marquise de S&#233;vign&#233; (1626&#8211;1696), <title>Lettres de Madame la Marquise de Sevigne a
                            Madame la Comtesse de Grignan sa fille</title> (1756).</note> as an Englishman is better than a Frenchman. the last series
                    in particular are full of every kind of merit. Richardsons Correspondence<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Laetitia
                        Barbauld&#8217;s edition of <title>The Correspondence of Samuel Richardson</title> was published in 6 volumes in 1804.</note> I
                    should think worse than any thing of any celebrity that ever was published, if the life prefixed did not happen to be quite as
                    bad. The few letters of Klopstocks Wife must be excepted from this censure. They are very interesting &amp; very affecting. indeed
                    the notice of her death coming as it does after that sweet letter in which she dwells upon her hopes of happiness from that child
                    whose birth destroyed her &#8211; came upon me like an electric shock.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Margaretha (Meta) Moller
                        (1727&#8211;1758) married the German poet Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803) in 1754; her correspondence with Richardson ended
                        with her untimely death aged thirty-one. Her last letter is full of hopes concerning her as-yet unborn first child; it ends
                        with her determination not only to mother but also to nurse it herself.</note> &#8211; The costume prints are excellent. Is it
                    possible that half a century can have so totally altered the appearance of the people of England! Greeks &amp; Romans are not more
                    unlike us than our Grandfathers were.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have met a very odd homo by name Worgan<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Worgan (1759&#8211;after 1812):
                        almoner, musician, resident of a cottage at Storr&#8217;s Hall, Windermere, who composed <title>A Set of Sonnets</title> (1810), and
                        hymns, one of which, &#8216;Windermere&#8217;, was included in the collection published by George Worgan (b. 1802), <title>Gems of Sacred
                            Melody</title> (1841).</note> whom if you have not seen you will for he is going to Acton this Xmas. he does wonders upon
                    the piano-forte. oddly enough he played &amp; sung the Old Mans Comforts<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s 1799
                        poem &#8216;The Old Man&#8217;s Comforts and how he procured them&#8217; (&#8216;You are old, Father William the young man cried&#8217;). For the text see
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, pp.
                        270&#8211;271.</note> in a large company, &amp; after praising the music they fell to praising the poetry, which nobody knew to be
                    mine. he himself fancied it was <ref target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowless</ref> &#8211; so I set him right.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> told me he had purchased Wilkes&#8217;s<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Wilkes (1727&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>): radical journalist, politician and pornographer, whose exclusion from his seat in
                        parliament had led to riots in 1768. Southey would attack Wilkes in his <title>Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note>
                    letters &amp; asked if I could recommend him a fit editor. I named <ref target="people.html#RoughWilliam">Rough</ref> [William] &#8211;
                    on account of his wife.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Rough had married, in 1802, Harriet (1778&#8211;c.1820),
                        the illegitimate daughter of a Mrs Arnold (dates unknown) and John Wilkes. Southey&#8217;s advice was intended to allow Rough to
                        suppress anything in Wilkes&#8217;s letters likely to cause his wife shame. Rough did so, undertaking the edition without payment
                        despite persistent financial problems.</note> &amp; have heard nothing of the matter since.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1804 <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> published <title>Letters from the Year 1774 to
                            the Year 1796 of J. Wilkes, Esq. to his Daughter ... With a Collection of his Miscellaneous Poems</title>, ed. Sir William
                        Rough, 4 vols.</note> How is <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> Mother? I hope in less peril than he
                    imagined, as you have never mentioned her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Good news. the bargain about our house is broken off,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s landlord,
                            <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">William Jackson</ref>, had been negotiating the sale of his house to Mr White
                        (names and dates unknown) of Keswick.</note> &amp; I shall be Lord of <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> as
                    long as it suits me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Are you a liker of conundrums? I manufactured a brace while dressing myself the other morning tolerably bad. Why is
                    Sir Cloudesly Shovel like Werter? &#8211; because he was felo-de-sea.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The eponymous hero of the
                        novel by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749&#8211;1832), <title>The Sorrows of Young Werther</title> (<title>Die Leiden des Jungen
                            Werthers</title>) (1774/1787) who killed himself; Admiral of the Fleet, Sir Cloudesley Shovell (1650&#8211;1707;
                            <title>DNB</title>), was full of the sea because he drowned in a notorious naval disaster off the Scilly Isles.</note> Why
                    might you say of the <del>Rock</del> Shores of Schaffhausen<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A city on the river Rhine in
                        northern Switzerland.</note> that they resemble a chamber pot? &#8211; because you might say to the river, is it not <hi rend="ital">You Rhine</hi>?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>