<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1475</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2597</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Newstead Abbey.  Previously  published: Catalogue of the Collection of Autograph Letters and Historical
                            Documents Formed Between 1865 and 1882 by Alfred Morrison, 6 vols (London, 1883&#8211;1892), VI, pp.
                    163&#8211;165.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1475" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1475" type="letter">
        <head>1475. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Anna Seward</ref>, <date when="1808-07-04">4 July 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Seward/ Lichfield<lb />Endorsement: July 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/
                            1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> specimen of Kehama/ (thro<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the 5 vol. of the Poetical Reg. w<hi rend="sup">h</hi>. I possess I have carefully searched for Garcia Ferrandez &amp; King Ramiro but in vain)<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />MS: Newstead Abbey<lb />Previously published:<title> Catalogue of the Collection of Autograph Letters and Historical
                            Documents Formed Between 1865 and 1882 by Alfred Morrison</title>, 6 vols (London, 1883&#8211;1892), VI, pp.
                    163&#8211;165.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-07-04">July 4. 1808</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wolseley<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Robert Wolseley (d. 1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740&#8211;1817). The family seat was at Wolseley Park, Rugeley, Staffordshire, near Seward&#8217;s home at Lichfield.</note> sent me your welcome letter yesterday morning, &amp; showed me the extract from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Mundys<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Noel Clarke Mundy (1739&#8211;1815), a landed gentleman of Derbyshire, and a
                        poet friend of Seward&#8217;s.</note> in the evening, when he &amp; his Lady did us the favour of drinking tea in my library. They
                    are not likely to remain here; the lodgings which they had pre-engaged prove to be ill-situated &amp; worse accommodated, &amp;
                    there seems little hope of their procuring any better. I am unluckily a prisoner in the house which prevents me from showing them
                    some of our home scenery, as I should otherwise gladly have done. A violent catarrh seized <del>be</del> me by the nose a
                    fortnight ago; this complaint is with me a very severe one, &#8211; the slightest exposure to air or sunshine renews &amp; increases it;
                    fits of sneezing eight &#8211; ten &#8211; twelve times successively shake me from head to foot, &amp; the house from top to bottom, &#8211; &amp;
                    leave me bathed in perspiration; &#8211; my eyes suffer, &#8211; &amp; all I can do is to sit in a darkened room &amp; play a solo upon the
                    pocket-handkerchief from morning till night.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will tell you freely &amp; fairly the impression which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> French&#8217;s squib<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps the anonymous parody <title>The Simpliciad: a Satiric-Didactic Poem containing Hints for
                            the Scholars of the New School</title> (1808), usually attributed to Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>) but
                        credited here to French Laurence (1757&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>).</note> upon <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> leaves upon my mind. You know that I am not blind to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> faults; &#8211; nor familiar as we are with each other, is there that kind of intimacy between us which would be
                    likely in any degree to blind me. But when I see a man take up the Poems of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref>
                    &amp; passing over pieces of such beauty as the Tintern Abbey, &#8211; the Leech-Gatherer, &#8211; the Brothers, Michael, the Song at Brougham
                    Castle &amp;c., fix upon the weeds of the collection,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poems Southey lists were
                        published in Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Lyrical Ballads</title> (1800) and <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> (1807).</note> &amp;
                    join in with the yelping pack of curs who are attempting to hunt him down, &#8211; I cannot but feel that it is no mark of a generous or
                    a good spirit. If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> French does not admire, &amp; greatly admire, the greater number of these poems, he does
                    not know what poetry is; &#8211; in that case his satire is the effect of that common dislike which <del>xx</del> bad poets
                        <del>normally</del> feel towards good ones. But if he has any sense of the merit of these better poems, something of more
                    importance than the understanding will be found in fault. This is a malicious age, an age of slander &amp; of selfishness, &amp;
                    the spirit of the age has infected him. What would he think of a critic who if Milton were mentioned, should immediately begin to
                    ridicule his psalms, &amp; his translation from Horace?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Milton&#8217;s (1608&#8211;1674;
                            <title>DNB</title>) translations of the Psalms, some of them schoolboy exercises, were published in his <title>Poems upon
                            Several Occasions</title> of 1673, as was his early translation of Horace&#8217;s (Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65 BC&#8211;8 BC)), &#8216;Ode
                        to Pyrrha&#8217; (<title>Odes</title>, I: 5).</note> What does every Englishman think of Voltaires criticisms upon Shakespere?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francois Marie Arouet (pen name Voltaire) (1694&#8211;1778) disparaged Shakespeare in his
                            <title>Dissertation sur la trag&#233;die ancienne et modern</title> (1748).</note> &amp; just such is the <hi rend="ital">jeu
                        d&#8217;esprit</hi>
          <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;lighthearted witticism&#8217;.</note> of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    French: &#8211; I give it a French name, for any English one would be too good for its witlessness. &#8211; What is the consequence of this
                    prevailing disposition to ridicule the defects of men of genius, instead of giving them the fair praise which they deserve? That
                    those persons who take their opinions from others are deterred from purchasing the books, &amp; the author is disheartened from
                    laying any thing more before an ungrateful generation. This is the case with Wordsworth: he has stopt the publication of his White
                        Doe,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Criticisms of the manuscript text by Coleridge and harsh reviews of his 1807
                            <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> persuaded Wordsworth to withhold his &#8216;White Doe of Rylstone&#8217; from publication until
                        1815.</note> &amp; it is more than probable that, tho he will continue to write as long as he lives, what he writes will be
                    reserved for an age in which justice will be done him. With respect to myself, these things give me no pain as they do him, but
                    they inflict upon me a heavier injury. I cannot subsist with the profits of my pen &amp; in consequence of the total failure of
                        Madoc,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805)</note>
          <del>it is</del> tho whole years elapsed in which I did not write a single verse, &amp; in all probability I never should have
                    written another, had it not been for that chance meeting with <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>. Assuredly
                    now I shall go on from poem to poem, but unless I can previously secure the fair price of the manual labour bestowed upon them,
                    not one of them shall go into the world, till I am gone out of it. By this means at least I can lay by some provision for my
                    children, &amp; elude the absurd laws of copyright, which would otherwise rob them of <del>my</del> &lt;the&gt; property just when
                    it will begin to be valuable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To what you say of the unlucky subject of Joan of Arc<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s 1796 poem
                        of this name, published while Britain was at war with France, was too revolutionary in its stylistic innovations and too
                        French in its subject matter to win him popularity and reputation.</note> I fully &amp; unequivocally assent. It will always
                    impede my national reputation; at the same time it will gain for me the more desirable applause of those whose morality is not
                    confined within geographical limits. The double negatives to which you justly object are the sins of my youth, &#8211; when I thought
                        <del>it</del> &lt;such phraseology&gt; must be good because it was to be found in Milton. &#8211; There is nothing I think in the
                        4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition so fine as the introduction of the Maid in this.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        excerpt from the ninth book of the first, 1796, edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title>, &#8216;The Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217;,
                        was published in the second, 1806, edition of that poem at the end of the second volume. &#8216;The Vision&#8217; was also published in
                            <title>Poems by Robert Southey. The Second Volume</title> in 1799, the 4th edition of which appeared in 1806.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first specimen of narration in irregular rhymes is the Gideon of Aaron Hill:<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Hill (1685&#8211;1750; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gideon, or, the Patriot</title> (1749).</note> but his
                    powers were not equal to what he undertook. I versified two Spanish stories in this manner in 1802, &#8211; incorrect copies of which
                    are very likely to be found in the Poetical Register under the titles of Garci Ferrandez, &amp; King Ramiro.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> These poems were published as follows: &#8216;Garci Ferrandez&#8217;, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register
                            for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838);
                        &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; in September 1803 in the <title>Morning Post</title> and on 12 May 1804 in the <title>Iris</title> (edited by
                            <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>) and then, revised, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register
                            for 1808</title>, <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and with revisions in <title>Poetical Works</title>
                        (1837&#8211;1838).</note> But whenever I have the pleasure of showing you Kehama,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> you will I think see new modes of rhyming, in which the ear only, &amp; not
                    the eye has been consulted. The line rhyming to its own middle is <del>common</del> common <del>to</del> &lt;in&gt; the ballad
                    stanza. I have not unfrequently thrown rhymes into the middle of the verse, &amp; sometimes made the beginning &amp; end
                    correspond with good effect.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2"> Expecting some new crime, in fear they stood,</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Some horror which would make the natural blood</l>
          <l rend="indent2">
            <hi rend="ital">Start</hi>, with cold shudderings thrill the sinking <hi rend="ital">heart</hi>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Whiten the lip, &amp; make the abhorrent eye</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Roll back, &amp; close, prest in for agony.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published as lines 143&#8211;147
                            of Book 8 of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810). See volume 4 of <title>Robert Southey Poetical Works
                                1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004).</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent1"> [MS torn]is a rattling sample &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Along the mead the hallowed steed</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Still wanders wheresoeer he will</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Oer hill or dale, or plain:</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> No human hand hath trick&#8217;d that mane</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> From which he shakes the morning dew;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> His mouth has never felt the rein</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> His lips have never froth&#8217;d the chain,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> For pure of blemish &amp; of stain,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> His neck unbroke to mortal yoke,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Like Nature free, the steed must be</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Fit offering for the Immortals he.</l>
          <l rend="indent1"> A year &amp; day the steed must stray</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Wherever chance may guide his way,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Before he bleed at Seeva&#8217;s shrine;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The year &amp; day have past away</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Nor touch of man hath marr&#8217;d the rite divine</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And now at noon the steed must bleed,</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> The perfect rite to-day must force the meed</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Which Fate reluctant shudders to bestow.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Then must the Swerga-God</l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Yield to the Tyrant of the World below,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Then must the Devetas obey</l>
          <l rend="indent1"> The Rajahs rod, &amp; groan beneath his hateful sway.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lines 27&#8211;49 of
                            Book 8 of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810). See volume 4 of <title>Robert Southey Poetical Works
                                1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>This is an unintelligible extract, but you will give me credit for being previously explained in the poem itself all that requires
                    explanation, &#8211; &amp; I have merely copied it to show you what a noise one may make with these bells when it is proper to chime
                    them: &#8211; you may judge what an uproar there will be when Kehama drives his brazen chariot in triumph over the burning pavement of
                    Hell.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I very much wish you would amuse yourself &amp; gratify very many persons by collecting your poetical works, many
                    of which are not now procurable. It is better you should do this yourself, than leave it to be done after you, &#8211; at what I hope is
                    yet a distant time: because as the proof sheets past under your eye, <del>xxxxxx</del> little improvements might probably suggest
                    themselves, &amp; your own annotations would necessarily be far more valuable than those of any other person.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Seward&#8217;s <title>Poetical Works</title> were edited after her death by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> in three volumes (Edinburgh, 1810).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Simpsons<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Simpson (1765&#8211;1820) and his wife, members of Seward&#8217;s
                        literary circle at Lichfield. Simpson was a lawyer and Seward&#8217;s literary executor.</note> should not have said that I <hi rend="ital">complained</hi> of your too-abundant praises. I said that they embarrassed me, &amp; that I knew not how to reply
                    to them, &#8211; <del>on</del> this you will readily <del>concede</del> &lt;understand&gt;, &amp; must have perceived; &#8211; their full
                    sincerity I never doubted. My own manners sin in the contrary extreme. I have seen so much base flattery in the world, that the
                    fear of <del>being</del> approaching towards that detestable habit <del>has</del> often <del>makes</del> gives me the appearance
                    of coldness &amp; suppression; &#8211; &amp; any obnoxious opinions which I happen to have, are sure to find their way beyond what Homer
                    calls the barriers of the [MS obscured]eth, least any persons should suspect me of endeavouring to conceal them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One word of politics. I have long said that if the deliverance of Europe were to take place in <del>y</del> our
                    days, there was no country in which it was so likely to begin as Spain: because in no other country <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt;
                    there such a feeling of patriotism. From the old coalitions against France I had never the slightest hope; first I rejoiced in
                    their defeature, because of their detestable object; latterly I <del>xxxx</del> despaired of their success, because of the
                    miserable cabinets in which they originated. But the spirit of liberty has now broken out, &amp; it is neither the shameful
                    negligence of this ministry in assisting it, nor all the power of Bonaparte, mighty as he is, that can destroy that indestructible
                    spirit. Spain will deli[MS obscured] itself, &amp; I shall yet live to sing a <hi rend="ital">Nunc dimittis</hi>, &#8211; which will not
                    be premature like that of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Price. &#8211; <note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nunc dimittis: the evening
                        prayer which, in the version in the Book of Common Prayer (1662), contains this prophetic vision: &#8216;Lord, now lettest thou thy
                        servant depart in peace: according to thy word. / For mine eyes have seen: thy salvation, / Which thou hast prepared: before
                        the face of all people; / To be a light to lighten the Gentiles: and to be the glory of thy people Israel&#8217;. In his <title>A
                            Discourse on the Love of our Country</title> (1789), Richard Price (1723&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) had greeted the fall of
                        the Bastille in prophetic tones as a sign of the coming salvation of mankind.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>