<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1310</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2432</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        d.113.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 83&#8211;86 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1310" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1310" type="letter">
        <head>1310. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1807-04-24">24 April
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 1807<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        d.113<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 83&#8211;86 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Cumberland.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1807-04-24">April 24. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is the fault of the printer that I have not written to you two months ago &amp; Heaven knows if I continued to
                    wait for him how much longer it might be before you would hear tale or tidings of me. The case stands this, &#8211; there is in the
                    press an edition of my last &amp; best poem, printed in such a form that it will be no labour to hold the book, whatever it may be
                    to read it &amp; I have been long in daily expectation that the forthcoming of this book would enable me to tell you it had been
                    sent you, together with a copy of Joan of Arc &#8211; greatly <del>revised &amp;</del> altered &amp; amended, in place of that which
                    Lewis <hi rend="ital">borrowed</hi>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second editions of <title>Madoc</title> (1807),
                        which was published in a smaller, duodecimo format, and <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1806).</note> But being weary of
                    expectation, &amp; wishing also to hear of you, I now dispatch this to say that it shall be sent, as soon as it is published. &#8211; As
                    to Lewis,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Lewis (1771&#8211;1843): clergyman and schoolmaster. Educated at Balliol and
                        Corpus Christi Colleges, Oxford (matric. 1792, BA 1796). He became a curate and master of the grammar school in Honiton,
                        Devon. A friend of Southey&#8217;s at Oxford; they lost touch in later years.</note> if ever you get into his reading desk it may
                    not be amiss to write under the eighth commandment &#8220;Mem: my book has been returned. N. L.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Circumstances have prevented me from returning to Portugal so soon as I intended. I am however likely (God willing
                    I may &lt;say&gt; certain, as far as human intentions can be so) <del>of</del> &lt;to&gt; procure<del>ng</del> a whole holyday for
                    your boys in the month of November next. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> will then lead me to London, &amp;
                    when I am so far South I have calls into the West, &#8211; having <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">an Uncle</ref> &amp;
                        <del>Tau</del> Aunt near Taunton. The Barnstaple coach will carry me to Tiverton, &#8211; &amp; for the rest of the way I have
                    shoulders to carry a very commodious knapsack &amp; feet to carry myself, &#8211; being a better walker than when we were at Oxford.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your last letter is fourteen months old, &amp; they may have brought forth so many changes that I almost fear to
                    ask for my god child Fanny,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lightfoot&#8217;s daughter, her dates are unknown.</note> &#8211; During
                    that time I have had a son born into the world, &amp; baptized into the church by the name of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, who is now six months old, &amp; bids fair to be as noisy a fellow as his
                    father, &#8211; which is saying something, for be it known that I am quite as noisy as ever I was, &amp; should take as much delight
                    &lt;as ever&gt; in showering stones thro the hole of the staircase against your room door, &amp; hearing with what hearty
                        <del>earnest</del> good earnest you fool! was vociferated in indignation against me in return. O dear Lightfoot, what a
                    blessing it is to have a boys heart! it is as great a blessing <del>xxx</del> &lt;in&gt; carrying one thro this world, as to have
                    a childs spirit will be in fitting us for the next.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you are in the way of seeing reviews &amp; magazines they will have told you some of my occupations, the main
                    one they cannot tell you for they do not know it, nor is it my intention that they shall yet a while. I am preparing that branch
                    of the history of Portugal for publication first, which would have been last in order. had not <del>xxx</del> temporal
                    circumstances given it <del>xxx</del> a peculiar interest, &amp; I may add utility, &#8211; that which relates to Brazil &amp;
                        Paraguay.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in three volumes
                        between 1810 and 1819. The remainder of his projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; was never completed.</note> The manuscript
                    documents in my possession are very numerous &amp; the utmost importance, &#8211; having been collected with unwearied care by <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> during a residence of above thirty years in Portugal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is about to make his appearance in the world of authors with, I trust, some
                    credit to himself.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett&#8217;s <title>View of the Present State of Poland</title> and
                            <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Early Times to the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title> were both
                        published in 1807.</note> When we meet I will tell you the whole course of his eventful history, &#8211; far more eventful it has
                    been than any he could have prognosticated on his <del>first</del> entrance at old Balliol. He is likely now to be happier than he
                    ever was. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> (of Ch. Ch) died about twelvemonths ago. The last time
                    I saw him was in 1798, at his own house where he forced me to dinner, &amp; where he so disgusted me by his ostentation that from
                    that time I took care to shun him. he died of a frenzy fever, &amp; I understand his family now impute<del>d</del> to a sort of
                    derangement that strangeness of conduct which had alienated him from his old friends. <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, I am sorry to say, is fatter than ever he was, &#8211; he is one of my most intimate &amp; most valuable friends. I
                    hear from <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>, or of him, frequently. His visit to Oxford at the Installation has
                    been the occasion of throwing him quite into the circle of my friends in London. I sometimes think with wonder how few
                    acquaintances I made at Oxford; &#8211; except yourself &amp; Burnett not one whom I should feel any real pleasure in meeting. Of all
                    the months in my life (happily they did not amount to years) those which were passed at Oxford were the most insufferable. What
                    Greek I took there I literally left there, &amp; could not help losing &amp; <del>the only thing</del> &lt;all&gt; that I learnt
                    was a little swimming (very little the worse luck) &amp; a little boating, which is very greatly improved, now that I have a boat
                    of my own upon this delightful lake. I never remember to have dreamt of Oxford, &#8211; a sore proof of how little it entered into my
                    moral being; &#8211; of school on the contrary I dream perpetually.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you remember the mad <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> of Trinity who fired a pistol
                    thro his window at one of the fellows, &amp; told him he was a little lump of corruption? &#8211; He is the author of a very curious
                    poem called Gebir,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Gebir</title> (1798), reviewed by Southey in the <title>Critical Review</title> 27 (September 1799), 29&#8211;39.</note> in
                    which, after you have construed &amp; unriddled it, there is a great deal of admirable poetry. I am very curious to see this man,
                    who is quite as crazy as ever.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey met Landor in Bristol in 1808, for the fullest
                        account of which see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 26 April 1808, Letter 1447.</note> &#8211; You seem to have &lt;some
                    of&gt; the worst of the Balliol men in your neighbourhood, &#8211; &amp; what a set they were! When I remember Jewell &#8211; Shepherd, &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Poole, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phelps,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Spencer Phelps (d.
                        1856), a student at Balliol College, Oxford, BA 1797.</note> Queen Phelps &#8211; that poor seven <hi rend="ital">weeks</hi> child
                    little Bradley &#8211; Spearing &lt;the Apostles&gt; &#8211; &amp; a few more.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Apart from Phelps these
                        Balliol acquaintances have not been identified.</note> I can but think what <del>x</del> specimens they were of that part of
                    the youth of England who are selected for the cure of souls! <hi rend="ital">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </hi> Poole I hear is <hi rend="ital">gone melancholy</hi>, as they say; &#8211; for it is impossible to say of him that he has lost his wits. I heard also
                    that Bailey<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> had lost a fellowship at Balliol by his jests upon poor
                    Thomas Howe:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Howe (dates unknown): clergyman. Possibly the son of John Howe of
                        Honiton, Devon. Educated at Emmanuel College, Cambridge and Balliol College, Oxford. Howe was Rector of Huntspill, Somerset
                        1804&#8211;1823. He was Southey&#8217;s tutor at Oxford in 1793&#8211;1794.</note> &#8211; who found them out, resented them, &amp; marred his
                    election: it was added that he was a curate at Devizes. Cad:<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cooke Rogers (dates
                        unknown). A Welsh student of Balliol college, who Southey knew briefly while he was there, and nicknamed Cadwallader. His
                        first name and dates are unknown.</note> is become a great disciplinarian. Some friend of <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikins</ref> dined one day at Balliol, &amp; I was made the subject of conversation in the Common
                    Room; &#8211; poor Cad was my only friend &#8211; I believe he <del>xxx xxx</del> allowed that I must be damned from all my heresies <del>to
                        xxx</del> &lt;that was certain&gt;, but that <del>still</del> it was a pity; &#8211; he <del>xxx</del> remembered me with a degree
                    of affection which neither a dozen years nor that heart deadening &amp; uncharitable atmosphere has effaced. I should be glad to
                    shake hands with him again. [there follows a long deleted passage]. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I beg my compliments &amp; best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot. Let me hear from you &#8211; &amp; believe
                    me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>