<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.894</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2016</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 51.  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 350&#8211;352.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="894" type="letter">
        <head>894. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-02-08">8 February
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS/ Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 8: 1804<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 51<lb />Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 350&#8211;352.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1804-02-08">Wednesday. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 8. 1804.</date>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our friend the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Captain</ref> is in high luck. if we could but make <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> pilot him thro the Critical<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Critical Review</title> published a review of James Burney&#8217;s <title>A Chronological History of the
                            Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (Vol. 1, 1803), in February 1804,
                        121&#8211;130.</note> &#8211; he will have cleared all the bars most happily. your letter came too late to help me out with that wretched
                        Malthus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An
                            Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the future improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of
                            W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        292&#8211;30.</note> &#8211; &amp; I regret it much. I wanted <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> to have
                    written the whole reviewal, for it was more his <hi rend="ital">call</hi> than mine &#8211; but in vain. he delayed me week after week,
                    &amp; at last sent me only a few notes which I have inserted, &amp; which you may distinguish by a difference of texture. his
                    language is more technically argumentative, &amp; his sentences are rounded, whereas mine are pointed &#8211; &amp; poisoned into the
                    bargain. I have not said enough &#8211; having been hurried in consequence of his delay, but however the blow is a hard one. time was
                    &#8216;that when the brains were out, the man would die&#8217;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Shakespeare, <title>Macbeth</title>,
                        Act 3, scene 4, line 78.</note> &#8211; Malthus however is safe from that kind of death. the ground I have taken is this &#8211; that he
                    supposes lust to be like hunger an appetite of physical necessity when he argues against <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref>, that when he proposes his own damned plan he founds it upon the possibility of moral restraint, &amp; the
                    practical virtue of chastity &#8211; ergo the scorpion strikes his tail into his own head &#8211; the end of his book confuting the beginning.
                    that half his book is altogether superfluous &#8211; &amp; that if his propositions respecting population be true they prove the very
                    evils in society for which he apologizes &#8211; for if a country be overstocked before it be half peopled <del>xxxxxx</del> in
                    proportion to its power of production, the fault lies in a bad system of society, not in the system of Nature. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Malthus therefore is cast in his action against God Almighty. I have shown also that the perfect system on his plan
                    would be to breed slaves &amp; regulate population by the knife of the sow-gelder. If he replies to any effect I will gibbet him
                    in a pamphlet, &amp; draw &amp; quarter him, for I have something of the same sense of strength in me in reference to this dog
                    that Milton must have had when he made minced meat of Salmasius.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Milton (1608&#8211;1674;
                            <title>DNB</title>) attacked Claudius Salmasius [Claude Saumaise] (1588&#8211;1653) for his <title>Defensio Regia pro Carolo
                            I</title> (1649), a defence of the monarchy provoked by the execution of Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain,
                        1625&#8211;1649), in his <title>Pro Populo Anglicano Defensio</title> (1651).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> gives me much pleasure.
                    he is one of the three great men of my acquaintance, &amp; the more I know him &amp; the longer I know him, the more do I admire
                    his knowledge &amp; love his moral character. To see him speculating by authority upon the taxes &amp; <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> upon the Poor laws would give me hopes for the well doing of the country. but you
                    purveying for <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">the Doctor</ref> &#8211; makes me think the old fable is reversed &amp;
                    that the Lion waits upon the Jackal.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Aesop&#8217;s fable &#8216;The Lion&#8217;s Share&#8217; the fox and
                        jackal are forced to wait while the lion apportions the game they have divided into portions at his request. The Lion then
                        allots them all to himself.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have discovered (at least it is a discovery to me) a very extraordinary fact in ecclesiastical history &#8211; nothing
                    less than a design in the Mendicant Orders to ape the Mohammedans &#8211; to set Jesus Christ on the shelf &amp; set up S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> Francisco &amp; Domingo<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Credited with establishing Catholic mendicant orders, Saint Francis of Assisi (Giovanni Francesco di Bernardone; 1181/2&#8211;1226) was the founder of the Franciscan order, and Saint Dominic (Domingo F&#233;lix de Guzm&#225;n; 1170&#8211;1221) the founder of the Dominican order.</note> in his stead. The facts on which this opinion is grounded have not to my knowledge been
                    brought together. The scheme originated with the Franciscans &amp; was perhaps chiefly ruined by the rivalry of the other shop. By
                    the life of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francisco (which I have written &amp; should like to show you) it is certain that he set
                    himself up avowedly as the living parallel &amp; pattern of the Redeeming God. I have Franciscan authority that the Friars dropt
                    the year of Christ at one time &amp; dated from the infliction of the five wounds on their founder. Add to this the Evangelium
                        Aternum<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Introductorium in Evangelium Aeternum</title> (c. 1250) was written
                        by Fra Gherardo of Borgo San Donnino (dates unknown), a Franciscan follower of the mystic Joachim di Fiore. The Franciscan
                        Joachists wished to spiritualise their order: they argued that Joachim&#8217;s three books (<title>Liber Concordiae Novi ac Veteris
                            Testamenti, Expositio in Apocalipsim, and Psalterium Decem Cordarum</title>) constituted the Eternal Gospel, replacing the
                        Gospel of Christ, since the spiritual life had ebbed from the Old and New Testaments. The existing priesthood and Bible would
                        be superseded and a kingdom of love would begin.</note> which they brought forward to supersede the Gospels, &amp; I think my
                    assertion is made very probable. This Evang. At. I must if possible hunt out. &amp; also the prophecies of the Abbot Joachim.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joachim di Fiore (1132&#8211;1202): Cistercian abbot, mystic and interpreter of Biblical prophecy
                        who argued that the world was approaching a third epoch (superseding the Old and New Testament epochs) &#8211; the epoch of the
                        Eternal Gospel, the Kingdom of the Holy Spirit, when all would live in love, no longer needing law.</note> these have both
                    been prohibited &amp; will therefore be difficultly attainable especially the former which was never printed, but the MSS. in
                    refutation of it exists in the Museum.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Library holds a manuscript containing
                        the &#8216;Protocol of the commission of three cardinals held at Anagni, 8 July, 1255, resulting in the condemnation for heresy of
                        the &#8216;Introductorius in Evangelium Aeternum&#8217;&#8217; (shelfmark Royal 8 F XVI).</note> The Revelations of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Brigida<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Birgitta Birgersdotter (1303&#8211;1373): Swedish saint whose visions of Jesus and a
                        blonde Virgin Mary were influenced by the Franciscans and published as <title>Revelationes Coelestes</title>.</note> (of
                    Sweden not the Irish Saint who used to hang her clothes upon sunbeams to dry them)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saint Brigid of Kildare (c. 451&#8211;525): Irish nun and founder of
                        a convent who, according to tradition, hung her wet mantle on a sunbeam when entering her house to welcome Saint Brendan of
                        Birr (died c. 573).</note> will probably throw some light upon this, &amp; I have sent to Lisbon for them.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s copy of <title>Revelationes Celestes &#8230; Beate Brigitte &#8230; de Regno Suecie</title>
                            (1517) was no. 2395 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> This is very curious. their scheme must have been to have established such a system of
                    priest government as the Jesuits effected in Paraguay.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s interest in the Jesuit
                        Reductions (the village colonies in which the Jesuits governed the Indians) culminated in <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> translating <title>An Account of the Abipones, an
                            Equestrian People of Paraguay. Translated from the Latin of Martin Dobrizhoffer, Eighteen Years a Missionary in that
                            Country</title> (1821). Dobrizhoffer was a source for Southey&#8217;s poem <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> the
                    unlucky vow of chastity prevented them from creating themselves into a cast, or else we might perhaps have had our Bramins in
                    Europe. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The parcel arrived to day uninjured, tho others which have come by the same conveyance with six fold the
                    circumference of brown paper have suffered sorely. It was fortunate that the reviewal was delayed, as I am now enabled to prove
                    what I could else have only hinted cautiously that his Lordship has fathered his own verses upon Camoens.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Percy Clinton Sydney, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems
                            from the Portuguese of Luis de Camoens</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        569&#8211;577.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am living in total seclusion, never seeing any person out of the family except the old carpenter.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Lawson (dates unknown).</note> this might not do for ever, but indeed at present it seems
                    to have sharpened my wits, perhaps from the uninterrupted exercise which they take &#8211; for except at meal times, &amp; an after
                    dinner nap I am always at my book or my pen, exercise of body being impossible in these incessant rains. The last week has been
                    given to Madoc,<hi rend="ital"> &amp;</hi> I have made a good weeks run. it is now settled that <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is to print it (with prints for the love of an outlandish costume) at his
                    cost, &amp; I share the eventual profits.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey
                        had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in 1805.</note> The poem will go to press early in
                    the summer, &amp; then &lt;shall&gt; I have performed my opus magnum, for such do I consider it, tho perhaps the History<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> will be in your eyes
                    the opus majus. When both are done I shall have a right to be lazy all the rest of my life &#8211; if so inclined. but in all
                    probability the first curse will be upon me<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat
                        bread, till thou return unto the ground; for out of it wast thou taken: for dust thou [art], and unto dust shalt thou return&#8217;,
                        Genesis 3: 19.</note> &#8211; if that can be called a curse which by the necessity of labour produces the enjoyment of its
                    fruits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has wild weather for his convoy! what are your speculations
                    upon S Domingo?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having defeated French forces in November 1803, the black general and
                        former slave Jean Jacques Dessalines (1758&#8211;1806) declared independence for the French colony of Saint-Domingue on 1 January 1804, renaming
                        it Haiti.</note> As for me I rejoice heartily at what <hi rend="ital">is</hi>, &amp; have good hopes of what will be. planters
                    throats go for nothing in my calculation of humanity, especially if they be Creoles or Scotchmen. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>