<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1030</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2152</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add
                        MS 47890 .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                        6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 256&#8211;258 [with omissions, and mis-dated 1804]; John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 315&#8211;319 [in part].Dating note: Internal
                        evidence of letter states that &#8216;it has lain two or three weeks&#8217; after dating of &#8216;Feby 11&#8217;.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1030" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1030" type="letter">
        <head>1030. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-02-11">[January&#8211;]11 February
                        [1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Amelia/ Barbadoes/ or
                        elsewhere./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ FEB 14/ 1805<lb />Seal: [illegible]<lb />MS: British Library, Add
                        MS 47890 <lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                        6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 256&#8211;258 [with omissions, and mis-dated 1804]; John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 315&#8211;319 [in part].<lb />Dating note: Internal
                        evidence of letter states that &#8216;it has lain two or three weeks&#8217; after dating of &#8216;Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 11&#8217;.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not possible that my letters can give you more pleasure than yours give me. You have always reason to suppose
                    that all is well with me when you hear nothing to the contrary. &#8211; I am only exposed to the common accidents of life &#8211; but you are
                    in the way of battle &amp; slaughter, pestilence &amp; hurricanes, &amp; every letter <del>from you</del> that arrives from you
                    relieves me from a certain kind of apprehension. I have written twice &#8211; after the receipt of your first letter about the Court
                    Martial &amp; before the arrival of your two which contain the sequel of the history.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Southey was court-martialled for neglect of duty, disobedience of orders and contempt in contradicting his captain, Sir
                        Henry Heathcote (1777&#8211;1851). The last charge only was proven, but he was dismissed from his ship, the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>. However the commander of the fleet in which Thomas served, Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood,
                        1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), appointed him lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class
                        frigate of the French navy captured in 1796, and a finer ship than his previous one. On taking up his appointment on the <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, Thomas found the ship&#8217;s crew struck down by fever.</note> My first was very short,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 17 December 1804, Letter 1004.</note> written the instant I had
                    read yours &#8211; to bid you draw on <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> for thirty pounds. my second to repeat what
                    the first had said lest it should not reach you<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 26 December
                        1804, Letter 1008.</note> &#8211; but while I was writing it, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> put at my disposal
                    for you fifty pounds. Thank heaven you are reinstated, but &#8211; that account of the fever <del>threw</del> &lt;struck&gt; a damp over
                    me &amp; I shall not be comfortable till I hear from you again. &#8211; You have never told me a word about the hurricane. &#8211; My
                        ballification<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning his attendance at a ball.</note> surprised you tho you could not
                    suspect me of dancing there. but I assure you you have surprized me more by saying you have eat a land crab. your stomach is more
                    courageous than I had believed it to be. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc still sticks in the press.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Edinburgh firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> was taking longer than planned to print <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805).</note> they loiter with the notes, &amp; will probably delay its publication till March. &#8211; I am now working at the
                    Review, &amp; have some ten days <del>work</del> job on hand to compleat the Annual quotum.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>An Account of Travels into the Interior of Southern Africa, in the years 1797 and 1798, including Observations on
                            the Geology &amp; Geography, the Natural History ... and Sketches of the Various Tribes Surrounding the Cape of Good
                            Hope</title>, Vol. II (1804), 22&#8211;33; Robert Percival (1765&#8211;1826), <title>An Account of the Cape of Good Hope</title>
                        (1804), 34&#8211;41; Daniel Mackinnen (1767&#8211;1830), <title>A Tour Through the British West Indies, in the years 1802 and 1803 giving
                            a Particular Account of the Bahama Islands</title> (1804), 50&#8211;56; John Barrow, <title>Travels in China: Containing
                            Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short Residence at the Imperial Palace of
                            Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804), 69&#8211;83; <title>Sir John Froissart&#8217;s
                            Chronicles of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II to the
                            Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans. Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804), 189&#8211;194; George Heriot
                        (1766&#8211;1844), <title>The History of Canada, From its First Discovery: Comprehending an Account of the Original Establishment of
                            the Colony of Louisiana</title>, 194&#8211;197; <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for the
                            Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of
                            such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 225&#8211;231; Edward Ledwich (1738&#8211;1823), <title>The
                            Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398&#8211;413; <title>Original Correspondence of Jean Jacques Rousseau, with Mad. La Tour
                            de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title> (1804), 485&#8211;488; Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with
                            Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804), 488&#8211;93; David Irving (1778&#8211;1850),<title> The Lives
                            of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary Dissertations on the Literary History of Scotland and the Early Scotish
                            Drama</title> (1804), 493&#8211;499; Walter Scott, <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of Ercildoune</title>
                        (1804), 555&#8211;563; Charles Abraham Elton (1778&#8211;1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804), 564&#8211;565; William Day (dates unknown),
                            <title>The Shepherd&#8217;s Boy: being Pastoral Tales</title> (1804), 567&#8211;568; E. Warren (dates unknown), <title>The Poet&#8217;s Day,
                            or, Imagination&#8217;s Ramble</title> (1804), 568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a Series of Prints, Designed by her Royal
                            Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with Poetical Illustrations by T. P</title> [Thomas
                        Park (1758/9&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>)] (1804), 568&#8211;580; Thomas Green Fessenden (1771&#8211;1837), <title>Original Poems</title>
                        (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777&#8211;1805), <title>The Powers of Genius</title> (1801), 571; Thomas Clio Rickman (1761&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in Celebration of the Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint Domingo, November 29,
                            1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield, <title>Good Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert Spencer (1770&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of Sorrow</title> (1804), 574&#8211;575; <title>British Purity: or, the World we Live in. A
                            Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries&#8230;By Lory Lucian and Jerry Juvenal, &#8230; Assisted by S. Scriblerus, etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804),
                        575; William Falconer (1732&#8211;1769), <title>The Shipwreck</title> (1804), ed., James Stanier Clarke (1766&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), 577&#8211;580; William Tooke (1777&#8211;1863), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles Churchill: with
                            Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his Life</title> (1804), 580&#8211;585; J. Amphlett (dates unknown),
                            <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title> (1804), 585; Joseph Jefferson (1766&#8211;1824), <title>Horae Poetic&#230;.
                            Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586&#8211;587; Alexander Campbell (1764&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804), 587&#8211;591; William Crowe (bap. 1745, d. 1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593&#8211;594; John Finlay (1782&#8211;1810), <title>Wallace, or, The Vale
                            of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594&#8211;596; Jessie Stewart (dates unknown), <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas
                            Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768&#8211;1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected with Literature. Imitated from
                            the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597&#8211;598; <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (1804),
                        621&#8211;634; Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language,
                            of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive Society</title> (1804), 634&#8211;644; [Anon.] <title>No
                            Slaves - No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour of the African Trade by a Liverpool
                            Merchant</title> (1804), 644&#8211;648; William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813), <title>Indian Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures
                            on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title> (1803), 658&#8211;670; John Gardiner (fl. 1758&#8211;1792),
                            <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670&#8211;674; Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the Fresco
                            Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918&#8211;923.</note> then what time is not devoted to the History<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> will go to the Spaniards
                        Letters,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> which are destined to furnish the extraordinary supplies for the year.
                    Since this war with Spain however I begin to have a sort of hope that you may fall in with a good prize<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of &#8216;prizes&#8217;, meaning ships and their
                        cargo, captured in armed conflict.</note> &amp; be able to lend me a couple of hundreds for furniture &#8211; if I should stand in
                    need &#8211; that is, if I should not get it before, or should not be able on account of political trouble to go to Lisbon before my
                    final settling, which last question will very speedily be determined.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My volume selected from the Anthology is published under the titles of Metrical Tales &amp; other Poems.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s contributions to the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) were
                        republished under his own name in <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805).</note> it contains only three pieces
                    in addition which are smuggled in without any notice on my part under their respective heads. the one an inscription &#8211; the other
                    two blank verse odes upon Indian manners like <del>xxx</del> The Hurons Address to the dead.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> These were &#8216;Epitaph on Algernon Sidney&#8217; (originally published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 25 December
                        1798), <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (London, 1805), p. 197; &#8216;Song of the Chikkasah Widow&#8217; (originally
                        published as &#8216;The Dirge of the American Widow&#8217; in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 11 September 1799), pp. 92&#8211;94; &#8216;The
                        Peruvian&#8217;s dirge over the body of his Father&#8217; (originally published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 9 December 1799), pp.
                        86&#8211;88. Southey&#8217;s poem &#8216;The Huron&#8217;s Address to the Dead&#8217; was published in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1800),
                        pp. 56&#8211;58, and in <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (London, 1805), pp. 83&#8211;85.</note> five hundred only are
                    printed &#8211; perhaps as it is a single volume, &amp; its contents very various it may sell well.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> _____</p>
        <p>Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 11. As this letter was not finished at a heat &#8211; it has lain two or three weeks &#8211; to own the
                    truth fairly <del>because</del> I had such a fear about me of the yellow fever, because you mentioned indisposition on the night
                    preceding the date of your last &#8211; that I had not heart to go on with it. Once I received a letter from a poor fellow three months
                    after he was dead, &#8211; it excited a most painful feeling, &amp; it is little less unpleasant to <del>xxx</del> address one to a
                    person who <del>xxx</del> you fear may not be among the living. However yours of Dec. 4. has just come to hand. You do not tell me
                    whether the fever is out of the ship &#8211; but I conclude that it must almost have done its work, &amp; will go out like a fire when
                    it no longer finds any thing that it can destroy. I have a sort of theory about such diseases which I do not understand myself &#8211;
                    but somebody or other will one of these days. They are so far analogous to vegetables as that they take root &#8211; grow &#8211; ripen &amp;
                    decay. Those which are eruptive blossom &#8211; &amp; seed &#8211; for the pustule of the small pox &amp;c is to all intents &amp; purposes
                    the flower of the disease, or the fructification by which it is perpetuated. Now these diseases like vegetables chuse their own
                    soil &#8211; as some plants like clay &#8211; others sand &#8211; others chalk, so the yellow fever will not take root in a negro &#8211; nor the yaws in
                    a white man, &amp;c. There is a noble hint for a new theory &#8211; <del>xxx</del> you will <del>xxx</del> see the truth of the analogy
                    at once &#8211; &amp; I can no more explain it than you can. but so it is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> &#8211; I beg his pardon &#8211; Brother Hempstretch is a third time shift. he is now in
                    the Egyptienne frigate<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Egyptienne</hi> was a 40-gun frigate, captured
                        from the French in 1801, and commissioned into the Royal Navy. She was captained by Charles Elphinstone Fleeming (1774&#8211;1840)
                        between 1803&#8211;1805.</note> &#8211; I suppose by <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunts</ref> means. It seems when he
                    wrote to the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">Old Gentleman</ref> from Taunton (who was then at Lyme<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lyme Regis, on the south coast, in Dorset.</note>) he was desired to go &amp; wait his return at the Cottage.
                    This did not content him &#8211; but he ordered in all his bills, <del>xxx</del> which so provoked the old man that he turned him out of
                    doors the morning after he came home. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> allows him 40 &#163; a year. &#8211;
                    Whether or no his friends may be able after all to save the nation the expence of thirteen pence halfpenny, by giving him this
                    third chance &#8211; I must confess myself very doubtful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall send you the Review<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Annual Review</title>; see note 6.</note> with Madoc &#8211;
                    which is finished but not yet published. it will be out early in March, &amp; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> will ship the parcel for you from Bristol. The Iris is at end &#8211; the Printer was embarrassed, &amp; sold it to
                    the other party just as it had established its sale.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title> was the Norwich newspaper edited, from 1803, by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have <del>xxx</del> been dreadfully shocked here by the fate of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> brother, Captain of the Abergavenny East Indiaman &#8211; which has just been lost in Portland Bay &#8211; almost as
                    shockingly as the Halsewell.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wordsworth (1772&#8211;1805), captain of the East Indiaman,
                        the <title>Earl of Abergavenny</title>, went down with his ship on the Shambles rocks off Portland Bill, on 5 February 1805.
                        The <title>Halsewell</title>, an East Indiaman under Captain Richard Pierce (c. 1747&#8211;1786), was wrecked near Swanage, on the
                        Dorset coast, on 5 January 1786, with the loss of 170 lives. Pierce died in the shipwreck, as did his two daughters, who were
                        on board the <title>Halsewell</title>.</note> 300 lives! &#8211; There has not been such a shock since the Halsewell. You will learn
                    the particulars from the papers if any reach you &#8211; &amp; if not I will not employ what little of the sheet is left on a subject
                    which makes my very flesh quiver. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bonaparte wants peace &#8211; a continual war is a far more probable event. what will become of Portugal Heaven knows,
                    &amp; till that be decided I can as little tell what will become of me. Meantime I shall continue to work hard &amp; economize. &#8211;
                    the Spaniards Letters<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                            Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> are begun &amp; promise well. I want you to help me in the
                    part about our navy &amp; sailors<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title>, Letter 26.</note> &#8211; send me any good stories which you think can properly fit in &#8211; &amp;
                    any remarks upon the discipline &#8211; martial laws &amp;c &#8211; in short any thing that comes uppermost, for however insignificant it may
                    appear to you, it will most likely appear to me in a very different light.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I could not but laugh at your purchase of the swab. Oh <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> if you did
                    but know as experimentally as I do how many things fall between the cup &amp; the lip! However, if death do not come in the way I
                    have made up my mind to see you an Admiral yet &#8211; &amp; very possibly Sir Thomas at the bargain. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> too will rise in the world &#8211; &amp; we have only to hope that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Hempstretch</ref> may not be exalted according to his deserts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Joe is in good health, &amp; is your dog still, as I pay the tax for him, by way of continuing your right &amp;
                    title. So that when you have made your fortune you may return &amp; take possession. The Bristol news you hear better from <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> than I can give it, &amp; at this place we have none. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> both go on
                    well, &amp; the <del>xxx</del> matter of next importance that all my old trousers, old pantaloons &amp; my silk breeches into the
                    bargain are going at once, &amp; so of necessity I must be new rigged in the spring. &#8211; We have had a delightful winter &#8211; the snow
                    has never lain a single hour in the valley &#8211; a circumstance perhaps unexampled. I want nothing here but to have my books about me,
                    being wholly careless about other society &#8211; But it is not convenient to be so far from libraries, booksellers &amp; book-stalls,
                    &amp; I must remove nearer London as soon as I have the means. Take a galleon I beseech you! &amp; come home in it &#8211; for I want
                    &lt;you&gt; to write the black letters on some parchment books. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211; God
                    bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>