<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1707</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2829</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1707" type="letter">
        <head>1707. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-11-11">11 November
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ with W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Burn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 7. George Street/ Hanover Square/ London. <lb />Stamped: [illegible]<lb />Postmark:
                        F/ NOV14/ 1809<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I had written to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> instead of you, &amp; made no mention of
                        Kehama,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, published in 1810.</note> I
                    should have deserved some displeasure, &#8211; but the fact is that to you I have always written upon more important subjects, &amp;
                    that I never supposed the they could be a secret having been announced in magazines twelve months ago, &amp; advertised at the end
                    of the last edition of Thalaba,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) was published in 1809.</note> &#8211; which by the bye I ordered to be sent you. It would have given me
                    quite as much pleasure to send the poem to her &#8211; as it could possibly give her to hear it, (I am afraid more.) &#8211; &amp; I would
                    have transcribed it for her, were it not for want of leisure. But busy as I am, I make a copy for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, &#8211; which <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percival</ref> franks to him, &#8211;
                    &amp; this gets on more slowly that it <del>ou</del> &lt;ought to do&gt;, &#8211; for a sailors life is a very dull one, &amp; Tom has
                    no greater pleasure than in receiving one of these little packets. You know how I am employed, &amp; how much time it would
                    require to transcribe between 4 &amp; 5000 lines. The history of the poem is thus &#8211; I began it at Lisbon &amp; brought with me to
                    this place in 1803 about 900 lines which remained untouched from that time till my last journey to the South. I had there some
                    talk with <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, about my own poem &amp; his.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor&#8217;s poem <title>Gebir</title> (1798), which Southey much admired.</note> I told him of this fragment, as
                    a thing laid aside, because I could not live upon praise without pudding,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning without
                        earning any money by it.</note> &#8211; &amp; I told him the outline of the story, &#8211; which was wild enough to delight him. He said
                        <del>the</del> to me, finish it &#8211; &amp; I will print it for you, &#8211; this offer stung me to compleat it. I have as much contempt
                    for ordinary praise as for ordinary censure, but you know in what respect I held Landors Gebir, notwithstanding all its obscurity.
                    &#8211; &amp; there is not that man living whose praise would gratify me so highly &#8211; upon such a subject. As I could not afford to write
                    poetry I resolve to create time for it by rising earlier, &#8211; &amp; that resolution I have kept, rising whenever my rest has not
                    been disturbed by the children. time enough to write about twenty lines before breakfast, &#8211; &amp; not a single line have I written
                    at any other hours than these. It is not finished, but very nearly so, there will be 24 sections (about the average length of
                    those in Madoc<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note>) &amp; the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> is begun. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is to have it on our usual terms, his advice
                    is that it be printed like Thalaba,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801) was published in the cheaper format of octavo.</note> &#8211; I am not satisfied that his judgment is right in this case,
                    &amp; shall consult my friends the Scotchmen.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The publishers <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James
                        Ballantyne</ref>.</note> The Poem itself will for some time get me less money than reputation, &amp; less reputation than
                    censure. but time sets all these things to rights. It will not be generally interesting, being of a far wilder character than any
                    thing that has ever yet appeared in prose or rhyme, except such writings as are altogether mythological. But it is written <hi rend="ital">me judice</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;in my own judgement&#8217;.</note> with great power,
                    &amp; they who like it at all will admire it very much. The metre is altogether my own, &#8211; rhyme in lines of any length &amp; in
                    any arrangement, &amp; with the rhythm of blank verse. The character of the versification has no other resemblance to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> than its irregularity, &#8211; mine is pitched in a higher key. If it were to be
                    printed in London, where franks are to be had, I would send my Aunt the proofs, sheet by sheet, they would not be worth the
                    postage from Edinburgh.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The journey of Nuno Vallo<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The account by Joao Baptista Lavanha (mid
                        1550s-1625) of the shipwreck in 1593 of the Santo Alberta off Southern Africa, and the subsequent trek of the survivors under
                        their elected leader Nuno Velho Pereira was published in <title>Naufragia da Nao S. Alberto</title> (1597).</note> is in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> hands. I cut it out of the volume that it may be bound seperately, &amp;
                    meant him to translate it for Pinkertons Collection of V &amp; Travels,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry was to
                        translate and abridge travels including Lavanha&#8217;s <title>Naufragia da Nao S. Alberto</title> (1597) for John Pinkerton
                        (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), compiler of <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels
                            in All Parts of the World</title> (1808&#8211;1814).</note> &#8211; if Pinkerton had not made his Collection as injudiciously as his
                    original work. The Naufragia<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 17.</note> certainly throws more light upon S.
                    Africa than any book with which I am acquainted. &#8211; There are some books of Labats respecting W. Africa<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Baptiste Labat (1663&#8211;1738), <title>Nouvelle Relation de l&#8217;Afrique Occidentale</title> (1728);
                            <title>Relation Historique de l&#8217;Ethiopie Occidentale</title> (1732); nos 1578 and 1580 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> which I have repeatedly sent for from Cataloguens without success, &#8211; the Un. History<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">  See for example <title>The Modern Part of an Universal History, From the Earliest Account of Time</title>, 42 vols (London, 1780&#8211;1784), XIII, pp. 150, 240, 265; XVI, pp. 312, 318, 340.</note> refers to them as the main authorities respecting Angola &amp; the
                    adjoining countries &#8211; Marchais Voyages which Labat published I have. <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Chevalier Reynaud
                        Des Marchais (dates unknown): French cartographer and navigator who travelled extensively along the west coast of Africa
                        between 1704 and 1727, in the service of the King of France. His maps and manuscripts were published posthumously by Labat in
                        1730&#8211;1731.</note> There is the narrative of an Englishman, in Purchas,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Purchas
                        (c. 1577&#8211;1626; <title>DNB</title>), <title>His Pilgrimage, or Relations of the World</title> (1625).</note> who was in
                    captivity among the Gongas of Angola,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andrew Battell (fl. 1589&#8211;1614), <title>The Strange
                            Adventures of Andrew Battell of Leigh, in Angola and the Adjoining Regions</title>. Between 1590 and c. 1610 the English
                        sailor Andrew Battell lived in Central Africa, first in Angola until 1606/7 and then in Loango. Information about his life
                        there was included in <title>Purchas His Pilgrimage, or Relations of the World and the Religions Observed in all Ages and
                            Places Discovered from the Creation unto the Present</title> (1613), Book 7, chapters 9 and 10.</note> &#8211; this narrative is
                    often quoted in the Un. History. Purchas is luckily to be reprinted, &amp; then <del>I x</del> Purchas will be to be purchased, &#8211;
                    a pun which I dare say he made upon himself poor fellow, for he was a desperate lover of punning.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may see Azaras maps<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Felix Manuel de Azara (1742&#8211;1821),<title>
                            Voyages dans l&#8217;Amerique Meridionale depuis 1781, jusqu&#8217; en 1801</title> (1809). Southey eventually owned a copy of this
                        work, no. 90 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> (if there be a copy left) at Dulaus, in Soho Square<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A. B. Dulau (dates unknown) and Co., 37 Soho Square.</note> where there is by far the best
                    collection of foreign books <del>in fxxxx xxx in</del> &lt;that is to be found in&gt; London. One of the partners is an emigrant
                    who was at Lisbon, &amp; used to be a good deal at the <ref target="people.html#GonneWilliam">Gonnes</ref>. I met him the last
                    time I was at Champion Hill,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese residence of the Gonnes.</note> but I forget
                    his name. There are two good prints of the Tamandua in Azara, &amp; the only view I have ever seen of Buenos Ayres.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Azara,<title> Voyages dans l&#8217;Amerique Meridionale Depuis 1781, Jusqu&#8217; en 1801</title> (1809). Plate
                        VII of the atlas volume of this work is &#8216;Le Tamandua noir, vari&#233;t&#233; du Tamandua ordinaire&#8217;. Plate XVII is a view of Buenos
                        Aires.</note> My distrust of translations is as great as your own: in this case there was no alternative.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref> is a better place than <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> , which is near enough to London to have all its expences <del>&amp; is</del> heightened, &amp; far enough
                    from it to be out of its advantages of society &amp;c, &#8211; the very worst of all possible situations. Your parishioners Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Harris &amp; Kemble ought to remember the New Price in their Easter dues.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to the &#8216;Old Price Riots&#8217; of 1809 which were caused by rising prices at the new Theatre at
                        Covent Garden after the previous one had been destroyed by fire. The riots lasted three months, and ended when John Philip
                        Kemble (1757&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>) the manager of the theatre &#8211; in partnership with Thomas Harris (d. 1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>) &#8211; was forced to make a public apology and return to the former prices.</note> According to their
                    present mode of proceeding I look every day to see that my old acquaintance <ref target="people.html#OpieAmelia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
            <hi rend="ital">Opie</hi>
          </ref> has been served with a summons by them for her names-sake.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The protests were known as the &#8216;O.P. riots&#8217;.</note> &#8211; I shall be glad to hear that you have taken
                    possession. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My book will not be ready before Xmas,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; for <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has loitered with
                    it. I must print <del>xx</del> the notes in double columns &amp; in as small a type as can correctly be used, for the sake of
                    diminishing the bulk of the volume. Your sheets had better be compleated &amp; stitched together as a copy in which you will make
                    corrections &amp; emendations. So much interest do I feel in this &amp; the other histories, that if I could afford it, I would do
                    nothing else till the whole series were compleated. The first vol. of the Hist of the Mother Country<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s proposed &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; which he never completed.</note> will be one of the most amusing
                    books that has ever appeared, &#8211; so rich will it be in incident, characteristic anecdote, &amp; matters of customs I believe there
                    must be a supplementary volume concerning Portugueze Africa:<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was never
                        written.</note> &#8211; but of this I shall be better able to judge hereafter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you pass near New Cavendish Street, <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> (N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 14) will show you the pictures of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my son</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">eldest daughter</ref>, as happily taken as possible. there is also a very good likeness
                    of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, &#8211; my own is more penseroso<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning
                        &#8216;thoughtful&#8217;.</note> than the original, &#8211; &amp; does not look like a man who is not merely of a happy, but even of a joyous
                    temperament.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent2">
            <date when="1809-11-11">Nov. 11. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>