<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1374</idno><idno type="nines">rce2496</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1374" type="letter"><head>1374. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Anna Seward</ref>, <date when="1807-10-25">25 October
                    1807.</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Seward/ Litchfield.<lb/>Endorsement: Oc<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1807<lb/>MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1807-10-25">Oct. 25. 1807.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> My summer season is in good part taken up by friends who come to these uttermost parts of the North to visit me,
                    &amp; by laying in a stock of exercise which lasts me during a bodily hibernation of six months, but <del>I</del> even during this
                    butterfly’s holyday I have fits &amp; heats of hard work, without which the press would outrun me, &amp; I should outrun my means.
                    There has been another &amp; more valid reason why ten weeks have been let pass since the date of my last letter, – it was likely
                    that I should soon be able to say when I should leave this place on my way to London, &amp; consequently when I should have the
                    gratification of halting at Litchfield, – instead of eyeing the outside only of its noble Cathedral while the stage changed
                    horses, – as I once did heretofore.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Critical Reviewer of Madoc is the same person who has spoken in the same spirit of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> late volumes. I have seen neither article, so that in the main object
                    of giving pain to me he has failed, – as indeed he would under any circumstance, for I am used to these things. His name is Le
                        Grice,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> was negatively reviewed in the <title>Critical
                            Review</title>, ns 7 (1806), 72–83, by Charles Valentine Le Grice (1773–1858; <title>DNB</title>). The review of
                        Wordsworth’s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> appeared in the <title>Critical Review</title>, ns 11 (August 1807), 399–403.
                        By December 1807, Southey had changed his mind about the authorship of this review; see Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 9
                        December 1807, Letter 1393. For the authorship of this review; see <title>William Wordsworth: The Critical Heritage. Volume 1
                            1793–1820</title>, ed. Robert Woof (London and New York, 2001), pp. 170–171.</note> – he was a school-fellow of
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> at Christs Hospital. Before my acquaintance with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> began I past five days at Cambridge, having walked thither from
                    Oxford with <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>, to see his brother, the <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Seward</ref>  whom you must have met, – &amp; who
                    is <del>on the</del> now an inhabitant of some better world than ours. We there met this Le Grice: – he was unusually courteous
                    towards me, &amp; I as unusually repulsive towards him, for never had I seen a man whose whole temper of mind appeared to me so
                    thoroughly perverted &amp; mischievous. Every thing was made the subject of his ridicule, &amp; he seemed to have laughed himself
                    out of every good principle &amp; every good feeling. Considerable talents he had, but only in this miserable direction: his face
                    was as white as a Ghosts, &amp; in this <del>dead</del> &lt;clayey&gt; &amp; unexpressive face were set two jet black eyes,
                    forming so strange &amp; hideous a contrast, that literally &amp; truly that face was the original from whence I described the
                    dead countenance of Donica animated by a Devil.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem ‘Donica’ of 1796 was
                        published in his <title>Poems</title> (1797 and later editions), in his <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and in his
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837–1838). For the text see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen.
                        ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, <title>Selected Shorter Poems</title>, ed. Lynda Pratt, pp. 118–122.</note> From
                    that time I never saw him. He remembers with what unconcealed dislike I turned my back upon all his proferred civilities, but what
                    has more weight with him, has been a notion that he could wound <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    thro me, &amp; thus pay off some of the scores of an old &amp; rooted envy. – This man is now settled at the Lands End in
                    Cornwall, where he married an old woman to whose children he went to be tutor. The eldest son is a miserable cripple, as deformed
                    in mind as in body. Le Grice &amp; the Mother have not proved faithful stewards to him, &amp; he vows vengeance against them both,
                    but him in particular, as soon as he shall be of age. Le Grice himself is an unsuccessful author; – he published a little volume
                    called by the strange name of Tineum,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Tineum</title> (1794), a miscellany of
                        prose and verse.</note> when he was at Cambridge; – it was ridiculed in the University, &amp; never heard of out of it.
                    Authors are said to be an envious race, – it may perhaps be true of such Authorlings as this, but not so of the truly great, as if
                    amply proved by the history of their friendships.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am very very much indebted to you for what you have done with the Critical Review. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Fellowes<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Fellowes (1771–1847), editor of the <title>Critical</title>
                        from1807–1814.</note> cannot of course sacrifice the consistency of that precious publication, – but the work will become more
                    respectable in his hands, – he will leaven it with something of a liberal &amp; of a christian spirit, &amp; will give me fair
                    play there for the future. This is a matter of some importance, for tho the breath of envy <del>I</del> cannot wither one laurel
                    leaf, – it may mildew a whole crop of corn.</p><p rend="indent1"> That note of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fs. gives me what I looked for in your own letters in vain, – an account of
                    your health, – but it is a sad one. He recommends distilled water. I am afraid this is but a whim taken up by women of fashion: –
                    &amp; am certain that water distilled in any metallic vessels must be far more impure than &lt;from a&gt; common spring
                        <del>we</del> or pump. You who knew Darwin<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Erasmus Darwin (1731–1802;
                            <title>DNB</title>), doctor, botanist, poet and mentor of Anna Seward.</note> should have some faith in <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>. I know him, &amp; without any personal liking towards him (for he is cold as
                    ice) have the highest respect for him as a man &amp; the highest confidence in his skill. If any known means can be of service to
                    your complaint, he will know what those means are; &amp; of all men living he is the one who is most likely to devise a new remedy
                    when old ones fail.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of Lady Wortleys letters<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In November 1804 Southey read and admired her
                        letters in James Dallaway (1763–1834; <title>DNB</title>), ed., <title>The Works of the Right Hon. Lady Mary Wortley Montagu
                            ... Published, by Permission, from her Genuine Papers</title>, 5 vols (1803); see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 21
                        November 1804 (Letter 991) and Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 27 November 1804 (Letter 993). Lady Mary Wortley
                        Montagu (1689–1762; <title>DNB</title>), author.</note> I can only speak upon recollections three years old: – as for her
                    voluptuous scenes I need not ask you to do me the justice of <del>supp</del> believing they were not what were praised or
                    remembered. Her letters from Italy are what delighted me, – so did those written to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wortley<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Wortley Montagu (1678–1761; <title>DNB</title>), British Ambassador to the Ottoman
                        Empire.</note> before her marriage. The world corrupted her, – she knew nothing of human nature except with all the varnish
                    &amp; tinsel &amp; rascality of high life about it, – &amp; consequently the pictures which she gives of <del>xxxxxxx xxxxx</del>
                    &lt;it&gt; &amp; of her own poor heart is a melancholy one. It is not therefore that I like <hi rend="ital">her</hi> better than
                    all other letter-writers, but her letters appear to me more natural (according to her nature) &amp; full of better sense, her
                    views of life considered than those of any one else. – I thank you for the passage concerning Madocs voyage; – there is a great
                    mass of evidence to prove the existence of Welsh-Indians in America, – whenever I can afford the time I will collect it to be
                    prefixed to some future edition of the poem.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works
                            1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, <title>Madoc</title>, introduction, for the Welsh
                        Indian materials and for details of later editions. The materials were not added.</note> – There is no variance between me
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, – what you say however is perfectly explainable. we have no
                    common friends, nor is it possible that two men so radically different should. – When next you favour me with a letter I pray you
                    mention the state of your health. Soon before, or soon after Christmas I hope &amp; expect to see you. The pen is a slow organ
                    when one has much to say.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>