<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1469</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2591</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library
                        of Wales, MS 4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1469" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1469" type="letter">
        <head>1469. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-06-19">19
                        June 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M
                        P./ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: FREE/ 22JU22/ 1808<lb />Seal: [partial, illegible]<lb />MS: National Library
                        of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I understood the Bill it has no other meaning than to give the Bookseller 28 years instead of 14, &amp;
                        <del>xx</del> in cases where the copyright has not been sold to extend the Authors property to his representative, for the
                        <del>said</del> &lt;same&gt; term.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 16 June a bill was introduced to parliament
                        advocating a change in copyright law. It intended to remove the dependence of copyright on the life of the author and replace
                        it by a single period of 28 years from the date of first publication.</note> The best thing to be done at present is as you
                    say to oppose it altogether, till it can be more maturely considered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Who framed the Bill?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bill was framed by John Villiers (1757&#8211;1838), M.P.
                    for Queenborough in consultation with Edward Christian (bap.1758&#8211;1823).</note> If the worthy Sheriff <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Sir Richard Philips</ref> &#8211; alias Sir Philip Richards
                    according to his true name &#8211; were in Parliament he might be suspected of it. &#8211; for it is some such &#8216;encouragement of
                        learning&#8217;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> An allusion to the Bill&#8217;s title: a <title>Bill for the further encouragement
                            of Learning in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, by securing to the Libraries of the Universities, and
                            other public libraries, copies of all newly-printed books, and books reprinted with additions, and by further securing the
                            copies and copyright of printed Books to the authors of such books, or their assigns, for a time to be limited.</title>
          </note> as he would hold out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Books which produce any profit at all have either a sudden popularity or a steady one which is most commonly slow
                    in its growth. Those of the first description do not last fourteen years. &#8211; The Winter in London<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Skinner Surr (bap. 1770&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Winter in London, or Sketches of Fashion.
                            A Novel</title> (1806).</note> &#8211; All the Talents<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eaton Stannard Barrett
                        (1786&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>All the Talents: a Satirical Poem in Three Dialogues</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; the
                    Pursuits of Literature<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas James Mathias (1753/4&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Pursuits of Literature, or, What you will</title> (1794&#8211;1797), a satire on contemporary authors.</note> &amp;c &#8211;
                    you may as well give a fishmonger the exclusive privilege of selling mackarel a week old, as give any property in these books
                        <del>after</del> beyond the old apprenticeship. On the other hand neither 14 nor 28 years are enough for works of permanent
                    value &#8211; the term of these ought to be unlimited. Admiral Gambier is sent to sing psalms before Copenhagen &amp; steal ships there, &#8211; he
                    comes back &amp; is made a Lord for so doing, &amp; all his heirs male are to be Lords as long as they last.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> James, Baron Gambier (1756&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and evangelical, known for
                        making his crew sing hymns and say Psalms. Gambier was given a peerage as a reward for commanding the expedition that, in
                        September 1807, bombarded neutral Copenhagen until the Danish surrendered its felt into British hands.</note> Literary profits
                    ought in justice to have the same perpetuity. Every Englishman likes to think that Blenheim is still the seat of the
                        Marlbro&#8217;s.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blenheim Palace, near Oxford, erected at the nation&#8217;s cost as a reward for
                        John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough, Prince of Mindelheim (1650&#8211;1722), having won the Battle of Blenheim in 1704.</note>
                    Equal pleasure ought to be felt, &amp; could be felt, if the descendants of Shakespear &amp; Milton (had they left any) were at
                    this day the proprietors of their works, &amp; in enjoyment of the ample income which would be derived from them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Except in making the copyright survive to our children this bill favours the booksellers to the material injury of
                    the author; &#8211; as you point out. &#8211; Give me the fee simple of my own works &amp; my childrens children will want no better
                    inheritance. This ought to be given us, &amp; instead of <del>enlargin</del> increasing the booksellers term it would be better if
                    authors could be prevented from selling for more than 7 years, &#8211; because bad books have all their harvest before that time runs
                    out, &#8211; &amp; good ones do not begin to get theirs till a later period.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent6"> Shall I not see you this summer?</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-06-19">Sunday 19 June.</date>
          </p>
          <p>
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> has left me this day. &#8211; he is appointed to the Dreadnought Admiral
                        Sothebys ship.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was a 98-gun second rate ship of
                            the line launched in 1801. She had fought at Trafalgar (1805) and was now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby
                            (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s
                            acquaintance.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>