<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1280</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2402</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        437&#8211;440.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1280" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1280" type="letter">
        <head>1280. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1807-02-25">25 February
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Pallas/ Plymouth Dock./
                        Single <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ FEB 28/ 1807<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        437&#8211;440.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you not urged your Captain to make urgent application for more men? you should do this, &amp; he should
                    represent the state of the ship.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey was serving aboard the <hi rend="ital">Pallas</hi>, a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860;
                            <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the capture of many French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command
                        passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown). According to a letter to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary
                            Barker</ref>, the ship was &#8216;so miserably manned&#8217; that Thomas was &#8216;almost worn out with duty&#8217;; see Southey to Mary Barker,
                        4 February 1807, Letter 1273.</note> Convince him that more hands are essential for her safety &amp; I warrant he will apply
                    for them; &amp; <del>it would</del> doing your duty as you do it would come with weight from you. One comfort the winter draws
                    towards an end &#8211; &amp; your raw hands must be getting more useful every day. I am glad Solly has joined, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughters</ref> correspondent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Amadis must have been Longmans mistake.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longmans had, at Southey&#8217;s behest,
                        sent Thomas Southey a box of his books including <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> Twill do however to give away,
                    whenever you find any person whom you like to give it to. Have they put it in instead of the Metrical Tales<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; which you have not mentioned among the contents of the parcel?
                    let me know this that if so it may be included in the next. The remarks on Thalaba should be in one of the volumes of Mackay &#8211;
                    where you have probably by this time found them. If not it is of little matter as they will appear in his works.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letters have left a weight upon my mind whenever I think of you; &#8211; &amp; in the heavy gale of Saturday
                    &lt;night&gt; last I think it was (the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>) &#8211; when the wind waked me <del>xxx xxxx</del> I did nothing but
                    think of you &amp; dream of you by turns. The days however are lengthening, &amp; you sure at least of soon getting a Master, if
                    not more hands. My best hopes are that you may soon be made, &#8211; &amp; yet not have interest enough to get a ship immediately &#8211; so
                    as to have a few months here among the mountains, &amp; a few fine weather cruises on the Lake. We are going to do wonders this
                    summer. Some arrangements of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> rendered it necessary that I should
                    either fix upon quitting this place &#8211; or retaining <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">the house</ref> &#8211; this last suited me best,
                    &amp; my mind is made up to continue here indefinitely &#8211; indeed I know not what could ever induce me to leave this country,
                    unless it were to return to Lisbon, for the longer I stay the better I like it. Oh that you could see it in snow &amp; sunshine!
                    &amp; in snow &amp; moonlight! &#8211; it is even more beautiful than in the finest autumnal evening. &#8211; We are going to paper the
                    parlour with cartridge paper, to have the abominable curtains there died a deep blue, &amp; to fringe them. To buy a carpet &amp;
                    white curtains for my study &#8211; which is of course to be ceiled &amp; plastered &#8211; &amp; to have my books round by the sea. The
                    outside of the house is to be finished. the walk up the garden is gravelling at this time, with such gravel &amp;c as is to be got
                    &#8211; which is the soil of the river. &amp; I mean to plant some trees which will shut out the lower end of the town, if not in my
                    time, in somebody elses. Every thing is to be made decent, &amp; my study beautiful. Think of the joy it will be to arrange my
                    books, &amp; see them all together, &amp; worship them every day!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I believe it will be necessary to give the History of the Rio de la Plata as well as of Brazil &#8211; in which case the
                    book would perhaps be entitled Brazil &amp; Paraguay.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was published as the
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> They are so interwoven in the first years of the history &#8211; &amp;
                        <del>xx</del> in the last as well, that I must either relate all myself &#8211; or be continually stopping to explain or refer the
                    reader to what he knows nothing about. I go on excellently well, &amp; expect with as much confidence as mortal man ought to
                    expect any thing, that the first volume will be compleated by the end of the summer.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was not published until 1810.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncles</ref> papers all relate to the second &#8211; there is however one folio MS. which
                        <del>xx</del> describes the colony in 1586. I will hope that you may be here during the summer to look over all my sea terms.
                    There shall certainly be such prints to the book as will explain it &#8211; a view of a Brazilian town &#8211; if it may so be called &#8211;
                    costume of the natives &amp;c. &amp;c. these ought to be so introduced in head &amp; tail-pieces as not to be very expensive,
                    while they would be very useful.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was not illustrated in this way.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My reviewing is compleated.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to Cochin
                            China, in the Years 1792, and 1793: Containing a General View of the Productions, and Political Importance of this
                            Kingdom; and also of such European Settlements as were Visited on the Voyage, with Sketches of the Manners, Character, and
                            Condition of their Inhabitants</title> (1806), 2&#8211;16; James Burney, <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in
                            the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (Vol. 2; 1806), 16&#8211;30; James Stanier Clarke
                        (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (1805&#8211;1806), 71&#8211;72;
                            <title>Report of the British and Foreign Bible Society</title> (1805), 155&#8211;160; Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820), <title>A
                            New and Appropriate System of Education for the Labouring People</title> (1806), 278&#8211;282; John Wooll (bap. 1767&#8211;1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of the late Revd. Joseph Warton, Master of St. Mary Winton College;
                            Prebendary of Winchester Cathedral; and Rector of the Parishes of Wickham and Upham, Hants: to which are added, a
                            Selection from his Works; and a Literary Correspondence Between Eminent Persons, Reserved by him for Publication</title>
                        (1806), 298&#8211;305; Lucy Hutchinson (n&#233;e Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown),
                            <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806), 361&#8211;378; James Grant Raymond (1771&#8211;1817), <title>The Life
                            of Thomas Dermody</title> (1806), 383&#8211;397; Henry Richard Fox, 3rd Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Life and
                            Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1806), 397&#8211;411; Richard Duppa, <title>The Life and Literary Works of
                            Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806), 411&#8211;425; George Chalmers, (bap. 1742&#8211;1825;
                            <title>DNB</title>), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Sir David Lyndsay</title> (1806), 482&#8211;494; Thomas Moore (1779&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epistles, Odes and Other Poems</title> (1806), 498&#8211;499; [Society of Friends of Pennsylvania],
                            <title>Accounts of Two Attempts Towards the Civilization of Some Indian Natives</title> (1806), 589&#8211;593; Thomas Clarkson,
                            <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar Customs, Religious
                            Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title> (1806), 594&#8211;607; Thomas Jarrold
                        (1770&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological and Political; in Answer to Mr.
                            Malthus&#8217;s &#8216;Essay on the Principle of Population&#8217;</title> (1806), 607&#8211;615.</note> there are four Letters of D Manuel<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> to finish &#8211;
                    which are begun &#8211; but I wait for the spur of a proof or two more to send them &amp; the work at the same time. The printer<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>).</note> is very slow &#8211; he has eight sheets
                    of the second volume in his hands, &amp; three of the third. I have twice written to hurry him. Palmerin<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> is now my evening work, &#8211; ten weeks will wash that off my hands, &amp; then I am a free man, with no other tie
                    on me than my own good will &amp; pleasure. The last of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Whites</ref> papers are to
                    reach me this week &#8211; what I have to do <del>xx</del> in the prefatory account may take five or six evenings, &amp; a longer time,
                    if longer were required would be well bestowed upon <del>things</del> the memory of so rare &amp; excellent a young man. From that
                    profile, from <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">a younger brother</ref> who very much resembles him, &amp; from memory, a
                        <del>xx</del> likeness of him has been made, which is said to be a striking one, &amp; is now in the engravers hands. There
                    will be some other prints &#8211; one from a drawing of his own, which was <del>meant</del> prefixed to one of the poems &#8211; representing
                    Time covering a part of the Globe &#8211; I have not seen it. Another will be a view of a Church yard in which he was used to frequent,
                    &amp; in which one of his sweetest poems was written. This was my desire, &amp; I have recommended that other views of places
                    which he particularly alluded <del>to by him</del> may be procured.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been
                        planning with <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, older brother of the recently deceased poet <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Kirke White</ref>, a posthumous edition of his works; see Southey to Neville
                        White, 24 November 1806 (Letter 1238), 20 December 1806 (Letter 1245) and 3 February 1807 (Letter 1271). This was published,
                        with plates, as <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will wonder to hear that I am become a regular walker; &#8211; every morning as soon as my fair mornings work is
                    done, off goes my jacket, on goes the bottle-green great coat &amp; the boots, &amp; away to trudge to Scriggins crag. it is too
                    cold for the Dutch grammar, so I can make no other use of the time than to look round me, &#8211; &amp; <del>xx</del> that in this
                    country can never tire. I look at the Lake &amp; the Mountains with more delight because the thought of leaving them is no longer
                    in my mind. The weather has been singularly capricious, but on the whole most unusually, &#8211; it might be said unnaturally &#8211; mild. We
                    had no snow till the last day of January, &amp; the Lake has not been frozen &#8211; indeed there has been scarcely any frost. Our
                    winters are not colder here than they are at Bristol &#8211; the difference is that our summers are not so warm.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> talk of dining here soon, &amp; are to fix their own day. &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> goes for Lisbon in the convoy &#8211; he leaves the river on Tuesday next
                    &#8211; I shall much miss him in the summer &#8211; as he has been here three summers following. The boat will not be well manned without him
                    &#8211; so we must be content to have it well <hi rend="ital">womanned</hi>. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> will
                    probably touch here on his way to the Highlands<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman did not visit the Highlands; see
                        Southey to John Rickman, 27 May 1807, Letter 1327.</note> &#8211; &amp; perhaps I shall persuade my old friend the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> to come down once more, Kickmanjiggify<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            Southey&#8217;s coinage, meaning to beautify&#8212;in this case by making decorated protective covers for the books.</note> more of my books, &amp; lend a hand in adorning the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry&#8217;s</ref> Emma I believe is married to a Mr Hoare.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Southey had met Emma Noel (d. 1873), while at the home of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles
                            Lloyd</ref> in <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. She was the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of Exton
                        Park, Rutland (1759&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to
                        become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple&#8217;s plans to marry, their relationship ended. William
                        Hoare (d. 1819) married Emma&#8217;s sister Louisa Elizabeth Noel (d. 1816); Emma married Stafford O&#8217;Brien (d. 1864).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> will not much regard this. The wound in his heart was not quite so
                    deep as a well, nor so wide as a church door. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> talks very often about
                    you. I took her the other evening to the window to see the hail which beat very hard against it. &#8211; Why does Uncle Tom , said she,
                    stay out such bad weather? &#8211; why does&#8217;nt he come home? &#8211; he never comes home now. &#8211; I asked her one day if she would have you for
                    a Pappa. no &#8211; she says &#8211; he&#8217;s a Uncle Tom &#8211; &amp; she insists upon it that you are a worthy Uncle &amp; a good sailor. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Love &amp;c &#8211; God bless you &#8211; RS.</salute>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Lose no opportunity of writing, &amp; if you have nothing else to say keep a sheet open to write down old
                        stories when they come to mind.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1807-02-25"> Wednesday Feby 25. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>