<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1401</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2523</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                        Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 254&#8211;259.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 36&#8211;38 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1401" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1401" type="letter">
        <head>1401. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1807-12-21">21 December
                        1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                        Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 254&#8211;259<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 36&#8211;38 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Senhora</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am flattered &amp; gratified by <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edwards</ref> offer of becoming
                    godfather to the unborn,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma Southey</ref> (b. 9 February 1808); Littleton did become her godfather.</note>
                    &amp; you will express to him any thankful acceptance of his offer in the best terms you can find. You have contrived to mingle
                    something unpleasant with this by requesting me to change the name intended: I have told <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> that should the child be a boy Danvers is to be his name, &#8211; &amp; assuredly Danvers his name must be.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, see Southey to Charles Danvers, 28 July 1807, Letter 1347.</note> I have
                    as great a respect for Sir Edward as is possible to have for any person with whom I am well acquainted only by <del>hearsay</del>
                    report, &amp; have seen so seldom. But were I to name a child of mine after him, the immediate question would be is he a
                    particular friend of yours, &#8211; &amp; to this what reply could be made? &#8211; It would be paying him a very mean compliment thus to set
                    aside one of my oldest &amp; dearest friends, a man whom I most entirely love, honour &#8211; &amp; esteem, &amp; whose name, I verily
                    believe, if there be anything good in the boy who bear it, will operate as an incitement in him to every virtue. If I judge
                    rightly of Sir Edward Littleton he would think within himself &#8216;what am I to Southey that he should show me this preference?&#8217; &#8211;
                    &amp; judge me to be one of a suppler spirit than it has pleased God to make me. &#8211; When you have reflected a little upon this, you
                    will feel that I am right, &#8211; &amp; as for the <hi rend="ital">never-forgiving</hi> of which you talk, it is I, Senhora, who have
                    to forgive you the imprudence with which you have subjected me to this risque of displeasing Sir Edward, &amp; appearing
                    insensible of the honour he has done me. Out of this you must bring me as you best can. I have a sort of feeling about naming my
                    children after my friends just as the Catholics have for calling them after their favourite saints. Should I have a third son his
                    name would be <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>, &amp; a fourth would have a good chance of being called
                        <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>. &#8211; On looking back one thing requires explanation &#8211; you may perhaps take
                    it in your head (are you liable Senhora to that female complaint which Doctors call the <hi rend="ital">pet</hi>? &#8211; I think not.)
                    &#8211; you may I say possibly think that if I will not call the boy Edward Littleton, I may as well let <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> be his sponsor; &#8211; the fact is that <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> is one of those dissenters who reject this ceremony altogether, &amp; look upon godfathership as a relic of
                    Popish superstition. I have a different feeling upon the subject, &amp; think the more ties there are of good will to bind man
                    &amp; man together, the better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If this unborn does not appear some time in January it will be very extraordinary, &#8211; for as nature is as punctual
                    as I am in all her operations he may certainly be expected about that time. You may therefore look for me in less than six weeks.
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> will accompany me as far as our roads lie together, which will probably be just
                    to <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Penkridge</ref> &#8211; then he strikes for Bristol &amp; I for Litchfield<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> To visit <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Anna Seward</ref>.</note> &amp; London. &#8211; This
                    expulsion of the English from Lisbon strips <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> of half his income, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">that</hi> half on which he himself lived. <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, &amp; what he
                    allowed <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> engrossing the other: My friend <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> loses the bulk of his fortune by it &#8211;20,000 &#163;. I know no man who ever made a
                    better use of affluence, &amp; there is none who will bear up against adversity more like a man. Whether my Uncles &#8216;great friends&#8217;
                    will do any thing for him remains to be seen. I generally suspect that a mans great friends are so called on the old law of
                    contrarieties, because they are very little his friends. &#8211; As for the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref>
                    he gets into a scrape wherever he goes, &#8211; &amp; certain it is that the most prudent thing he can do is to marry as soon as he can,
                    &#8211; tho in any body else so circumscribed it would be a great imprudence. But he never can get into practice till he has a wife to
                    make fathers &amp; mothers easy. Mary Sealy (do you remember her?) is the present object. Her father<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Sealy (c. 1752&#8211;1821), an old Lisbon acquaintance of Southey&#8217;s.</note> has refused him, &#8211; but I believe
                    every thing is settled between him &amp; the Lady, &amp; as soon as he can find a place to go to Harry will start with no other
                    property in the world than a wife. Huzza! we were not born to sink in the world, or we had long ago gone to the bottom. I knew
                    little of <ref>Mary Seeley</ref> &#8211; except that she has a sweet face, indication of much good. &amp; <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs Gonne</ref> preferred her greatly to all the young Lisboners, &amp; always said every thing
                    that was good of her. Now I look upon her opinion on such subjects as infallible. Of all human beings (<hi rend="ital">damn
                        the </hi>
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge"> Count</ref>! &#8211;) whom I have ever seen that woman is the most like what Angels must be,
                    &amp; we usually like best those persons whom we resemble most. So I am very well satisfied with my sister elect, tho a little
                    more anxious than I would wish to be about their outset in life. &#8211; I think sometime of the cr[MS obscured] that fall from the rich
                    man&#8217;s table &#8211; or rather of the guineas which are locked up in the bureau of that wretched <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Uncle at Taunton</ref>, whom I always call <hi rend="ital">Mr.</hi> Southey, by way of
                    disowning.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your very very very amusing letter about the Reverend. I cannot tell you how much it amused us. And
                    now the best thing you can tell me is that his Reverence is off again, for as fortune must have shuttle cocks to knock about, she
                    cannot chuse a fitter one than Kurles,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps the Rev. Kyrle-Ernle Money, vicar of Much
                        Marcle, Herefordshire.</note> as you call him. <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady Hollands</ref> is a very
                    handsome present. eight volumes in Russia binding &#8211; with R.S &#8211; on the back. I only regret that she did not know &#8216;my partiality for
                    black letter.&#8217; &#8211; as the Ordinary said to Jonathan Wild about the punch, when Jonathan proposed a bottle of wine to him in
                        Newgate.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Jonathan Wild</title> in <title>The Works of Henry
                            Fielding</title>, ed. Leslie Stephen (London, 1882), V, p. 192.</note> &#8211; Espriella seems generally known.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> I can only
                    console myself by proving that the world <hi rend="ital">had no reason</hi> for knowing it because it only knows me as a poet
                    &amp; Espriella is not in the same stile as Madoc Thalaba or Joan of Arc.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) and <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796).</note> It
                    cannot be helped, &amp; it is no matter. &#8211; Pray rummage up your memory for the new volumes.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A sequel to <title>Letters from England</title> never appeared.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Today, being the shortest day, I have a library-table come home, &#8211; of dantzic oak,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Oak from Danzig.</note> standing on two claws, &amp; with drawers all round. Handsome enough for me, well made
                    &amp; excellently convenient. We all admire it much. Worse news &#8211; two brothers were drowned yesterday on the lake, &#8211; attempting to
                    cross it on the ice! &#8211; a great shock as you may well suppose it to everybody here; &#8211; knowledge of the place seeming in some degree
                    to affect us like knowledge of the persons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> has been writing, by her desire, to your friend Mrs Skepper,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Dorothea Benson (1773&#8211;1856), the widow of Thomas Skepper (c. 1771&#8211;1805), a lawyer in
                        York. After being widowed, she became the housekeeper of the friend of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, <ref target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Basil Montagu</ref>. She married Montagu in 1808, becoming his third wife, and conversed
                        on literary subjects with the Wordsworth circle.</note> &amp; I am asked if the letter may not be franked up to you to be
                    franked on. So expect it in a blank cover. &#8211; My first batch of reviewing goes off this evening. Did I tell you that overtures were
                    made me from the Edinburgh offering about double pay to what the Annual gives?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Archibald
                        Constable (1774&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), the Edinburgh publisher of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> and Walter Scott&#8217;s
                            <title>Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (1805) and <title>Marmion</title> (1807), had asked through Scott whether Southey
                        would become a contributor to the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>; see Southey to John Rickman, 1 December 1807 (Letter 1387)
                        and Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11 December 1807 (Letter 1396).</note> &#8211; You would have been pleased with the way in
                    which I rejected this offer on the ground of my decided disapprobation of the system on which that journal was conducted &#8211; &amp;
                    all the opinions which it professed.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 December
                        1807, Letter 1392.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-12-21">Monday. Dec 21. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>