<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1156</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2278</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. D. 3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1156" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1156" type="letter">
        <head>1156. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-02-11">11
                        February 1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ to
                        be left at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthrie&#8217;s. Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: FEB/ 1806/ 11 <lb />Endorsement: 1806<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. D. 3<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Harry &#8211;</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have taken some steps about your graduating expences &#8211; let me know what sum they require, &amp; by what time, &#8211;
                    &amp; I will arrange matters with <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is made Under Secretary of State in the Home Office, which introduces him to
                    public business in the pleasantest manner possible, &amp; gives him 1500&#163; a year. I am in a fair way of getting whichever of the
                    two situations I want shall first be vacated; &#8211; of course you will say nothing of this to any person whatever. it is asked for me,
                    &amp; I have the interest of <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady Holland</ref> besides, who have both promised to second the application. &#8211;
                    Another good thing from this change is that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> is very likely to get
                    something &#8211; tho unluckily it must be in the very worst country in Europe. And I do not think it impossible that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> may be benefitted thro <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">James Losh</ref>, to whom
                    I think of writing in his behalf.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey expected that his friend James Losh would be
                        able to influence Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>) on his brother Tom&#8217;s behalf, as he had been
                        appointed First Lord of the Admiralty in the new administration. Losh and Grey were friends based on their common interests as
                        residents of Northumberland, members of the Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society, and a shared concern to bring about
                        parliamentary reform.</note> The Devil has not often done so good a job as when he took his majestys minister to himself.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), the Prime
                        Minister, whose second term of office ended with his death on 23 January 1806.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is no saying where Syphilis first appeared, because it was not noticed till it became alarmingly
                        general.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Southey was soliciting information from his brother for his university
                        dissertation to graduate as MD. This was on the origins and course of syphilis, in which he suggested an American origin for
                        the disease.</note> There were no medical journals in those days, &amp; no histories of singular cases. The disease excited no
                    attention till it was spread over Europe after the siege of Naples.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1495 French forces
                        under Charles VIII (1470&#8211;1498), occupied Naples. Some sixteenth century writers argued that these troops spread the disease,
                        which had recently reached Italy on ships returning from America.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> you may see thinks Charles had it himself on the way there.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roscoe, in a footnote to p. 162 of volume 1 of <title>The Life and Pontificate of Pope Leo
                            X</title>, 4 vols (Liverpool, 1805), attributes the origin of the syphilis epidemic to Charles VIII&#8217;s
                        licentiousness.</note> Bernal Diaz may very likely mention the Bubas &#8211; but I not caring about the subject when I read his
                    work, have no references to it, &amp; the book is at Bristol.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey owned a copy of the
                        first edition of Bernal D&#237;az del Castillo (1492&#8211;1585), <title>Historia Verdadera de la Conquista de la Nueva Espana</title>
                        (1632). D&#237;az describes how the Aztecs were devastated by an epidemic disease, thus rendering them vulnerable to conquest by
                        Cortes and his men. The disease is usually thought to have been smallpox.</note> The late translation would probably have the
                    passage, if it be worth looking after.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernal D&#237;az del Castillo, <title>The True History
                            of the Conquest of Mexico</title> (1800), trans. Maurice Keating (d. 1835).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I knew a Mr Browne<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Lisbon merchant. Dates unknown.</note> at Lisbon very
                    slightly, but do not conceive that he has left the place, for he was in business there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The account which you give of your health is but an unpleasant one. take care of yourself, &amp; remember that we
                    have all of us more chance of consumption than a good estate. I shall be glad to hear that you are better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My eyes are troublesome, tho the disorder every time it returns abates in strength. I have for this fortnight past
                    been obliged to go to cards for the sake of sparing them, &amp; in the course of that time have given <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> some severe bastings. But last night she invited me
                    to such a baste as perhaps never was equalled in the history of Quadrille. Had it not been for me who made the called [sic] King,
                    &amp; by leading another of the same suit enabled her to make a little trump, there would have been a vote against us. She must
                    never laugh<del>x</del> at you again &#8211; I told her you should hear of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My reviewing will be finished on Monday <del>week next</del>, after which I shall never review again, except it be
                    a chance article as a volunteer. this is a great comfort. Next winter I shall be in Portugal, &amp; whether I be there in an
                    official situation or not &#8211; my employment will be the same. My anxiety is to finish the work, as for printing it that will be a
                    pleasure but it would be still pleasanter to have good reasons for delay.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s plans
                        to return to Portugal to finish his &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; did not materialise and his work remained unfinished.</note> Don
                        Manuel<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> will occupy
                        <del>the</del> a month after the review-work is over, &amp; then I go to London meaning to be absent from home six weeks, one
                    of them at Norwich, unless <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> should be in London. It is
                    very long since I have heard from him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent the MS. to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> last week,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Walter Scott, 4 February 1806, Letter 1152. Southey had been sent a manuscript volume
                        containing rare medieval metrical romances belonging to a Mrs Sherbrook (first name and dates unknown), and was consulting
                        Scott on the possibilities of its publication on her behalf; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 11 January 1806, Letter
                        1146.</note> &amp; by post apprized him of it. In my letter I spoke a good word for <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> book, which will I suppose soon be published.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Duppa, <title>The
                            Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806). Southey reviewed this
                        work in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 411&#8211;425.</note> &#8211; James Grahames is the last book which I have
                        reviewed;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Sabbath</title> (1805), in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 588&#8211;591.</note> it is certainly of very
                    high merit, tho full of faults, or rather faulty throughout in diction &amp; arrangement, &#8211; but he has the true heart &amp; soul
                    of a poet. If you are in the habit of seeing him tell him that somebody should do for the Cameronians what <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> has done for the Borderers, &#8211; the subject matter is better inasmuch as
                    liberty of conscience is nobler than cow-stealing.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cameronians were followers of
                        Richard Cameron (d. 1680), who in 1666 separated from the Scottish Presbyterian church, holding religious assemblies in
                        fields, after his tradition of preaching. In 1680 they rejected the authority of Charles II (1630&#8211;1685, King of England,
                        Scotland and Ireland 1660&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>), declaring war on him as a tyrant and usurper, which led to Cameron&#8217;s
                        capture and execution. The Borderers, or Reivers who inhabited the land on either side of the Scottish-English border, engaged
                        in lawless activities such as cattle-rustling.</note> I cannot conceive finer or nobler matter for poetry than their intrepid
                    &amp; unconquerable heroism affords &#8211; Were I a Scotchman these are the countrymen of whom I should be proud. Malcolm Laings
                    history of that period is one of the most provoking books which I have ever read.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Malcolm
                        Laing (1762&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), was a Scottish advocate and historian, who published <title>The History of Scotland,
                            from the Union of the Crowns on the Accession of King James VI to the Throne of England, to the Union of the Kingdoms in
                            the Reign of Queen Anne, with Two Dissertations, Historical and Critical, on the Gowrie Conspiracy, and on the Supposed
                            Authenticity of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> in 1800.</note>
          <del>The</del> He gives you the spirit of the things instead of the things themselves &#8211; &amp; you get an opinion from his book
                    without an[y] of the specific facts whereon it should be founded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">young one</ref> gets on more rapidly with her tongue than you would
                    conceive. no letters from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> by the last packet &#8211; the ship was probably cruising.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-02-11">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 11. 1806. &#8211;</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>