<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1567</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2689</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bunce Collection, Birmingham University Library, BU4.  Previously  published: Ernest Betham, ed., A House
                            of Letters: Being Excerpts from the Correspondence of Miss Charlotte Jerningham (the Honble. Lady Bedingfield), Lady
                            Jerningham, Coleridge, Lamb, Southey, Bernard and Lucy Barton, and others, with Matilda Betham; and from Diaries and
                            Various Sources; and a Chapter upon Landor&#8217;s Quarrel with Charles Betham at Llanthony (London, 1905), pp.119&#8211;121
                        [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1567" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1567" type="letter">
        <head>1567. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Mary Matilda Betham</ref> [fragment], <date when="1809-01-17">17
                    January 1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] Wrexham Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. twenty
                        five 1809/ Miss Betham/ Stoneham/ Suffolk/ W Williams Wynn<lb />Stamped: WREXHAM/ 202<lb />Postmark: FREE/ 24 JA 24/
                        1809<lb />MS: Bunce Collection, Birmingham University Library, BU4<lb />Previously published: Ernest Betham, ed., <title>A House
                            of Letters: Being Excerpts from the Correspondence of Miss Charlotte Jerningham (the Honble. Lady Bedingfield), Lady
                            Jerningham, Coleridge, Lamb, Southey, Bernard and Lucy Barton, and others, with Matilda Betham; and from Diaries and
                            Various Sources; and a Chapter upon Landor&#8217;s Quarrel with Charles Betham at Llanthony</title> (London, 1905), pp.119&#8211;121
                        [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-01-17">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 17. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You make a right distinction, my dear Miss Betham, between the egotism of words &amp; of actions. The egotism of
                    the heart seldom reaches to the lips, &#8211; none are so intensely selfish as the race of fawners &amp; flatterers, who always talk
                    about <hi rend="ital">you</hi> for the sake of making <hi rend="ital">themselves</hi> appear amiable. Those letters are always the
                    most interesting which are most about the writer. Am I wrong in supposing that generous minds express themselves more fully by the
                    pen than by word of mouth, whereas a knave never lays himself open except he is thrown off his guard in conversation? &#8211; I have
                    myself not so much a principle, as an instinct of unreservedness, &#8211; nor do I know whether I can help it or no, for I never
                        <del>have tr</del> tried the experiment. My very reserve resembles the rolling itself up of a hedgehog, &amp; is a
                    manifestation too plain to be mistaken that I do not like my company. Yet I am sensible that I express myself more fully &amp;
                    more freely when writing by my own fire side, than ever I do <del>xxxx</del> at an after-dinner table, or in the most confidential
                    &lt;personal&gt; intercourse.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In June then we hope &amp; look to see you here. What the picture wants can easily be given it, &#8211; or rather what it
                    has too much of can easily be taken away.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Betham had painted a portrait of Southey in
                        March 1808.</note> My<del>ne</del> &lt;face&gt; has had none of that bloom for about seventeen years &#8211; There must be a strong
                    Southey character about it, for every body recognizes me, but thinks more of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref>. But Henry&#8217;s face has got him into so many love-scrapes that I
                    have told him he ought not to go about without a muzzle, a precaution of which I never felt the slightest occasion myself. My skin
                    thickened just as I ceased to be a boy, I was always lean, &amp; at that age when men in general think of nothing but their
                    pleasure I had <del>so much</del> occasion both for thought &amp; feeling which have left their indelible stamp <del>behind</del>
                    upon my strong features.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By the time you arrive my Hindoo Poem will probably be finished.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note> Should it be compleated to my own satisfaction, I have a
                    wish about it which I will not explain till you have seen the story, &amp; then I think you will guess it. I promise to myself
                    many pleasures in seeing you here, &#8211; in showing you the mountains from these windows, &#8211; in rowing you to the spot where we boil
                    our kettle by the lake side, &#8211; in seeing you, tempted by emulation at the example of my boat<hi rend="ital">women</hi>, take the
                    oars in your hand instead of the pencil, &#8211; in guiding you over the mountains &amp; into the glens, &#8211; in talking to you about your
                    poems &amp; telling you what you could do, &#8211; &amp; in showing you how very happy a man may be upon very scanty means, who cares
                    nothing for the pomps &amp; vanities of the world, &amp; preserves a boys heart when the grey hairs are beginning to show
                    themselves. And in pointing out to you the house where your father lodged, &amp; the school in which he taught,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Betham&#8217;s father, William Betham (1749&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman, antiquary,
                        schoolmaster, was born at Little Strickland, near Morland, Westmorland, twenty-five miles east of Keswick, and schooled in
                        Keswick.</note> when your spirit was just ripe for this human stage of <del>existence</del> &lt;being&gt;, &#8211; for preexistence
                    is a part of my creed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope &amp; trust one day to have an opportunity of personally thanking Lady Bedingfield.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Jerningham, Lady Bedingfield (1771&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), Betham&#8217;s friend since the 1790s,
                        was proposing to illustrate one of Southey&#8217;s poems.</note> In the work which I have at present in the press there is one part
                    which will I think equally please &amp; displease her. It is that which relates to the Jesuits, &#8211; main actors in the history of
                    that portion of South America which falls within my limits.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> Ample &#8211; most ample justice is rendered to their love
                    of God &amp; of man, &#8211; &amp; I hope the sincerity &amp; even zeal with which I have done this may atone to her for the manner in
                    which I cannot but speak of the Catholick mythology.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My hope &amp; faith in the Spaniards remains unshaken <del>amid</del> by their reverses, <del>or f</del> even by
                    the far more lamentable panics &amp; pusillanimity of our Government. The papers in the Courier signed G. upon the Cintra
                    Convention are by <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, &amp; will be separately published, &#8211; they express
                    our opinions here.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the Convention of Cintra (signed 30 August 1808), British
                        generals allowed a defeated French army to evacuate Portugal. On 27 December 1808 and 13 January 1809 Wordsworth published, in
                            <title>The Courier</title>, an article condemning the Convention. In May 1809 Longmans published the article as a
                        pamphlet, entitled <title>Concerning the Relations of Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common
                            Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the Convention of Cintra</title>.</note> Were I a single man I
                    would hasten to Spain as to a crusade, &amp; if possible get to Zaragoza in time for the siege.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two sieges of Zaragoza took place, in 1808&#8211;1809. For Southey&#8217;s accounts, see <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 306&#8211;321, and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811),
                        508&#8211;527.</note> Oh doubt not that that country will redeem, is redeeming itself! Even if Bonaparte bears down all opposition
                    for a time, &amp; conquers the country, he will not have conquered the people, &#8211; wherever the pressure of his armies is withdrawn
                    they will rise against him, &#8211; his whole force will be required to keep them down, (even if he gets them down) &amp; ultimately the
                        <del>will</del> vengeance of God &amp; Man will strike him there, when his work is done.</p>
        <p>[MS torn]</p>
        <p>me to express her thanks for the picture, &amp; to say how glad she shall be to express them herself.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>