<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1058</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2180</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 326&#8211;328 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1058" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1058" type="letter">
        <head>1058. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-04-13">13 April 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ APL18/ 1805<lb />Endorsement:
                        13 April 1805<lb />MS: Bodleian Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 326&#8211;328 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I learnt of your pamphlet<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford&#8217;s pamphlet, <title>A Letter to the Right
                            Hon. William Pitt on his Political Experiments</title> (1804).</note> from one who knew it by mere accident, &#8211; &amp; of
                    having so learnt wrote to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to send me down one.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [c. 7 November 1804], Letter 988.</note> Put me by another &#8211; for
                    I am afraid this has been lost for me &#8211; as I did not hide your light under a bushell.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a notion that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Glasse<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Glasse
                        (1734&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), vicar of Wanstead and a member of a circle of high-church Anglican clerics responsible for
                        founding the <title>British Critic</title> in 1793.</note> could get your reviewal of Madoc inserted in the British
                        Critic<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was damned, though not by Bedford, in the <title>British
                            Critic</title>, 28 (1806), 395&#8211;410.</note> &#8211; you best know whether you are intimate enough with him to ask him the
                    question &#8211; if the thing could be so done it would be of use to me. the Review is a most execrable one &#8211; but it sells among the
                    clergy &amp; the godly &#8211; a good article would have great effect there for its novelty, &#8211; &amp; the old women <hi rend="ital">of
                        both sexes</hi> who are edified once a month by the periodical criticisms of the Bishop of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Giles&#8217;s (for
                    he you know is editor<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#NaresRobert">Robert Nares</ref>, founding
                        editor of the <title>British Critic</title>.</note>) might very truly &amp; happily be told of the pious purport of the poem.
                    &#8211; The book will want some such hearty shove <del>xxx</del> as being a heavy quarto, &#8211; <del>x</del> my profits are wholly dependent
                    upon the sale, &amp; are very likely to be nothing. Two guineas is a great price. I hoped it would not have exceeded 25 &#8211; or 30
                    shillings &#8211; but it grew under correction &amp; the notes take up much room tho not a fourth of what I had collected are inserted.
                    You have divined the object of the priestcraft &#8211; the only defensible machinery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a translation of Sallust by Gordon.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Gordon (d. 1750),
                            <title>The Works of Sallust, Translated into English, With Political Discourses Upon that Author, to Which is Added a
                            Translation of Cicero&#8217;s Four Orations Against Catiline</title> (1744).</note> I have never seen it, but having read his
                        Tacitus<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gordon, <title>The Works of Tacitus</title> (1728&#8211;1731).</note> do not think
                    it likely that any new version would surpass his for he was a man of great powers. It is not likely that <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longus Homo</ref>, or any other Homo would pay for such a translation &#8211; because the
                    speculation is not promising &#8211; every person who wishes to read Sallust being able to read the original. &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longus Homo</ref> would probably print it as he <del>xxx</del> prints my books &#8211; at his
                    risque &#8211; allowing you half the profits but this is not a worthy or adequate employment, &#8211; because the book is too well known it
                    would add nothing to the general stock of knowledge. There are some Greek authors which we want in English &#8211; Diodorus Siculus<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Diodorus Siculus, a 1st century Greek historian who wrote the <title>Bibliotheca
                            Historica</title>.</note> in particular. But why not chuse for yourself &amp; venture upon original composition? In my
                    conscience I do not think any man living has more of Rabelais<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fran&#231;ois Rabelais (c.
                        1494&#8211;1553), the French author of <title>La Vie de Gargantua et de Pantagruel</title> (1532&#8211;1552).</note> in his nature than
                    you have. a grotesque satire a la Gargantua &#8211; in which if you please the Colonel may be William &amp; somebody else the
                        Butler<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Colonel&#8217; could be either of the Rabelaisean characters, Colonel
                        Maul-chitterling and Colonel Cut-pudding. &#8216;William&#8217; and &#8216;the Butler&#8217; are invented characters often referred to in Southey&#8217;s
                        letters to Bedford.</note> &#8211; would set all the kingdom staring &amp; place you in the very first rank of reputation. Now
                    instead of sitting up till morning go to bed in reasonable time this night &amp; dream upon this hint. Depend upon it <del>xxx xxx
                        xxxx &amp;</del> all the political pamphlets &#8211; &amp; all the wisdom in the world would have less effect than a good
                    extravagant Romance &#8211; such as might almost be picked out of the Schrammiana &amp; Butleriana.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> These comic inventions, originating in schoolboy stories at Westminster, were never published by Bedford but
                        provided the hint for Southey&#8217;s comic novel/miscellany <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask if I shall come to town this summer. certainly not &#8211; unless some very material accident were to render it
                    necessary. I do not want to go &#8211; I should not like to go. &amp; I can&#8217;t afford to go. solid reasons M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford
                    as I take it for not going. This is an inconvenient residence for many reasons &amp; I shall move southward as soon as I have the
                    means, &#8211; either to the neighbourhood of London or Bath &#8211; when that may be Heaven knows. for I have not yet found out the art of
                    making more money than goes as fast as it comes in bread &amp; cheese, which these damned ministers make dearer &amp; dearer every
                    day, &amp; I am <del>xxx</del> of that class which feels every addition. However I am well off as it is, <del>x</del> perfectly
                    contented, &amp; ten times happier than half the boobies who walk into that Chapel<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">That
                        is, MPs, for the House of Commons met in St Stephen&#8217;s Chapel, Westminster.</note> there in your neighbourhood &amp; when they
                    are asked if I shall give 16 pence for tenpenny worth of salt<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The government had imposed
                        an additional duty on salt earlier in 1805.</note> &#8211; say yes &#8211; for which the Devil scarify them with wire whips &amp; then put
                    them in <del>x</del> brine say I.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I look daily for your proof<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The proofs of Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly
                        edited anthology, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; &amp; have given <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Artaxerxes</ref>
          <del>x</del> a fillip to quicken him in the business. the Preface will take
                    me some trouble tho I believe myself quite master of the subject. it will be in part a comment upon the designed motto from Hesiod </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent1"> &#916;&#949;&#965;&#964;&#949;&#961;&#959;&#957; &#945;&#965;&#964;&#949; &#947;&#949;&#957;&#959;&#962; &#960;&#959;&#955;&#965; &#967;&#949;&#953;&#961;&#959;&#964;&#949;&#961;&#959;&#957; &#956;&#949;&#964;&#959;&#960;&#953;&#963;&#952;&#949;&#957;</l>
          <l rend="indent1"> &#913;&#961;&#947;&#965;&#961;&#949;&#959;&#957; &#960;&#959;&#953;&#951;&#963;&#945;&#957; &#8008;&#955;&#965;&#956;&#960;&#953;&#945; &#948;&#969;&#956;&#945;&#964;&#7938; &#949;&#967;&#959;&#957;&#964;&#949;&#962;</l>
          <l rend="indent1"> &#935;&#961;&#965;&#963;&#949;&#969; &#959;&#965;&#964;&#949; &#966;&#965;&#951;&#957; &#949;&#957;&#945;&#955;&#953;&#947;&#954;&#953;&#959;&#957; &#959;&#965;&#964;&#949; &#957;&#959;&#951;&#956;&#945;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Specimens of the Later
                                English Poets</title> was published with a preface by Southey but without a motto from the ancient Greek poet, Hesiod.
                            The lines translate as &#8216;After that the dwellers on Olympus made a second race, much worse, of silver, not like the golden
                            race in stature or in thought&#8217;, Hesiod, <title>Works and Days</title> (written between c. 750&#8211;650 BC), 127&#8211;129.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall endeavour to account for the decline of poetry after the age of Shakespeare &amp; Spenser<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Faerie Queene</title>
                        (1590&#8211;1596).</note> in spite of the great exceptions during the Commonwealth &amp; to trace the effect produced by the
                    restorers of a better taste of whom Thomson<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Thomson (1700&#8211;1748;
                        <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Seasons</title> (1730). Thomson is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), II, 107&#8211;111.</note> &amp; Gilbert West<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Gilbert West (1703&#8211;1756; <title>DNB</title>), poet and translator of the odes of Pindar (c. 522&#8211;443 BC). He is included in
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, II, pp. 241&#8211;246.</note> are to be esteemed as the chief before the
                        Wartons<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Warton (bap. 1722&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>), poet and literary critic,
                        who is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, III, pp. 317&#8211;327; Thomas Warton (1728&#8211;1790;
                            <title>DNB</title>), poet laureate and historian, who is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>,
                        III, pp. 465&#8211;469.</note> &#8211; with this difference that what he did was the effect of his own genius &#8211; what they &#8211; by a feeling of
                    the genius of others. <del>X</del> This reign will rank very high in poetical history. Goldsmith &#8211; Cowper, Burns<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Oliver Goldsmith (1730&#8211;1774; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Deserted Village</title>
                        (1770), who is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, III, pp. 77&#8211;82; William Cowper (1731&#8211;1800;
                            <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Task</title> (1785), included in <title>Specimens</title>, III, pp. 470&#8211;482;
                        Robert Burns (1759&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>Poems, Chiefly in the Scottish Dialect</title> (1786).</note>
                    are all original &amp; all unequalled in their way. Falconer<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Falconer (bap.
                        1732&#8211;1769; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Shipwreck</title> (1762). Southey had reviewed James Stanier Clarke&#8217;s
                        (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) 1804 edition of Falconer&#8217;s poem in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805),
                        577&#8211;580. He is included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, II, p. 397&#8211;400.</note> is another <del>x</del>
                    whose work will last for ever &#8211; but I need not preach out my preface to you &#8211; only just to observe that I would not have the motto
                    taken as applicable to our own times &#8211; but to the whole period from James 2<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> James II and
                        VII (1633&#8211;1701, King of England, Scotland and Ireland 1685&#8211;1689; <title>DNB</title>).</note> to the end of the last reign. We
                    have been fetching up the lee way which our immediate predecessors lost.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The vignette of the Snake is misplaced in both the copies I have seen, so as to look perfectly ridiculous.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), was published with three illustrations: the engraved
                        title-page with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn&#8217;s</ref> shield upon a <hi rend="ital">troph&#233;e</hi>, the palm and
                        cross upon the rock (after the Table of Contents), and the snake before the cave, intended for the title-page of the second
                        part, &#8216;Madoc in Aztlan&#8217; but placed incorrectly (after page 320, instead of after page 184).</note> It is meant to form the
                    half title to the second part of the poem, &#8211; if as I suspect the error runs thro all the copies remember that it be remedied in
                    yours when it goes to the binders.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This Rochefort squadron will effectually mar poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> fortune which
                    else he was almost certain of making<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The squadron of French ships commanded by
                        Contre-Admiral Zacharie Allemand (1762&#8211;1828) and based at Rochefort, which slipped past the British blockade and harassed
                        British ships in the Atlantic and West Indies. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of
                        ships and cargo captured in armed conflict, and Southey was particularly concerned that the presence of the French squadron
                        would mean the loss of the Spanish ships (and resultant prize money for his brother) taken by HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>
                        in December 1804.</note> &#8211; &amp; indeed if he escape being taken or killed we must think ourselves fortunate.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-04-13">Tuesday. April 13. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>