<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1157</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2279</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add
                        MS 47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 25&#8211;27 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1157" type="letter">
        <head>1157. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-02-15">15 February
                        1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Amelia/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kitts./ or elsewhere/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ FEB 19/ 1806<lb />MS: British Library, Add
                        MS 47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 25&#8211;27 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <date when="1806-02-15">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 15. 1806.</date>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Once more, my dear Tom, to the hopeless task of writing to one who never gets any of my letters! &#8211; Yours of Dec. 1.
                    is just arrived &#8211; very long, as you perceive after date but that is to be attributed I suppose to its mode of conveyance, as it
                    does not come by packet, &amp; is not marked ship letter, but bears the London post mark.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A world of events have taken place since last I wrote, &#8211; indeed so as almost to change the world here. Pitt is
                    dead,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>) had become Prime Minister for the second time on 10 May 1804 and
                        died in office on 23 January 1806.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenvilles</ref> in
                        place,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Ministry of all the Talents&#8217;, established in February 1806, included
                        William Wyndham Grenville, 1st Baron Grenville, as Prime Minister 1806&#8211;1807, and Charles James Fox as Foreign Secretary and
                        Leader of the House of Commons until his death in September 1806.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> Under Secretary of State in the Home Office.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey expected to benefit from the change in office as his friend and patron Charles Watkin Williams Wynn
                        was appointed Under Secretary of State in the Home Office under his uncle, Lord Grenville.</note> I have reason to expect
                    something, &#8211; of the two appointments at Lisbon which would suit me, whichever falls vacant first is asked for me. both are in <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox&#8217;s</ref> gift, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> as
                    well as Lady H. speak for me. It is likely that one or other will be vacated ere long, &amp; if I should not succeed there, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will look elsewhere. Something or other will certainly turn up ere it be very
                    long. &#8211; I hope also something may some way or other be done for you. a brother of the Duke of Bedford is one of the Lords of the
                        Admiralty<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Russell (1767&#8211;1840), brother of John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford
                        (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), was appointed a Civil Lord of the Admiralty in the new administration.</note> &#8211; to whom I
                    have given <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> a hint to apply thro the Duke. Gray is first Lord,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), was appointed First Lord of the
                        Admiralty under the new administration.</note> &#8211; &amp; it is not impossible that he may be got at thro <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">James Losh</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Losh and Grey were friends
                        based on their common interests as residents of Northumberland, members of the Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society,
                        and a shared concern to bring about parliamentary reform.</note> &#8211; You are mistaken about <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobins</ref> death &#8211; it is John Tobin who is dead,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Tobin (1770&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>), brother of James Webbe Tobin, was a London solicitor and playwright.</note> &#8211; I
                    was promised letters from James to his brother long ago, &amp; conclude they have been written, but will apply again when I see
                        <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">James</ref> which will probably be very soon. You shall lose nothing for want of
                    application on my part.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincent supersedes Cornwallis in the Channel Fleet.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), took command of the Channel fleet in HMS <hi rend="ital">Namur</hi> in 1800. He was replaced by Sir William Cornwallis (1744&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>) in February 1801 when St
                        Vincent became First Lord of the Admiralty.</note> Sir Samuel was made Admiral in the last list of promotions.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), who
                        had been in command of the fleet in which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref> served until 1805.</note>
                    As for peace or war one knows not how to speculate. If I were to guess any thing it would be that by way of getting all parties
                    out of the scrape with credit, Bonaparte may offer us Malta which he cannot take, as an indemnification for Hanover which we must
                    lose. I should be glad this compromise were made. &#8211; You have news enough here to set you in a brown study for the rest of the day
                    &#8211; I will only add an anecdote which I believe is not in the papers, &amp; which sailors will like to know. The flag of the Victory
                    was to be buried with Nelson,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horatio, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233;
                        (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), who died at the Battle of Trafalgar on 21 October 1805.</note> but the sailors when it was
                    lowering into the grave tore it to pieces &#8211; to keep as relics. His reward has been worthy of the country, a public funeral of
                    course &amp; a monument, besides monuments of some kind or other in most of the great cities by private <del>expence</del>
                    subscriptions. his widow made Countess with 2000 &#163;. a year<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Herbert (Fanny)
                        Nisbet, n&#233;e Woolward (1761&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), Viscountess Nelson was granted an annual pension on her husband&#8217;s death
                        of &#163;2000 for life.</note> &#8211; his brother an Earl with an adequate pension, &amp; 200,000 &#163; to be laid out in the purchase of an
                    estate, never to be alienated from the family.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nelson, 1st Earl Nelson
                        (1757&#8211;1835), Church of England clergyman. After his brother&#8217;s death he succeeded as Baron Nelson of the Nile and shortly after
                        Viscount Merton and Earl Nelson of Trafalgar and Merton, as well as Duke of Bront&#233; (in Sicily). He was granted an annual
                        pension of &#163;5000 as well as &#163;100,000 to purchase an estate (Stanlynch Park, near Downton in Wiltshire, which was renamed
                        Trafalgar House).</note> Well done England!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They have made it a custom to give every Captain who is killed in a general action a monument, &amp; a very foolish
                    custom it is. Why has not Captain Hood as good a claim as if he had fallen on the first of June?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Alexander Hood (1758&#8211;1798) died of a wound to the thigh sustained when his ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> engaged the French ship <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi> off the coast of Brittany.</note> &amp; if Captains in the
                    navy why not Colonels in the army? &#8211; it is making the honour too common. If a great column or pyramid were erected, on which their
                    names were to be inscribed as on a marble gazette it would be very well. But upon this plan S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls will be
                    turned into a mess room in the course of a war or two more. When you are fourscore you must contrive to go off in a blaze
                        <del>xxx</del> &amp; get there, &#8211; because by that time I shall be gone before you, &amp; as I have a sneaking sort of a notion
                    that by &amp; by I may have a monument there myself, &lt;<del>one of these days</del>&gt; it will be very awkward <del>if</del> to
                    find myself among so many sailors <del>if I do</del> &lt;unless&gt; you are <del>xxx</del> there to introduce me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As several of my last letters have been directed to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kitts<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Kitts, part of the Leeward Islands group, in the West Indies.</note> I conclude that by this time one or
                    other of them may have reached you. Yours is good news so far as relates to your health, &amp; to the probability of going to
                    Halifax, better summer quarters than the Islands. If you should go there such American books as you may fall in with will be
                    curiosities in England &#8211; the New York publications I conclude travel so far north. Reviews &amp; Magazines, novels or poetry, any
                    thing of real American growth I shall be glad to have. Keep a minute journal there &amp; let nothing escape you</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have long been hard at reviewing, &amp; have this day begun my last article &#8211; which is upon the authenticity of
                    Ossian, concerning which all the evidence has at last been produced, &#8211; &amp; the question is as much at rest as any such question
                    ever can be. Macpherson has forged nineteen twentieths of the whole, &amp; altered the other <del>half t</del> half-title. Of this
                    you will be satisfied when you see my statement in the fourth Annual,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Macpherson
                        (1736&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish writer, who published <title>Fragments of Ancient Poetry Collected in the Highlands
                            of Scotland</title> (1760). The success of this work prompted Macpherson to publish two epic poems, <title>Fingal</title>
                        (1762) and <title>Temora</title> (1763), which he claimed were translations of works by a 3rd century bard named Ossian.
                        Controversy about the authenticity of the poems emerged when the original manuscripts could not be located, and after
                        Macpherson&#8217;s death it became evident that although some legitimate manuscript sources were used, the poems had principally
                        been written by him. A committee had been established to investigate the controversy and published its findings in 1805.
                        Southey reviewed several works on this topic in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806): Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian, Containing the Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse,
                            with Notes and Illustrations</title> (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald Macdonald (1739&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Some of
                            Ossian&#8217;s Lesser Poems Rendered into Verse [from Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s
                            Critical and Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the
                            Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805), 679&#8211;699.</note> &#8211; but there will always be a set of people
                    whom it is impossible ever to convince of what they do not chuse to believe. With this my reviewing concludes &#8211; I trust &#8211; for
                    ever: except any occasional article which I may volunteer for a friends books or upon a favourite subject &#8211;but as a regular
                    employment I have done with it. It took up more time than any other species of composition, because it was the least interesting
                    of all. Next winter it would have been impossible for me to bear a part in the volume, as I shall be abroad; &amp; as things now
                    promise, I shall either remain abroad with an appointment which will supersede the necessity of publishing at all for the sake of
                    the profits, or shall return from thence with the first volumes of my History in a state for immediate publication.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s plans to return to Portugal to finish his &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; did not materialise and
                        this work remained unfinished.</note> At present then my engagements stand thus &#8211; in the course of a week this reviewal will
                    be finished. A month will then be given up to finish Espriellas letters<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> as far as
                    they can be finished here &#8211; after which I go to London, to compleat them, &amp; to compleat also the Specimens over which <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &#8211; to my sore vexation, sore inconveniences, &amp; loss of gain, has
                    dawdled two whole years.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The jointly-edited project that Southey undertook with Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>.</note> I shall remain a month there with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, &#8211; see
                    the Spaniard fairly in the press, from whence he will not be very long coming out in two or three pocket volumes, full of
                    miscellaneous &amp; stimulating matter. If <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> does not
                    meet me in London, I have promised to go to <del>xxx</del> Norwich out of my way home &amp; stay a week with him. At all events I
                    shall be home (barring accidents) by the end of May. Early in October is the time fixd in my own mind for my voyage to Lisbon, &#8211; I
                    may be sent sooner by good fortune &#8211; or prevented by the expulsion of the factory from going at all,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British merchants based at the Lisbon factory were forced from Portugal by the coming invasion by
                        Napoleonic forces, which occurred in November 1807.</note> &#8211; but if nothing occur either way, then I go. During the summer my
                    history will be my employment, &amp; to fit for the press the Life of the Cid.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> Do you meantime continue to write here, which is a safe
                    direction, from whence your letters will be forwarded, if <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> should not be here to
                    receive them first, for if I go with the probability of soon returning she will not accompany me &#8211; &amp; indeed there is some
                    reason for supposing that she will not be able.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have now all I know of myself &amp; of my own plans. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                    is preparing for his examination in April which will enable him in June to receive his title, &amp; touch the pulses &amp; pockets
                    of his majesty&#8217;s subjects.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey graduated as MD on 24 June 1806.</note>
                    You ask always about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> &#8211; &amp; I as constantly repeat bad news &#8211; nothing have I
                    heard since the story that he affects to have turned Roman Catholick &#8211; a farce which will last no longer than it serves to dupe
                    somebody or other. If ever there was a thorough rogue it is our unlucky brother, he is utterly without any feeling of common
                    honour or common honesty. &#8211; To turn to better subjects you would delight in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my
                        daughter</ref> who is all life &amp; quickness. she is very stout &amp; strong being larger in all her limbs than her cousin
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sarah</ref> who is twenty months older. She has the Southey jig,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey describes this family trait in an earlier letter: &#8216;I was in a passion &#8230; &amp; this
                        was accompanied by an angry jig or stamping which I inherited, &amp; which my maternal relations call the Southey jig&#8217;; see
                        Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 30 September 1797, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                        Letter 259.</note> is very passionate, but neither peevish nor obstinate, &amp; a look of displeasure makes her cry. You would
                    soon love her very dearly, for she is a favourite with every body. Here she comes &#8211; as usual every evening &#8211; to see the print of
                    the Arabian Nights Entertainments in the Novelists Magazine,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Novelists&#8217; Magazine</title>, 18 (1785) printed a translation of Antoine Galland&#8217;s (1646&#8211;1715) French rendition of
                        the Arabian Nights&#8217; Entertainments.</note> before she goes to bed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I tell you that I have promised to supply the <del>biography</del> &lt;lives&gt; of the Spanish &amp;
                    Portugueze authors in the remaining volumes of <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikins</ref> great
                    General Biography?<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin&#8217;s <title>General Biography: or, Lives, Critical and
                            Historical, of the Most Eminent Persons of all Ages, Countries, Conditions, and Professions, Arranged According to
                            Alphabetical Order</title> was published in 10 volumes between 1799&#8211;1815. According to Kenneth Curry (<title>New Letters
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, p. 403) Southey contributed the following entries to
                        volumes VI (1807), VII (1808) and VIII (1813): Volume VI: &#8216;Vasco Lobeira&#8217;, 314&#8211;317; &#8216;Francisco Rodrigues Lobo&#8217;, 318; &#8216;Fernam
                        Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Gregorio Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Francisco de Losa&#8217;, 344&#8211;345; &#8216;Joam de Lucena&#8217;, 371&#8211;372; &#8216;Miguel de Luna&#8217;, 388; &#8216;Fr.
                        Francisco de Santo Agostinho Macedo&#8217;, 434&#8211;435, &#8216;El Enamorado Macias&#8217;, 437&#8211;438; &#8216;P. Fr. Pedro Malon de Chaide&#8217;, 506; &#8216;D. Jorge
                        Manrique&#8217;, 523&#8211;524; &#8216;Don Juan Manuel&#8217;, 529&#8211;530; &#8216;Ausias March&#8217;, 542&#8211;543; &#8216;Juan de Mariana&#8217;, 555&#8211;557; &#8216;Vicente Mariner&#8217;, 558;
                        &#8216;Luis de Marmol Carvajal&#8217;, 569; &#8216;P. M. Fr. Juan Marquez&#8217;, 574&#8211;575. Volume VII: &#8216;Juan de Mena&#8217;, 28&#8211;30; &#8216;Don Inigo Lopez de
                        Mendoza&#8217;, 37&#8211;38; &#8216;D. Diego Hurtado de Mendoza&#8217;, 38&#8211;39; &#8216;Menezes&#8217;, 41&#8211;42; &#8216;Christoval de Mesa&#8217;, 59&#8211;60; &#8216;George de Montemayor&#8217;,
                        174&#8211;175; &#8216;Ambrosio de Morales&#8217;, 194&#8211;198; &#8216;Alonso de Castro Nunez&#8217;, 466; &#8216;Antonio de Naxara&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Abraham Nehemias&#8217;, 469;
                        &#8216;Florian de Ocampo&#8217;, 471&#8211;472; &#8216;Fr. Diego de Olarte&#8217;, 487; &#8216;Fr. Andres de Olmos&#8217;, 497; &#8216;Jerome Osorio&#8217; [with Thomas Morgan
                        (1752&#8211;1821)], 530&#8211;533; &#8216;Alonso de Ovalle&#8217;, 548; &#8216;Andres de Oviedo&#8217;, 555&#8211;556; &#8216;Gonzalo Fernandez de Oviedo&#8217;, 556&#8211;557; &#8216;Lorenzo
                        de Padilla&#8217;, 578; &#8216;Pedro Paez&#8217;, 578&#8211;580; &#8216;D. Juan de Palafox y Mendoza&#8217;, 585. Volume VIII: &#8216;Josef de Ossau, Salas y Pellicer&#8217;,
                        25&#8211;26; Bartholom&#233; Pereira&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Luys Pereyra&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Antonio Perez&#8217;, 46&#8211;47; &#8216;Ruy de Pina&#8217;, 173; &#8216;Juan de Pineda&#8217;, 175; &#8216;Fernam
                        Mendes Pinto&#8217;, 178&#8211;179; &#8216;Thome Pires&#8217;, 182&#8211;184; &#8216;Fernando de Pulgar&#8217;, 385.</note> This will not interfere with my own plans
                        &amp;<del> is for the most part</del> &lt;where it does it is&gt; little more than printing the skeleton of what is hereafter
                    to be enlarged. I can tell you nothing of the sale of Madoc, except that <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has
                    told me nothing, which is proof enough of slow sale, &#8211; but if the edition goes off in two years or indeed in three, it will be
                    well for so costly a book.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Madoc</title> was published by Longman
                        in 1805, in a luxurious quarto, costing two guineas.</note> There is a reaction in these things, my poems make me known first,
                    &amp; then I make the poems known, &#8211; as I rise in the world the books will sell. &#8211; I have occasional thoughts of going on with
                    Kehama now when my leisure time approaches, to keep my hand in, &amp; to leave it for publication next winter.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note> Not a line has
                    been added to it since you left me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> goes on comfortably at Bristol, living with the two Maddox&#8217;s in Park
                        Street.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles and John Maddox (or Madox; dates unknown) of Park Row,
                        Bristol.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> as usual always in a hurry, &#8211; he has two little girls, who, unhappy children! have
                    been christened or rather heathenized, the one Zoe to please her mother,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emmeline King,
                        n&#233;e Edgeworth (1770&#8211;1817).</note> the other Psyche to please her grandfather!<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Lovell Edgeworth (1744&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I make regular enquiries after Joe, &amp; preserve your right &amp;
                    title to him by paying the tax: you have learnt by my former letters if any have reached you, poor Cupids disgraceful end, the
                    consequence of his evil courses.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cupid and Joe were dogs: Joe belonged to Thomas Southey;
                        Cupid had been Southey&#8217;s. Both were looked after by Danvers. In a previous letter, Southey reported that Cupid &#8216;has been hung
                        at last for robbing a hen-roost&#8217;; see Southey to Thomas Southey 1&#8211;5 January 1806, Letter 1140.</note> poor fellow &#8211; I do not
                    think of him, &amp; of his family grin, without sorrow. No news yet of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &#8211; we are seriously uneasy about him, it is above two months since he ought to have been home &#8211; our hope is
                    that finding the continent overun by the French he may have returned to Malta. &#8211; <note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Coleridge was in the process of returning from Malta via the continent and reached England in August 1806.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211; God bless you Tom </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>