<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1408</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2530</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                            Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information, 3:13 (January 1808).  Previously 
                        published: Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information, 3:13 (January 1808), pp.
                    1&#8211;2.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1408" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1408" type="letter">
        <head>1408. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the <title>Athen&#230;um</title>
          </ref>, <date when="1808-01">[January 1808]</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                            <title>Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, 3:13 (January 1808)<lb />Previously
                        published: <title>Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, 3:13 (January 1808), pp.
                    1&#8211;2.</p>
        <epigraph>
          <p rend="center">CRITICAL MISREPRESENTATION.</p>
          <p rend="center">
            <hi rend="ital">To the Editor of the Athen&#230;um.</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <opener>
          <salute>Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> YOU have with much propriety declared, that the complaints of offended authors against their critics cannot be
                    inserted in the Athen&#230;um; it is not the place for them. Every critical journal ought to be open to such replies, under obvious
                    restrictions; and if admittance were refused to a fair defence in one, it should be granted in another. Such a regulation would be
                    some check upon the licentiousness of reviewers; as it is now, their gross ignorance and their wilful misrepresentations pass
                    current, and do their work of malice, because there is no place in which they can be exposed. It will not be supposed that this
                    censure of reviewers is meant to be general and indiscriminating; but it cannot be denied, that every existing journal furnishes
                    some proofs of its truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Notwithstanding your prohibition, I presume that you will permit an error in literary history to be set right,
                    wherefrom-ever it may occur. It is said in a late number of the Critical Review, that Mr. Hole&#8217;s Arthur &#8216;failed of success,
                    because published <hi rend="ital">at the same time</hi> with the Joans of Arc, Alfreds, and C&#339;ur de Lions, which disgusted the
                    world within the very name Epic.&#8217;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> On p. 305 of an article on Rev. Richard Hole
                        (1746&#8211;1803), the <title>Critical Review</title>, 10 (March 1807), 302&#8211;311, Hole&#8217;s <title>Arthur, or the Northern
                            Enchantment</title> (1789) is compared favourably to Southey&#8217;s <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796), to <title>Alfred</title>
                        (1800) by <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, and to Sir James Bland Burges (1752&#8211;1824;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Richard I. A Poem in Eighteen Books</title> (1801).</note> Arthur, or the Northern
                    Enchantment, was published in 1790, Joan of Arc in 1796, the Alfreds and C&#339;ur de Lion in 1800. The failure of Mr. Hole&#8217;s poem,
                    therefore, is not attributed to the true cause; and it cannot b[e] necessary to point out why this false one has been
                    invented.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr. Holes Arthur failed of success because it did not deserve it. The poem had fair play; it appeared before
                    reviews were converted into tools of party, and before the butchers&#8217; phrase, &#8216;cutting up,&#8217; was supposed to be synonymous with
                    criticising. The journals gave it at least as much praise as it deserved, and it failed in spite of them, as the Epigoniad<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wilkie (1721&#8211;1772; <title>DNB</title>), published an Homeric epic on the sacking of
                        Thebes, <title>The Epigoniad, a Poem in Nine Books</title> (Edinburgh, 1757).</note> had done before it. The subject was not
                    ill chosen (for that we have the authority of Dryden<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Dryden (1631&#8211;1700;
                            <title>DNB</title>) approved of the subject of ancient Thebes as a subject for British poetry when praising Chaucer&#8217;s
                            <title>Knight&#8217;s Tale</title> in the dedicatory verses to his <title>Palamon and Arcite</title> (published in his
                            <title>Fables, Ancient and Modern</title> 1700).</note>) but it was ill handled, so ill handled, indeed, that all
                    advantage which it really possessed were made of no use. There is no name with which a chivalrous or a poetical mind associates
                    more delightful recollections than with the name of Arthur, but it is with the Arthur of the Round Table and of Spenser; for there
                    are enough indications in the Faery Queen, that if that wonderful poem had been completed, the hero would have been sufficiently
                    identified with the Arthur of Romance.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey would revert to this theme in his edition
                        of <title>Morte d&#8217;Arthur</title>: <title>The Byrth, Lyf and Acts of King Arthur</title> (1817).</note> Mr. Hole&#8217;s bears no
                    more resemblance to him than to Arthur O&#8217;Bradley;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The hero of the comic popular ballad
                        &#8216;Arthur O&#8217;Bradley&#8217;s Wedding&#8217;, extant by the early seventeenth century. The refrain is &#8216;O! rare Arthur O&#8217;Bradley! wonderful
                        Arthur O&#8217;Bradley!/ Sweet Arthur O&#8217;Bradley, O!&#8217;</note> and the reader, when he discovers this, feels as if he had met an old
                    friend with a new face.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The world has, perhaps, been &#8216;disgusted with the very name of epic.&#8217;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Quoting the <title>Critical Review</title>, 10 (March 1807), 302&#8211;311 (p. 305).</note> Mr. Hole&#8217;s could not have suffered from
                    that disgust, because it was published ten years before the swarm was occasioned by the success of Joan of Arc, notwithstanding
                    the great and numerous defects of that poem, defects which have been weeded out in each successive edition, but which never can
                    be totally removed.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent7"> S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>