<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1056</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2178</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4873 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 82&#8211;87.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1056" type="letter">
        <head>1056. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1805-04-09">9 April
                        [1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                        Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 26
                        Aug<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4873 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 82&#8211;87.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is that moral mannerism which you have detected.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is replying
                        to a letter of Taylor&#8217;s, dated 5 April, expressing admiration and offering detailed criticism of <title>Madoc</title> (1805).
                        Taylor noted the similarity of Southey&#8217;s poetic heroes and asked, &#8216;is there not a perpetual tendency to copy a favourite ideal
                        perfection&#8217;? For Taylor&#8217;s letter, see J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William
                            Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 79&#8211;81.</note> Thalaba is a male Joan of Arc, &amp; little <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Barbauld</ref> thought Joan of Arc was modelled upon the Socinian Christ.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s second edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796) was reviewed by Anna Laetitia
                        Barbauld&#8217;s brother, <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref>, in the <title>Analytical Review</title>, 23
                        (February 1796), 170&#8211;177. Aikin attributed to Joan the moral qualities that Unitarians (or &#8216;Socinians&#8217;) who disbelieved
                        Christ&#8217;s divinity, attributed to Jesus the man.</note> he was mistaken. Early admiration &#8211; almost adoration of Leonidas<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Leonidas (c. 540&#8211;480 BC): the Spartan king who, with three hundred of his warriors, made a
                        heroic stand against the Persian army at the Battle of Thermopylae, fighting on until all were killed. He was the subject of a
                        verse epic by Richard Glover (1712&#8211;1785; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Leonidas, A Poem</title> (1737), which Southey
                        admired.</note> &#8211; early principles of Stoicism derived from the habitual study of Epictetus,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Epictetus (55&#8211;135): a Greek Stoic philosopher. Epictetus taught in Rome and Greece, living a simple life and
                        arguing that fate decides events, which must be accepted calmly and dispassionately.</note> &amp; the French revolution at its
                    height when I was just eighteen, &#8211; by these <del>xxxx</del> my mind was moulded. But are not the characters in Madoc those which
                    the circumstances would form? my Aztecs have not a jot more heroism than the two Mexicans who grappled with Cortes on the terrace
                    of the palace, to precipitate themselves with him,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hern&#225;n Cort&#233;s de Monroy y Pizarro
                        (1485&#8211;1547) was seized during fighting on the upper platform of the Teocalli, or mound-temple, by two Aztec warriors who
                        attempted to throw him, and themselves, to their deaths. The story is told in several of the books Southey owned, which he
                        used in researching <title>Madoc</title>: Antonio de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625), <title>Historia General de los Hechos
                            de los Castellanos en las Islas y Tierra Firme del Mar Oceano</title> (Amberes, 1728), vol. II, book 10, chapter 9; Juan
                        de Torquemada (c. 1557&#8211;1664), <title>Monarquia Indiana, con el Origen y Guerras de los Indios Occidentales, de suas
                            Problaciones Descubrimiento, Conquista, Conversion</title> (Madrid, 1723), book 4, chapter 69; Antonio de Solis y
                        Ribadeneyra (1610&#8211;1686), <title>Historia de la Conquista de Mexico</title> (Madrid, 1798), book 4, chapter 16.</note> &#8211; nor
                    than some score of other American Indian heroes whom you may recollect in Spanish history. disinterestedness, ardent affection,
                    contempt of life, &amp; love of glory are the virtues peculiar to &#8211; or predominant in men above barbarism &amp; not yet arrivd at
                    civilization when they happen to be made of good materials. I could <del>xxxx</del> find out historical likenesses enough to
                    justify Coanocotzan &amp; his successor. Tlalala has more of the savage in him, &#8211; Ocelopan yet more &#8211; Amalahta is all savage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A list of characters from <title>Madoc</title>.</note> the differences are of disposition.
                    Neolin is the common mixture of rogue &amp; madman to be found in all from Zerdasht<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Zoroaster/Zarathushtra, the Iranian prophet, revered by Parsis, who lived in the tenth or eleventh century BC, according to
                        most scholars. Southey had long intended to write an epic poem on his life, events from which were revealed to the West by
                        Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil Du Perron (1731&#8211;1805), the French Orientalist, who caused the sacred texts of the Parsis, the
                        Avesta, to be translated into Persian by Brahmins when he resided in India. He then translated them into French, as the
                            <title>Zend-Avesta</title> in 1771, thus introducing Zoroastrianism to Europe for the first time. Southey owned a copy of
                        this book but did not carry out his plan, for which see letter 925 of this edition.</note> to Richard Brothers,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Brothers (1757&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), the self-proclaimed prophet of millennial
                        destruction, who attracted a large following in 1795 before being confined to an asylum by government order.</note> with the
                    courage &amp; presence of mind of Mohammed. Tezozomac an Indian S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Domingo.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saint Dominic (Domingo F&#233;lix de Guzm&#225;n) (1170&#8211;1221), the founder of the Dominican friars, a man who made zeal,
                        self-denial and militant proselytism central to his life and to the order he founded.</note> the rest are all common
                    characters except Erillyab.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;queen&#8217; of the Hoaman tribe in
                        <title>Madoc</title>.</note> her character I had at first conceived very differently &#8211; meaning to make her of a<del>n</del>
                    yielding nature, &#8211; governed by her son against her own better judgement, &amp; after his death resigning the power in confession
                    of her own weakness. What she now is grew up as I wrote. Once my design was to kill Amalahta by her hand &#8211; &amp; this also was
                    altered when I came to the execution &#8211; whether for the better or not I am still doubtful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In classing Madoc in Wales with the historical plays of Shakespere you bestow the highest praise, &amp; what I feel
                    to be the most appropriate. It has the historical verisimilitude, &amp; the dramatic truth. the other part &#8211; which is sui
                        generis,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;unique&#8217;.</note> you over- &amp; under-rate. It is below Milton
                    &amp; Homer &#8211; infinitely below both, for both are unapproachably above my strength of wing. it is below Tasso<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Torquato Tasso (1544&#8211;1595), author of the epic <title>La Gerusalemme Liberata</title>, translated
                        as <title>Jerusalem Delivered</title> (1580).</note> in splendour &amp; in structure of fable, above him in originality, &amp;
                    equal in feeling even to Spenser.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), author
                        of the epic <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596), and one of Southey&#8217;s favourite authors.</note> With the others I
                    will not admit comparison. Virgil<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), author of the
                        revered Latin epic, the <title>Aeneid</title> (19 BC).</note> &amp; Camoens<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lu&#237;s Vaz
                        de Cam&#245;es (1524&#8211;1580), author of the <title>Lusiads</title> (1572).</note> are <del>versifiers</del> &lt;language-masters&gt;
                        <del>both</del> of the first order &#8211; nothing more &#8211; &amp; the Messiah &#8211; pardon me if I say that of what you admire in that
                    poem at least 9 tenths appear<del>s</del> to me bubble &amp; bladder &amp; tympany, &#8211; just what I should produce for a
                    mock-heroic, &amp; could produce with facility. there is one uniform substitution of <hi rend="ital">bulk</hi> for <hi rend="ital">sublimity</hi>.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803) wrote the epic
                            <title>Messias</title> (1748&#8211;1773).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of Erillyabs<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 10.</note> abated veneration, you will see on reperusal is erroneous. The time
                    from his return to the death of her son being not many days. Once I thought &#8211; as you advise &#8211; of marrying them; but Erillyab is at
                    least eight &amp; thirty &#8211; too old to produce an heir, &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> first of all I designed Llaian for his wife &#8211; but at last
                    I felt it <del>xxxx xxxx</del> preserved his character <del>xxxx</del> &lt;better&gt; to let the line of Kings proceed from
                    Malinal &amp; Goervyl.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is explaining the reasons why his eponymous hero, Madoc,
                        does not marry in his poem.</note> &#8211; Caradoc &amp; Senena were suffered to remain for the sake of the Ladies<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The characters are lovers in <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; yet perhaps I should not have
                    relaxed my sentence of extermination had it not been for the incident of the harp &amp; Tlalala.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 2, Book 11, lines 54&#8211;79.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The language is I hope pure English undefiled &#8211; always straight forward to the point. the style certainly my own &#8211;
                    as much as is the Bees honey &#8211; for I read too little English poetry to catch the manner of any predecessor. it savours more of
                    chronicles &amp; romances Spanish as well as English.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I now think the second part wants similies in all its land battles &#8211; &amp; if I continue to think so will pour in
                    learning enough &#8211; &amp; bedeck it with diamonds from Golconda<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Golkonda, a city of
                        south-central India, now ruined, once the centre of the world diamond trade and legendary for its wealth (c.
                        1364&#8211;1512).</note> &amp; gold from Ophir<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> A city of gold mentioned in the Bible (1
                        Kings 10. 11&#8211;12), from which Solomon received gold, silver, sandalwood, precious stones, ivory, apes and peacocks every three
                        years. In <title>Paradise Lost</title> Milton identifies the city with Sofala in Mozambique (Book 11, 399&#8211;401).</note> &amp;
                    topazes from Brazil &amp; amber from Scandinavia, the furs &amp; feathers of the wild Indian &amp; the woven air of the voluptuous
                    Orientalist &#8211; You see I have recovered my state of desertion, &amp; think at least as well of my poem &amp; myself as any body
                    else is likely to do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> calls for a third edition of Joan of Arc.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published by Longmans in 1806. For the alterations, see
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), I.</note> I am
                    squeezing out the whey, &amp; shall <del>xxxx</del> cut out unsparingly. I have not much to add &#8211; tho much might be added had I
                    the history of that period by Godefroy<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Autre Histoire, d&#8217;un Autheur Inconnu, Contenant Partie du Regne du Mesme Charles VII Sc&#807;auoir Depuis l&#8217;an 1422. Iusques
                            en 1429. Dans Laquelle se Voyent Diuerses Circonstances Curieuses ... sur tout de la Pucelle d&#8217;Orleans, du Surnom de
                            Laquelle cette Histoire est Communement Appelle&#769;e</title>, ed. Denis Godefroy (1549&#8211;1622) in Jean Chartier (fl.
                        1558&#8211;1574), <title>Histoire de Charles VII. Roy de France</title> (1661).</note> &#8211; &amp; time to go thro Monstrellet,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Enguerrand de Monstrelet (c. 1390&#8211;1453), author of a chronicle of French history,
                            translated by Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) as <title>The Chronicles of Enguerrand De Monstrelet; Containing an Account of the
                            Cruel Civil Wars Between the Houses of Orleans and Burgundy; Of the Possession of Paris and Normandy by the English; Their
                            Expulsion Thence; And of Other Memorable Events That Happened in the Kingdom of France, as well as in Other
                            Countries</title> (1809&#8211;1810).</note> &amp; no worthier employment, &amp; none more urgent. To weed out as many of
                    its faults as I can is a work of duty as well as of gratitude for what it has done for me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You say you miss <del>mythology</del> &lt;machinery&gt; which surprises me. I hoped <del>my</del>  &lt;the&gt;
                    snake, <del>my</del>the ventriloquism, &amp; the priest craft at Patamba, &amp; the earthquake so timed as to appear a judicial
                    visitation of vengeance &#8211; would have had the effect of machinery without the absurdity, which is to me intolerable except in
                    Romance, there it is of the essence of the fable, &amp; you shall have your fill in Kehama.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; I repent the size of the book &amp; am not
                    pleased at the price<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was published in a two-guinea quarto.</note> &#8211; one half of the edition is thereby condemned to be furniture in noblemens
                    libraries &#8211; the other to collect dust on the publishers shelves. I ought to have relied enough upon myself to have known that it
                    no more needed a quarto page to <del>attract</del> get it notice &#8211; than I need a cocked hat to get into company. Next time I will
                    try a five shilling plan &amp; print for the people.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of
                            <title>Madoc</title> was produced more cheaply, in duodecimo, rather than quarto.</note> I think Pelayo the Restorer of
                        Spain<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> A thought that eventually led to Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Roderick, the Last of
                            the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; have thought of <del>Egbert</del> the Trojan Brutus,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brutus of Troy, the legendary founder and first king of Britain, described by the twelfth-century chronicler
                        Geoffrey of Monmouth (c. 1100&#8211;c. 1155) in his <title>Historia Regum Britanniae</title> (c. 1136).</note> of Egbert,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Egbert (d. 839, King of Wessex from 802 until 839; <title>DNB</title>), who, through
                        victory in battle, achieved control of the neighbouring kingdom of Mercia, and the submission of the Northumbrian people.
                        Egbert was described in the <title>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</title> (late 9th century onwards) as the &#8216;Ruler of Britain&#8217;.</note>
                        Athelstan<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> Athelstan (893/4&#8211;939, King of England c. 924 to 939; <title>DNB</title>),
                        whose success in battle against the Scots led to his claiming the title &#8216;King of all Britain&#8217;.</note> &amp; your Edmund
                        Ironsides<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund II (d. 1016; <title>DNB</title>): king of the southern part of
                        England from 23 April to 30 November 1016 and known as &#8216;Edmund Ironside&#8217; because of his defence of Wessex against the Viking
                        invasion from the north.</note> &#8211; now this moment for the first time think of the Barons &amp; King John.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> King John (1167&#8211;1216; <title>DNB</title>) faced a rebellion by his barons which led to the
                        signing of the Magna Carta in 1215.</note> Oh for an English subject! If we had beat the Spaniards in 1588 by land instead of
                    sea that had been the story.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would be well if I <hi rend="ital">could</hi> write tragedy &#8211; the true chrysopoetic<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors"> A play on the word &#8216;chrysopoeia&#8217; meaning transmutation into gold.</note> vein; &#8211; there are plans by me &#8211; &amp;
                    one opening scene &#8211; but I never had courage to proceed, &amp; the sense of fear &amp; the disgust at the thought of trimming it to
                    the taste of some Green room critic have deterred me. Besides if I know my own strength it is in narrative, &#8211; &amp; dramatic parts
                    introduced into narrative are widely different from the drama. &#8211; Yet if I had any well founded hope that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Kemble<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Philip Kemble (1757&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), actor-manager of Drury
                        Lane and Covent Garden theatres.</note> would be propitious or that Master Helisabad (the true name of the young Roscius as
                    somebody has very wittily discovered &#8211; corrupted into Betty!)<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Henry West Betty
                        (1791&#8211;1874), a child actor, was termed &#8216;young Roscius&#8217; after the Roman actor Quintus Roscius (c.126&#8211;62 BC). He caused a
                        sensation when he made his Drury Lane debut in 1804. &#8216;Helisabad&#8217; is a Latinate pun on &#8216;Elizabeth&#8217;, the full form of the
                        colloquial name &#8216;Betty&#8217;, as well as the name of the hero&#8217;s companion in <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, translated by Southey
                        in 1803.</note> &#8211; would be my magnus Apollo<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning Southey&#8217;s mentor or
                        luminary.</note> &amp; study a part &#8211; I would bring my stomach to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Iris is wanting for Lord Melvilles sake.<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey regrets the closure
                        of the newspaper that Taylor had edited, <title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title>, depriving him of
                        a source of news about the censure, resignation and impeachment of Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War 1794&#8211;1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. During 1802&#8211;1805,
                        Melville&#8217;s use of public funds while Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800), was investigated by a Royal Commission. After its
                        report, on 9 April 1805, Melville was censured in the House of Commons for allowing Alexander Trotter (dates unknown), the
                        naval paymaster, to misuse public funds. Melville resigned and impeachment proceedings were commenced against him.</note> &#8211;
                    poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is in the thick of the danger. he wrote to me on the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> &#8211; saying he had sent prizes in which would enable him to remit a bill for 1000 &#163;, little thinking
                    that the French were then among the Islands, &amp; in all probability will sweep away the foundation stones of his fortune! <note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804 HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas Southey was a
                        lieutenant, captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden
                        with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be
                        allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict, but Southey was concerned that the French
                        Mediterranean Fleet, which had sailed from Toulon to the West Indies in March 1805 under Vice-Admiral Pierre-Charles
                        Villeneuve (1763&#8211;1806), would gain possession of these vessels.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS. <date when="1805-04-09">April 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            </date>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>