<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.979</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2101</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="979" type="letter">
        <head>979. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1804-10-22">[early&#8211;c. 22 October 1804]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J C
                        Mottley/ Portsmouth/ <hi rend="ital">for S. T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi>
            <lb />Postmark: E/ OCT22/ 1804<lb />MS:
                        University of Kentucky Library<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: The postmark is 22 October 1804, but there is an internal
                        reference to the letter being started two weeks before this, and the date cited in it of &#8216;Oct 19&#8217;.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Coleridge</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Three letters from you since your arrival at Malta have reached England &#8211; One to <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara </ref> &#8211; one to <ref target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Sarah Hutchinson</ref> &amp;
                    one to me &#8211; for one it must be called to make the arithmetic of the sentence right &amp; avoid small fractions. Ere this you also
                    must have heard from us &#8211; or should have heard &#8211; but letters <hi rend="ital">out</hi> are never so safe as letters <hi rend="ital">home</hi>. All well. the books about which you have been dreaming are safely piled in the wing room of the old house, for
                    your study has just undergone its transmogrification. The box which so disappointed you by its not containing letters was sent off
                    while you were yet in England, &amp; receiving news faster than it could travel by waggon, &amp; this I suppose you soon
                    recollected after your disappointment. Having thus dispatched the business of this epistle a clear sheet lies before me. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref> goes to school &amp; hath received from me his volunteer Godfather the
                    new name of Job, because he <hi rend="ital">is to be</hi> so patient<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The biblical
                        character, Job, who remained steadfast to God despite the extreme tests sent to try his patience.</note> &#8211; a name which Job
                    doth not take patiently. I leave to <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his mother</ref> the task of Boswellizing<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Boswell (1778&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) was the friend and biographer of Samuel Johnson
                        (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>).</note> him to you, which if she does not do she is to blame. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> a few days ago amused himself by swallowing seventeen shillings &amp;
                    sixpence &#8211; in the shape of a half guinea, &amp; a seven shilling piece. <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara</ref> came up
                    to me in terrible alarm, which was somewhat relieved by my immediately remarking that there would be work for a gold-finder. &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> proposed to her to farm him out &#8211;, offering either sixpence a <hi rend="ital">chance</hi>, or half a crown a day till the money was recovered. &amp; to be at the expence of recovering it. Both
                    pieces having been scalded &amp; scrubbed are carefully wrapt up in paper &amp; preserved in <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Saras</ref> pocket as relics. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sariola</ref> runs about &amp; improves in speech &#8211; I call her Queen Alfred from her exceeding likeness to Alfred
                        Estlin.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alfred Estlin (dates unknown): solicitor of Burnham, Somerset, the second son
                        of John Prior Estlin (1747&#8211;1817), the Unitarian minister who was Southey&#8217;s and Coleridge&#8217;s friend in Bristol.</note> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> is a great tyrant, a very Bonaparte, suffering nobody to be at peace till
                    she has had her way &#8211; but baiting the sleeplessness or rather restlessness at night as quiet &amp; as good tempered as heart could
                    wish. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> herself is growing fat, &amp; has a better proportion of flesh to bone
                    than at any period since I have known her &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara</ref> as you left her, in excellent good
                    health. &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref> just in the same diseased state of body &amp; mind as usual. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now then for the outside of the house &#8211; the scaffolding is not yet taken down, but the wall is compleated, your
                    room has now only one window in front, &amp; that ugly chasm which threatened disruption horrible in some high wind, is filled up
                    &#8211; like the sutures in a skull. This has been done too late for plaistering, so the outside &amp; the in will remain ragged till
                    next summer. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> continues here about a month longer, &amp; <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> is now with us. We have found pleasant neighbours in the Islanders &#8211; <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the Colonel</ref> being very good natured &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">his
                        wife</ref> &amp; her sister truely womanly women.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Charter (first name and dates
                        unknown), whose visit to stay with the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Peachys</ref> is referred to in Southey to
                        Thomas Southey, 12 September 1804, Letter 978.</note> A ball has been mustered at Woods<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Queen&#8217;s Head, Keswick, owned by George Wood (d. 1812).</note> chiefly by Harrys generalship. There are also more
                    strollers here &amp; there has been a riot at the theatre. the General<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Peche, who had
                        served in the East India Company&#8217;s army, gazetted as Colonel in 1796 and Major-General in 1798.</note> &amp; Colonel &amp;
                    their party having been driven out by the townspeople, who would not suffer places to be kept for them. luckily we were too late
                    to be involved in the fray, for tho we should perhaps have turned the scale, it was better to have been out of it. A good deal was
                    certainly owing to White the bellygerent,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr White (dates unknown), a local man who
                        negotiated to buy <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> from the builder and owner of the house, <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">William Jackson</ref>. &#8216;Belly gerent&#8217; because he was both aggressive and fat.</note> who endeavours all he can to make the people insult M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Pech&#233;,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The wife of General Peche; her first name and dates are
                        unknown.</note> &amp; certainly if what I have heard of him had come from any other quarter than <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref>, I should have felt myself bound to inform the General that he might
                    prosecute him &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Eight &amp; twenty sheets of Madoc are printed. twelve more are in the printers hands &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> of Edinburgh &#8211; &amp; I just now stuck in the mud in the last insertion
                    of new story, being the sixteenth section of the second part.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was correcting proofs
                        of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) even while still revising the sections of the manuscript not yet sent to the printer. It was
                        completed in October 1804.</note> however the compleat leisure of a week will carry me on a long way, &amp; if no untoward
                    accident intervene the whole <del>of my l</del> will be done before this can reach Malta. You will instruct me accordingly as you
                    regulate your movements, whether to send out a copy or not &#8211; perhaps my plans may in some degree influence you. I certainly
                    intend, if not prevented by any public or private events, to remove to Lisbon about this time twelvemonths, with the intention of
                    remaining there two or three years &#8211; the longer the better. If you do not return home in the summer this will induce you to touch
                    at Lisbon. Of myself there is nothing more to communicate save that I have resolved upon adding a History of the Monastic Orders
                    or Monachism to my other historical labours <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s plans for such a history were not
                        realised.</note> &#8211; &amp; that I succeed in keeping diabetes under by vigorous exercise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Orator Bellew<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Kelly Bellew (d. 1804), of Bath, died at
                        Clifton, Bristol.</note> is dead, he has left behind him his travels nearly fit for the press, &amp; a huge heap of common
                    place books which had they gone to his heir<del>s</del> Theophilus Swift<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Theophilus Swift
                        (1746&#8211;1815), barrister and author whose poetical works include <title>The Gamblers</title> (1777), <title>The Temple of
                            Folly</title> (1787), and <title>The Female Parliament</title> (1789).</note> instead of his executor <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, would have been published to the great annoyance of all his
                    acquaintance &#8211; for it was the Orators custom to record all his conversations with the literati <del>of his acquaintance</del>,
                    &amp; to comment upon their characters. The poor orator had a very flatulent sort of an intellect, yet his collection may one day
                    be curious. he will have recorded a curious anecdote of me, how I sent him to search &lt;in the Vatican&gt; for the writings of
                    Porphyry against the Xtian religion<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Porphyry (234?&#8211;305?) a Neoplatonist philosopher born
                        in Tyre in Phoenicia, whose many writings included commentaries on Plato, Aristotle, Plotinus (204/5&#8211;270) and Ptolemy (90&#8211;168)
                        as well as <title>Against the Christians</title>. The Vatican was unlikely to yield <title>Against the Christians</title> to
                        anyone, since the book was burnt by order of the Christian Roman emperor Constantine (272&#8211;337).</note> &#8211; &amp; he will not
                    have discovered that in making Taylor the Pagan<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Taylor (1758&#8211;1835): &#8216;the Pagan/the
                        Platonist&#8217;&#8211; translator and editor of many neoplatonic philosophers including Porphyry, Plotinus and Proclus (412&#8211;485).</note>
                    set him upon this quest I was only amusing myself with both.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Since this letter was begun &#8211; which has lain some fortnight in my desk, a transaction which you as well as I have
                    long foreseen &amp; foretold &#8211; has taken place. <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> has sold the house to the
                        Belly-gerent<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 7.</note> for &#163;2400, &amp; we shall all be unkennelled at
                    Whitsuntide. Poor Jackson had not the heart to tell me this himself, &amp; the thought of it broke his rest for many nights. he
                    offers to build us another house in poor Banks&#8217;s field,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> to look out some
                    place for us till it be done &#8211; to lend us furniture &#8211; money &#8211; anything for our accommodation. Tho I meant to take flight in the
                    autumn it is not very convenient to have my nest taken in the spring, &amp; I am certainly confoundedly puzzled &amp; perplexed:
                    for these rumours of war, &amp; that accursed fever which it seems is got to Gibralter<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Yellow fever killed an estimated 60% of Gibraltar&#8217;s population in 1804.</note> &amp; which I fear will sooner or later extend
                    over the whole of the Spanish peninsula, if not over the whole of Europe, make me think of Lisbon with a sort of prudent fear, nor
                    in fact should I be prepared with ways &amp; means for removing in May instead of October, were there no other obstacle. For you
                    the inconvenience is less &#8211; or perhaps it ought to be regarded as a fortunate circumstance that you should be thus compelled to
                    leave a situation manifestly injurious to your health, &amp; yet so suited to your inclination that you would probably never have
                    mustered up courage to leave it. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> will travel southward paying
                    visits, with little inconvenience, &amp; little if any increased expence &#8211; till we can get a house. We must go somewhere into
                    lodgings, &amp; I shall make a desperate effort to raise a couple of hundreds for furniture &#8211; for it is time that I &amp; my books
                    were gathered together. perhaps before our settling take place you may be in England, but do not you in the slightest degree
                    hasten your return on that account. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> too is unsettled &#8211; <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">his house</ref> is too small for a growing family, &amp; for one who wants a room to retire
                    to out of the reach of domestic noise. I suppose we shall all ultimately draw near London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Montague</ref> is at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>,
                    unless he should yesterday have left it. he brought <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref> down with him [MS torn]
                    Dyer came here for three days, &amp; then set off to join Montague fearing he should else be left behind, but Montague came over
                    himself the next day &amp; remained three days also leaving George at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. I
                    thought it might be possibly of some use to poor <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">White</ref> (the Nottingham poet) who
                    is gone as a sizar to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Johns to get Montague to notice him &amp; befriend him, &amp; this he has promised to
                    do. I should have told you that I wrote to the poor boy &amp; received from him a very interesting letter.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> White had written to Southey on 9 July 1804 seeking advice about publishing his verse. His letter
                        is reprinted in <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White of Nottingham, ed. Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London, 1808), I,
                        pp. 125&#8211;128.</note> the Methodists have caught him, &amp; allow him 30&#163; per year from their fund which is in Thorntons<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Thornton (1720&#8211;1790): a rich merchant and Anglican who supported evangelical causes,
                        sponsoring John Newton (1725&#8211;1807) as well as Kirke White.</note> hands for the purpose of educating Evangelical minors in the
                    establishd church. So long as his own opinions accord with those of his unknown benefactors as he calls them, it is well that
                    their money should be so employed. meantime I will from time to time learn how he goes, &amp; be ready to give him a lift when he
                    has outgrown them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My rascally brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> having been once more sent to sea has
                    either again left his ship, or been turned out of it, &amp; is sharping about the country once more. I had a bill sent here from
                    Plymouth, from a brothel I suspect by the penwomanship &amp; female orthography. he must now be left to his fate, which if it be
                    short of the gallows <del>xxx xxxxx xxxx</del> will be better than he deserves. this is an evil, but not of the first magnitude &#8211;
                    a scratch in the extremities. I shall not suffer it to disturb me. &#8211; Wet &#8211; cold &#8211; &amp; wintry already (Oct 19) &amp; for this
                    week past, while you are enjoying the fruits &amp; the sunshine of a Mediterranean climate. In spite of the Lakes &amp; Mountains
                    this is not a place to winter in, &amp; if you were here now you would reconcile yourself to relinquishing this spot, lovely as it
                    is to the Great Bellygerent.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 7.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am just beginning my campaign against the books of the year.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                        means his reviewing work for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> Could you see the ponderous pile before <del>you</del>
                    you would groan in compassion. &amp; the proportion of good to bad is even less than in former years. One work however of sterling
                    merit there is &#8211; Barrows Travels in China,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short
                            Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804).
                        Southey reviewed the book in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 69&#8211;83.</note> a most excellent &amp;
                    important volume. he tells us that the best Commentaries on the Chinese Laws, in the manner of Blackstone<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Blackstone (1723&#8211;1780), author of the <title>Commentaries on the Laws of England</title>
                        (1765&#8211;1769).</note> were soon to be published in a translation &#8211; by Sir G. Stanton<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sir George Thomas Staunton, 2nd Baronet (1781&#8211;1859), translated the <title>Fundamental Laws of China</title> (1810).</note> of
                    course, a young man of whom great things are evidently to be hoped. &#8211; Of the annual poetry all is bad; <del>x</del> one volume
                    entitled the Shepherds Boy by William Day,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Day (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Shepherd&#8217;s Boy: being Pastoral Tales</title> (1804). Southey reviewed the book in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1804</title>, 3 (1805), 567&#8211;568.</note> beats the Shepherds Farewell<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Roderick (bap. 1710&#8211;1756), &#8216;The Shepherd&#8217;s Farewell to his Love&#8217;, a popular eighteenth-century song. See <title>A Collection
                            of Poems in Three Volumes. By Several Hands</title> (London, 1748), II, pp. 311&#8211;314.</note> hollow. Miss Sewards Life of
                        Darwin<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ...
                            with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804) in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>,
                        3 (1805), 488&#8211;493.</note> is one of the most womanising productions of the year. tho in such English! &#8211; &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our summer visitors are all past away. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is going &amp; I
                    shall soon be left quietly to my winter operations. Yet a little while &amp; Madoc will be done. only 2 &#189; of the old books remain
                    to be corrected. On the whole I have not satisfied myself in the poem. the experiment has quite <del>satisfied</del>
                    &lt;convinced&gt; me of the impolicy of being very long about anything. As soon as it is done I must set hard to money making &#8211;
                    for this poem will have slow return if any, some praise it may possibly procure &#8211; but no solid pudding. it does not please me much
                    &#8211; &amp; will assuredly profit me but little. &#8211; All well here &amp; at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>. I had
                    just bought a Jack Ass before this catastrophe of the house &#8211; had christened John, &amp; meant to have created him a Knight of the
                    most ancient order of the thistle. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you Coleridge! do not come home before you have got well &#8211; but get well as fast as you can &#8211; &amp; above
                    all be attentive to your diet &#8211; i.e. be regular in it.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>