<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1024</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2146</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 68.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 375&#8211;377.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1024" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1024" type="letter">
        <head>1024. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1805-01-23">23 January
                        [1805]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ Jan. 23:/ 1805<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 68<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 375&#8211;377.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-01-23">Wednesday Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 23. </date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter, for the main part, was answered before it was received, so that for that matter I have only to thank
                    you for what you have done in it. It never was my opinion that the expedition would take place, till the papers <del>xx</del>
                    positively affirmed it. I cannot think any military man would advise it, knowing the state of the Portugueze army, &#8211; still less
                    that we should be so mad as to send troops to a city, so near the seat of pestilence, &amp; so perilously exposed to it. Being a
                    spare bodied man myself, more in danger of diseases of debility than of inflammation, I have &#8211; at this distance &#8211; no fear of the
                    fever, &amp; think that my constitution &amp; plentiful fumigations would secure me if it came in my way. At least it is not that
                    fear &#8211; which should keep me from going to Lisbon to do my work thoroughly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Metrical Tales you will before this time have received<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        contributions to the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) were republished under his own name in <title>Metrical Tales
                            and other Poems</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; if my directions have been executed by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. a mere republication whereof in some former letter I advised you,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly Southey to John Rickman, 6 August 1804, Letter 975.</note> &#8211; issued at no expence of time, &amp; no risk of loss &#8211; in
                    the <del>xxxxx</del> hope of some little profit. &#8211; little enough it will be, as only 500 are printed &amp; Artaxerxes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s nickname for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, after the Persian
                        emperor Artaxerxes I (also named Longimanus) who reigned 465&#8211;424 BC.</note> &amp; I are to share equally. I thought I had
                    explained to <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> about the Cottonian extracts in a letter written some time ago.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See letter 995 of this edition. Charles Cotton (1630&#8211;1687; <title>DNB</title>) was a poet
                        and translator of Montaigne. Charles Lamb quoted from his poem &#8216;The New Year&#8217; in his 1821 Elia essay, &#8216;New Year&#8217;s Eve&#8217;. Poems
                        by Cotton appear in Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly authored <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols
                        (London, 1807), I, pp. 35&#8211;47.</note> the plan of the Specimens is to arrange them chronologically from every poet &#8211; i.e.
                    versifier &#8211; who had died between the years 1685 &#8211; &amp; 1800, &#8211; in fact a sequel to <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George
                        Ellis&#8217;s</ref> book,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title>
                        (1790, 2nd edn 1801, 3rd edn 1803).</note> done by R.S. for the lucre of gain. having brief notices of the <del>xxxx</del>
                    writers prefixed. had the series extended farther back I should have begged more assistance from Lamb. as it was I applied about
                    Cotton, knowing that he had made extracts from him, &#8211; not having read the book myself tho I possess it &#8211; &amp; &#8211; under the nose &#8211;
                    not being very desirous to <del>xxxx</del> trust my lazy deputy where any taste was required.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> conduct has been so far approved by Sir Samuel Hood<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>).</note> that he
                    has made him First Lieutenant of the Amelia &#8211; a larger &amp; finer frigate than that wherefrom he was dismissed,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly
                        the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission
                        65 were killed or wounded. Thomas had been placed under arrest (and was subsequently court-martialled), and Lieutenant Charles
                        Hayman (d. 1804), his replacement on the raid, died. After the court martial, Thomas was made lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a finer ship than the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, because she was a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class frigate
                        of the French navy captured in 1796 and then commissioned into the navy.</note> &#8211; &amp; his new
                        Captain<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Charles Fahie (1763&#8211;1833).</note> says that the Commodore speaks so
                    highly of him that he expects to see him a Commander ere long. I knew Tom had acted well, but was not quite so sure that he had
                    acted prudently.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> be driven from Portugal, &amp; my design of going
                    over in consequence frustrated &#8211; I should put the first volume to press in the course of next winter.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> Of materials arranged &#8211; &amp; unarranged
                    for the several divisions, I have <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;more than&gt; as much as would make seven such volumes as the
                        Sharonical<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to Sharon Turner&#8217;s, <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title>
                        (1799&#8211;1805).</note> &#8211; a great capital of labour lying dead. With the needful works of reference at hand, nothing more is
                    required than to transcribe them for the printer &#8211; for I have all the arrangement methodized in my own mind, &amp; could fit in
                    the new matter to its place as I wrote on. I am confident that the work is what it ought to be. <del>that every thing</del> having
                    followed this for my rule &#8211; to relate every thing &#8211; <del>to be as</del> &amp; to write first as intelli &#8211; nay &#8211; you shall have it
                    in a Triad &#8211; the three excellencies of historical composition &#8211; language as intelligible as possible &#8211; as concise as possible,
                    &amp; as rememberable as possible.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Welsh sayings collected in groups of three lines, the
                        earliest of which predate Saxon times. Preserved in different versions, partly in the fourteenth century White Book of
                        Rhydderch and Red Book of Hergest, the triads were associated with bardic recitation. They include stories of King Arthur and
                        of Llywarch Hen (whom Southey would discuss in his 1829 text <title>Sir Thomas More: or Colloquies on the Progress and
                            Prospects of Society</title>). Southey cited the triads in the preface to <title>Madoc</title> (1805) from the translation
                        of Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg; 1747&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>) in his <title>Poems, Lyric and Pastoral</title>
                        (1794).</note> Nothing provokes me like a waste of words. Me judice<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;in my
                        own judgement&#8217;.</note> I am a good poet &#8211; but a better historian, &amp; the better for having been accustomed to feel &amp;
                    think as a poet. A new but happily a last cargo <del>xxxx</del> interrupted me just as I was setting to.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Of books for Southey to review for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> they are almost killed off, &amp;
                    meantime I had collected matter for a chapter on the Hindoos, &amp; begun the Fuero Viejo, the Code of Castilian laws which
                    succeeded to the Gothic code.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3387 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was D.
                        Ignatius Jordan de Asso y del Rio (1742&#8211;1804), and D. Miguel de Manuel y Rodriguez (fl. 1780), <title>El Fuero Viejo de
                            Castilla, con Notas Historicas, y Legales</title> (1771).</note> I shall do a world of work this summer &#8211; if nothing
                    happens to prevent me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George I</ref> that I shall write to him as soon as I am at leisure &#8211;
                    to acknowledge the receipt of 3/6 &amp; certain books &#8211; for which I thank him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have been very kind to <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">G. Fricker</ref>. his migration to London has
                    thus far been very fortunate. but I do not approve the way in which it was brought about &#8211; more than you do. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is very zealous to serve others &#8211; &amp; is capable of making
                        <del>xxx</del> sacrifices &amp; acting very generously on such occasions. but in this case as he had no time to act &#8211; he
                    should have done nothing unless he could have done more.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> For details of Coleridge&#8217;s
                        attempts, before he left Britain for Malta in 1804, to help George Fricker find employment in London, see <title>The Collected
                            Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, ed. Earl Leslie Griggs, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956&#8211;1971), II, 1064 (Coleridge to
                        Rickman, 15 February 1804), and 1067 (Coleridge to Southey, 17 February 1804).</note> Had I thought it expedient to bring <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref> to London on a temporary situation &#8211; for the chance of his getting a permanent
                    one &#8211; I should have gone to work the straight way, &amp; applied to you. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> should not have done it, because I had not, &amp; he must have known that had it seemed proper to me I
                    should. His name &amp; mine are usually coupled by strangers, not by those who know us. we have very few common friends &#8211; indeed
                    scarcely any. the friends of one are nothing more than acquaintance of the other &#8211; when so much. The total difference of our
                    habits &amp; manners is the cause, &#8211; the way he has of trying to please strangers, &amp; the mortal dislike I have of that way.
                    Every body sees wherein we differ, because it is in those points which touch every body. the things wherein we agree belong
                        <del>xxx</del> to a confidential fire side. &#8211; We are uneasy at his long silence, no letter of a later date than June. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>