<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1646</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2768</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1646" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1646" type="letter">
        <head>1646. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-06-27">27 June
                    1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/ Hereford <lb />MS:
                        Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-06-27">June 27. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There was a report raised &amp; propagated with some industry that the yellow fever came from Bulama,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> An island near Sierra Leone, on the West African coast.</note> &#8211; but it was invented for
                    party purposes &amp; the yellow fever is an old disease, &#8211; so old as to be mentioned by Capgrave in the Life of an old British
                        Saint,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Capgrave (1393&#8211;1464; <title>DNB</title>), theologian, and historian who
                        wrote several accounts of saints&#8217; lives.</note> &#8211; indeed I suppose it differs in little or nothing from the Black Vomit, &#8211;
                    that symptom being often its last effect. An account of that expedition to Bulama when the fever is said to have been brought
                    back, has been published by Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Beaver,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip Beaver (1766&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, who in 1791 participated in a scheme for colonizing Bulama. The scheme failed and he
                        returned in 1794, publishing his experiences in <title>African Memoranda</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; a man with all the abilities
                    of Robinson Crusoe. It is one of the most interesting books I have ever seen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That Capt Southey of the Pilot I take to be a lad by name William S. who wrote to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> about three years ago claiming kin, &amp; whose father keeps a tavern in Upper
                    Brooke Street.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fashionable street near Hyde Park, London and so a likely watering
                        hole of military officers.</note> His preferment is therefore easily accounted for, &#8211; as a Commission may serve for a receipt
                    in full to a long bill. I hear from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> frequently, generally once in ten days. He is
                    off Rochefort.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a letter from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> to this purport &#8211; that <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> had a great desire to serve me; &#8211; that he talked about it to him &amp; to <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis</ref>, &amp; would have offered me a situation of 300&#163; a year in his own
                    department, but that the salary was judged insufficient for the attendance required. This thought therefore was laid aside &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> was commissioned to devise with me any plan that would suit my own
                    inclinations. He proposes a professorship, &#8211; which of course must be in Scotland, &#8211; those in our own Universities being fenced
                    about with tests, which I could not overleap even tho the atmosphere of Oxford or Cambridge were less uncongenial. I have however
                    asked <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> if the place of Historiographer cannot be created for me, with a salary of
                    400&#163;. this I should prefer to any thing else.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unbeknownst to Southey, this postion was
                        already filled by Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>). On his death, it was given to James Stanier Clarke
                        (1765?&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). For Southey&#8217;s letter to Scott, see Southey to Walter Scott, 16 June 1809, Letter
                        1645.</note> For tho <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> speaks of diplomatic situations, &amp; it is not
                    unlikely that I might go as Secretary to Portugal, your removal from that country, takes away one main inducement, &amp; having
                    got my books together, &amp; a family growing up, it must be some great &amp; certain advantage now <del>which</del> to induce me
                    again to unsettle myself. What the Professorships at Glasgow &amp; Edinburgh are worth I know not, neither am I solicitous about
                    them, &#8211; if one falls &amp; is offered me it will be time enough to think about it then. They would serve me more effectually by
                    making me Chronista Mor<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A royal chronicler.</note> &amp; letting me stay where I
                    am.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will be far better to put forth the list of books in John Bells hands, than in Sealys.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was hoping that books he required from Lisbon could be supplied either by Sir John Bell
                        (1782&#8211;1876; <title>DNB</title>), an army officer who served in Portugal throughout the Peninsular War, or Richard Sealy (dates
                        unknown) a wealthy Lisbon merchant, the father-in-law of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert
                            Southey</ref>.</note> The Provas to Seabra&#8217;s work we should have, &#8211; Vieyras sentence is among them of which you have sent
                    me a MSS.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Seabra da Silva&#8217;s (1732&#8211;1803) <title>Deduc&#231;ao Chronologica e
                            Analytica</title> (1767). Southey later obtained a copy, no. 2599 in the sale catalogue of his library. He was
                        particularly interested in the &#8216;Provas&#8217;, or references. Seabra&#8217;s work included attacks on the Jesuit missionary, diplomat and
                        writer Antonio Vieira (1608&#8211;1697) who was exiled and then sentenced to imprisonment for heresy in 1665.</note> another of
                    those MSS. is printed among his letters.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Vieira, <title>Cartas</title>
                        (1735&#8211;1746).</note> Lord Valentia frequently refers to Joam de Castro&#8217;s work,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        George Annesley, Viscount Valentia (1770&#8211;1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and
                            Egypt in the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809). Valentia refers to the voyage of the Portuguese naval
                        officer and fourth Viceroy of Portuguese India, Jo&#227;o de Castro (1500&#8211;1548) on pp. 288, 342 and 343. Southey owned a copy of
                        Castro&#8217;s <title>Mappa de Portugal</title> (1672), no. 3250 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> which I believe I
                    formerly mentioned to you, &amp; which I suppose has been published in French. I have Lord Vs travels to review for the
                        Quarterly,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Valentia&#8217;s <title>Voyages and Travels to India,
                            Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title>, in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 88&#8211;126.</note> &#8211; they give the death blow to Bruce,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Bruce&#8217;s (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>), <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the
                            Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title>. Southey reviewed the second edition of 1804&#8211;1805, in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1805</title>, 4 (1806), 2&#8211;16.</note> who will hence forward be added to the catalogue of Scotch impostors, &#8211; a catalogue
                    which I verily believe no other country can equal. In Abyssinia he certainly was, but by the concurrent testimony of all who
                    remember him there, held none of the offices or honours which he bestows upon himself, neither was he present in any of the
                    battles in which he boasts to have borne a part. Worse than this one of his voyages in the Red Sea is pure fiction, &amp; his
                    latitudes &amp; longitudes mere guess work. Salt is gone back to Abyssinia as Embassador to carry a present.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Salt (1780&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), secretary and draughtsman to Viscount Valentia,
                        whose <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt</title> he had illustrated and partly
                        written, was sent by the government in March 1809 on a diplomatic mission to the Abyssinian court.</note> Ld V. thinks a
                    gainful trade might be opened with that country &#8211; in which the East India Company do not agree with him. It is not a little
                    curious to see something like the politics of Alboquerques age<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alfonso de Albuquerque
                        (1453&#8211;1515) established the Portuguese empire in the Indian Ocean by taking territory and building fortresses that dominated
                        all the sea lanes to the Atlantic, Red Sea, Persian Gulf, and to the Pacific.</note> coming round again, disputes about Ormuz,
                    &#8211; the French fortifying Isle Camaran, &amp; allying themselves with the Moors of the Red Sea, &#8211; &amp; an Embassy from the King of
                    England to the Neguz upon the ground of their conformity in religion.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Salt&#8217;s envoy to
                        the Abyssinian Christians echoed the diplomatic voyages of 1512 and 1513 between Ethiopia and Portuguese Goa; these resulted
                        in the Ethiopian diplomat Mateus (d. 1520) travelling to Portugal and returning home accompanied by Portuguese
                    envoys.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our communication thro <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">the Speaker</ref>  is <del>xxx x</del>
                    at an end during the recess.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>,
                        who worked as Abbot&#8217;s secretary, was unable to frank mail for Southey when Parliament was not in session.</note> I can however
                    still send large packets, &#8211; tho not receive them. <del>xxxx x</del> Make up this chapter into a parcel &amp; let it go by the
                    stage, directed to <del>x xxxxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pople</ref> &lt;Printer&#8217;s Office.&gt; Old Boswell Court, Strand,
                    London. Have you received the printed sheets? &#8211; There is a work in Dulaus Catalogue<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> A.
                        B. Dulau and Co., 37 Soho Square. &#8216;Dulaus, in Soho Square where there is by far the best collection of foreign books <del>in
                            fxxxx xxx in</del> &lt;that is to be found in&gt; London. One of the partners is an emigrant who was at Lisbon, &amp; used
                        to be a good deal at the Gonnes&#8217;; see Southey to the Herbert Hill, 11 November 1809, Letter 1707.</note> with this title
                    Voyage dans l&#8217;Amerique Meridonale, par D Felix Azara. Commandant dans le Paraguai depuis 1781, jusqu&#8217;au 1801. 4 Vol octvo with an
                    Atlas &#8211; I should at once have sent for this&#8230;&#8211;but the unaccountable price of four guineas has deterred me, so I shall apply to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> to borrow it for me.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        eventually owned a copy of Felix Manuel de Azara (1742&#8211;1821), <title>Voyages dans l&#8217;Amerique Meridionale depuis 1781, jusqu&#8217;
                            en 1801</title> (1809), no. 90 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I spent a week lately at Durham, &#8211; my next visit there is to be timed so as to hit the Residence dinners &amp; the
                    &#8216;Long Main.&#8217; &#8211; Cock-fighting being like Bull-fighting to be seen once in ones life &amp; not more.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> There is still an inn in Durham called the Fighting Cocks; a &#8216;main&#8217; is a fight between two birds of equal
                        weight.</note> Durham itself is a singularly beautiful place, &#8211; &amp; the two Libraries belonging to the Bishop, &amp; to the
                    Chapter will tempt me to go there again. I got something there by the Archdukes victory<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the battle of Aspern-Essling (21&#8211;22 May 1809), the French attempted to cross the Danube near Vienna but were driven
                        back by Austrian forces commanded by their leader Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen (1771&#8211;1847).</note> &#8211; for a bottle of
                    Tokay was produced to drink his health upon the occasion. It was the first time I ever met with the wine &#8211; yet I distinctly
                    recognized its likeness to a <del>xxx</del> &lt;wine&gt; which you once found at Lisbon with the strange label of Pampo
                        Rodai,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roda is a town on the Ebro, where some of the finest rioja wines are still
                        produced. Tokay is a Hungarian sweet white wine.</note> &amp; which you said was Spanish Tokay.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>