<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1499</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2621</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>University of Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727.  Previously  published: Peter Mann , &#8216;Two
                        Unpublished Letters of Robert Southey&#8217;, N&amp;Q, NS 22 (September 1975), 397&#8211;399.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1499" type="letter">
        <head>1499. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Anna Seward </ref>
          <date when="1808-08-31"> [late August/early September 1808]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/
                        Miss Seward/ Lichfield/ [inserted in another hand] 6 Buxton Crescent<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark:
                        [illegible]<lb />MS: University of Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727<lb />Previously published: Peter Mann , &#8216;Two
                        Unpublished Letters of Robert Southey&#8217;, <title>N&amp;Q</title>, NS 22 (September 1975), 397&#8211;399.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> is gone to Spain, to fight as a private soldier in the Spanish army. One
                    such Englishman we lost in such a course as this when Sidney<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586;
                            <title>DNB</title>), poet, courtier and soldier, took a shot to the thigh while fighting in support of the Protestant
                        Dutch against Spain in the Netherlands; he died of his wound three weeks later.</note> fell, &#8211; &amp; in spite of the half-envy
                    which his letter excited, a shuddering comes over me when I think of the passions &amp; feelings, &amp; noble qualities, &amp;
                    mighty genius, of which a chewed-bullet, <del>&amp;</del> a half-pennyworth of powder <del>may</del> &amp; a rusty musquet in the
                    hands of a rascally Frenchman, may in one moment deprive the world. Such a man cannot fail to distinguish himself &#8211; if he be not
                    speedily cut off, &#8211; he has a body answerable to his mind, &amp; will learn how to command, sooner than an ordinary man could be
                    taught the routine of loading &amp; firing. Till he went I had no other emotions in beholding this great struggle, than joy, &amp;
                    eager expectation, &#8211; being in full faith that the good cause will triumph. &#8211; He has two companions with him to whom he preached
                    this crusade, &#8211; God be with them! It is many a long day since the heart of England has beat with so generous a warmth as at this
                    time animates it! Old honour, old generosity, old heroism are appearing again <del>afr</del> among us &#8211; England is herself again,
                    the cause of liberty, disgraced &amp; almost destroyed as it has been by that cursed monkey nation, is once more to be fought for,
                    once more to be triumphant.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The story of the 8000 Frenchmen put to the sword, tho officially announced here, does not appear to be
                    authenticated; &#8211; is in fact disproved by subsequent transactions in that quarter, with which it is utterly inconsistent. &#8211; What I
                    blamed in ministry was their <hi rend="ital">tardy</hi> aid. Wellesley lingered in Dublin weeks after he ought to have been in
                        Lisbon.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arthur Wellesley, later to become Field Marshall and 1st Duke of Wellington
                        (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), sailed in July with an expeditionary force to Portugal. He would spend the next six years
                        fighting Napoleon&#8217;s armies in Iberia.</note> Not an hour should have been lost, &#8211; Lord Chatham<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> General John Pitt, 2nd Earl of Chatham (1756&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>). Chatham had been passed over as the
                        commander of British forces in the Peninsula in favour of Wellesley. Southey&#8217;s assessment was not borne out when, in 1809,
                        Chatham proved an ineffectual commander during the Walcheren expedition.</note> would have secured the Pyrenees at the first
                    outset, shut all succour out, &amp; shut <del>th</del> Murat<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joachim-Napol&#233;on Murat
                        (1767&#8211;1815), the brother-in-law of Napoleon and a cavalryman. Murat was in charge of the French army occupying Madrid when the
                        popular uprising that so inspired Southey and Landor began, on 2 May 1808. Napoleon made him Marshal of France and Admiral of
                        France, 1st Prince Murat, and King of Naples from 1808 to 1815.</note> &amp; his ruffians in, so that not a man could have
                    escaped. There are scenes of tremendous horror which I could &#8216;behold &amp; smile by Mercys side&#8217;.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Southey&#8217;s poem &#8216;To Horror&#8217;, published in <title>Poems 1797</title>.</note> &#8211; an insurrection which should
                    make the Negroes masters of the Sugar Islands is one. To hear that not a Frenchman returned into his own country would be another.
                    It is not in my nature to justify such a system of warfare. my heart belies my understanding, conviction &amp; Christian faith,
                    when it rejoices even in defensive war, &#8211; <del>for the</del> I acknowledge the principles of Quakerism upon this point &lt;but&gt;
                    I have not yet subdued my instincts to them: &#8211; but if this utter extermination were to take place, certainly my feeling would be
                    that an aweful judgement had been dispensed, the most aweful since the Deluge, &amp; one whose wholesome effect would remain as
                    long as the memory of the event should be preserved. It is curious to see how &lt;differently&gt; history affects us with the same
                    events, when the causes are different. We read of the massacre of the Danes<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In September
                        1807, British forces had bombarded Copenhagen, then neutral, to prevent Napoleon gaining possession of the Danish fleet. Over
                        2000 Danes, mostly civilians, were killed.</note> in this country with deep &amp; painful humiliation, &#8211; I would give half my
                    limbs that it could be blotted out from remembrance &#8211; <del>would</del> that it had never been perpetrated. The Sicilian papers
                    excite no such horror, <hi rend="ital">there</hi> we do not sympathize with the sufferers: the patience of humanity had been
                    outraged beyond all endurance, &amp; dreadful as the vengeance was we acknowledge that it was just.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Killings by the royalist peasants and the Crown in the kingdom of Naples and Sicily of the nobles who, in the
                        hope of reform, had allied themselves to the French.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your estimate of the value of my copyrights moved me to a doleful smile. I sold the copyright of J of Arc<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796).</note> for 50 guineas &amp; 50 copies. I sold the edition of Thalaba<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> for 115 &#163;, &#8211; &amp; the edition hangs on hand. the fate of Madoc you know.
                    No bookseller would give me 500 &#163; &#8211; nor half the sum, for the best poem which it is &lt;in&gt; my power to produce. Constable
                    would not even make me an offer for Kehama, when, in return to his overture (which proved to relate to his rascally review) I
                    asked him thro <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> what he would give for it. <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), publisher of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> and of
                        Scott&#8217;s <title>Marmion</title> (1808). For the letter to Scott mentioned here, see Southey to Walter Scott, 4 October 1807,
                        Letter 1369.</note> It is only Scott who can get his thousands.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott sold the
                        copyrights of his first two poems to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> for &#163;500 each; for
                            <title>Marmion</title> Constable paid him 1000 guineas.</note> He has got the Goose. My Swan&#8217;s eggs are not golden ones.
                    Now that looks like a sarcasm, &amp; it belies me in looking so. Poor I was born, &amp; poor I shall die, 40,000 &#163; having been
                    left from me only, &amp; <del>three</del> the three fourths of it, &lt;of&gt; <del>of</del> which in the common order of things I
                        <del>am</del> should still be expected, will be left from me again, without the slightest provocation, plea, or pretext in
                    either case. But as soon as I am dead, then it will be like the man in the spectator, I shall be made with gold. &lt;I shall then
                    be&gt; be-wept, be-rhymed, be-biographized, be-monumented, &#8211; whereas I may now be-starved &#8211; &amp; be d___d if I please. Which I do
                        <hi rend="ital">not</hi> please. It is not in the power of the world to depress me. My spirits are unconquerably good, &#8211; my
                    heart has been upon the anvil, &amp; there is no breaking it, &#8211; I am a happy man, &amp; the Devil himself shall never
                        <del>tell</del> &lt;make&gt; me otherwise. If he takes me by the beard I will take him by the horns.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Joanna Baillie<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1762&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish dramatist,
                        friend of the <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Aikins</ref> and of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>.</note> drank tea with us &#8211; she has a quick eye, frank &amp; winning manners, &amp; that kindly nature, that
                    because there were children in the room, she could not help playing with them, &amp; half her conversation was in familiar sport.
                    She left upon us a very very favourable impression, &amp; when next I see her <del>I shall</del> it will be as natural for me to
                    go &amp; shake her &lt;by the&gt; hand, &#8211; as it for me to make an iron bend of the back on coming within the atmosphere of <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Barbauld</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There will be human sufferings in Kehama.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title>, published in 1810.</note> human passions, &amp; human virtue tried in the burning fiery furnace. I have
                    perceived that no person <del>adm</del> equally admires Madoc &amp; Thalaba,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        two previous poems, <title>Madoc</title> (1805) and <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> &#8211; <del>I mean</del>
                    &amp; that whoever admires the one speaks with a sort of respectful dislike of the other. Now I who could write both, do not
                    understand why other persons should find <del>it</del> a <del>thirst</del> taste for the one incompatible with a taste for the
                    other, &#8211; yet assuredly so it is. Certainly they are, as they were meant to be, essentially different. To me it seems that I should
                    have judged the author of Thalaba capable of writing Madoc but could not have deduced the opposite inference, &#8211; I should have seen
                    the power over human feelings indicated in the one, I should not have suspected the creative magic of fancy in the other. that the
                    one is the best poem, the other exhibits the greater power of poetry. The public agree with me that they are alike in merit, &#8211; buy
                    neither, &amp; leave them to keep one another company in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Longmans</ref> cellars.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All strangers judge as you have done from my lean &amp; treasonable appearance. I am however a strong man, &amp; no
                    person ever managed himself better. &#8211; I look daily for your poem in the Courier,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        editors have not traced the appearance of Seward&#8217;s poem in <title>The Courier</title>; it is likely that Coleridge, Southey&#8217;s
                        contact at the <title>Courier</title> in 1808, did not cause it to be published there. However,&#8217;Verses Written in the Blank Leaves of
                            <title>Southey&#8217;s Madoc</title>&#8217; appeared in <title>The Poetical Register, and Repository of Fugitive Poetry for
                            1808&#8211;9</title>, 7 (1812), p. 235.</note> &amp; am surprised at not seeing one day the paper missed, &#8211; yet if it had there
                    been inserted &#8211; it would ere this have found its way into other prints.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>