<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1466</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2588</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    147&#8211;152.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1466" type="letter">
        <head>1466. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1808-06-13">13 June 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    147&#8211;152.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-06-13">June 13. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Coleridge,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have the last census of Spain here, and perhaps you may like to give the Courier a statement of the population of
                    the Northern Provinces, as taken in 1797, and published in 1801.</p>
        <table cols="5" rows="8" width="740">
          <row>
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="180">Males from the </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140">Population.</cell>
            <cell width="180">Age of 16 to 50.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140">Asturias</cell>
            <cell width="140">&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </cell>
            <cell width="140"> 364,238</cell>
            <cell width="180"> 80,554</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140">Galicia</cell>
            <cell width="140">&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </cell>
            <cell width="140">1,142,630</cell>
            <cell width="180">225,454</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140">These Provinces</cell>
            <cell width="140">Alava</cell>
            <cell width="140">&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </cell>
            <cell width="140"> 67,523</cell>
            <cell width="180"> 15,367</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140">are what we</cell>
            <cell width="140">Guipuzcoa</cell>
            <cell width="140">&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </cell>
            <cell width="140">104,491</cell>
            <cell width="180">23,343</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140">call Biscay.</cell>
            <cell width="140">Vizcaya</cell>
            <cell width="140">&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </cell>
            <cell width="140"> 111,436</cell>
            <cell width="180"> 25,801</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="140" />
            <cell width="180">400,519</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p rend="indent1">These are the provinces which have asked assistance; but there is probably a French force at Ferrol, which may, for
                    awhile, keep part of Galicia in awe. The people are a hardy race, and most of them good shots, because there are no game laws,
                    plenty of game, and wolves in the country. Probably every man has his gun. One hardly dares indulge a hope; but if Europe is to be
                    redeemed in our days, you know it has always been my opinion that the work of deliverance would begin in Spain. And now that its
                    unhappy government has committed suicide, the Spaniards have got rid of their worst enemy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This account of Lisbon, which has just reached me, may also fitly appear in the Courier,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This account does not appear to have been published in <title>The Courier</title>.</note> for the edification of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> and such politicians: &#8211; &#8216;Every private family has a certain number of French
                    officers and soldiers quartered upon them, who behave with their accustomed insolence and brutality. The ladies of one family very
                    naturally, upon the intrusion of these unwelcome guests, retired to their own apartments, where they proposed remaining; but these
                    civilised Frenchmen required their presence, and would admit of no excuse. <hi rend="ital">Il faut que les dames viennent</hi> was
                    the only reply which they made;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French translates as &#8216;The ladies must come&#8217;.</note> and of course the
                    women were compelled to be subject to their ribaldry and impertinence. Whole families of the middling class are seen begging at
                    the corners of the streets; and women, who had till now borne an unblemished reputation, prostitute themselves publicly to gain
                    wherewithal to buy bread. The soldiers and the flower of the peasantry are sent to recruit the French armies in distant parts.&#8217;
                    Nothing can exceed the misery and the despondency of the people. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were I minister, I would send half the regular army without delay to Spain; the distance is nothing, &#8211; a week;
                    would be but an average passage; and these seas are not like the German Ocean, where so many brave men have been sacrificed in
                    useless expeditions during stormy seasons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of public affairs enough! We have had a bilious fever in the house, which was epidemic among the children of the
                    place. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has suffered severely from it; I thought we should lose him. The
                    disease has reduced him very much, and left him in a state of great debility. <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is
                    scarcely ever without some kind of infectious fever, generally among the children. When these things get into a dirty house, they
                    hardly ever get out of it; and I attribute this more to the want of cleanliness than to the climate. But ague is beginning to
                    re-appear, which had scarcely been heard of during the last generation; &#8211; this is the case over the whole kingdom, I believe. What
                    put a stop to it then, or what brought it back now, is beyond the reach of our present knowledge. You love the science of physic;
                    and Nature, who seems to have meant you for half a dozen different things when she made you, meant you for a physician among the
                    rest. I will tell you, therefore, two odd peculiarities of my constitution; the slightest dose of laudanum acts upon me as an
                    aperient; &#8211; if I am at any time exposed to the sun bareheaded for two minutes, I infallibly take cold. This probably shows how
                    soon I should be subject to a stroke of the sun, and indicates the same over-susceptibility which the nitrous oxide did, a smaller
                    dose affecting me than any other person who ever breathed it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have read that play of Calderon&#8217;s<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Calder&#243;n de la Barca (1600&#8211;1681),
                            <title>La Devocion de la Cruz</title> (1637), the plot of which turns on the miraculous imprint of the sign of the cross
                        in the flesh of the hero and heroine &#8211;lovers &#8211; who are thereby identified as brother and sister. At the play&#8217;s close, the
                        heroine undergoes an apotheosis, being lifted to heaven with the cross at whose foot she has taken shelter. Maria Gisbourne
                        reported in 1820 that Coleridge had told her this was the play of Calderon&#8217;s that he had read; see Maria Gisborne &amp; Edward
                        E. Williams, <title>Shelley&#8217;s Friends. Their Journals and Letters</title>, ed. Frederick L. Jones (Norman, OK, 1951), p. 41.
                        Southey&#8217;s library contained Calderon&#8217;s <title>Autos Sacramentales Allegoricos y Historiales</title> (1717).</note> since my
                    return: its story is precisely as you stated it, and in the story the wonder lies. Are we not apt to do with these things as
                    naturalists do with insects? &#8211; put them in a microscope, and exclaim how beautiful! &#8211; how wonderful! &#8211; how grand! &#8211; when all the
                    beauty and all the grandeur are owing to the magnifying medium? A shaping mind receives the story of the play and makes it <hi rend="ital">terrific</hi>; &#8211; in Calderon it is <hi rend="ital">extravagant</hi>. The machinery is certainly most
                    extraordinary; and most extraordinary must the state of public opinion be, where such machinery could be received with the
                    complacency of perfect faith, &#8211; as undoubtedly this was, and would be still in Spain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At last I have got all my books about me, and right rich I am in them &#8211; above 4000 volumes. With your Germans,
                    &amp;c., there is probably no other house in the country which contains such a collection of foreign literature. My Cid will be
                    published in about six weeks. Brazil is not yet gone to press,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808). The first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> was not published
                        until 1810.</note> &#8211; the price of paper has deterred me; and yet there is little likelihood of any reduction, indeed no
                    possibility, till the North is again open to us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is the moment for uniting Spain and Portugal; and the greater facility of doing this in a commonwealth than in
                    a monarchy would be reason enough for preferring that form of government were there no other. Portugal loses something in
                    importance and in feeling by being incorporated in the Spanish monarchy; it would preserve its old dignity by uniting in a federal
                    republic, &#8211; a form which the circumstances of Spain more especially require, and its provincial difference of laws and dialects.
                    Each province should have its own cortes, and the general congress meet at Madrid, &#8211; otherwise, that city would soon waste away.
                    No nation has ever had a fairer opportunity for reforming its government and modelling it anew. But I dare say this wretched
                    cabinet will be meddling too much in this, and too little in the desperate struggle which must be made; &#8211; that we shall send tardy
                    and inefficient aid &#8211; enough to draw on a heavier French force, and. not enough to resist the additional force which it will
                    occasion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The crown, like the Ahrimanes of the earth,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The fallen angels in Persian
                        Zoroastrianism. Expelled from heaven, they lived on earth but, refusing to abandon their ambitions of rule and hurting the
                        earth&#8217;s inhabitants out of spite, were sent to live between the earth and the stars.</note> will sacrifice any thing rather
                    than see the downfall of royalty.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That best of all good women, <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs. Wilson</ref>, has borne the winter better
                    than any former one since we have known her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am thinking about a poem upon Pelajo, the restorer of Spain.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This
                        &#8216;thinking&#8217; brought forth <title>Roderick Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> Do you wish to serve me? Puff Espriella, in
                    the Courier, as the best guide to the lakes.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Letter 41 of <title>Letters from England by
                            Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) conducts the reader on a detailed tour of the
                        area, including, innovatively, fellwalking. Southey&#8217;s request that Coleridge &#8216;puff Espriella&#8217; does not appear to have been acted on.</note> All well. God bless you!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>