<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1566</idno><idno type="nines">rce2688</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington
                        Library, HM 4861 .  Previously  published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William
                            Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 261–266.Dating note: date changed in MS from ‘Feby’ to
                        ‘Jany’. The letter is dated ‘Jan 15’ in Robberds. In his reply of 10 March, Taylor thanks Southey for two letters, of which
                        this must be ‘the one enclosing Coleridge’s prospectus received in January’ (p. 270).</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1566" type="letter"><head>1566. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1809-01-15">15 [January]
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single sheet<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Huntington
                        Library, HM 4861<lb/> Previously published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William
                            Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 261–266.<lb/>Dating note: date changed in MS from ‘Feby’ to
                        ‘Jany’. The letter is dated ‘Jan 15’ in Robberds. In his reply of 10 March, Taylor thanks Southey for two letters, of which
                        this must be ‘the one enclosing Coleridge’s prospectus received in January’ (p. 270).</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-01-15">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Changed from ‘Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>’.</note> 15. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> At length I have laid hand on a Prospectus, which I send you rather as a thing worth having, than for any other
                    use; for <del>it was</del> &lt;<ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>&gt; sent &lt;it&gt; abroad hastily,
                    without consideration on his own part, or consultation with any body else, – &amp; both the how &amp; the when <del>xxxx</del>of
                    publication remain yet to be settled.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge’s</ref> new periodical <title>The Friend</title>, the first number of which was published on 1 June
                        1809.</note> My advice to him is not to venture upon any periodical task, because I am quite certain he <del>will</del> never
                    will <del>d</del> be ready in time; – but to publish a half crown or five shilling number [MS torn] whenever he can be ready with
                    one. That something should be done I am very anxious, because if <del>t</del> what there is in <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> be not drawn out of him in this way, it will never be drawn out of
                    him at all.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for De Lery,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de Léry (1536–1613), <title>Histoire d’un
                            Voyage fait en la Terre du Bresil</title> (1578), was no. 1709 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which
                    has proved of greater value than I expected, inasmuch as De Bry,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The collection of travel
                        narratives published by Theodor and Johann Israel De Bry (1528–1598), <title>Peregrinationes</title> (1598–1613).</note> like
                    a right Roman Catholick has omitted the whole chapter relating to Ville-gagnon,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas
                        Durand, de Villegaignon (or Villegagnon) (1510–1571), who invaded Brazil in 1555 to claim it as a French colony, with a group
                        of Huguenots and Calvinists who were escaping Catholic persecution. Disgusted by disputes between the Protestant and Catholic
                        colonists, Villegagnon condemned some of the Calvinists to death, withdrew his support, and returned to France. In 1558 the
                        colonists were defeated by the Portuguese.</note> – the main part of the preface, – &amp; most of the parts which expose
                    Thevets ignorance &amp; knavery.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> André Thevet (1502–1590), whose <title>Les Singularitez
                            de la France Antarctique</title> (1557) purported to be a first-hand account of a French expedition to Brazil. The
                        ‘Collection’ could be his <title>Cosmographie Universelle</title> (1575). Southey owned editions of both works, nos 2852 and
                        2677 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Even from the book thus mutilated I had, by the help of Thuanus,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques Auguste de Thou (Thuanus) (1553–1617), author of <title>Historia sui Temporis</title>
                        (1620) and <title>Memoires</title> (1620).</note> formed an opinion, which the additional facts thus got at, compleatly verify
                    &amp; establish. My Bayle I fear is <del>xxxx</del>the first edition, for I can find nothing there upon the subject.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre Bayle (1647–1706), <title>Dictionnaire Historique et Critique</title>, the first edition
                        of which was published 1695–1697.</note> Moreri has something about it, in his usual meagre &amp; wretched way.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Moréri (1643–1680), <title>Le Grand Dictionnaire Historique</title> (1732), no. 1917 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I do not by any means either dispute or <del>xxxx</del>&lt;doubt&gt; that the Caraibes of the French are our
                    Carribs, <del>xxxx</del>– but in De Lery the word is different.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de Léry (1536–1613),
                            <title>Histoire d’un Voyage fait en la Terre du Bresil</title> (1578), no. 1709 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> It means there the Tupi<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An Indian tribe of the Amazon.</note>
                    priests, who were Tupis themselves: but it is used improperly both by him &amp; some of the Portugueze writers, for Marcgrave
                    (what is the Dutch orthography of that name?) makes the distinction, &amp; explains Paye to be the Conjurer, Caraiba his power of
                        conjuration.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Georg Marcgrave/Georg Marggraf (1610–1648), born in Saxony, Marggraf
                        went to Brazil in 1638 in the expedition of the Dutch led by John Maurice/Johan Maurits of Nassau (1604–1679). Marggraf’s
                        papers on natural history were published, after his death, with editorial input from Joannes de Laet (1581–1649) as part of
                        the work of the expedition’s physician Willem Piso/Willem Pies (1611–1678) (1581–1649) in the <title>Historia Naturalium
                            Brasiliae</title> (1648).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Courier, not the Edinburgh Review, speaks my opinions with respect to Spain. The only political revolution
                    which that country needed took place &amp; ipso facto upon the kidnapping of the royal family, by the establishment of the
                    different Juntas – for Spain has only to recur to its old constitution, long suspended, but never repealed or destroyed, to be a
                    free nation. As for religious reformation – that as you perceive Buonaparte is enacting, – a proof, if proof were needed, that the
                    whole clergy are against him, as well as the whole people. Every thing is to be expected from the Spaniards except what our
                    Ministers choose to expect, that they should at once be able to stand against equal or superior numbers of the French in the
                    field. We should have borne the first brunt, &amp; trained them to be soldiers just as they teach the young skaiters in Holland. –
                    But it would fill a larger sheet than this to point out all the gross blunders which we have committed. Still I am confident that
                    Spain will finally deliver itself, tho <del>it</del> we shall perhaps see it at first over-run, – I am the more confident because
                    in <del>xxx</del> &lt;every&gt; instance <del>xxx</del> my expectations with regard to that country <del>xxx</del> have been
                    verified.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Grenvilles &amp; Foxites will seperate upon the question of peace.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Factions within the Whig party who were followers of the policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James
                            Fox</ref> or <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>.</note><ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> hankers after the former, &amp; would gladly have them in with him. Neither
                    the King<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738–1820, King of Great Britain 1760–1820;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> nor the people will like it; – the King will never be so well pleased as with an administration
                    composed of his <hi rend="ital">menials</hi>, for such they are, – &amp; the people dislike the Grenvilles: the Republicans
                    however will be with them against the peacemakers. I have but one opinion &amp; one feeling here, – that the scabbard must be
                    thrown away, &amp; that our whole disposable force should be sent to Spain. The very Quakers admit that peace cannot be wished for
                    upon any other principle than their own. Your admiration of <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> is to me quite
                    surprizing. <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbet</ref> may be an honest writer by popularity, because he has gone
                    regularly on from the extreme point of <del>Jacobinism</del> Anti-Jacobinism to the other end of the political scale.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A severe review of <title>Cobbett’s Political Register</title>, in <title>The Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 10 (July 1807), 386–421, had created a long lasting enmity between <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis Jeffrey</ref> and the radical (ex-Tory) journalist <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">William Cobbett</ref>.</note> But <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> must be a rogue, because he has gone backwards &amp; forwards. Look at the wretched justification of war in the
                    first number, &amp; compare this with the wretched justifications of peace now.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        gave chapter and verse for Jeffrey’s <title>Edinburgh Review</title> articles on the war in the notes to his poem
                            <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814). He cited ‘Mr Whitbread’s <title>Letter on Spain</title>’,<title> Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, no. 24 (July 1808), 441; ‘Exposition of the Practices and Machinations which led to the Usurpation of the
                        Crown of Spain, and the Means adopted by the Emperor of the French to carry it into Execution’, <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, no. 25 (October 1808), 215; ‘Emancipation of Spanish America’, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, no. 26
                        (January 1809), 298.</note> Look at his defence of all existing abuses when the party to whom he had at last attached himself
                    were, as he supposed, safely <hi rend="ital">in</hi>, &amp; then judge what credit is due to his democracy when they are out.
                    There was an able article in the Courier some weeks ago, setting him against himself in two parallel columns, &amp; never was
                    pamphleteering tergiversation more decidedly proved.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">This article has not been
                        traced.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Your argument that schools, not churches, ought to be the instrument of conversion, is I believe the only one which
                    I have not entered into in my reviewal of the Baptist Mission &amp; Buchanan controversy.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s review was of the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published from
                        1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the
                            Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an
                            Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to
                            Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the
                            Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on
                            the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807), published in the newly formed
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226. Claudius Buchanan (1766–1815; <title>DNB</title>) was an East
                        India Company chaplain who laboured zealously for the promotion of Christianity and education in India.</note> The schools are
                    the necessary consequence of the mission, – without it they could do little, – for it is not desirable to undermine an old
                    superstition without giving something in its place. This was the error of Voltaire<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Francois Marie Arouet (pen name Voltaire) (1694–1778), atheist, satirist and philosopher.</note> &amp; the French Anti-Xtians,
                    – had they been content with Socianism,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Based on the teachings of Faustus Socinus
                        (1539–1604) who rejected traditional Christian doctrines, such as belief in the Trinity and the divinity of Christ.</note> or
                    what is better with a philosophical Quakerism France would at this day have been <del>xxxx</del>free, &amp; we should have won
                    that game sixteen years ago, which was lost for us by the union of Atheism with Jacobinism. As for the crazy Calvinism of the
                    Missionaries, I regard that just as you do, &amp; take especial care never to be misunderstood when the subject comes in my way, –
                    but Missionaries must be crazy (according to the common acceptation of the word) or they would not be Missionaries, – &amp; I hold
                    it something worse than craziness to keep out of sight the great qualities connected with their enthusiasm. </p><p rend="indent1"> No enquiry has yet been made here concerning Mr Bolingbroke.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Bolingbroke’s (1785–1855; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to the Demarary</title> (1807) was revised by William Taylor
                        and published as <title>A Voyage to the Demarary, Containing a Statistical Account of the Settlements there and of those on
                            the Essequebo, the Berbice and other Contiguous Rivers of Guyana</title>, in 1809.</note> I am <del>very</del> glad that
                    you are once more got into a review, tho it will not fall in my way to see the Critical,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Taylor had been invited to review regularly for the <title>Critical Review</title>.</note> – this years Annual I fear will
                    seem very flat to me from your default.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Review</title>, for which
                        Taylor and Southey had both written reviews. Southey’s last contributions appeared in the volume for 1808.</note> My own
                    articles in it were none of them written with much pleasure. they are few in number, &amp; I suspect there is little reason to
                    wish there had been more of them, unless the books had been better, – for unlike you, I stick to my text, &amp; if that is not a
                    lucky one, the discourse is not likely to make amends for its defects. Perhaps it is bad policy in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> not to pay such a price as to make exertion incumbent, &amp; enable his
                    authors always to afford it.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>