<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1667</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2789</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1667" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1667" type="letter">
        <head>1667. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-08-10">10 August
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-08-10">August 10. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My views on the Stewardship are at end, &#8211; a practical farmer &amp; miner being required.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In July 1809, Southey was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the
                        stewardship of the Derwentwater Estates (which were owned by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the
                        incumbent. Southey asked several friends to intercede on his behalf for the position, including <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">George
                            Beaumont</ref>, but in the end it was considered unsuitable for him; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August
                        1809, Letter 1669.</note> Had it suited me my interest would have carried it, &#8211; for <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> received the application in the handsomest manner &amp; left it to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref> to express his full acquiescence to Lord Mulgrave,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in
                    whose gift it is, &amp; with whom <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G</ref> is &lt;so&gt; intimate, that he fully
                    expected to succeed if the thing were not already promised. I find that it really is as Lord Mulgrave has stated, &amp; that the
                    present possessor, with a Clerk, is employed 17 or 18 hours out of the four &amp; twenty. &#8211; On <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott&#8217;s</ref> part there has been nothing but hearty good will towards me, &#8211; of that I am
                    well assured. On <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref> he assures me it has been the same, &#8211; indeed to what
                    purpose should he aim at cajoling his friends, or me? &#8211; The office of precis-writer he would have offered me had it been worth my
                    acceptance, &amp; I rather think both from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> letter, &amp; from something which
                    my old schoolfellow Dickenson (the member for Somersetshire) <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dickinson
                        (1771&#8211;1837), a pupil at Westminster School, who later went on to Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795). He was Civil Lord
                        of the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806.</note> said to me the other day, that he expected the Secretarys&lt;hip&gt; at Lisbon might have
                    been agreeable to me. As things now are that is out of the question, &#8211; &amp; all I can do is to make interest for the succession
                    to old Dutens, whenever he chuses to vacate the office of Historiographer, which for what merits Heaven knows was bestowed upon
                    this Frenchman many years ago with a salary of 400&#163; a year.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a French Protestant, held the post of Historiographer Royal until his death on 23 May 1812. Southey&#8217;s
                        campaign for the post proved unsuccessful and it was given to James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    &#8211; This desire I have made known to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, &amp; this there is good prospect of my
                    obtaining thro <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref>, &#8211; if not by any other channel. His answer to <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> conveyed an invitation to me. Senhouse is going to visit him on Monday
                    next, &amp; I shall take that opportunity. The grounds at <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref> are the finest in
                    England, &#8211; I shall see them at leisure &amp; having Humphrey Senhouse in the house shall contrive to pass two days there
                    pleasantly enough.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Molina is translated by an American &amp; printed in America.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni
                        Ignazio Molina (1740&#8211;1829), <title>Compendio della Storia Geografica, Naturale, e Civile del Regno del Chile</title> (1776).
                        An American edition appeared as <title>A Geographical, Natural, and Civil History of Chili</title> in 1808.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> sent it to me to know if it should be reprinted here, &#8211; &amp; I added the two
                    Appendices &amp; a few notes.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The English edition of this work was published in London in
                        1809, entitled <title>Geographical, Natural and Civil History of Chile: Translated from the Italian</title>. </note> As to
                    Mort Arthur, they have made me play the dog in the manger towards <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, who would
                    have edited it if he had not heard that I was about it, &#8211; but I shall soon put an end to all further procrastination &amp; tell
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">L</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">R</ref> that if they do not chuse to
                    publish it at once, <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> &amp; Miller<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Edinburgh bookseller Robert Miller (dates untraced), one of several partners with Ballantyne in publications at this
                        time.</note> will, &#8211; for I will not prevent <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">S.</ref> from doing it, unless I do it
                        myself.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longman published Southey&#8217;s edition of Thomas Malory&#8217;s (c. 1415&#8211;1471;
                            <title>DNB</title>)<title>, The Birth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur: Of his Noble Knyghtes of the Rounde Table, they&#8217;r
                            Merveyllous Enquestes and Aduentures ... : and in the end, Le Morte D&#8217;Arthur, with the Dolourous Deth and Departyng out of
                            thys Worlde of them Al</title>, in 1817.</note> &#8211; P. Girbals Travels are printed in the Mercurio Peruano<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Father
                                Narciso Girbal y Barcel&#243; explored the Mara&#241;on and Ucayali rivers in 1791. His travels are serialised in the <title>Mercurio
                                    Peruano</title>, a journal published in Peru between 1790 and 1795. Southey had access to the twelve-volume edition
                                <title>Mercurio Peruano, de Historia, Literatura y Noticias P&#250;blicas que da &#225; luz la Sociedad Academica de Amantes de
                                    Lima</title> (1791&#8211;1795), where Girbal&#8217;s travels occupy volumes II, ff. 138&#8211;44, 241&#8211;44; III, ff. 49&#8211;66; V, ff. 89&#8211;123; VI,
                                ff. 170&#8211;87; IX, ff. 2&#8211;18; XI, ff. 276&#8211;91.</note> which I gutted when last in town, &#8211; I believe all the travels which were contained in this work are given in the appendix to a book made up from it
                    under the catchpenny title of the Present State of Peru.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Skinner (dates unknown),
                            <title>Present State of Peru: Comprising its Geography, Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and
                            Manners of its Inhabitants, the State of Literature, Philosophy, and the Arts, the Modern Travels of the Missionaries in
                            the Heretofore Unexplored Mountainous Territories</title> (1805). Girbal y Barcel&#243;&#8217;s travels feature on p. 440.</note> The
                    copy of the Mercurio which John Allen<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Allen (1771&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), a
                        political and historical writer, expert on Spanish affairs, who was part of the Holland House set around <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref>.</note> obtained for me had Sobrevielas map of the Ucayali<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Solreviela y Girba (dates unknown), responsible for the map published in the
                            <title>Mercurio Peruano</title> of the Ucayali River in Peru, the main headwater for the Amazon River.</note> &amp; I took
                    it to Arrowsmith to copy.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer
                        of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map
                            of America</title> (1804), which depicted North and South America. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1817) contained Arrowsmith&#8217;s <title>Map of Brazil and Paraguay with the Adjoining
                        Countries</title>.</note> It had long been a desideration with him</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The chest with the large folios came here. Unluckily neither Bayle<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre
                        Bayle (1647&#8211;1706), <title>Dictionnaire Historique et Critique</title>, the first edition of which was published
                        1695&#8211;1697.</note> nor Moreri<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Mor&#233;ri (1643&#8211;1680), <title>Le Grand Dictionnaire
                            Historique</title> (1732). No. 1917 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> are the best edition, &amp; I
                    sought in vain in the former for some account of Villegagnon<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Durand, Sieur de
                        Villegagnon (1510&#8211;1571) a Commander of the Knights of Malta and later a French naval officer.</note> to which I wished to have
                    referred. I do not wonder that Pinkertons book surprized you. It is patched up with such utter carelessness that he gravely tells
                    you Chili tho so written, is to be pronounced Cili, translating from Molina, &amp; forgetting that the Italian Pronunciation is
                    not the same as the English.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), editor of
                            <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in all Parts of the World</title>
                        (1808&#8211;1814), a <title>New Modern Atlas</title> (1808&#8211;1809). Pinkerton cites Molina (for whom see note 6 above) on Chile
                        throughout the chapter on Spanish possession in South America in <title>Modern Geography</title> (1803 and 1807).</note> I
                    have heard that a good work of the same kind by a D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Playfair has appeared.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Playfair (1738&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), <title>System of Geography, Ancient and Modern</title>
                        (1808&#8211;1814).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The name of Faccius<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bartholomew Facius (before 1410&#8211;1457), author of
                        biographies of writers, painter and statesmen.</note> is new to me, &#8211; I will look in Tiraboschi<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The thirteen volume history of Italian literature by Giraloma Tiraboschi (1731&#8211;1794), <title>Storia della
                            Letteratura Italiana</title> (1777&#8211;1786), no. 2859 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> for some information
                    about him. Jacobus de Voragini is an old acquaintance of mine, if as I believe, he be the author of the Aurea Legenda.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacobus de Voragine (in Italian: Giacomo da Varazze or Jacopo da Varazze; c. 1230&#8211;1298) was the
                        Archbishop of Genoa and chronicler of the <title>Legenda Aurea</title> (or Golden Legend), a collection of the lives of the
                        saints of the medieval church. Many manuscript copies were made of this work and after the invention of printing in 1450 many
                        editions were published in Latin as well as every major European language.</note> Your extract from him is curious. The
                    Sangreal occurs in Mort Arthur,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Another name for the Holy Grail, from the Old French
                        &#8216;Saint Graal&#8217;. It makes its appearance in Arthurian legend between the late-twelfth century and mid-thirteenth century, and
                        features in Thomas Malory&#8217;s (c. 1415&#8211;1471; <title>DNB</title>)<title> Le Morte D&#8217;Arthur</title> (1485) published by William
                        Caxton (c. 1415&#8211;1492).</note> but there is a distinct Romance of that title, which I have never seen.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably the work of the twelfth-century author, Chr&#233;tien de Troyes, who wrote a series of Arthurian romances,
                        including <title>Le Conte del Graal</title> (or &#8216;The History of the Grail&#8217;).</note> I have read some of the Round Table
                    Romances lately, with the specific purpose of illustrating Mort Arthur, &amp; somewhat more for my own amusement.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of Malory&#8217;s <title>The Birth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur: Of his Noble
                            Knyghtes of the Rounde Table, they&#8217;r Merveyllous Enquestes and Aduentures ... and in the end, Le Morte D&#8217;Arthur, with the
                            Dolourous Deth and Departyng out of thys Worlde of them Al</title> was published by Longman in 1817.</note> They are very
                    inferior to the Spanish books of chivalry, I have however gleaned from them a few extracts which throw some light upon the manners
                    of their age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hardcastle was here yesterday. The Treasurer of the Missionary Society &amp; one of its main supports &amp;
                        Directors.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Hardcastle (1752&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), merchant and
                        evangelical, who held the position of Treasurer for the Missionary Society (renamed the London Missionary Society in 1818) for
                        twenty years from its inception in 1795, and wrote many of the society&#8217;s documents as well as frequently chairing meetings of
                        its Board of Directors (<title>DNB</title>).</note> He tells me they meditate a mission to Madagascar.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London Missionary Society sent one of their members, William Ellis (1794&#8211;1872;
                            <title>DNB</title>) to Madagascar in 1853, but entry was refused him several times, until 1861, when, despite its troubled
                        political situation, his four year visit laid the foundations for Christianity in the island.</note> Flacourts account of that
                    Island which you bought in London turns out to be an excellent book;<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#201;tienne de Flacourt
                        (1607&#8211;1660), a French governor of Madagascar whose <title>Histoire de la Grande Isle Madagascar</title> was published in 1661.
                        Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 938 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; I want a work which you read in Lisbon &amp; which I
                    have sought for in vain to connect Flacourts Hist. of the French Colony there with the account in Dellons Travels,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French doctor, traveller and writer Charles Dellon (1650&#8211;1710) published <title>Relation d&#8217;un
                            Voyages des Indes Orientales</title> (1685) and <title>Nouvelle Relation d&#8217;un Voyages fair aux Indes Orientales</title>
                        (1699); Southey owned a three-volume edition of 1709, no. 814 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; It is called
                    Relations de Bresil &#8211; Madagascar &amp;c<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 2363 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library was Claude-Barthe&#769;lemy Morisot (1592&#8211;1662), <title>Relations Veritables et Curieuses de l&#8217;Isle de Madagascar et du
                            Bresil, et Histoire des Derniers Troubles du Bresil</title> (1651).</note> &#8211; I particularly want it because by your
                    memoranda it appears that some detail of the Dutch improvements in Pernambuco was given there. &#8211; At any rate I shall find it at
                    Edinburgh, for there is a copy in the Advocates Library, tho I could not make <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>
                    find it for me. &#8211; I have sent a list of books to a young man who is going to Cadiz, &amp; who I believe will take some pains to
                    procure them for me. Seville I should suppose to be a good storehouse for them. Sealy I am afraid is not likely to care much about
                    executing such a commission at Lisbon, one list should be put into John Bells hands.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey was hoping that books he required from Lisbon could be supplied either by Sir John Bell (1782&#8211;1876;
                        <title>DNB</title>), an army officer who served in Portugal throughout the Peninsular War, or Richard Sealy (dates unknown) a
                        wealthy Lisbon merchant, the father-in-law of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert
                        Southey</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> got over to Lisbon as a private in the ranks, &#8211; how he got out
                    of the Militia is best known to himself. A Major Chamberlin<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Thomas Chamberlain
                        (d. 1828), Major in the 24th Foot Regiment.</note> whom I never before heard of wrote to tell me this, &amp; that he hoped to
                    get him a commission in a Port. regiment which he was raising, &amp; that Lord John Fitzroy<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord John Fitzroy (1785&#8211;1857), attach&#233; at the British Embassy in Lisbon and son of Augustus, 3rd Duke of
                        Grafton (1735&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>) Prime Minister 1768&#8211;1770.</note> would equip him. Presently came a letter from this
                        <del>xxxx</del> &lt;unlucky&gt; lad himself dated Abrantes, saying he was Lieutenant &amp; Adjutant in the Portugueze regiment
                    of Olivara &amp; that if I asked him to what he was indebted for his promotion, he must answer to his own good conduct. Not a word
                    of Chamberlin nor of Lord Fitzroy! &#8211; Of course I answered Chamberlins letter,<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter
                        does not appear to have survived.</note> &#8211; but I had no heart to reply to his.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Booza<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> Felipe Bauz&#225; y Ca&#241;as (1764&#8211;1834), hydrographer to the Spanish navy
                        and a friend of Arrowsmith.</note> may throw light upon Paraguay, &amp; the course of the Spanish Moors.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>