<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1206</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2328</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>University of
                        Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727 1:1.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1206" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1206" type="letter">
        <head>1206. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard Duppa</ref>, <date when="1806-08-05">5 August
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Richard Duppa Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 51. Great
                        Marlborough Street/ Oxford Street/ London./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [illegible] <lb />MS: University of
                        Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727 1:1<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1806-08-05">Tuesday August 5 &#8211; 1806</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Duppa</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The reason why I have not written to you before, since my return from London, is a very simple one &#8211; I beseech you
                    let it also be satisfactory. You gave me a splendid copy of your Life of Michel Angelo.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Richard Duppa, <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title>
                        (1806).</note> This book I did not take home with me &#8211; because it was a heavy book to bring here, &amp; to take back again
                    early in the next Spring, &#8211; I had rapidly read it at <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>, &amp; should get a copy
                    from <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> for special purposes of half the weight &#8211; he having to pay its
                    carriage back. Now this other copy from the King is not yet arrived.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed
                        Duppa&#8217;s book in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 411&#8211;425.</note> Come it will, for I have not only spoken
                    for it in town, but written for it since, &amp; it shall pass thro nobodys hands but my own. I did not like to write to you till I
                    could have sent you a letter critical, in which I had pointed out every thing which appeared to me capable of amendment; &amp;
                    this as soon as the book comes I will do, &#8211; or if you be preparing for another edition, will do it sooner, by sending to <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> for <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>. Meantime
                    conscience has been dunning pins into me every day &#8211; &amp; I now submit to you the plain case, which will certainly account for a
                    long &amp; unfit silence &#8211; &amp; I trust excuse it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Printer goes on slowly with Espriella, nor do I hurry him.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) was printed by Richard
                        Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and
                        Francis with his son William Francis (1817&#8211;1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> but we both are getting on. One of your
                    letters is printed with certain interpolations, it is that about shopping &amp;c.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Shopping
                        in London is described in Letters 7 and 11 of <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> That concerning Westminster Abbey
                    goes to the press in the next exportation<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England,</title> Letter 23.</note> &#8211; I have added to it some catholick falsehoods respecting the history
                    of the church, &amp; some little else. At your leisure, give me an account of the Exhibition in 1803.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The exhibition of pictures at the Royal Academy of Arts was not described in <title>Letters from
                            England</title>.</note> a few general remarks will do as to the thing itself &#8211; what I most wish is to <del>have</del> said
                    what good the Academy does; if any &#8211;; what merit is due the King &amp;c. The merits of Mr Alderman Boydell &amp; the history of
                    his Shakespeare is also another subject which you will handle far better than I &#8211; or to speak truly &#8211; which I could not handle at
                        all.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Boydell (1720&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>) was appointed Alderman of Cheap ward
                        in London in 1782 and held the position until his death in 1804. He began a large venture to produce depictions of scenes from
                        Shakespeare&#8217;s works, exhibited in a Shakespeare Gallery in Pall Mall, London, the publication of an illustrated edition of
                        Shakespeare&#8217;s plays, and the release of a folio of prints depicting scenes from Shakespeare&#8217;s works. Some of the most
                        illustrious painters of the day contributed, such as Benjamin West (1738&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) and Henry Fuseli
                        (1741&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>). The Shakespeare gallery was not described in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> And
                    &lt;for&gt; any thing else which occurs to your recollection, be sure that I shall easily find fit place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> arrived yesterday &#8211; from sea, &amp; my spirits have not
                    yet recovered their usual temperate tone. &#8211; for it disjects me to see him looking prematurely old &#8211; to think that in fourteen
                    years he has only been nine months on shore &#8211; &amp; that we three brothers who are now in one house have never been together till
                    now during the whole of that time, &#8211; &amp; very possibly when we separate <del>again</del> &#8211; as in a few weeks we must &#8211; never may
                    meet <del>again</del> together again. Family ties, when they are good for anything, grow stronger as we grow older, &amp; as fewer
                    are left us. We then feel how different they are from other friendships, be those friendships never so sincere, &#8211; I will never
                    breed up a child either to the navy or army &#8211; nor send one to the East Indies. It is very well for birds, whose love is only
                    instinct, to <del>part</del> be turned adrift as soon as they leave the nest, &#8211; but it as an evil thing for a family to be
                    scattered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was very desirous of getting some live land-crabs for <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> &#8211;
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> took on board a fine cargo, &#8211; but in spite of all possible care the last died
                    when they were off the Isle of Wight.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had promised to bring some land crabs
                        with him from the West Indies; see Southey to John Rickman, 20 January 1804 (Letter 886) and Southey to John King, [1]&#8211;5 March
                        1804 (Letter 904).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have the measles in the house &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> is expected to
                    sicken in about a week. Till it is over I shall be more uneasy than is quite reasonable upon the doctrine of chances: &#8211; the
                    disorder is &lt;something fatal&gt; &amp; I remember losing a sister to it. In about [MS torn] months I expect an addition to my
                    family &#8211; of which I am very glad.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert Southey</ref>, the Southeys&#8217; first son, was born 11 October 1806.</note> In
                    the spring I hope to effect my renewal to Portugal, bag &amp; baggage &#8211; There [MS torn] remain some three or four years. The
                    climate will be of service to me, &amp; perhaps lengthen the lease I have of this body of mine, &#8211; a lease which seems to stand in
                    need of a renewal. Nor tho I most truly do hope, trust &amp; believe that whenever the lease be out I shall get into a better
                    tenement, I would yet willingly keep the present one as long as I can.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> called on <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; was told he was
                    too ill to see him &#8211; I rather suspect it must have been <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R</ref>
                    that was ill<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Susannah Rickman had recently suffered a miscarriage; see Southey to Mary
                        Barker, 26 May 1806, Letter 1187.</note> &#8211; &amp; in either case am very &#8211; very &#8211; sorry of the intelligence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably heard that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">an Uncle</ref> of mine is dead, who if he had
                    made no will, must have left me a rich man. Certainly rather than <del>xx</del> have been born rich, I would always continue poor;
                    but if wealth had fallen in my way now I think it would have done me no harm. However it was no disappointment as I expected
                    nothing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is my idle season; tho it must be a short one &#8211; for I cannot afford much idleness. I am finishing Espriella,
                    &amp; making a very curious book called The Chronicle of the Cid,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> &#8211; very curious it will be &#8211; but I fear it will get me
                    more credit than money, &#8211; &amp; I stand more in need of pudding than of praise. &#8211; Thalaba has been published piece-meal in the
                    American newspapers;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> &#8211; so long a poem was I believe never <del>xxxx</del> before
                    printed in so singular a way. Remember me at Stockwell.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stockwell Park, Surrey, residence
                        of Thomas Woodroffe Smith (c. 1747&#8211;1811), a wealthy Quaker merchant, and his second wife, Anne Reynolds (dates unknown) of
                        Carshalton. The Smiths were friends of <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref> and
                        Duppa.</note> I mean to review <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> Book upon the Quakers this year.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Clarkson, <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View
                            of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar Customs, Religious Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of
                            the Society of Friends</title> (1806), in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 594&#8211;607.</note> &#8211; Remember
                    me also at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>. I am afraid that family will soon be broken up, &amp; do not like to
                    think so, because I shall never remember old <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford</ref> without
                    remembering many pleasant hours days &amp; weeks which I have past under his roof. God bless you. Do not follow my example, but
                    put me to shame by a letter. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">her
                        sister</ref> desired to be remembered. The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref> and <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P</ref>. enquire for you. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I xxxx on the top of Great Gable<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mountain in the Lake District near Wasdale Head, southwest of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</note> last week &#8211; &amp; he would have sent a sigh toward the Isle of <del>xxxxx</del> Man &#8211; to Miss
                        Scriggen<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> &#8211; only unluckily the wind happened to be the wrong <hi rend="ital">way</hi>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>