<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1277</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2399</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D (undated
                        letters).  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 436&#8211;437.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1277" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1277" type="letter">
        <head>1277. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkins Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-02-15">15
                    February [1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D (undated
                        letters)<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 436&#8211;437.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> That <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>  does not see <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">his brothers</ref>  state is plain from the way in which he writes of him. I
                    have let him see it in the best way I could by advising what he may very likely think very ridiculous, but which I am persuaded is
                    the only chance he has of ever recovering so as to be capable of doing any thing, &#8211; <del>which</del> &lt;it&gt; was &#8211; that <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> should take him as if for a frolic to hear some of the most
                    famous preachers and try to get him <hi rend="ital">assinated</hi> with Methodism &#8211; a sort of <hi rend="ital">assination</hi>
                    which is to other madness what vaccination is to the small pox.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this suggestion,
                        see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 2 February 1807, Letter 1270.</note> If this should take &#8211; which from what I know of
                        <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> is very likely &#8211; it would do just what mercurial girdles
                    do for the itch, draw the disorder to one place &amp; keep it there; &#8211; his madness would find vent in a licit way, &amp; he might
                    be as mad as he pleased with perfect impunity &#8211; yea &amp; <del>&amp; can</del> get credit for it into the bargain. &#8211; You will
                    perceive by the first and last of the letters in this packet that on this subject I am likely to have studied as many cases
                        <del>xx</del> as most people <del>besides</del> in addition to all my Catholick experience which is very great. &#8211; If ever I do
                    any thing in English history it will be to write its Church History &#8211; &amp; there are few subjects which would please me better.
                    In that &amp; in a previous history of the Monastic orders which has been long in my mind, I could say every thing, &#8211; &amp; this
                    is one of my great projects<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> was published
                        in 1824. The history of the monastic orders was never completed.</note> &#8211; if I live to get thro my Portugueze affairs<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; was never completed.</note> &#8211; &lt;for which&gt; By Gods
                    blessing a very few years will now suffice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A John Louis Goldsmid<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1789&#8211;1835), banker and book collector.</note> of
                    Roehampton hearing that I wanted to translate Esplandian<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Las Sergas de
                            Esplandi&#225;n</title>, (1510) one of a series of Spanish chivalric romances by Garci Rodr&#237;guez de Montalvo (1450&#8211;1504) of
                        which <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, which Southey translated in 1803, is the first.</note> wrote to offer me the use of a
                    French set of all the books of the Amadis family. I have thanked him &amp; asked if he has any of the Palmerins<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Palmerins comprise eight books, dating from the early sixteenth century, about the deeds
                        and desires of Palmerin d&#8217;Oliva, emperor of Constantinople, and his descendants. Southey translated the sixth: <title>Palmerin
                            of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; Is
                    this one of the Jews? Jew or Gentile it was very civil, &amp; I am much obliged to him, tho his information happened to be
                    wrong.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your frank was misdated &#8211; but luckily not so heavy as a rascal which cost me 6/5 the other day for a mistake in the
                    year. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> observed upon it that <del>xx</del> his old friend 1806 was a sort of
                        Vampire.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The vampire was a creature new to most Britons, Southey having been one of
                        the first to introduce it to English culture in his 1801 poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer.</title> For more on the franking
                        error mentioned here; see Southey to John Rickman, 30 January [1807] (Letter 1269) and 13 February 1807 (Letter 1274).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some arrangements of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> render it necessary that I
                    should either resolve upon fixing myself here or quitting the place; &#8211; the least evil of the two is to determine upon the former,
                    &#8211; which indeed is hardly any evil, for I <del>am</del> grow more &amp; more rooted to the country &#8211; &amp; certainly should never
                    like any other place so well. Besides it is far cheaper than the South. So I am <del>there</del> devising how to get my books here
                    by water, &amp; rejoicing as much in projecting their arrangement &#8211; as ever Bonaparte can do in portioning out new conquests. The
                    main inconvenience of the situation would be at an end when <del>I</del> my books were collected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have seen neither of the works which you mention &#8211; nor am I likely to see them &#8211; Beloe ought to have made
                    something curious because he is in the Museum &#8211; but he is a British Critic &#8211; &amp; that includes all possible terms of
                        vituperation<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Beloe (1756&#8211;1817), keeper of printed books at the British
                        Museum, 1803&#8211;1806, author of <title>Anecdotes of Literature and Scarce Books</title> (1807&#8211;1812), reviewer for the Tory
                        journal <title>The British Critic</title>.</note> &#8211; Those fellows live in an atmosphere of as impenetrable
                        <del>stupidity</del> darkness as Sir John Maundeviles old Emperor of Persia in his province of Hangson &#8211; if you remember that
                    delectable history.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the largely fantastical <title>The Voyages &amp; Travels of Sir
                            John Mandevile</title> (many English editions from 1375), the province Hanyson of the country of Abchaz is described as
                        being in a perpetual darkness sent by God to protect Christians from destruction at the hands of the Persian emperor&#8217;s
                        army.</note> No light ever penetrates into the vacant interlunar cavities of their <del>perixxxx</del> pericrania &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> has begun very early to collect his works<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Ballads and Lyrical Pieces</title> was published in 1806.</note> &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your nameless daughter must be <del>xx</del> now advancing towards weeks of kissability, &#8211; &amp; it will soon be
                    time to instruct her in the first commandment of the nursery &#8211; <del>which is</del> thou shalt not piddle thy father.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-02-15">Sunday 15. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>