<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1253</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2375</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don.D3.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 432&#8211;434.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1253" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1253" type="letter">
        <head>1253. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-12-30">30
                        December 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. H. Southey. M.D./ with W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK/ 8<lb />Endorsement: 1806
                        <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don.D3<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 432&#8211;434.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not received any answer as yet from <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> &#8211; for which
                    there must be some reason, &#8211; perhaps his letter is waiting for a frank &#8211; I expect that he will be able to lessen your Hospital
                    expences materially.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the newspaper, in the first place it was 2 &amp; not 3 guineas per week &#8211; in the second I could not get you
                    the situation, &amp; in the third should not advise you to accept it if I could. &#8211; Here are a few more reviewing books &#8211; which
                    shall be sent to London to you as soon as you let me know where to direct them. &#8211; &amp; in the parcel certain drafts for dinners.
                    &#8211; The first Tuesday you are in town call at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4 Tavistock Street, Bedford Square &#8211; it leads from Tottenham
                    Court Road into the square thus &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">[sketch map]</p>
        <p rend="indent1">About one o clock you will find <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> there, &#8211; that being his day &amp;
                    hour. I have desired him to introduce you at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burns<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burns
                        (dates unknown), a member of the English Factory, Lisbon. For Southey&#8217;s letter to May, see Southey to John May, 29 December
                        1806, Letter 1252.</note> &#8211; my letters will be to <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, &#8211; to the <ref target="people.html#TuffinJohnFurnall">River Tuffin</ref>, &#8211; &amp; one from <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    to <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> which will introduce you to a pleasant house. You have
                    heard me speak of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne &#8211; of all human beings whom I have ever seen she is the most thoroughly excellent.
                    I will also depute you to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &#8211; you need not fear
                    having acquaintance in plenty. When you write to me consign the letter to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall not join &lt;you&gt; quite so soon as was my purpose. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My
                        Uncle</ref> urges me to lay every thing else aside for the sake of getting out the portion of my history which relates to
                    Brazil as speedily as possible.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The prospective flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil
                        (occurred 29 November 1807) prompted Southey, at his uncle Herbert Hill&#8217;s request, to begin a history of Brazil, using papers
                        sent him by Hill and stored by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>; see Southey to John Rickman, 23 December
                        1806, Letter 1247. Southey had asked <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Wynn</ref> to use his position as Under
                        Secretary of State in the Home Office, to ascertain whether the government might provide him support during the preparation of
                        a work likely to supply useful information in the new political situation.</note> the MSS. materials which he has been half
                    his life collecting, are of exceeding value &amp; importance &#8211; &amp; there never can be a time when information of this kind would
                    be more eagerly received. I have therefore sent to London &amp; Bristol for all my books &amp; MSS. upon this subject &amp; shall
                    probably remain here till I get thro them, unless any lucky chance, such as a shower of gold, should enable me to remove
                    Southbound &amp; settle. This will not alter your plans; &#8211; when you have gone thro your hospital course you are big enough &amp;
                    ugly enough to get to Lisbon by yourself. &#8211; if <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> should not wish me to
                    come over &amp; compleat this business there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Find William Dimond<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wyatt Dimond (c.1750&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>),
                        actor and theatre manager.</note> out, if he be in town. You may learn by inquiring of his publisher. He will be very glad to
                    see you, &amp; is very likely to have certain things called orders at his disposal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not whether <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> will lecture or not.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to a letter to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>,
                        Coleridge was to &#8216;lecture &#8216;at the Royal Institution upon the Principles common to the Fine Arts&#8217;; see Southey to Charles
                        Danvers, 13 January 1807, Letter 1258. He did not in fact lecture there until 1808, on the subjects of the Principles of
                        Poetry, Shakespeare and Milton.</note> He went from hence this day fortnight to join the <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> in Leicestershire,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Over the
                        winter of 1806&#8211;1807 Wordsworth and his family were living in a farmhouse owned by <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref> near his new house at Coleorton, Leicestershire.</note> &amp; took <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Job</ref> with him, &#8211; they assuring him that the cough which the children had was
                    not the hooping cough. On his arrival he finds that it is. But as they disregarded the danger of bringing <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> into it for the sake of having his company, so is he pleased with
                    theirs that he keeps him in it. If Hartley was to catch it &amp; die of it &#8211; &amp; poor fellow there cannot possibly be a worse
                    subject for the disease, <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> would break his heart &#8211; &amp; deserve to
                    do it. &#8211; It strikes me that he will not lecture &#8211; tho his name has been announced. <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> &amp; the other children <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> are to join him at Bristol in the early spring &amp; go to his family in Devonshire,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s brother, <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George</ref> was a schoolmaster at
                        Ottery St Mary in Devon.</note> &#8211; so that we shall have the house to ourselves &#8211; I know not for how long, &#8211; but were they
                    fairly to quit it, greatly should I be tempted to have the study plaistered &amp; here take up my abiding place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> asked me if I knew any thing of Ensor<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ensor (1769&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), Irish political writer, who published a treatise on
                            <title>The Principles of Morality</title> in 1801. He wrote many books and pamphlets on Irish politics, in which he
                        attacked the English government.</note> &#8211; since his letters came I hear that he is the brother in law of Isaac Weld &#8211; who went
                    to America to see whether it would be wise in him to emigrate there, &#8211; did not like it, &#8211; wrote a book to say so, &#8211; &amp; then had
                    the modesty to ask a reward from the Irish Government upon the merit of the Anti-American book. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Weld (1774&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), Irish explorer and topographical writer. In 1795, he travelled to
                        the United States and Canada, spending over two years in America. In 1799 he published his account of his <title>Travels
                            Through the States of North America and the Provinces of Upper and Lower Canada During the Years 1795, 1796 and
                            1797.</title> His book was well received in Britain, but was negative about aspects of American life compared to the
                        Canadian territories.</note> This Weld is now at Ambleside, &amp; is said by <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> to be a much less able man in conversation
                    than his book promised, &amp; moreover a very unpleasant one. He is a great coxcomb &amp; ostentatious of atheism, which he says
                    is also the opinion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ensor &#8211; as <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> T.</ref>
                    surmised Ensor is therefore Irish &amp; most probably in the revolutionary politics. I have not seen his book</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Write to Lisbon. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is appointed to the Pallas Frigate.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, launched in 1804, was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was
                        Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the capture of many
                        French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown).</note> I have not heard from
                    him since he set off to join her, but understand he is First Lieutenant &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; I am in much hurry, being very eager to clear off all <del>that is</del> on hand that I may set
                    fairly to work upon Brazil. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> T.</ref> &amp; to his
                    father &amp; mother especially &#8211; to others at your discretion,
                    making remembrances when you think them due &#8211; I will only particularize <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-12-30">Tuesday. Dec 30. 1806. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>