<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1239</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2361</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS 4812D.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    429&#8211;431.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1239" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1239" type="letter">
        <head>1239. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1806-11-25">25
                    November 1806</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Wales MS 4812D<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    429&#8211;431.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> When first I thought it probable that the court of Portugal would remove to Rio Janeiro<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 29 November 1807, as the French invaded Portugal, a British squadron under the command of Sir William
                        Sidney Smith (1764&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>) escorted the Portuguese Prince Regent, John VI (the Duke of Braganza)
                        (1767&#8211;1826), and the Queen, his mother, across the Atlantic. The Portuguese monarchy then ruled from Brazil.</note> I felt an
                    inclination to follow them, which arose more from curiosity than from any wiser motive. On cooler reflection South America seems
                    an unfit place for me. I should be afraid to carry my family to a country where none of the comforts of Europe are to be found,
                    &amp; few even of the decencies; &amp; to go without them for any length of time, is out of the question. Books supply the want of
                    society to me sufficiently. But how it would be where I should have neither, I cannot say. This however is comparatively of little
                    importance, &#8211; amusement &amp; occupation may be found everywhere by one who knows where to look for them. But my employments would
                    be disturbed &#8211; it would be impossible to carry a library with me, there will be none there. &#8211; &amp; to suspend my history for some
                    years would be every way disadvantageous. &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> were I to die what I have done would be of little value, &#8211; as little
                    as that of the materials of a great house compared to the finished building. I am not made of very lasting stuff &#8211; a warmer
                    climate than this is certainly desirable for one who has a better chance of inheriting consumption than of succeeding to any other
                    inheritance, &#8211; but perhaps the disorders to which Europeans are subject in a climate so totally different as that of S America
                    from their own, the ignorance of the native physicians. &amp; the inexperience of any of our own who might be there, more than
                    counterbalance any advantage which could be derived from southern sunshine. I wish you would talk this over with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, &#8211; my present opinion is that unless I could go either to Portugal or Holland,
                    it is better that I should remain in England, &#8211;but I will do whatever you may think best. You perhaps have an ambition for me
                    which I do not feel for myself. I have no wish for any other rank in society than what literature can give me. Could I chuse my
                    own fortune it should be to have the place of Historiographer created for me,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The post
                        of Historiographer Royal was held, until his death, by Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>). Despite Southey&#8217;s hopes.
                        it was then given to James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> with such a salary as would be adequate to
                    my habits of life; I could then accumulate enough by my writings for my children</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may be sure that those lines upon <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref>  shall never
                    get into print or be seen by any but my nearest friends.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, 17&#8211;18 October 1806, Letter 1228.</note> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">old man</ref> thanked God upon his deathbed that he had cut me off. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">His brother</ref>
                     has succeeded to about 30,000&#163; which he is utterly incapable of enjoying. A few days after the funeral
                    250&#163; were paid him. What shall I do with this money? said he to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">his sister</ref>. I&#8217;ll tell you what to do with it was her reply; send it to the young men. He has done more than I expected. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>  &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                     went down to <del>xx</del> him; &#8211; he gave them 40 &#8211; to cloath themselves, &amp; when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> left him another ten for his journey. He has talked of offering me a
                    house in Taunton which is his till the boy comes of age to whom that &amp; the Dorsetshire estate has been left; but this is only
                    talk I believe, &amp; was not intended to reach me. If he should make the offer I should accept it, because somewhere I must go
                    &amp; that speedily. My books are spoiling at Bristol,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers,
                        18 October 1806, Letter 1229.</note> &#8211; &amp; if Adam supplants <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Abbot</ref>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Adam (1751&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), politician and advocate, did not replace Abbott
                        as Speaker of the House of Commons.</note> as the Courier says, those which are at <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> will be unhoused, &amp; what I shall do with them God knows. This house I have outgrown, &amp; it will no
                    longer hold us. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southeys</ref>  offer therefore would be so seasonable
                    that I would willingly risk the consequences of having him for my neighbour, utterly illiterate as he is; &#8211; but he will not make
                    it. &amp; I must look out for myself, tho as compleatly undetermined where to go as Adam &amp; Eve when they were turned out, with
                    this difference that the whole earth was theirs. &amp; I have not a single spot in it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Seal the inclosed with your great seal</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> God bless you </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-11-25">Nov. 25. 1806 </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>