<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1214</idno><idno type="nines">rce2336</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 427–429.Dating note: Southey states before dating at the bottom of the letter that it ‘has lain a
                        long while unfinished’.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1214" type="letter"><head>1214. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1806-09-03">[started before, and continued on] 3 September 1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W
                        Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M P./ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 427–429.<lb/>Dating note: Southey states before dating at the bottom of the letter that it ‘has lain a
                        long while unfinished’.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> How heartily I congratulate you upon the tidings communicated in your last.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Mary Wynn was expecting her first child; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [started before, and continued on] 17
                        September 1806, Letter 1216.</note> You would better understand if you could see the hundred ways <del>with</del> &lt;in&gt;
                    which I play the fool to <del>amuse</del> &lt;delight&gt; my daughter &amp; myself at the same time. You have a new pleasure in
                    store, which no man knows any thing about till he feels it. – My young one is not expected till the end of next month, yet I
                    strongly suspect that <del>xx xxx</del> the arrival will be sooner, &amp; should not be surprised at it any day or any hour.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert, the Southeys’ first son, was born 11 October 1806.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Is there any truth in the reports about the Prince of Brazils removal?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This
                        did not happen until 29 November 1807, when, as the French invaded Portugal, a British squadron under the command of Sir
                        William Sidney Smith (1764–1840; <title>DNB</title>) escorted the Portuguese Prince Regent, John VI (the Duke of Braganza)
                        (1767–1826), and the Queen, his mother, across the Atlantic. The Portuguese monarchy then ruled from Brazil.</note> If the
                    thing were as probable as it is desirable I should heartily rejoice, &amp; even be better pleased with the prospect of visiting S.
                    America than Portugal. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> suppressed the most <del>obnox</del> violent stanzas of his songs, tho
                    they were sung in full force.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> As well as longer works of poetry, Scott composed shorter
                        ballads based on Border traditions, and had just published <title>Ballads and Lyrical Pieces</title>, a collection of patriotic Scottish
                        ballads and songs.</note> I am a little surprized at him, – not at the opinions themselves, but at the ungracious avowal of
                    them. Scotts politics were always of a <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;true&gt; fire – &amp; – faggot kind, but he ought not to have insulted
                    an administration which had behaved so handsomely to him, – &amp; if the bird had been in the bush instead of in the hand, I
                    suspect he would not have done it. – The House of Commons should stigmatise Lord M. by some explanatory Law, to show that they do
                    not acquiesce in such an acquittal.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742–1811;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War 1794–1801 and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804. During 1802–1805,
                        Melville’s use of public funds while Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782–1800), was investigated by a Royal Commission. After its
                        report, on 9 April 1805, Melville was censured in the House of Commons for allowing Alexander Trotter (dates unknown), the
                        naval paymaster, to misuse public funds. Melville resigned and impeachment proceedings were commenced against him. His trial
                        opened on 29 April 1806, attracting a great deal of public interest, but by 12 June Melville had been acquitted of nearly all
                        the charges.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The mention of Banks is by <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Banks (1735–1805; <title>DNB</title>), a sculptor who is discussed in Duppa’s contribution to Southey’s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807), Letter 23.</note>
                    he understands these things, &amp; I do not. I have just finished an account of <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna
                        Southcott</ref>, which, if you are not well informed upon the subject – will surprize you.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> An account of the millenarian prophet and writer, Joanna Southcott, is given in Letter 70 of <title>Letters
                            from England</title>.</note> You will hardly <del>credit</del> believe that such blasphemies should be tolerated, or such
                    credulity be found in England at this time. It would be a fit thing to ship her &amp; a ship load of her disciples off for Botany
                    Bay.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Palmerin has taken me in for more work than I expected.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        published an English translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> Its
                    descriptions are all mutilated, the <del>xx costumes</del> more curious customs always omitted &amp; the whole so diluted with
                    wordy amplifications &amp; long speeches that the English Romance is nearly as long again as the Portugueze. – good evidence for
                    the originality of the latter. I shall insert all the omissions which are of the slightest value, &amp; cut out as much of the
                    rigmarolery as possible. If it sells I will then print Primaleon, which precedes it in the family series, &amp; is a better
                        Romance,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The cycle of romance stories of Palmerin d’Oliva, emperor of Constantinople,
                        his sons, Palmendos and Primaleon, and grandson, Palmerin of England. <title>Primaleon</title> was the second book in
                        the series, written by an anonymous Spanish author (probably Francisco Vázquez; dates unknown) and published in 1516. It was
                        translated from the French by Anthony Munday (bap. 1560–1633; <title>DNB</title>), between 1595 and 1619. Its popularity can
                        be established from the fact that ten Spanish editions were published between 1512 and 1588. <title>Palmerin de
                            Inglaterra</title> by Francisco Moraes Cabral (1547) is the fourth book in the series.</note> tho now of less celebrity,
                    for Palmerin has a certain degree of fame, founded upon the praise in D Quixote, which I shall take care to <del>print</del>
                    &lt;insert&gt; in the advertisement.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616),
                            <title>The History and Adventures of the Renowned Don Quixote</title>, trans. Tobias Smollett (1721–1771;
                            <title>DNB</title>), 6 vols (London, 1792), a priest praises the stylistic clarity of <title>Palmerin of England</title>,
                        describing it as a unique work that is to be esteemed for two reasons ‘first, because, it is in itself excellent; and
                        secondly, because it is said to have been composed by an ingenious king of Portugal’ (I, p. 46).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Did I tell you that I had seen M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dickson?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Untraced.</note> – we met at the Windermere boat race – where Curwen<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian
                        Curwen (1756–1828; <title>DNB</title>), Workington landowner and MP for Carlisle, lived at Belle Isle on Windermere.</note>
                    dines with as many gentlemen as chuse to give half-a guinea for the vilest ordinary dinner that ever baulked an appetite, – &amp;
                    then gets praised in the newspaper for his hospitality.</p><p rend="center">————</p><p rend="indent1"> This letter has lain a long while unfinished. We have had the measles in the house, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref> is just safe thro them, tho by no means recovered from their effects.
                    You have had a letter from <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord H</ref> – to acknowledge my letter of thanks<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s letter to Lord Holland; see Southey to Lord Holland, 10 August 1806, Letter
                        1209.</note> – a supererogation of civility on his part. In mine I pointed out to him the Walking Picture of the Castle of
                        Otranto<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Horace Walpole’s (4th Earl of Orford; 1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>)
                        Gothic novel <title>The Castle of Otranto</title> (London, 1764) a figure in a painting walks out of the frame (pp.
                        19–20).</note> in the Jerusalem of Lope.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lope Felix de Vega Carpio (1562–1635),
                            <title>La Jerusalém Conquistada</title> (1609), Canto I.</note> Eight years ago I got the poem from Dr Williams Library in
                    Redcross Street,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Williams’ library, London, was established by a bequest from the
                        dissenting minister, Daniel Williams (c.1643–1716; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; analysed it – this will turn to some
                    account now, first in reviewing his book<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Henry Richard Fox, 3rd Lord
                        Holland, <title>Some Account of the Life and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1806), in the <title>Annual Review
                            for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 397–411.</note> &amp; secondly as I will put the analysis in some order – versify the extracts
                    &amp; <del>xxx</del> insert it in Longmans new Magazine,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The short-lived
                            <title>Athenaeum, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807–1809), published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> – into which I think of emptying a whole bundle of unemployed
                    notes in the shape of scraps, – having them at hand it is as well to get paid for them first &amp; use them afterwards. Did I tell
                    you that Thalaba has been printed piecemeal in an American newspaper? Probably the first time that so long a poem
                    ever made its appearance in such a shape. – If small profits answered as well to authors as Mr Lackington<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either James Lackington (1746–1815), bookseller and publisher, or his cousin George Lackington (1777–1844),
                        who took over the publishing firm of Lackington, Allen &amp; Co. after James Lackington’s retirement in 1798.</note> says they
                    do to booksellers, certainly I ought to be in the way of making a good fortune –</p><p rend="indent1"> A waterspout has fallen lately within five miles of us on the <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>
                    road. The people here call it with more propriety a <hi rend="ital">burst</hi>. A thunder cloud discharged its waters upon this
                    end of Hellvellyn, &amp; before rain enough had fallen in the valley to make the house eaves drop, the torrent came rushing down
                    the gills in Legberthwaite<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Legburthwaite is a village southeast of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> and north of Thirlmere, in the Lake District.</note> with force &amp; fury – to
                    use the very language in which one of the inhabitants described it to me. You may <del>xxxxxxx</del> form some notion of its force
                    when I tell you that it has covered the fields with gravel &amp; stones – that the water crost the road (about two hundred yards
                    at least from the foot of the mountain, with such power as to bear down twelve yards of a <del>x</del> wall five feet in length
                    clean from the ground, &amp; scatter the stones twenty &amp; thirty yards off over the field. We had three such bursts last year,
                    neither of them so destructive as this – &amp; till last year there had <del>not</del> been only one <del>for</del>since the great
                    one fifty nine years ago – of which you may read in all the books about Cumberland.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had a sick house. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> was seized with an ague as soon as he
                    came. It did him this service, that it enabled him – indeed obliged him – to decline an appointment to a sloop of war that came
                    after him – a berth by no means desirable, nor indeed respectable for one of his standing. I was obliged to put off <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> – &amp; sorely unwilling to do it – but I hope &amp; expect that
                    he will come in October.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-09-03">Wednesday Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 3. 1806 </date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>