<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1501</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2623</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30928.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 84&#8211;85 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1501" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1501" type="letter">
        <head>1501. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1808-09-04">4 September
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30928<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 84&#8211;85 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was very anxious to hear from you, after we had heard of poor M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Jardine&#8217;s death.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Widow of David Jardine (1766&#8211;1797), Minister of the Trim Street Unitarian Chapel, Bath. She was
                        the daughter of George Webster of Hampstead. The Jardines owned a small estate at Pickwick, near Bath. Danvers was now to
                        become the guardian of the orphaned children.</note> What the shock must be to you I will know, &amp; I was fearful least she
                    might have neglected to make a will &amp; so the guardianship of the children might have devolved upon persons whom she would not
                    perhaps have chosen. Your charge will now give you new anxieties in life, but it will give new interest as well, &amp; I heartily
                    rejoice that they are in such hands: &#8211; for my own sake too I must rejoice in any arrangement which will bring you once more, &amp;
                    more than once more to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. &#8211; The Legacy is indeed unhealthy. it can however only be
                    suspended, &#8211; not lost, &#8211; for of course, David will fulfill his mothers will as soon as it is in his power.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask me about my Laudanum recipe for a cold &#8211; It retains its effect, but I am afraid to use it, because the
                    slightest dose immediately acts upon my liver: &#8211; eight drops will act as an aperient;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        laxative.</note> &amp; the f&#230;ces are quite white, &amp; the discharge attended with the same heat as if, on the contrary, it
                    were a bilious diarrh&#339;a. Tell <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> this, as an anomaly which may be worth speculating
                    upon. It has recurred so often that I am <del>xxx</del> perfectly certain of the connection between cause &amp; effect. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> An odd circumstance has occurred this evening, greatly to the honour &amp; glory of your Aunt.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers&#8217;s aunt was the traveller Celia Fiennes (1662&#8211;1741; <title>DNB</title>). Danvers gave
                        Southey a manuscript of her diary, which Southey drew on for <title>Letters from England</title>. Extracts from it were also
                        included in his and Coleridge&#8217;s <title>Omniana</title> (1812).</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                    Robert Wolseley (Sir Williams son) are lodging in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>; &#8211; they brought letters to me from <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref>, &amp; we see a good deal of them.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Robert Wolseley (d. 1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740&#8211;1817). Wolseley married a Miss Hand; her first name and dates are not known. The family seat was at Wolseley Park, Rugeley, Staffordshire, near Seward&#8217;s home at Lichfield.</note> This evening we drank tea with them, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> W.
                    mentioned that Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> was famous for his fine strawberries: &#8211; it directly occurred to me that there was a very
                    remarkable strawberry mentioned in &#8216;my aunts&#8217; journal &#8211; &amp; that it was at Wolseley. I could not be satisfied till this point
                    was ascertained, &#8211; home I came &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W. with me, &amp; there we found not only the strawberry (the breed of
                    which now seems to be lost) but such a minute description of the house &amp; grounds as has delighted him; &#8211; &amp; he is now
                    transcribing it for old Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> &#8211; as the most interesting piece of family history they have ever yet met with.
                    The then Lady Wolseley was your Aunts Aunt, &amp; the house was her head quarters for six weeks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This book of your Aunts is certainly a very curious one. D Manuel<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        putative author of Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807).</note> has been indebted to it more than once, &amp; the translator of that valuable work is of the opinion that this
                    M.S. ought to be printed, as a great store house for county historians &amp; family history; Every person whose family is
                    mentioned would derive great pleasure from seeing what is there said &#8211; &amp; if a subscription could be obtained just to clear the
                    whole cost of the impression, I should think it a very desirable thing to print it, &#8211; not as a book for public sale, &#8211; but just
                    the number for the subscribers. It is very probable that this could be effected. Shall I try it? that is ascertain the expence,
                    &amp; put out my feelers to see what subscribers are to be found; &#8211; as for profit that is out of the question; &#8211; it may possibly
                    occur, &amp; if it should &#8211; God knows you have heavy call for it. But in case the thing can be done, I could see it transcribed
                    here, &amp; correct the press &amp; manage the whole business, only for the pleasure of the thing &#8211; as the man said to Shepherd of
                        Liverpool<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rev. Dr William Shepherd (1768&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), pastor at the
                        English Presbyterian Chapel, Gateacre, Liverpool. Shepherd lived at The Nook, Gateacre, whence he and his wife ran a boarding
                        school. Southey had met the couple in Liverpool when he visited Roscoe in February 1808.</note> when he was going to shoot a
                    favourite goat for him. A preface of a dozen lines might state the fitness of <del>xxx</del> printing it, &amp; fully justify it.
                    Your Aunt could neither write English nor spell it, but she was a woman of great observation, &amp; her journal contains more
                    information concerning the state of England at the end of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century than is to be found in any other
                    work of the time, or even to be gleaned from all. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Cid<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        (1808).</note> will speedily reach you, &amp; <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rexs</ref> copy in the same parcel. You will
                    have seen my Letters advertised for a new edition.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters written during
                            a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797) were being reprinted in an expanded form as <title>Letters written
                            during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> By copious omissions &amp; some valuable
                    additions I have converted them into a respectable work &#8211; so much indeed altered &amp; amended that it shall be sent to displace
                    the former one from your shelf as soon as it is ready.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know perhaps that <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> is gone to Spain. I thought he
                    would go &#8211; he wrote to me from Falmouth, &#8211; a letter truly characteristic of the man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I learn to day by a note from <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> accompanying a proof that <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is with his brother at Huntspill,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        small town near Bridgwater in Somerset.</note> employed in making a selection from Miltons Prose Works,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Extracts from the Prose Works of Milton</title> (1809).</note> &#8211; which is an employment so much like idleness that I
                    should think it would <del>suit</del> just suit him. Some time ago he broke a blood-vessel, but is recovering from that accident.
                    Not a line has he written me since his departure from this place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The things from Mrs Rings<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> This could be the wife of Joseph Ring
                        (1772&#8211;1813), Sarah (n&#233;e Wallis; dates unknown) whom he married in 1795. Joseph Ring was a member of a family of Bristol
                        potters and had taken over the family business selling earthenware, china and glass in May 1807. However his mother, Elizabeth
                        Ring (dates unknown), also ran an independent concern at Bridge Street, Bristol.</note> should come by water, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> will probably have something to send with them, &#8211; &amp; we are in want of a
                    coffee-pot, concerning which I had better say what little is to be said, &amp; then give you full powers to chuse one. As silver
                    is out of the question, &amp; plated-metal an abomination, bronze &#8211; like what urns are made of is the best substitute, &amp; I
                    think I have seen coffee pot of it, in a sort of jug shape. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> does not
                    &lt;like&gt; the little urns which look children of the great ones.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Kehama<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> is in rapid progress. My new Travels<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project was not completed.</note> are begun, &amp; probab[ly] I shall soon go to press with my History<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> let
                    the price of paper be what it will. &#8211; To my great joy <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">AAikin</ref> is deposed from his
                    Annual throne. He mangled my articles so cruelly, &amp; let his <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Aunt</ref> &amp; his
                        sister<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy Aikin (1781&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>).</note> indulge themselves in so
                    many innuendos &amp; inventions of detraction at my expence, that it is a real advantage to me to have the Review rid of them. I
                    am so glad of the change that I shall review several articles for the next volume, which otherwise I should not have done. The new
                    Editor <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">Thomas Rees</ref> is very civil to me, &#8211; &amp; better fitted for the office than K
                        <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur</ref> in the main requisites of method &amp; dispatch.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I shall look after the cork jacket that it may be at hand next summer for its ingenious inventor. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yours affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-09-04">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 4. 1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>