<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1635</idno><idno type="nines">rce2757</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4863 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        274–277.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1635" type="letter"><head>1635. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1809-05-24">24 May
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1
                        June<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4863 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        274–277.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-05-24">May 24. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is likely that there will be a Review started excluding all contemporary publications, &amp; chusing its
                    subjects from all others, – its title Rhadamanthus.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Greek mythology Rhadamanthus was a
                        wise king who was one of the judges of the dead. Southey’s plans for this periodical were never fulfilled.</note> This is a
                    scheme of mine. I threw it out in a hint to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the letter to Scott, see Southey to Walter Scott, 11 March 1809, Letter 1597.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> came here on his way from London, commissioned to treat with me
                    concerning it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Ballantyne’s visit, see Southey to John Rickman, 16 May [1809] (Letter
                        1629), and Southey to Thomas Southey, [16 May 1809] (Letter 1630).</note> The terms proposed are 100 a year for the Editor,
                    ten guineas a sheet for the writers, the place of printing Edinburgh, the mode quarterly 5/ numbers. Definitely settled it is not,
                    but I have little doubt that it will be so. I hope I am not wrong in counting <del>you</del> upon you as my right hand. Scott
                    proposes to bear a part, &amp; will be a very useful assistant, but I reply upon you &amp; upon myself to build up &amp; support
                    the work.</p><p rend="indent1"> Setting aside the moral advantage that we neither hurt the feelings nor the fortunes of any person, – there will
                    there will be the main advantage of chusing any subject, &amp; never having a dull one forced upon us. As soon as things are
                    compleatly arranged I will write to you stating what subjects are looked out for myself for the first two or three numbers, &amp;
                    you meantime will hit upon what may best suit yourself. I should request from you an article upon political oeconomy, – any branch
                    on which you feel most disposed to write.</p><p rend="indent1"> Since you heard from me last many events have taken place in my family. I had a <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">daughter</ref> born in March, – &amp; yesterday we buried <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">the one</ref> who was born last year, – a severer sorrow than perhaps any one who has never
                    experienced it can believe. My <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">little boy</ref> has had the croup &amp; been saved from
                    it, – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">his mother</ref> was alarmingly ill during her lying-in – thus you see the house has
                    scarcely been free from sickness. – But for these interruptions you would ere this have heard the Kehama was compleated.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> I am in the penultimate section. – You wish the same time had been bestowed
                    upon a subject which had any possibility of becoming popular, – my two next poems will satisfy you in this point, they are to be
                        Pelayo,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> This poem became <title>Roderick Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note>
                    &amp; Robin Hood.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Drafts of this poem were not made until late 1823, when Southey began to
                        work on it as a collaborative effort with Caroline Bowles (1786–1854; <title>DNB</title>). It was published incomplete, edited
                        by Bowles, as <title>Robin Hood: A Fragment</title> (1847).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am afraid the Quarterly will proclaim itself Anti-Jacobine, &amp; in that case of course we part. My defence of
                    the Missionaries attracted much notice, &amp; has made Sidney Smith very angry in the last Edinburgh.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of and leading contributors to the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title> reviewed the activities of British missionaries in India negatively, Southey opposed his
                        views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Smith’s review of ‘Ingram on Methodism’ appeared in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 11 (January 1808), 341–362, and he reviewed ‘Indian Missions’ in the next issue 12 (April 1808), 151–181).
                        In the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226, Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative
                            to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)],
                            <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the
                            Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the
                            Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas
                        Twining (1776–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of
                            Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society,
                            as Directed to India</title> (1807). In his turn, Smith responded in ‘Styles on Methodists and Missions’, in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 14 (April 1809), 40–50.</note> I shall make &lt;him&gt; more angry one of these days
                        <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> by attacking the Methodists <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del>, &amp; &lt;yet&gt; showing why they must inevitably
                    succeed against such an establishment &amp; such dissenters as ours; &lt;&amp; such opponents as he.&gt; It is neither by
                    invective nor by ridicule that any thing can be done against them, &amp; to oppose them by ordinary orthodox means is as hopeless
                    as it is to present regular armies against Buonaparte, till they are formed upon his own plan. The way must be to split them into
                    Moderates &amp; Jacobines, – to make concessions, to show what are the good principles in human nature to which they owe part of
                    their success, &amp; to borrow their tactics. John Wesley<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wesley (1703–1791;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Church of England clergyman and a founder of Methodism.</note> Life &amp; Works will form one of the
                    first subjects in Rhadamanthus.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Though Southey’s plans did not materialise, he published
                            <title>The Life of John Wesley and the Origin and Progress of Methodism</title> in 1820.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Had we a Cabinet of any ability, I believe that at this moment Buonaparte might receive his death-blow. Being
                    myself for thorough reform, – for Forsyth-ing the rotten tree of the Constitution,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert
                        Forsyth (1766–1846; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish lawyer and writer and former associate of the Scottish democrats
                        transported for treason in 1794, who advocated root and branch reform of parliament. See his <title>Political
                            Fragments</title> (1830).</note> &amp; if that did not do, – for planting a new one in its place, – I care not about the
                    struggle of parties, &amp; grow <del>xxxx</del> to perceive that there is the same utter lack of <del>xxxx</del> common honesty
                    &amp; common talents in both. Of the two I believe I hate the Whigs the worst, for their rascally failings towards Spain, – &amp;
                    of the Whigs Whitbread<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Whitbread (1764–1815; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician.</note> for the way in which he always speaks of Buonaparte. <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref> will do something in Spain, having <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">his brother</ref> at the head of the army, but there is not vigour in the
                    Cabinet to second him with sufficient force – By the by – that wretched article upon Spain in the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                    Quarterly is by <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ellis
                        [with <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>] reviewed <title>Exposé des Manoeuvres et des Intrigues qui
                            ont Préparé l’Usurpation de la Couronne d’Espagne, et des Moyens Employés par l’Empereur des Francais pour la Mettre á
                            Exécution…; Traduit de l’Espagnol par M. Peltier</title> [alternative title <title>Affaires d’Espagne</title>] (1808) and
                        Pedro Cevallos Guerra (1760–1840), <title>Conféderation des Royaumes et Provinces d’Espagne contre Buonaparte</title> ([1810])
                        in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 1–19.</note> My opinion respecting that country has never for a
                    moment been shaken. Portugal was three score years under the Philips, – yet all those years they were systematically preparing the
                    revolution which restored to them their own line of Kings. No usurper will ever be safe upon that throne. I am firmly persuaded
                    that there is more real patriotism among the Spaniards than would be found among any other people under heaven.</p><p rend="indent1"> A letter by this nights post informs me of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>
                        marriage.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Southey had married <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary-Harriet Sealy</ref> the daughter of a Lisbon acquaintance of Southey’s.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> If M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Martin<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Julia Martin, née Smith
                            (dates unknown) born in Norwich, sister of James Edward Smith (1759–1828; <title>DNB</title>) the botanist, who married in
                            1804 Thomas Martin (1769–1850), first a Unitarian minister in Yarmouth, then a Liverpool merchant and Secretary of the
                            Liverpool Royal Institution. The Martins were members of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William Roscoe</ref>
                            circle; Southey met them on his visit to Liverpool in February 1808.</note> be at Norwich thank her for me, for the Memoir
                        of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rathbone.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Rathbone (1757–1809), a Liverpool
                            ship-owner and merchant and a Quaker, who opposed the slave trade. Southey possibly refers to his authorship of <title>A
                                Memoir of the Proceedings of the Society called Quakers, Belonging to the Monthly Meeting of Hardshaw, in Lancashire
                                …</title> (1805).</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>