<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1102</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2224</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4851 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        93&#8211;97.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1102" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1102" type="letter">
        <head>1102. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1805-09-02">2 September
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 14 October<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4851<lb /> Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        93&#8211;97.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; the women are at a ball. I have swallowed a solitary
                        <del>supper</del> meal &amp; am writing after supper &#8211; a thing which I never did half a &lt;dozen&gt; times in my life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You seem to have mistaken my meaning &#8211; do not suppose that I am not quite satisfied with the quantum<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;amount&#8217;.</note> &amp; quite gratified with the quomodo<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;manner&#8217;.</note> of your praise, &#8211; that I like mere praise &#8211; or that I dislike <del>any</del>
                    &lt;all&gt; censure. All I wish is that you &amp; I should not differ about what the faults are.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to his poem <title>Madoc</title> (1805), which Taylor reviewed for the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 19 (July 1805), 656&#8211;658.</note> I perceive a want of jewelry, &#8211; which is remediable; &#8211; a bad story which
                    is incurable. clumsy butchery in the Section Goervyl,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 2, Book 16.</note> &#8211; &amp; a catastrophe which transfers the readers interest from the hero to
                    the enemy,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The poem ends with Yuhidthiton, the remaining leader of the defeated and
                        chastened Aztecas, leading his people into exile, rather than with Madoc, the Welsh colonist, presiding over a new American
                        civilisation. These alterations were not incorporated. For an account of the publication history of <title>Madoc</title>, see
                        the editor&#8217;s introduction to <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II.</note> both faults which I will eradicate. I do not perceive the levelness of manner. On the contrary I think the diversity
                    greater than in any other such poem: that 1. many parts are in a loose dramatic verse, 2. some in a high declamatory tone, 3. some
                    of a steady sober elevation, 4. others mere verse without poetry, aiming at nothing more than to carry on the tale with as little
                    loss of time as possible, &amp; others 5. the fewest of course &amp; the best, where either the personage or the poet are under
                    the influence of passion. I have figured them to specify instances. &#8211; 1. the book about Bangor. the scene with Goagan. the first
                    introduction of Neolin. 2. the festival of the dead. 3. The opening of the Gorsedd: the opening of the second part after the first
                    paragraph. 4. Cadwallons narrative &amp; most of the narrated narrations &#8211; i.e. when any body tells a story. the last class need
                    not be enumerated &#8211; for they lie in single sentences chiefly. <del>xxxx</del> &#8211; the scene with Llewellyn is the finest passage in
                    the whole.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Llewelyn &#8216;the Great&#8217; (c. 1173&#8211;1240), Prince of Gwynedd and effective ruler of
                        Wales in his later years. The scene Southey refers to, Madoc&#8217;s meeting with Llewelyn on Bardsey, occurs in Part 1, Book 13 of
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805). For the full text of the poem see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), II.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now loveliness of manner I think the characteristic of Leonidas<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Glover (1712&#8211;1785; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Leonidas, A Poem</title> (1737).</note> &amp; Virgil,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had previously compared <title>Madoc</title> favourably with the revered Latin epic, the
                            <title>Aeneid</title> (19 BC) by Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC). See letters 1032 and 1057 of this edition.</note> the
                    one never rising, the <del>xxxx</del> other never dismounting from his stilts. I do not think the language or habit of thought
                    &amp; expression any ways Spenserian, tho I love Spenser above all other poets &amp; have him in my heart of hearts &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Having said this much, you will perceive what my animadversions would be on your critique &#8211; which I should like to
                    see &amp; animadvert upon. If you will desire <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> (I have a wicked way of
                    giving nicknames) &#8211; to send it by twopenny post to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &#8211; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Stephens Court &#8211; New Palace Yard &#8211; he will frank it here, &amp; I will thro him frank it back. &#8211; Could you suppose that I should
                        <del>send</del> interpolate any thing for insertion? </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The next thing in your letter is that I could thro <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        May</ref> get into the Monthly,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had suggested in a letter to Southey (dated 26
                        August 1805, in J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>,
                        2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 90&#8211;93) that his friend John May could be influential in publicising <title>Madoc</title> in the
                            <title>Monthly Review</title>. A review of <title>Madoc</title> was published in this periodical, by John Ferriar
                        (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), but it was a hostile one. See <title>Monthly Review</title>, n. s. 48 (October 1805),
                        113&#8211;122.</note> &#8211; by what means? for this is dark as Erebus<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Greek god of darkness
                        who dwelt in the underworld.</note> or as Maurices Indian Antiquities<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Maurice
                        (1754&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), assistant keeper of manuscripts at the British Museum, who produced large works on Indian
                        religion, including <title>Indian Antiquities</title> (1793&#8211;1800).</note> to me. Explain this to me &amp; I will write to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> quam citissim&#233;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;at the
                        soonest&#8217;.</note> &#8211; or if you be assured of it write to him to save time, &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> will gladly do the thing &amp; find fault as honestly as possible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Joan of Arc is almost out of the press &#8211; else I should have been very glad of your book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published in 1806.</note> perhaps I am not
                    sorry that you did not offer a temptation to my conscience, <del>which</del> at the expence of my time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For Noah<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s plan to write a poem on the subject of &#8216;The Deluge&#8217;,
                        which never materialised.</note> you will see how acceptable your advice is when I tell you that the book of Enoch has been
                    for this very purpose a desideratum with me for five years, &amp; that I mean at Edinburgh if possible to get a sight of the
                    fragment which Bruce translated.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1773, the Scottish explorer, James Bruce
                            (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>) had reported discovering the Book of Enoch on his travels in Africa: &#8216;Amongst the articles
                        I consigned to the library at Paris was a very beautiful and magnificent copy of the prophecies of Enoch, in large Quarto;
                        another is amongst the books of scripture that I brought home, standing immediately before the book of Job, which is it&#8217;s
                        proper place in the Abyssinian Cannon: and a third copy I presented to the Bodleian Library at Oxford&#8217;, <title>Travels to
                            Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title>, 2 vols (2nd edn, 1804), II, p. 422. Southey reviewed this
                        work in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 2&#8211;16.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I never saw Ohtheres voyage<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ohthere [&#211;ttarr] (fl. 871&#8211;899;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was a Norwegian explorer who visited the royal court of Wessex during the reign of Alfred the Great
                        (848/9&#8211;899). The information he provided on Scandinavia was included in the late ninth-century Old English translation of
                        &#8216;History Against the Pagans&#8217;. This work, originally by the late fourth-, and early fifth-century historian and theologian
                        Paulus Orosius, provides the only source of knowledge about Ohthere and his voyages.</note> &#8211; but will as soon as I can. there
                    is a good story in Saxo Grammaticus of the voyage of Thorkill,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Danish historian Saxo
                        Grammaticus (c. 1150&#8211;1220), recounts the voyages of Thorkill in his <title>Gesta Danorum</title> (or &#8216;Deeds of the
                        Danes&#8217;).</note> wherein much of the Odyssey is parodied, &amp; some of the romances forestalled.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> returns he shall read Lessings Letter to
                        me.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had recommended Gotthold Ephraim Lessing&#8217;s (1729&#8211;1781), <title>Briefe, die
                            Neueste Litteratur Betreffend</title> (or <title>Letters on Modern Literature</title>) (1759&#8211;1763) to Southey because one
                        of them mentions a German history of Portugal (Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William
                            Taylor of Norwich</title>, II, p. 92).</note> When I have learned German I will read every thing in the language relative
                    to Portugal myself.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never
                        completed.</note> It is my plan when peace comes to go for a year into Holland to learn Dutch &amp; buy books &amp;c &#8211; &amp;
                    there, to make a book of memorandums to pay the extra expence which I cannot afford. German will then be easily added by an easy
                    removal of residence. I shall eat herrings, drink Rhenish, &amp; be very happy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I ever send you my dreams about the Deluge<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s plan to write on
                        this subject never materialised.</note> &#8211; for I dreamt much about it when on my voyage home from Lisbon. The subject has been
                    long my favourite, &#8211; because I believe it quite enough to touch it reverently. I disbelieve just so much as to rationalize it,
                    &amp; the very foundation of the event being the <del>xx</del> corruption of mankind I could <del>xx</del> make it jacobinical to
                    my very hearts wish. Enoch &amp; the Talmuds would furnish glorious notes &amp; help a grand machinery, &amp; my philosophy should
                    be Burnetts with the help of Whistons Comet.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Whiston (1667&#8211;1752;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was a natural philosopher and theologian who posited the theory that the biblical flood had been
                        caused by the activity of a divinely guided comet, which had caused the deluge through the condensation of vapours from its
                        tail. In his <title>New Theory of the Earth</title> (1696), he also identified sedimentary rock and marine fossils found in
                        continental areas as vestiges of the flood. His work drew on, and corrected, the work of the natural philosopher Thomas Burnet
                        (c.1635&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), in his <title>Theory of the Earth</title> (1684&#8211;1690).</note> &#8211; Where is your paper on
                        Jude?<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had published a theological article, &#8216;On the Readings and Writings of
                        Jude&#8217; in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 11 (February 1801), 18&#8211;23.</note> Whether this Deluge-scheme ever ripen or not,
                    I design to get as much Rabbinical learning as can be got without <del>learning</del> Hebrew &#8211; a language of which I have totally
                    forgotten the very little I ever knew. I have a notion that the Oriental tongue of our early romances came to us from the Jews &#8211;
                    not the Arabians. this hint was thrown out in the review of Ledwich last year,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed Edward Ledwich (1738&#8211;1823), <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804) in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1804</title>, 3 (1805), 398&#8211;413.</note> &amp; it pleased me to see that <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref>
          <note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ellis, <title>Specimens of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805) which
                        Southey reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 536&#8211;544.</note> has had the same thought concerning
                    the intercourse between Europe &amp; the East kept up by European Moors &amp; Jews I have some facts to adduce in my history &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-09-02">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 2. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>