<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1115</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2237</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 405&#8211;406.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1115" type="letter">
        <head>1115. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1805-10-27">27 October
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS./ 27 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1805<lb />MS:
                        Huntington Library, RS 80<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 405&#8211;406.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-10-27">October 27. 1805.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First I must congratulate you on the experiment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The inclosed sheets contain Don Manuels journey to London.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). The account of
                        the journey to London is given in Letters 4 and 5.</note> there is no date, because I have no almanac of 1802, &amp; no means
                    of ascertaining on what day the proclamation of peace took place.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Manuel Espriella&#8217;s
                        fictional visit to England occurred between April 1802 and September 1803. The Treaty of Amiens, which temporarily ended
                        hostilities between France and Britain, came into force on 25 March 1802. The celebrations after the proclamation are described in
                        Letter 8.</note> You can supply the dates, only letting <del>xx</del> it be as near the time of Governor Walls execution as
                    may be.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Wall (1737&#8211;1802; <title>DNB</title>) was a military officer in the African
                        corps who, in 1778, became Lieutenant-governor of Senegambia. His brutality and maladministration culminated in the deaths by
                        flogging of three African corps members, who were punished for mutiny. In 1784, after his return to England, Wall was arrested
                        and charged with murder, but escaped abroad. In 1801 he gave himself up for trial, and having been found guilty was executed
                        on 28 January 1802. Southey recounts these events, and Wall&#8217;s public hanging in London, in <title>Letters from
                        England</title>, Letter 9.</note> There is also a blank (page 9) for lack of a book of the roads. In that same page is a
                    prosingish sort of passage, following the word <hi rend="ital">dramatist</hi> to the end of the paragraph, which if you think of
                    as I do, you will draw your pen across it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Letter 2 is a description of the interior of
                        a Devon coaching inn, with a portrait of the &#8216;dramatist&#8217; Shakespeare on the wall.</note> &#8211; The second importation whenever it
                    arrives will let you more into the temper of the book. this is the mere stuffing, the necessary preliminary matter; &amp; in this
                    manner will all the journies be written which for the sake of verisimilitude &amp; of correspondence of book to title page Don
                    Manuel must take. &#8211; On revision I perceive an omission of country houses in these journals, something shall be said about them in
                    speaking of the vicinity of London.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> An English country house is described in Letter
                        14.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have about three times as much more transcribed or in a state for transcription, but not in regular sequence.
                    when about 100 of these pages in continuance are copied &amp; have past under inspection I shall put them to press for the sake of
                    gaining time &amp; spurring myself. I calculate upon making 300 such. Artaxerxes will publish in what shape seemeth good unto him
                    &#8211; &amp; the most profitable will be the best. If it be desirable to extend it to two octavos, or three duodecimos, I can add some
                    fifty or fourscore pages more.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> was published in three volumes.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want no more secresy than just enough to create a little wonder &amp; a little enquiry at first, &#8211; &amp; this &#8211;
                    you will see by the second batch the book will infallibly excite. &#8211; Let <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> &amp; Bedford see the
                    papers &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> knows I have a secret, but does not yet know what it is.
                    He will add something to my stores, &amp; will visit certain conventicles which I want to describe. You will correct &amp; amplify
                    at pleasure &#8211; only remember that in some places where you may detect an awkward word or phrase, that it is a translation. I have
                    aimed at this, but not so often as I could wish. There is no interleaving, because blank paper would swell the packet, &amp; you
                    can with little trouble insert national foolscap where needful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Edinburgh is a magnificent city &#8211; too good for the villainous country in which it stands. I took with &lt;me&gt; no
                    great liking for Scotland &amp; have returnd with less, &#8211; above all with an utter abhorrence of Presbyterianism. Upon my soul I
                    think even <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> himself would have turned Episcopalian if he had heard as I did,
                    a fellow talking broad Scotch to the Lord in a kirk built in the middle of Melrose Abbey<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Melrose Abbey is a picturesque ruin located in the Scottish borders. It was founded in 1136 by Cistercian monks, and in the
                        early seventeenth century a portion of the Abbey&#8217;s church (or kirk) was converted into a parish church for the surrounding
                        town of Melrose. It was used until 1810 when a new church was erected in the town. The Abbey is close to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott&#8217;s</ref> then home, <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Ashestiel</ref>.</note> &#8211; the Abbey itself being the most beautiful ruin in the whole <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;Island&gt;, &amp; the Kirk such
                    that no English pig would condescend to set foot in it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The land of itch &amp; oatmeal was truly called by Johnson a dolorous country. <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>) described Scotland as &#8216;a most dolorous country!&#8217; in James
                        Boswell&#8217;s (1778&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Journal of a Tour to the Hebrides with Samuel Johnson LL.D</title> (London,
                        1785), p. 398.</note> Such a dismal people God keep me from ever again beholding. they look as if they never laughed. &amp; so
                    deplorably ugly are they, that on my conscience I think an act of parliament should be past to prevent intermarriages. Of the men
                    of letters, with the exception of old Playfair,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Playfair (1748&#8211;1819;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was a professor of mathematics and natural philosophy at Edinburgh university, a geologist, builder of
                        scientific institutions, founder member of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, and a man of letters. He published several works on
                        mathematics and geology as well as writing reviews on scientific topics for the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> who I
                    suspect has English blood in his veins &#8211; I think very little. I met <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> the
                    reviewer of Thalaba<hi rend="ital"> &amp;</hi> Madoc<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey reviewed <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1 (October 1802), 63&#8211;83, and <title>Madoc</title> (1805)
                        in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> even if my temper had been more irascible, the sight of
                    a thing not above five feet two would have quieted me. In argument he was quick, conceited &amp; as shallow as heart could wish. I
                    could not be angry with an homunculus,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning a little or diminutive man; a mannikin.
                        </note> &amp; so we are very good friends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> was a delightful companion, an easy temper, a quiet mind, playful or serious
                    at proper seasons, a cool judgement, &amp; a memory excellently stocked. The Scotchmen looked as little beside him in intellect as
                    they did in body. I wish you knew him more, &#8211; he is a sound man, &amp; the more you knew him the higher you would value him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My busy season is come upon me &#8211; I am on the brink of reviewing &amp; wish it were over. Such a cart load of books!
                    but it is my last year,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey planned a return visit to Portugal but did not, in the
                        event, travel.</note> &amp; I shall get thro it steadily. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>