<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1588</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2710</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4862 .  Previously  published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 266&#8211;270.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1588" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1588" type="letter">
        <head>1588. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1809-02-23">23 February
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 10 March<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4862 <lb />Previously published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 266&#8211;270.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you let me see that book of Raymond Breton&#8217;s<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Raymond Breton (b.
                        1609&#8211;1679), a French Dominican missionary to the Lesser Antilles islands, compiled a French-Carib and Carib-French dictionary
                        (1665) and authored a manuscript narrative of the mission, <title>Relatio Gestorum a primis Praedicatorum Missionariis in
                            Insulis Americanis Ditionis Gallicae Praesertim apud Indos Indigenas quos Caribes Vulgo Dicunt ab Anno 1634 ad Annum
                            1643</title>. Breton is cited by Bolingbrooke/Taylor as an authority on the Carib language (see note 2).</note> which is
                    mentioned in Bolingbrokes Voyage P. 146.?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Bolingbroke (1785&#8211;1855;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to the Demarary</title> (1807). This work was revised by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> and published as <title>A Voyage to the Demarary, Containing a
                            Statistical Account of the Settlements there and of those on the Essequebo, the Berbice and other Contiguous Rivers of
                            Guyana</title>, in 1809.</note> &#8211; It will enable me to ascertain whether the Caribs are of the great Tupi<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> An Indian tribe of the Amazon.</note> family, as I am inclined to suppose they are, from their
                    word for Priest, &amp; from the maraca which their jugglers use <del>fro</del> thro the whole country from the Plata to the
                    Orinoco, &#8211; whether farther north I know not. You are certainly wrong about the word Caraiba, &#8211; both Marcgraff<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Georg Marcgrave/Georg Marggraf (1610&#8211;1648), born in Saxony, went to Brazil in 1638 in the
                        expedition of the Dutch led by John Maurice/Johan Maurits of Nassau (1604&#8211;1679). Marggraf&#8217;s papers on natural history were
                        published, after his death, with editorial input from Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649) as part of the work of the expedition&#8217;s
                        physician Willem Piso/Willem Pies (1611&#8211;1678) in the <title>Historia Naturalium Brasiliae</title> (1648).</note> in old times
                    &amp; Dobrizhoffer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus,
                            Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784). Southey eventually owned a copy of this work, no. 843 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library. It was translated by Sara Coleridge (with Southey&#8217;s encouragement), as <title>An Account of the
                            Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822).</note> in our own explain it to mean the power of sorcery or of
                    priesthood, &#8211; the inspiration which the Payes<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Payes, discussed by Southey in his
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, 188&#8211;256, were, he says, &#8216;at once quacks, jugglers and
                        priests&#8217; of the Indian nations (p. 227).</note> affected to possess<del>ion</del>. De Lery<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613), <title>Histoire d&#8217;un Voyage fait en la Terre du Bresil</title> (1578), was no. 1709
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; Thevet<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet
                        (1502&#8211;1590), whose <title>Les Singularitez de la France Antarctique</title> (1557) purported to be a first-hand account of a
                        French expedition to Brazil.</note> use it as synonymous with Paye by mistake, the one knowing little of the language, the
                    other nothing. You (for doubtless it is aut Diabolus aut<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;either the Devil
                        or&#8217;.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>) have thrown more new &amp; interesting speculation
                    into M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bolingbrokes book than is to be found in any other book of travels. But in your defence of slavery, as
                    in your defence of popery you weaken your own cause by <del>xxxx</del>injudiciously slurring over its weak side. You had
                        Stedman<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Gabriel Stedman (1744&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Narrative of a
                            Five Years Expedition against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</title> (1796). This work, illustrated by William Blake
                        (1757&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), depicted the cruelties inflicted on slaves by planters.</note> on your table, &amp; yet
                    scarcely hint at the horrors of slavery under a Dutch or a Jew master! You speak excellently of the end which their traffic has
                    been destined to fulfill; &#8211; I thank you for what you have said, it is a more far seeing, a more philosophical view of the subject
                    than any other person has ever taken, &#8211; perhaps than any other person is capable of taking. But when you call it vassallage you
                    have kept out of sight <del>the</del> all the difference between the feudal &amp; the commercial systems of society, between the
                    love of glory &amp; the love of gain, a country house, &amp; a Barons hall. I could have written a good <del>rev</del> reviewal of
                    this book, &amp; would have written a very ample one; &#8211; &amp; am sorry <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">King Thomas</ref> did
                    not send it me for that purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Claim for me in your next articles for Sir Richards Portfolio that Ode to Indolence printed in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Proctors<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A person of this name was admitted to Trinity Hall, Cambridge,
                        in 1783.</note> name two or three months ago in his Magazine,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;To
                        Indolence&#8217; appeared in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 27 June 1799 and the <title>Annual Anthology</title>&#184;1 (Bristol,
                        1799), pp. 126&#8211;128; it was then reprinted as &#8216;An Ode, upon Indolence&#8217;, as the work of the &#8216;Rev. John Proctor, late of Trinity
                        Hall, College, Cambridge&#8217; in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (1808), 456&#8211;457. &#8216;Extracts from the Port-folio of a Man
                        of Letters&#8217;, was a regular feature of the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, compiled by Taylor for its publisher <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Richard Phillips</ref>. The following notice was inserted in the &#8216;Port-folio&#8217; section
                        of the <title>Monthly</title>, 28 (1809), 397: &#8216;The ode ascribed in your twentysixth volume, to the Rev. John Proctor, (p.
                        450,) is slightly varied from an ode of Mr. Robert Southey: it is a beautiful poem; was probably on that account transcribed
                        by Mr. Proctor, and has been found among his papers by a friend, who mistook it for an original effusion&#8217;.</note> &#8211; with
                    alterations but not improvements. If the said M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Proctor be dead, the case probably is that he had copied out
                    the poem &amp; altered it to his own fancy, &amp; some of his friends finding it among his papers have supposed it to be his own.
                    If he be alive I can only call him as the school boy did Guy Faux<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guy/Guido Fawkes
                        (1570&#8211;1606; <title>DNB</title>), gunpowder plotter who attempted to destroy king and parliament by fire.</note> in his epigram
                        <del>xxxxxxxxxxxxxxx</del> calidus, frigidus: &#8211; calidus a warm admirer of my verses, frigidus, a cool fellow for stealing
                    them. You will see in the Annual that Sir Richard has inserted without leave, license or acknowledgement an old paper of mine from
                    the Magazine, in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whittinghams Travels in Spain.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 56&#8211;57 appeared a review of a narrative republished by <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips</ref> to take advantage of the new interest in Spain and Portugal caused by
                        the war. The narrative was originally part of the third volume, 1803, of Phillips&#8217;s series <title>A Collection of Modern and
                            Contemporary Voyages and Travels, the Tour through Spain, and Part of Portugal; with Commercial, Statistical, and
                            Geographical Details</title>. It was repackaged as a stand-alone work in 1808, padded with matter from elsewhere,
                        including, on pp. 230&#8211;235, an old contribution of Southey&#8217;s on Iberian literature in English from the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 1 (1796), 451&#8211;453 (see Southey to the Editor of the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 3 July 1796,
                            <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 164). The review in the <title>Annual</title>
                        points out the &#8216;dirty business&#8217; of the plagiarism, although it does not identify &#8216;Whittingham&#8217;, George Downing Whittington (c.
                        1781&#8211;1807), whose name was used to advertise the book (although it does not appear on the title-page and it was a common
                        practice of <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips</ref> to tag a hack writer&#8217;s name to material derived from
                        various sources).</note> I am really sorry that this Sherriff in the past &lt;tense&gt;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillips served as a sheriff of London in 1807. He did not become Lord Mayor.</note> &amp; Lord Mayor in the
                    future-in-urbe <del>xxxx</del> should be for ever committing some little dirty two penny-half penny piece of roguery, when he is
                    really so able &amp; so useful a man, &#8211; &amp; might have been so truly a respectable one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Twenty sheets of my first volume are printed, &amp; it will probably be published in June;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> &#8211; for
                        <del>I</del> my second I am in want of the Jesuits Annual Letters from Paraguay.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Cartas &#193;nuas de la Provincia del Paraguay</title> (or <title>Annual Letters from the Province of Paraguay</title>)
                        were reports of the Jesuit missions in Paraguay (1607&#8211;1767).</note> It is scarcely more difficult to get heretical books at
                    Lisbon than it is to get Catholick ones in England except that sort of desperate trash which is of our own home manufacture.
                    Hating Popery as I do ex intimo corde,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;From the bottom of my heart&#8217;.</note> I am yet a
                    great admirer of the Jesuits, <del>&amp;</del> there is no body of men to whom literature has been so much beholden. In fact all
                    the monastic orders have in this respect done their duty. The most base &amp; beggarly of them have done more as a body, than any
                    or all our Universities. It should have been Buonapartes policy to have restored the Jesuits, &#8211; he should have done it for his
                    immediate interest &amp; for his future character. Thorough villain as he is he is not much worse than Constantine,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Constantine the Great (272&#8211;337), the emperor whose conquests founded a new Roman empire in the
                        east.</note> &amp; the praise of a grateful sect can yet do wonders in white washing a negro reputation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two things amused me in the last Monthly Review, &#8211; the sagacity with which the William-Taylorism of the
                        <del>book</del> Demarary book are accounted for by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bolingbrokes official situation,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> See the review of the <title>Voyage to Demerary</title> in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 57
                        (1809), 1&#8211;10.</note> &#8211; &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Evans&#8217;s verses upon Madoc,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        same number of the <title>Monthly</title> included, on pp. 20&#8211;29, a review of a poem by John Evans (1756&#8211;1846), <title>The
                            Bees</title>, quoting some of Evans&#8217;s verse on Madoc the supposed colonist of America.</note> &#8211; (not my Madoc but the
                    Prince himself) &#8211; which are certainly made upon the most approved receipt for verse-making. I have seldom seen a worse reviewal
                    than that of Bolingbroke: the writer must have wretchedly ignorant to extract the account of the Feast of Dead, &#8211; which is to be
                    found in so very many books, (you are wrong in supposing it to be Mexican) &#8211; &amp; he must have been perversely stupid to pass
                    over without any notice the great &amp; striking novelties which the book really contains. I do not mean in matter of fact, of
                    which there is little enough, but in <del>the</del> its deductions &amp; views.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whether any thing concerning the affair of the D of York &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarke<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of
                        the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by
                        allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for
                        which promotion was arranged.</note> is to be found in the Revelation I have not yet heard, but it is certainly one of the
                    most important Signs of the Times.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> A hit at the many millenarian interpreters of the
                        Bible who, on the basis of the prophecies of Daniel and in Revelation, predicted the imminent end of the world. Southey
                        discussed Richard Brothers (1757&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>) and Joanna Southcott (1750&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>) in letters 69
                        and 70 of <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> The
                    people here are very ignorant, &amp; revolution is prophecied by those who certainly have no wish to see their predictions
                    verified. W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith has done himself no credit in this investigation, &amp; the House of Commons never appeared
                    to less advantage than by the gross leaning towards the Duke which they have manifested throughout.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Smith (1756&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), dissenter and radical MP, was involved in the inquiry into the
                        Duke&#8217;s conduct and argued he should not be retained as Commander in Chief.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had a good deal of sickness in the house, but it is well over &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope to have Kehama finished early in the spring, &amp; much to my satisfaction.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note> The metre of my next poem is yet undecided:
                    &amp; this is the only point about it which requires farther consideration. I am full of great plans &amp; God be thanked never
                    was better disposed nor better able to go thro with them. &#8211; The Cid fell to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scotts</ref>
                    care in the Quarterly,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) was
                        reviewed by Scott in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 117&#8211;134.</note> to <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref> in the Annual.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon Turner reviewed
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 91&#8211;99.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1809-02-23">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 23. 1809.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>