<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.983</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2105</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 63.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 362&#8211;364.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.983" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="983" type="letter">
        <head>983. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-10-15">15 October 1804</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Stephens Court/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ OCT 18/ 1804<lb />Endorsement:
                        RS./ 15 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ 1804<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 63<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 362&#8211;364.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-10-15">Monday Oct 15. 1804.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My silence has been longer than yours, &#8211; occasioned by that want of leisure which always is the consequence of loss
                    of time. Fine weather &amp; the wish of showing the country to my friends, &amp; moreover the sad necessity of working the legs to
                    keep the kidney quiet, have been so many motives for morning exercise. business of course accumulated for the evening, &amp;
                    letter writing as the least important has always been the most readily postponed. <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> is now gone, &amp; <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George I</ref> is gone, our only neighbours whom we care
                    about go tomorrow also &#8211; I shall then shut myself up for the winter tho not like the bee to rest, or feed upon my summer
                    gatherings, for alas my summer gatherings supply no winter store.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have nothing but ill to communicate. that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">rascally brother</ref> has
                    again left his ship or been turned out of it, &amp; is again sharping about the country. I have made up my mind to the fitness of
                    his being hung, &amp; am therefore prepared to think any thing short of the gallows will be good luck for him. Of course I pay
                    none of his alehouse debts, &amp; give him up as utterly irreclaimable. The whole current of politics public &amp; private is set
                    in against me. A war with Spain will renew all the alarm at Lisbon &amp; prevent me from taking a family there &#8211; &amp; even if
                    this blow over; I should think it more advisable for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to remove from the
                    neighbourhood of that accursed yellow fever than for me to approach it. for to Lisbon it will get sooner or later, beyond a doubt.
                    So that about going there I am quite at <hi rend="ital">a stand</hi>. Meantime, as if the very Diabolus ipse<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as the &#8216;devil himself&#8217;.</note> had taken upon himself the management of my
                    affairs, this excellently good house which we inhabit has been sold over our head to one White,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr White (dates unknown), a local man who negotiated to buy <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta
                            Hall</ref> from the builder and owner of the house, <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">William Jackson</ref>.</note>
                    a fellow all paunch, whom I compare to Bonaparte, as being the great belly-gerent &amp; we must turn out at Whitsuntide. the World
                    is all before me, as it was before Adam,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The World was all before them, where to choose&#8217;,
                        Milton, <title>Paradise Lost</title>, Book 12, line 646.</note> &amp; by the Lord I am almost as much unprepared for the
                    occasion &amp; as little furnished as Adam himself. However I must clap my shoulder to the wheel. Madoc will soon be done. 346
                    pages are printed. a month more will nearly carry it thro the press.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was
                        correcting proofs of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) and still revising sections of the manuscript not yet sent to the
                        printer.</note> My untouched regiment of authors must be killed off<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is
                            referring to his reviewing work for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> &#8211; I shall attack them immediately &#8211; &amp; I have a plan
                    for making a saleable book in the shape of translated Letters from a Spaniard in England<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The first reference to the project that was published in 1807 as <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title>.</note> meaning thereby to transmute certain of my opinions &amp; some of my knowledge
                    into chairs tables &amp;c. hoping I should have said, for this is the philosophers stone in the pursuit of which some damned thing
                    or other has always baffled me. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will never do my work in London.
                    I was a fool for trusting him. could I have got at the books as he can two mornings might have done it.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The project that Southey undertook with Bedford and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> I thought to make him work but he is
                    one of the incurables whose cases do not entitle them to a place in St Lukes.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Luke&#8217;s
                        Workhouse on the corner of Shepherdess Walk and City Road, London.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Towards London I suppose we must move, &amp; I shall make one great effort to gather together my books &amp; be
                    gathered to them. thirty miles will not be too far, ten not too near. but thirty better than ten, &amp; it matters not in what
                    direction. Kent or Hertfordshire or Surry the pleasantest counties, &amp; your population calculation would induce a preference of
                    the latter, downy counties favouring longevity, &amp; I having much to do would willingly live as long as possible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By all means take a wife, if only in abhorrence of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Malthus&#8217;s Essay,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) called for &#8216;moral restraint&#8217; &#8211; late marriage and sexual
                        abstinence in order to control population increase &#8211; in <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the
                            Future Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title>
                        (1803). Southey&#8217;s review of Malthus appeared in <title>The Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292&#8211;301.</note>
          <hi rend="ital"> &amp;</hi> if you do take one I bespeak a Godfathership for myself, having a liking for these conventional sorts
                    of relationry which used in old times to mean something. Tis a fit thing in the present state &lt;of the world &gt; to propagate
                    health &amp; intellect. besides marriage doubles a mans enjoyment. home is not quite home without it, nor a house quite furnished
                    without a wife.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The book concerning which <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">the Captain</ref> enquires is not among my
                    collection but his question shall be transmitted to Lisbon &amp; I promise him an answer.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Rickman and Southey were finding books to help their mutual friend James Burney to continue his <title>A Chronological History
                            of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (1803&#8211;1817), the first part of
                        which was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 3&#8211;12.</note> Did I tell you that I had
                    determined instead of compressing a sketch of the history of Monachism into certain episodical chapters, to give full &amp; fair
                    play to the subject in a seperate volume?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s intended &#8216;History of Monachism&#8217; was never written.</note> probably to be the most am[MS torn] of the whole series. It does <del>xx</del> provoke
                    me &amp; at times dispirit me this work should be so perpetually interrupted by two-penny-half-a-penny jobs, in which the main
                    consideration is &#8211; how many pages will this make.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George I</ref> is the better for his journey. We have discovered here a most odd &amp;
                    perfect resemblance to the profile of George 3<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great
                        Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in the outline of a mountain called Causey Pike &#8211; the Peak forming his majestys
                        nose.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Causey Pike lies in the Newlands valley, south of Keswick and visible from
                        Greta Hall. Seen from Derwentwater, it displays a prominent bump on the ridge line near the summit.</note> I mean to send a
                    paragraph about it to the Whitehaven paper.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware&#8217;s
                        Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note>
          <del> xxxx</del> a party of Gentlemen went up on purpose to christen it <hi rend="ital">Georgris</hi>, omitting the main resemblance it bears to the royal head &#8211; in being almost as thick. what is become of <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George II</ref> ?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are some lines of an old French Poem which I want for a note to Madoc. the poem is entitled Legend (if I
                    mistake not &#8211; de Pierre Faifeu<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 2269 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was
                            <title>Po&#232;tes Anciens Francais; Savoir, La Farce de M. Pierre Pathelin avec. son Testament &#8211; Fr. Villon, G. Cretin, Jean
                            Marot, P. Facifeu, G. Coquillart, et Martial de Paris, dit d&#8217;Auvergne</title>, 2 vols, (1723&#8211;1762). This set included
                        Charles de Bourdign&#233;, <title>La L&#233;gende de Maistre Pierre Faifeu</title> (1723).</note> &#8211; of the name I am certain, &amp; it
                    forms one of eight little volumes standing in the room below. the extract I want is from P. 58. the whole of the 22 Chapter some
                    20 or 30 lines, which George<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey could be referring to <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Fricker</ref>, <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> or
                            <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref>.</note> may copy out for me, &amp; you can inclose in the first
                    frank. With a story from Niebuhr, a fact which I know of John Henderson &amp; the Jewish Water of Jealousy it will form a good
                    note of parallelisms.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The extract from Faifeu, an extract from Carsten Niebuhr
                        (1733&#8211;1815), <title>Travels Through Arabia and other Countries in the East</title> (1792), the story of the water of jealousy
                        and the following anecdote about John Henderson (1757&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>) appear as a note to <title>Madoc</title>, Part
                        2, Book 20: &#8216;I remember an anecdote of John Henderson, which is characteristic of the man. The maid servant one evening, at a
                        house where he was visiting, begged that she might be excused from bringing in the tea, for he was a conjuror, she said. When
                        this was told him, he desired the Mistress would insist upon her coming in; this was done: he fixed his eye upon her, and
                        after she had left the room said, take care of her; she is not honest. It was soon found that he had rightly understood the
                        cause of her alarm&#8217; (<title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works, 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, pp. 347&#8211;350; 588&#8211;590).</note> &#8211; You expect too much from this said poem of mine. It
                    dissatisfies me. it has been too long in hand, &amp; the patchwork of different years is but too visible. I do not find in it any
                    of the merits you are disposed to look for. On the whole Thalaba is a far better poem,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> tho of a lower class.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. tell me when the days of franking return. we are all well &#8211; but the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> is so prematurely quick that I am by no means easy about her &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>