<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1118</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2240</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 350&#8211;353.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1118" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1118" type="letter">
        <head>1118. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-11-13">13 November 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ NOV16/
                        1805<lb />Endorsement: 13. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1805<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 350&#8211;353.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1805-11-13">Nov. 13. 1805.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There has been as great a gap in our correspondence as I have seen in the seat of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Domine&#8217;s</ref> pantaloons, after he has been sliding down Latrigg.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fell overlooking the town of Keswick in the Lake District.</note> Sir I shall be very happy to
                    give you a slide down Latrigg also, if you will have the goodness to put it in my power so to do &#8211; &amp; then you will understand
                    the whole merits of the simily.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Sir there are many reasons to be assigned for the aforesaid gap in the correspondence on my part, whereas there are
                    only two possible causes for that in the pantaloons. I have been to Edinburgh Sir, &amp; have been doing half a thousand things
                    since my return &#8211; <del>but</del> you &#8211; on your part have &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; upon which &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; in consequence &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; &amp; thus &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; from which it
                    appears undeniably that &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; &amp; this I take it to have been the reason of your silence. There Sir is a Specimen of my
                    skills in divination, &#8211; in return for which I shall be happy to receive from you Specimens<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey is referring to entries for his and Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s jointly-compiled anthology <title>Specimens of the
                            Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> of something else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I inclosed to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> certain papers for your perusal <hi rend="ital">sub sigillo</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;under seal&#8217;. For the accompanying letter, see Southey to
                        John Rickman, 27 October 1805, Letter 1115.</note> there was no reason why he should have been in any hurry to write, but as
                    there is reason that you should tell me whether you really are aboveground or not &#8211; you may let me know that they have arrived
                    safely. A second batch is ready tho not in exact sequence. I wish from you hints &amp; emendations for what is done or what is yet
                    to do. You cannot judge till the next importation arrives of the range &amp; variety of the matter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you Butlerize Mr Bedford.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey often prompted Bedford to publish
                        their comic inventions, which originated in schoolboy stories at Westminster. They were never published by Bedford, but
                        provided the hint for Southey&#8217;s comic novel/miscellany <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> By the core of Williams
                        heart,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Southey&#8217;s uncle, William Hill (dates unknown), brother
                        of his mother, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret Southey</ref>, as aspects of his character provided material
                        for Southey&#8217;s own comic publication, <title>The Doctor</title>.</note> which I take to be the hardest of all oaths, &amp;
                    therefore the most impossible to break I will never cease presenting you with that question &amp; that advice, till you actually
                    set that good ship afloat, in which you are to make as fair a voyage to the port of Fame as ever Englishman accomplished. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford it appears to me that Englishman accomplish that said expedition better by sea than by land &#8211; &amp;
                    that therefore the metaphor is a good one &#8211; A Sea-horse better than Pegasus. &#8211; Do do begin, &amp; begin by writing letters to me
                    which may be your first crude thoughts, &amp; I will unpack my memory of all its out-of-the-way oddities &amp; give them to you
                    for cargo &amp; ballast.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> will have told you of our adventures in Scotland, if the non-adventures of a
                    journey in Great Britain at this age of the world can deserve that name. I am returned with much pleasant matter of remembrance
                    well-pleased with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, with Johnny Armstrongs Castle on the Esk<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gilnockie tower, built by John (or &#8216;Johnny&#8217;) Armstrong (d. 1530), an outlaw in the Scottish
                        borders.</note> with <del>Xxxx</del> pleasant Tiviotdale, with the Tweed &amp; the Yarrow:<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rivers in the Scottish borders.</note> astonished at Edinburgh, delighted with Melrose,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Melrose Abbey, founded in 1136 by Cistercian monks, is a picturesque ruin, near Walter Scott&#8217;s
                        then home, <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Ashestiel</ref>, in the Scottish borders.</note> sick of Presbyterianism, &amp;
                    above all things thankful that I am an Englishman &amp; not a Scotchman. The Edinburgh reviewers I like well as companions, &amp;
                    think little of as any thing else.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Writers for the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> such as
                        Francis Jeffrey, John Playfair (1748&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), and Walter Scott.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> has more knowledge &amp; a sounder mind than any or all of them. I could
                    learn more from him in a day than they could all teach me in a year &#8211; Therefore I saw them to disadvantage inasmuch as <del>xxx
                        xxx xxx xxxx</del> I had <del>xx</del> better company at home. And in plain English, living as I have done &amp; by Gods
                    blessing <del>xxx</del> continue to do, in habits of intimate intercourse with such men as <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, the Scotch men certainly did appear
                        <del>x</del> to me very pigmies, &#8211; literatuli.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A diminutive form of literati, or men
                        of letters, intended to be derogatory.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I go to Portugal next year, if politics permit me, &#8211; &amp; expect to to take <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> with me for at least a two years residence,
                    taking the voyage &amp; the trouble of removal. this is a pleasant prospect. I love the country, &amp; go well prepared to look
                    for everything that I can want. My winter will be fully employed &amp; hardly I am at my reviewing,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> of which this year I take my leave for ever. It is an irksome
                    employment, over which I lose time because it does not interest me. A good exercise certainly is it, such I have found it, but it
                    is to be hoped that the positive immorality of serving a literary apprenticeship <del>xxx</del> &lt;in&gt; censuring the works of
                    others will not be imputed wholly to me. In the winter of 1797 when I was only twenty three &amp; a half I was first applied to to
                    undertake the office of a public critic!<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> As a reviewer for the <title>Critical
                            Review</title>.</note> precious criticism! &amp; thus it is that these things are done. I have acquired some knowledge,
                    &amp; much practice in prose at this work, which I can safely say I have ever executed with as much honesty as possible but on the
                    whole I do &amp; must regard it as an immoral occupation, <del>xxx</del> unless the reviewer has actually as much knowledge at
                    least of the given subject as the author &lt;upon&gt; whom he undertakes to sit in judgment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When will your worship call upon me for my Preface? <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> May I [MS torn] you &#8211; that <del>my</del> Patres nostri<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as &#8216;Our Fathers&#8217; and is a reference to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, whose publishing house was in <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref>, London.</note> frequently reminds me that we are losing time thereby hinting that loss of time is
                    loss of money.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a death is Nelsons!<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horatio, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233;
                        (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), who died at the Battle of Trafalgar on 21 October 1805.</note> it seems to me one of the
                    characteristics of the sublime that its whole <del>xxxx</del> form is never perceived at once. the more it is contemplated the
                    deeper is its effect. &#8211; When this war began, I began an ode which almost I feel more disposed to compleat &#8211; take the only stanza
                    &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> O dear England! O my mother Isle</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> There was a time, when, woe the while!</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In thy proud triumphs I could take no part; &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> And even the tale of thy defeat</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In those unhappy days was doomed to meet</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Unnatural welcome in an English heart &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> For thou wert leagued in an accursed cause</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> O dear dear England! &amp; thy holiest laws</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Were trampled underfoot by insolent Power.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Dear as my own hearts-blood wert thou to me</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> But even Thou less dear than Liberty </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">I never ventured on &#8211; for fear lest what follows should fall flat in comparison. almost I could now venture, &amp;
                    try at a funeral hymn for Nelson<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write this hymn.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you&#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>