<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1052</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2174</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library,
                        Add MS 30927.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1052" type="letter">
        <head>1052. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-03-30">March&#8211;5 April
                        [1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey./ H. M. S. Amelia/ Barbadoes,/
                        or elsewhere./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ APR 8/ 1805<lb />Endorsement: 6 B M<lb />MS: British Library,
                        Add MS 30927<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1805-03">March.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is time that another letter should arrive from you &#8211; &amp; you may well imagine that I am always anxious to hear
                    of your safety. Not but that in my reason I am satisfied that with your habit of body, your seasoning, &amp; the mode of living
                    you have adopted, you are as safe as a sailor can be. The papers tell me you have taken a ship from Teneriffe &#8211; &amp; I have been
                    wishing she had been sent into an English port instead of Barbadoes that I might have <del>been</del> purchased some of her
                        Canary<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A highly popular sweet white wine.</note> if it was good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Not a particle of news to communicate since my last. Every thing remains just as it was. whether Madoc be published
                    or not heaven knows &#8211; &amp; if not heaven knows why &#8211; but I suppose not or I should surely have received some letter to
                    acknowledge it from one or other of the many to whom it is to be sent. I am at my Spaniards letters, which I think of printing in
                    two such volumes as the Amadis &#8211; as to size &amp; type.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803) was published in four volumes duodecimo, printed by N. Biggs, Crane Court, Fleet
                        Street; <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) appeared in
                        three volumes duodecimo. Both were published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> my progress is
                    slow, but what is done is to my taste, &amp; if my old letters were at hand from which I could collect something, &amp; also the
                    books which are necessary for consultation I think four months would be an ample allowance of time to compleat the work. One of my
                    ears would be a cheap price to pay if I could get you at my elbow to help me out with a few tough stories.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1805-04-05">April 5.</date> Your letters, of Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 14 &amp; Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 19 are just
                    come to hand. the same post brings news of the French at Dominica<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> This Caribbean island,
                        in British possession since 1763, was invaded by France early in 1805. The British retained possession and made the island a
                        colony.</note> &#8211; &amp; I perceive that had you been watering there &#8211; as you would if your Captain had not been changed<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby (1779&#8211;1804), eldest son of Sir John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl
                        of Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>) was the captain of Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, until
                        he died on 6 August 1804 at Surinam, from yellow fever. He was replaced by William Charles Fahie (1763&#8211;1833).</note> you would
                    have been in Limbo. Upon my life Tom so many hairs-breadth escapes almost make me superstitious &#8211; &amp; I could willingly believe
                    that a red ribband &amp; star are in store for you.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The decoration of the &#8216;Order of the
                        Bath&#8217; or a knight of the realm.</note> It is not such honours as that which I despise nor which deserve to be despised. the
                    honours which are honourably acquired are useful to the community &amp; fair objects of fair &amp; laudable ambition. It is the
                    making them hereditary which is mischievous. When once any great events are associated with a name that name ought to remain
                    sacred, &#8211; I would no second Duke of Marlbro<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Churchill (1655&#8211;1720;
                        <title>DNB</title>), a war hero, was made 1st Duke of Marlborough in 1702. He had no surviving sons, and his title was allowed
                        (by a special Act of Parliament) to pass to his eldest daughter in her own right.</note> &#8211; no second Lord Nelson,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In October 1805, The Reverend William Nelson (1757&#8211;1835), brother of the naval hero Horatio, 1st
                        Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233; (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>) inherited a barony when the latter was killed at the
                        Battle of Trafalgar. He was subsequently created Earl Nelson and Viscount Merton of Trafalgar and Merton in the County of
                        Surrey in recognition of his brother&#8217;s services, and inherited the Dukedom of Bront&#233; in Italy.</note> enough for the children
                    of such men the real advantages which their fathers can leave them, &#8211; the solid wealth, &amp; the high example, tenfold more
                    powerful that if they find themselves born Lords &amp; Legislators, when if nature has not made them fools it is ten to one but
                    education does.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc was published only on March 27<hi rend="sup">th </hi>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> was to send off your copy by the first ship to Barbadoes. the Annual Review
                    has been delayed by a mutiny among the printers, but as <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> says in true Officer
                    like style &#8211; the men have now <hi rend="ital">returned to their duty</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1805
                        journeymen printers were paid by master printers per job, rather than by the day or week, according to a complicated scale of
                        prices. Disputes about the scale were settled when a joint committee was set up with equal representation of masters and
                        journeymen.</note> &#8211; &amp; my valuable lucubrations are not likely to be long withheld from the world. As soon as it is
                    published (which will be within the month certainly) I have ordered both this &amp; the 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Volume to be sent
                    for you to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles of Antwerp</ref> &#8211; &amp; they may very probably arrive in time to take
                    their chance with the great quarto. &#8211;You do not get my letters. I can recollect four which you have not received specifically &#8211;
                    &amp; how many more heaven knows. But be you never uneasy at <hi rend="ital">not</hi> hearing. no news is always good news in such
                    cases as this, when only the ordinary chances of nature are to be taken into calculation. If any evil were to befall, you would
                    learn it by private channels enough, &#8211; &amp; if not my death would find such food for newspapers &amp; magazines that
                        <del>you</del> &lt;it&gt; would speedily travel wherever they find their way. We go well. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> in the Egyptienne<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Egyptienne</hi> was a 40-gun frigate, captured from the French in 1801, and commissioned into the Royal Navy.</note> (for
                    I must repeat the often-told tale) &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> at Edinburgh, soon coming here for
                    the summer. the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> in her twelfth month, still well &#8211; tho I <hi rend="ital">have</hi> had some alarms &#8211; a great tyrant, &amp; just now beginning to prefer her father to any body else, because he shows
                    her the book &amp; pictures in such a tone of voice as the showmen use &#8211; &amp; gives her what he calls a small toss. She is by no
                    means a pretty child &#8211; but has an uncommonly intelligent look. You would like her &#8211; &amp; I wish you were here to see her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When your bill of exchange arrives I shall consult my mercantile friends about the best means of employing it to
                    advantage. I am uneasy about these Frenchmen &amp; damn &#8211; as I do on every occasion &#8211; the miserable mismanagement in every
                    department at home. Long before this Admiral Cochrane<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral Sir Alexander Forrester
                        Inglis Cochrane (1758&#8211;1832, <title>DNB</title>), made commander of the Leeward Island station in 1805.</note> will have
                    arrived &#8211; but what may have happened meantime God knows! &amp; at all events your cruising is cut up till their three deckers are
                    out of the way. however I hope the best. &#8211; I see Delafons of the Dasher is dead in the E. Indies.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain John Delafons (d.1805), who had captained the 16-gun sloop <hi rend="ital">Dasher</hi> in the East
                        Indies from 1803, died at Prince of Wales Island, Torres Strait.</note> Is this the same Delafons? for I thought he had left
                    the Dasher long since, &amp; had got a 74.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Delafons&#8217; brother, Thomas (b. 1772), was
                        also a naval officer. In May 1801, as a Lieutenant, he was appointed to the 74-gun <hi rend="ital">Irresistible</hi>, under
                        Captain William Bligh (1754&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>). In 1805&#8211;1806, in command of the <hi rend="ital">Nimble</hi>, he was in
                        the Caribbean under Admiral Sir Alexander Forrester Inglis Cochrane. By 1844 he was infirm and had retired to Greenwich
                        Hospital. A third brother, William (b. 1789) was in the West Indies from December 1805&#8211;1806, as a midshipman on the 74-gun <hi rend="ital">Superb</hi>.</note> &#8211; <del>xxxx xxxx xxxx in yours xxx xxxx xxx xxxxx xxx xxx xxxx xxxxxx xxx xxx
                        xxxxxxxxxx</del> The attack on Martinique is of course at an end<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1804 the British
                        had fortified Diamond Rock, giving them command of the sea approaches to the western side of the French colony of Martinique.
                        In early 1805, French boats made an unsuccessful attempt to take the rock, but were swept out to sea by currents. In May,
                        however, a large French fleet besieged the rock and the British were forced to surrender.</note> &#8211; But no more of these
                    things, it is idle to fill a letter from England with speculation on what may have happened in the W Indies.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> No letter from the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">Old Gentleman</ref> yet &#8211; nor indeed from any body to whom
                    Madoc has been sent, for there has not been time. I wrote to him in a very <hi rend="ital">family</hi> sort of stile &#8211; telling him
                    all about you, as if he had never taken it in his head to quarrel. Lisbon politics still remain unsettled &#8211; if Gibraltar be
                    besieged we shall of course be expelled from so important a port,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the event the
                        British garrison and fleet preserved Gibraltar from attack from the French and Spanish fleets. Britain and Portugal remained
                        allied, and it was not until 1807 that French armies invaded Portugal from Spain.</note> &amp; indeed this is most likely, &#8211;
                    in fact I almost expect <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just begun to correct Joan of Arc for a third edition. flat &amp; unprofitable work<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act 1, scene 2, line 133.</note> in the literal sense of the words, as the copy-right is not my own. So
                    it must be set down to the account of reputation. the alterations will be minute &amp; numerous, &#8211; such I trust as to make the
                    language correct &amp; to weed out all the feebler &amp; faultier parts. The Vision is by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> desire to be printed at the end of the poem.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of
                            <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published in 1806, with the &#8216;Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217;, originally published in the
                        second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> (1799), printed at the end.</note> The gap therefore in the second Vol of
                    Poems is to be filled up &#8211; &amp; this I think of doing with the best or least bad pieces from my very first volume &#8211; the
                    Retrospect &#8211; the Rosamund to Henry &#8211; &amp; perhaps one or two from the Monthly Magazine.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In the new 1806 edition of the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799), Southey included two poems first published in his
                        and Robert Lovell&#8217;s joint collection <title>Poems</title> (1795), &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217; and &#8216;To Hymen&#8217;. &#8216;Rosamund to Henry, written
                        after she had taken the veil&#8217; appeared in the 1795 volume, but not in 1806. Other poems brought into the 1806 edition of
                        <title>Poems</title> to make up for the removal of the &#8216;Vision&#8217; were, &#8216;Translation of a Greek Ode on Astronomy, written for the prize at Cambridge, 1793&#8217; (pp.  3&#8211;9); &#8216;To Hymen&#8217; (pp. 25&#8211;39); &#8216;Remembrance&#8217; (pp. 40&#8211;43); &#8216;To Recovery&#8217; (pp. 49&#8211;51); &#8216;Youth and Age&#8217; (pp. 52&#8211;53); &#8216;The Traveller&#8217;s Return&#8217; (pp. 5 4&#8211;55); &#8216;Autumn&#8217; (pp. 56&#8211;58); &#8216;The Destruction of Jerusalem&#8217; (pp. 59&#8211;62); &#8216;The Spanish Armada&#8217; (pp. 63&#8211;66); &#8216;St Bartholomew&#8217;s Day&#8217; (pp. 67&#8211;69); &#8216;To a Bee&#8217; (pp. 74&#8211;75); &#8216;Metrical Letter&#8217;, pp. 76&#8211;79. See <title>Robert
                            Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, pp. 157&#8211;160.</note> they may
                    get in silently &#8211; for to print new poems there would be injuring my purse without adding to my reputation. You see there is enough
                    work for the printers &amp; I hope to have the Letters of D Manuel Alvarez Espriella ready for the press by next winter.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; If your
                    consignment comes to hand I shall in putting <del>xx</del> it out consider myself as good security, &amp; lend myself enough to
                    furnish a house, if it seem adviseable to remove near London, &amp; get my books about me, &#8211; for the evil of being without them is
                    inconceivable to any but a man of literary pursuits. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Annual reaches you look at M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Kinnens Tour in the West Indies,
                    &amp; you will see that your letters have been of use to me.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Daniel
                        Mackinnen (1767&#8211;1830), <title>A Tour Through the British West Indies, in the Years 1802 and 1803 Giving a Particular Account
                            of the Bahama Islands</title> (1804), in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 50&#8211;56.</note> If you would
                    keep a journal &amp; put down all you see &amp; <del>xxx</del> you hear, my life on it it would prove exceedingly valuable. the
                    best accounts we have of other countries are all made by such men as you, &#8211; who related what they saw &#8211; caring for nothing but to
                    say merely what they wanted to say. As soon as ever such men ceased to write travels because style was thought of &#8211; travels ceased
                    to be good for any thing. I wrote in one of my letters pretty fully on this subject. Send me all your stories about Pompey<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Pompey&#8217; was a popular name for African slaves, after Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus, also known
                        as &#8216;Pompey the Great&#8217; (106&#8211;48 BC), a military and political leader of the late Roman republic.</note> &#8211; get his history from
                    himself, &amp; write it as nearly as you can recollect in his own words. If you visit a planter see in what his house differs from
                    an English one both inside &amp; out. Little as you may think of your own letters they contain more than often gets into print &#8211;
                    look at M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Kinnens book for instance! he writes without a heart, &amp; with little pigs-eyes that see nothing
                        <del>above</del> higher than his nose. I spared him because he is M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenans brother<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mrs Keenan (first name and dates unknown) was the sister of Daniel MacKinnen. Her husband, John Keenan (fl. c.
                        1780&#8211;1819), exhibited a portrait of Southey at the Royal Academy in 1803.</note> &#8211; &amp; even his book was better than none.
                    &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is coming home from Malta full of Mediterranean politics, &amp;
                    earnestly desirous that we should take Egypt before the French take it, on which subject he has, as Secretary to the Governor Sir
                    A Ball<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander John Ball, 1st Baronet (1757&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>): Rear Admiral who
                        directed the blockade of Malta and became its governor. Coleridge wrote a biography of Ball in <title>The Friend</title>
                        (1809&#8211;1810). See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II,
                        pp. 252&#8211;256, 287&#8211;294, 347&#8211;356, 359&#8211;369.</note> addressed several memorials to government. We expect him, if no accident
                    intervenes, in May.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge arrived back in England in August 1806, but did not come
                        back to live in Keswick.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> comes about midsummer. <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref>
                    is going to Liverpool, to take private pupils, a fit office for him, he will find good society there, &amp; good encouragement.
                    Will you believe that Miss Phillott is turned Methodist? outrageous Methodist? it is even so! I am sorry, because I liked her
                    &amp; thought her a woman of good solid sense.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Phillott (first name and dates
                        unknown) was an acquaintance of Bristol days and a member of a prominent family of professionals and tradesmen centred on
                        Bath.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps when you get made<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning promoted to captain.</note> it may be
                    the means of bringing you to England. I wish to God you were within reach. the longer I live the more important do family ties
                        <del>xxx</del> become. When I read in the Whitehaven paper that the first Lieut. of the Galatea was killed<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> made an
                        unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war
                            <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or
                        wounded. Southey had suspected that his brother was among the dead, having read in <title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware&#8217;s
                            Whitehaven Advertiser</title> that the first lieutenant had been killed. Thomas had been placed under arrest, and
                        Lieutenant Charles Hayman (d. 1804), his replacement on the raid, died.</note> &#8211; it went thru me like a shot &#8211; &#8211; Let us live
                    in hope &#8211; &amp; we have reason, &amp; reason to be satisfied with the past as far as it depends on ourselves, for we have made our
                    way up, when if we had not risen by our own efforts we should have been trodden down into the dirt. As for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> he will make his fortune by marrying I have no doubt, with his face &amp;
                    manners. You will be Sir Thomas yet &#8211; &amp; I promise you whenever Sir Thomas takes another ship there shall be a better song made
                    about it than was made about the last. Never Admiral had such a poet as you shall have. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Specimens<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly edited anthology,
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> are now at last going to press, thus long delayed by
                    <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> laziness, &amp; the mutiny.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">See note 8.</note> this may bring me in something &#8211;
                    but for this &#8211; &amp; Madoc &#8211; &amp; the Volume from the Anthology which is called Metrical Tales<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s contributions to the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) were republished under his own name
                        in <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; I get nothing immediately &#8211; preferring to share the eventual
                    profits. so I shall do with <hi rend="ital">Espriella</hi>, &amp; make the bookseller advance enough upon his credit to set my
                    accounts square. My history<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never
                        completed.</note> goes on. indeed you would not wonder that I do so much if you knew in how utter a solitude we live, during
                    the whole spring &amp; winter without any neighbour whatsoever, &amp; I always, except at meal times, in my study, taking no
                    exercise except just in the home ground with the child in my arms &#8211; &amp; yet &#8211; thank God &#8211; never in better health. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. never lose an opportunity of writing &amp; if you get no letters from me
                    &#8211; blame any body rather than me &#8211; for I continue to write &#8211; God bless you Tom!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>