<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1701</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2823</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.74.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1701" type="letter">
        <head>1701. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-10-24">24
                        October 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        Durham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.74<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sent you my French Anna Comnena<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Comnena (1083&#8211;1153), daughter
                        of Alexios I Komnenos (1048/1056&#8211;1118), Byzantine emperor 1081- 1118, wrote the <title>Alexiad</title>, a history of her
                        father&#8217;s reign. Southey is probably referring to her narrative in the French-compiled dual Latin/Greek edition of Byzantine
                        texts, <title>Byzantinae Historiae Scriptores</title> (1645&#8211;1711).</note> by Miss Lamb.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Mary Lamb</ref>.</note> Fynes Morison<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Fynes Moryson (1565/6&#8211;1630), traveller and writer who spent three years compiling a history of the countries he had visited.
                        He abandoned this work to begin a shorter account of his travels, translated from Latin into English as <title>An Itinerary:
                            Containing His Ten Years Travel Through the Twelve Dominions of Germany, Bohemia, Switzerland, Netherland, Denmark,
                            Poland, Italy, Turkey, France, England, Scotland and Ireland</title> and published in three volumes in 1617.</note> is too
                    big for a Lady&#8217;s trunk, that therefore must go by waggon when I have any thing else to send with it, &#8211; but it is worth while to
                        <del>xx</del> examine your two Libraries first,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bishop&#8217;s Library and the Chapter
                        Library in Durham.</note> in hope of saving carriage, &#8211; these old travellers being among the likelier books to be found there.
                    My Sandys<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Sandys (1578&#8211;1644; <title>DNB</title>), writer and traveller, whose
                        journey through Europe and the Levant during 1610&#8211;1612 was published as <title>A Relation of a Journey begun an. dom. 1610.
                            Foure bookes. Containing a description of the Turkish empire, of Aegypt, of the Holy Land, of the Remote parts of Italy
                            and Lands Adioyning</title> (1615).</note> is as you may perhaps recollect in the <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">College Green</ref>. There is a most excellent vol. of travels in Asia Minor
                    published about forty years ago by Chandler, who travelled for the Dilettante Society, &#8211; a thoroughly good book, &#8211; almost a model
                    for such works.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Chandler (bap. 1737, d. 1810; <title>DNB</title>) was a classical
                        scholar and traveller who was commissioned by the Dilettante Society to undertake a tour of exploration in Asia Minor and
                        Greece. His journals from the expedition appeared in two parts: <title>Travels in Asia Minor</title> (1775) and <title>Travels
                            in Greece</title> (1776).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will get Anna Comnena in about a fortnight. Be very particular in your references so that you may with as
                    little trouble as possible verify them by the original whenever we lay hands on it, for I need not tell you how much is always
                    lost in translations. You will see my land marks thro the book, but I have never yet had time to make the purposed use of them.
                    For the Latin conquest I have the two great authorities for you Ville Hardouin<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 1135
                        of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was Geoffroy de Villehardouyn, Mare&#769;chal de Champagne (1148&#8211;1213), <title>L&#8217;Histoire
                            de la Conqueste de Constantinople par les Barons Franc&#807;ais Associez aux Venitients, l&#8217;an 1204</title> (1584).</note> &amp;
                        Nicet&#226;s,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Nicetas, or the Triumph Over Incontinence</title> (1633) by Jerome Drexelius (1581&#8211;1638), a Jesuit writer of devotional
                        literature. The work was no. 860 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> the former is among the <hi rend="ital">rarissima</hi>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;very rare&#8217;.</note> I have also got S Louiss expedition<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Louis IX (1214&#8211;1270), commonly termed Saint Louis, King of France from 1226 to
                        1270, who went on two crusades to the Middle East in 1248 and 1270.</note> &amp; Guillermus de Nangis<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French chronicler, Guillaume de Nangis (d. 300).</note> in the Hist. Francoram ab Anno 900 ad 1285,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Histori&#230; Francorum ab Anno Christi DCCCC ad Ann. M.CC.LXXXV, Scriptores Veteres XI. &#8230; Glaber, Helgandus, Sugerius
                            Abbas, M. Rigordu, Guillermus Brito, Guillermus de Nangis, et Anonymi alij, Extrema Stirpis Carolin&#230; et Carpetiorum Regum
                            res Gestas usque ad D. Philippum Ludovici Filium Regem Explicantes</title> (1596).</note> but this is a book which I
                    should think must be in your Durham Libraries. This volume contains the Philippines of Guillerme de Brito<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guillermus Brito (dates unknown).</note> &#8211; which must be another of your documents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Biddulphs Travels<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Biddulph (fl. 1600), a Protestant chaplain
                        appointed by the Levant Company to the Aleppo factory whose letters reporting his travels were published as <title>The Travels
                            of Certaine Englishmen into Africa, Asia, Troy, Bythinia, Thracia, and to the Black Sea: And into Shyria, Cilicia,
                            Pisidia, Mesopotamia, Damascus, Canaan, Galile, Samaria, Judea, Palestina, Jerusalem, Jericho, and to the Red Sea: and to
                            Sundry Other Places</title> (1609).</note> are in the supplement to Churchills Collection,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Collection of Voyages and Travels</title> published by John (c.1663&#8211;c.1714; <title>DNB</title>) and Awnsham Churchill
                        (1658&#8211;1728; <title>DNB</title>) in four volumes in 1704. The third edition of 1744&#8211;1746 was no. 695 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> where indeed you will find other &amp; better travellers in the Levant, &#8211; but read them all. Is not
                    this Collection in your Libraries? &#8211; Purchas<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Purchas (c. 1577&#8211;1626;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>His Pilgrimage, or Relations of the World</title> (1625).</note> I know is there, &amp; must
                    certainly contain much which is to your purpose. Maundrel<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Maundrell (bap.
                        1665&#8211;1701; <title>DNB</title>), Church of England clergyman and traveller in the Middle East, whose travels were published
                        after his death in <title>A Journey from Aleppo to Jerusalem at Easter A.D. 1697</title> (1703). His account was intended to
                        bring George Sandys&#8217; narrative (see note 4) up to date (<title>DNB</title>).</note> will have something &amp; so will
                    Bertrandon La Brocquiere lately Englished by Johnes.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bertrandon de la Brocqui&#232;re (c.
                        1400&#8211;1459), <title>The Travels of Bertrandon de la Brocqui&#232;re to Palestine: and his Return from Jerusalem Overland to France,
                            During the Years 1432 &amp; 1433</title>, translated by Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1807).</note> The
                    latest description of Acre,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A city several times besieged during the Crusades: in 1189&#8211;1191 during the Third Crusade and in 1291, when it was the final city in the Levant to fall to the Muslims.</note> &lt;a place&gt; with which
                    you will have much to do in C&#339;ur de Lions Crusade,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard I, also known as Richard Coeur
                        de Lion, Richard the Lionheart (1157&#8211;1199; <title>DNB</title>), King of England (1189&#8211;1199), Duke of Normandy and Aquitaine,
                        and Count of Anjou. He and a European army of crusaders captured the city of Acre in 1191.</note> &#8211; is in Brownes miserable
                        travels.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> George William Browne (1768&#8211;1813), <title>Travels in Africa, Egypt, and
                            Syria: From the year 1792 to 1798</title> (1799).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not send me the Dictionary, <hi rend="ital">per se</hi> it is not worth carriage, when I come next to Durham I
                    shall visit Sunderland &amp; Newcastle in search of books, &amp; perhaps pack up a respectable box full.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your news of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> was to be expected. Botany Bay is the best thing
                    that can be hoped for him, &amp; all we can hope for ourselves is that whether he be lucky enough to get there, or whether he dies
                    as you say in his shoes, it may be by some alias, &#8211; a thing not unlikely as his own name will soon be too bad to serve him
                    longer.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent for the Gesta Dei<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey eventually owned <title>Gesta Dei per
                            Francos, siue Orientalium Expeditionum et Regni Francorum Hierosolimitani Historia a Variis, Sed Illius Aeui Scriptoribus,
                            Litteris Commendata, etc</title>, edited by Jacques Bongars (1554&#8211;1612), no. 1193 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> from a Catalogue &#8211; but it was gone. I have now sent for Maimbourgs Hist. des Croisades<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Maimbourg (1610&#8211;1686), <title>Histoire des Croisades pour la Deliverance de la Terre
                            Sainte, par le P. Louis Maimbourg, de la Compagnie de Jesus</title> (1682).</note> with more likelihood of success, &#8211; for
                    Maimbourg is not an author of good repute. Nevertheless <del>Hi</del> his history cannot but be useful, &#8211; just as a bad map is
                    better than no map at all. It will at least give you the modern names of places, &amp; show you the relative proportions &amp;
                    importance of the different Crusades. Fullers History<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Fuller (1607/8&#8211;1661;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Church History of Britain</title> (1655).</note> is among the many books which I have lost
                    &#8211; His Pisgah View of Palestine<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fuller, <title>Pisgah-Sight of Palestine</title>
                        (1650).</note> is here, &amp; will supply you with some amusing notes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> is at rest. His brother Joseph,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Joseph Jackson (dates unknown).</note> my present Landlord, is an uncommonly respectable
                    man, &#8211; the great favourite of Ld Sackville<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sackville-Germain, 5th Duke of Dorset, 2nd Viscount Sackville (1767&#8211;1843).</note> who
                    at this time pays his expences as a Fellow Commoner at Cambridge that he may by taking a degree qualify himself to hold his
                    livings. He goes home by way of Durham, &amp; I shall desire him to knock at your door, that you may show him what civilities you
                    can. His brother Ben,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Benjamin Jackson (dates unknown).</note> may perhaps be with him, &#8211; &amp; he I dare say has better accommodation at his home than are to be found at
                    the inn at Alston.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> A small town in Cumbria on the River South Tyne.</note> Verbum sit sat
                        sapienti.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;a word to the wise is sufficient&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made a bold push for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, &amp; have got <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> to ask Ld Mulgrave<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>): diplomatist and politician who was appointed First Lord of the
                        Admiralty in 1807.</note> to promote him.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s request to Sir George
                        Beaumont, see Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 12 October 1809, Letter 1692.</note> It went sorely against the grain to ask
                    this favour, but I made up my mind to the fitness of doing it, tho my wishes for its success are a good deal stronger than my
                    hopes</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When is the Long Main?<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> A large cock fight held regularly at Durham.</note>
                    &#8211; for I purpose attending it, &#8211; if possible. I will bring <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> will either come &amp; fetch us, &#8211; or return with us. Tell her she never
                    can know half my agreable accomplishments till she see me in my own house.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-10-24">Oct 24. 1809.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">&#8211; You will have received Anna Comnena before this time, &#8211; I sent for Basnage Hist de Juifs<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques Basnage De Beauval (1653&#8211;1723), <title>Histoire des Juifs</title> (1706, Eng. trans.
                            1708).</note> &#8211; without success</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>