<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1668</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2790</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 513&#8211;516.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1668" type="letter">
        <head>1668. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-08-10">10 August
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 513&#8211;516.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1809-08-10">August 10. 1809.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This candle has just <hi rend="ital">put out</hi> that sort of view which I feel most pleasure in looking at, &#8211; at
                    least it is to be supposed it gives the most pleasure, for I look at it longer than at any other.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Southey&#8217;s first floor study window in <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> It is
                    one of our still, grey, evenings, the rain which has been falling since noon has ceased for awhile, but there is yet plenty of it
                    to come down, &amp; broken clouds are moving slowly, below a <hi rend="ital">leaden stratus</hi> which threatens us for tomorrow.
                    Johnny Tugman stretches from his headquarters the whole breadth of Borrowdale, the mountain top is visible above him, &amp; Castle
                    Crag stands out dark &amp; alone in front.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The cloud and mist lying low in the valley of
                        Borrowdale, in which stands Castle Crag, to the south of Derwentwater.</note> Up in Newlands &amp; along Brandelhow a few
                    light clouds are hovering on the fell sides.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Newlands is a valley running to the southwest
                        of Keswick; Brandelhow a fell that rises on its eastern side.</note> &#8211; If I had not been resolved to write to you before
                    supper this weather would have kept me at the window as long as there was light enough to see from it. We sallied this morning for
                    a walk to the Vale of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Johns, by a route which you never took, <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> &#8211; about 2&#189; miles the Ambleside road, then turn to the left across the
                    vale of Naddle, &amp; over Naddle fells by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Johns Chapel, &#8211; from thence along the terrace which runs on the
                    side of Naddle nearly to Domine Ford.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A route across the hills and valleys leading to St
                        John&#8217;s Vale, to the east and south of Keswick.</note> It is one of the finest things in this country. When we were almost at
                    the extent of our walk rain came on, &#8211; we stopt an hour &amp; half <del>xxx</del> with some good people of the name of Wetherall,
                    who gave us gooseberry wine &#8211; &amp; were exceedingly <del>xxx</del> amused by my giving them an account of the Jumpers.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> So-called from their habit of jumping and bouncing for joy during worship, the Jumpers were
                        Calvinistic Methodists. The practice began in Caernarvon, North Wales, beginning in the 1740s, and spread through
                        Cardiganshire, persisting into the early nineteenth century.</note> However it was useless to wait &amp; we had a wet walk
                    home, &#8211; not <hi rend="ital">back</hi>, for my convoy would not submit to turn back, so we fairly proceeded, crost the Greta<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This river rises to the north of St John&#8217;s Vale and flows west, past Southey&#8217;s home, into
                        the river Derwent.</note> &amp; returned on the other side of the Vale. A good wetting did us no harm, &amp; we &lt;are&gt;
                    now quite comfortable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> has made me a delightful picture of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, which is the admiration of every body who has seen it. She has also succeeded
                    very happily on <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, the face is done, the rest as yet incompleat. Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">eldest niece</ref> is to sit next. With me she has failed from over anxiety to do it
                    well, so <del>I am</del> my face is rubbed out from a finished picture, in hopes of being better put <del>xxx</del> in again. You
                    cannot tell how much we wish you were here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That boat-business provokes me. Whenever those attempts end disastrously the Captain who permitted them to be
                    undertaken ought to be called to an account, &amp; severely reprimanded if it appears that there was not the strongest probability
                    of <del>them</del> succeeding. &#8211; It will be a good thing to keep Walcheren &amp; hermetically seal up the Scheld against all
                    preparations for invasion.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren expedition was an unsuccessful British attempt to
                        open another front in the Netherlands in support of the Austrian Empire&#8217;s struggle with France. Approximately 40,000 soldiers
                        with supporting horses and artillery landed at Walcheren on 30 July 1809. There was little fighting but the army sustained
                        heavy losses from sickness, and in December 1809 the rest of the force withdrew.</note> The rest of our plans I do not
                    comprehend, &#8211; but if Austria had only been true to herself we should soon have seen the deliverance of Europe.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain and Austria were in alliance against France in 1809, but Napoleon advanced into Austria
                        where he suffered a significant defeat at the battle of Aspern-Essling (22 May 1809). The Austrians failed to follow up this
                        victory, which allowed Napoleon to seize the capital, Vienna, in early July. The Austrians were then defeated by the French at
                        the battle of Wagram on 5&#8211;6 July 1809.</note> My own plan for the expedition had at least the merit of boldness, &amp; would I
                    think have been practicable. It was to mask Cronstadt, land &amp; seize Petersburgh by a coup de main, &amp; depose
                        Alexander.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I of Russia (1777&#8211;1825), Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825, had
                        declared war on Britain in October 1807. Though there was little military action between the two countries, during August 1809
                        British ships were victorious in battles with the Russians in the Gulf of Finland.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This reminds me of telling you something. At Paterdale the other day I heard there was a Gentleman from
                    Petersburgh, &amp; looking at his portmanteau I read his name Edward Bayley Esq S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Petersburgh.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Clive Bayley (1776&#8211;1841), a British merchant in St Petersburgh.</note> I immediately
                    recollected that a family of that name &amp; place had lodged with my mother in Duke Street, for she often used to talk of them
                    with much pleasure, &#8211; so I said to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles</ref> I had half a mind to introduce myself
                    &amp; ask him to come to see me. What does that man of Antwerp<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s nickname for
                        Danvers was &#8216;Charles of Antwerp&#8217;.</note> do, but happening the next morning to go down stairs before me, &amp; finding him
                    about to start, he stops him telling him I wanted to speak to him. Of course all that was then to be done was to do the thing as
                    willingly as I could &#8211; &amp; here we had him. It was his brothers family<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bayley had
                        twelve brothers.</note> who had then been in England. He himself is a very pleasant well informed man. I got from him a good
                    deal of information, &#8211; have his address, &#8211; in order to get him to send me Russian books whenever the state of affairs permits him
                    to return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had an invitation to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref> thro <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> who is going there next week, &#8211; &amp; I must needs go too. So I
                    shall see the grounds at leisure &amp; overhaul the library.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is coming, I shall take him to Irton.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southwest of Wastwater in Eskdale, Cumbria. Irton Hall, designed around a fourteenth-century Pele tower, was the seat of the
                        Irton family, Lords of the Manor of Irton and Melthwaite since medieval times.</note> We have some pleasant acquaintance in
                    the <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Brownes</ref> &amp; Wolseleys<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Robert
                        Wolseley (d. 1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740&#8211;1817) was a fellow pupil of Southey&#8217;s at Westminster School. He
                        and his wife (first name and dates unknown) visited Keswick several times in 1808 and 1809.</note> who were both here last
                    year, but the latter soon take their departure. The family at Dale head<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dale Head Hall,
                        Thirlmere, had been the residence of the Leathes family since the seventeenth century.</note> &#8211; that house on <hi rend="ital">this</hi> side Thirlmere which has newly been enlarged &amp; repaired want much to get acquainted with us, &amp; I am well
                    disposed to gratify them, hearing much that is good of them, <del>&amp; to</del> Moreover it will be pleasant to have a house of
                    call there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will transcribe another number of Kehama<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was sending Thomas
                        drafts of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, which was published in 1810.</note> this week sans fail, &amp; get on as fast as
                    possible. My cold has just left me, &amp; but just. This is perhaps the very first day that I have felt quite rid of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> who starts an Edinburgh Annual Register which will have an immense
                    sale, has applied to me to write for it the history of Spanish affairs for the last year,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey agreed to provide historical material for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note>
          <del>xxx</del> most probably I shall do it, &#8211; &amp; if so I shall speak English both about the Convention of Cintra<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> A British inquiry into the circumstances surrounding, and the conduct of those involved in
                        agreeing, the Convention of Cintra (1808), under the terms of which the defeated French were allowed to evacuate their forces
                        from Portugal. See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 379&#8211;381.</note> &amp; the <hi rend="ital">flight</hi> of Sir John Moore.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British commander, Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), who was killed
                        in battle at Corunna on 16 January 1809 after a disastrous retreat. For Southey&#8217;s account, see <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 442&#8211;459. Although he praised many of Moore&#8217;s personal qualities, Southey suggested
                        that he was not &#8216;equal to the difficulties of his situation&#8217; (458).</note> Two histories of that flight I have got &#8211; sent down
                    for the Annual Review, in which I did not intend to have done another stroke.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Annual Review</title> closed before Southey could write this review for it.</note> It was one of the most
                    disastrous &amp; disgraceful flights upon record &amp; would everlastingly have tarnished our army had he not luckily been
                    compelled to fight at last. By God Tom such a man as Lord Peterborough of old,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles
                        Mordaunt, 3rd Earl of Peterborough and 1st Earl of Monmouth (1658?&#8211;1735), army officer renowned for his daring actions in
                        Spain.</note> or Lord Cochrane now,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald
                        (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and formerly Tom Southey&#8217;s captain. Cochrane gained renown through a campaign
                        of daring and brilliantly executed raids harassing and attacking settlements on the Spanish and French coasts.</note> at the
                    head of that army, would have a fair chance of ridding Europe &amp; the world of it chief plague. Huzza &#8211; fight on my merry men
                        all,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> A line which occurs in both the broadside ballad &#8216;John Armstrong&#8217;s Last farewel&#8217;
                        (c. 1701) and &#8216;The Ballad of Chevy Chase&#8217; (first recorded in the 15th century).</note> &amp; we shall do the business yet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 416 pages of Brazil.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> &#8211; Curious enough &#8211; one of these accounts of Sir John Moores campaign gives a
                    view of the castle of Almourol,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Almourin Castle, on an island in the Tagus in
                        Portugal.</note> without knowing that it is the main scene of adventure in Palmerin<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>Palmerin of England</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; which I so regretted not having seen.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>My Bristol six shilling shoes have turned out so well that I have sent for four pair more.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> The postscript is written at the top of the first sheet.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>