<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.905</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2027</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.905" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="905" type="letter">
        <head>905. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-03-01">1 March
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MAR 3/ 1804<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you see <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> on his return ask him to tell you how a
                    Gentleman from Bristol came with his wife &amp; family to his house upon the strength of having dined with him at the Anchor
                    Society&#8217;s dinner,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 July 1791 Thomas Clarkson and hundreds of others attended a dinner
                        at the Crown and Anchor tavern in London to celebrate the second anniversary of the fall of the Bastille.</note> &amp; how the
                    said Gentleman had travelled one &amp; twenty miles in that most difficult country <hi rend="ital">throughout</hi>, not baiting
                    his horse or his family at the usual halting place, &amp; how he eat up a large plum-cake before M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &lt;or
                        M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>&gt; Clarkson <del>a</del> came in, which the servant produced because the children were crying for
                    hunger, &amp; how the Gentleman asked questions &amp; was very penurious, &amp; the wife was little &amp; crooked &amp; ugly,
                    &amp; still more penurious than the husband, &amp; how she quarrelled about half a pound of cherries in the streets of Penrith, &#8211;
                    the Gentlemans name being Coates.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Coates (dates unknown), was a Clifton resident.
                        He was known to <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and was a subscriber to a number of Bristol literary works. His brother was Matthew Mills Coates (dates
                        unknown) of the law firm Morgan and Coates in Bristol. Both brothers were radicals and may have been related to Mary Coates
                        (1753&#8211;1783), the first wife of the Bristol Unitarian minister John Prior Estlin (1747&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Ought
                    we not to make a book of Billiana for the benefit of posterity.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A pun on the name William
                        (Coates) when shortened to &#8216;Bill&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been some days from home &#8211; as thus &#8211; Tuesday to <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> where
                    I found <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> &amp; proceeded with him to <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>. Wednesday perambulating that neighbourhood &#8211; Thursday over the mountains to <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">C&#8217;s.</ref> at Ulswater &#8211; Friday seeing that place, &amp; to day home &#8211; in all 71 miles,
                    which my legs have very dutifully performed, with no other sufferance than natural stiffness. this has been a highly pleasurable
                    expedition &#8211; &amp; I have learnt more of the arts of the Negroes from C.s. collection of their ornaments &amp;c than all my books
                    had taught me. Poor man, he has now heart to look at them once more, &amp; to talk of their sufferings &amp; emancipation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letter<del>s</del> with its inclosures went to <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Smith</ref> punctually to my promise, &#8211; &amp; will probably induce a reply, as I offered my services when they come into the
                    North, in looking out lodgings for them, if they will stay as long as they ought to stay to see the country well, &amp; in
                    directing their route, &amp; in showing them such things as might else escape their notice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The wine is very good <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers [c. 15 January 1804]
                        (Letter 885) and 1 February 1804 (Letter 892), on the despatch of this wine.</note> &#8211; but I am sorry to say four bottles of
                    the Bucellas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A white wine produced in Portugal.</note> were broken. they were at the top
                    &amp; were not well packed, &#8211; &amp; as you may suppose alarmed me for the rest of the cargo. the concrete acid is certainly not
                    the acid of lemons. I know not if a mineral acid can be exhibited in that form, but if it can this is mineral by the testimony of
                    my teeth. The box is arrived<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers [c. 15 January 1804], Letter
                        885, in which he asked Danvers to send the pocket book or books.</note> &amp; to my great grief &amp; wonder contains the
                    wrong pocket book &#8211; for as you say you have no other I cannot conceive where the one wanting can be, which is a black leather one,
                    rusty enough in appearance but brimfull of matter, &#8216;of no use except to the owner&#8217;. If you should find it on a second survey I
                    must have it sent down, for it contains half my notes, &amp; also my memorandums for Madoc,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in
                        1805.</note> &#8211; &amp; if you cannot find it in your own possession I will beg you to open the smallest of the boxes at
                        Horts,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764&#8211;1849), Unitarian minister and writer, who taught in
                        the school run by John Prior Estlin (1747&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>). He was one of many acquaintances who stored books for
                        Southey.</note> if not put in there with the stray things that were last packed, it must be lost. this is a serious evil to me
                    &#8211; for I am now not only advancing with the second part of the poem, but have also begun to transcribe the first for the press, in
                    the hope of taking that with me to London where I must travel in the course of the spring to finish another book concerning which
                    I cannot remember whether or not I have written to you heretofore &#8211; the Specimens of Modern English Poetry, as a companion book to
                        <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis&#8217;s</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Specimens of the
                            Later English Poets</title>, edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford</ref>, was published in 1807 as a companion work to the <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd
                        edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803) compiled by George Ellis.</note> of which two editions have sold. this will cost me some bodily toil
                    in hunting for forgotten books &#8211; all else is play-work &#8211; it is to be printed on the same terms as Madoc! &#8211; &amp; will, in my
                    opinion beyond a doubt be far more profitable both to me &amp; the publishers &#8211; so much for the reward of intellectual labour! It
                    must however be remembered that <del>both</del> in literature as well as in trade a mans <del>xxxx</del> name is good for nothing
                    unless it be known that he has some capital. &#8211; I must draw nearer London that is certain, for I can always there have as much
                    silent money-getting work as my necessities require, without those inconvenient delays, &amp; heavy expence of carriage which make
                    weighty objections to this situation, even if this suited me better. As far as I can see before me my wisest plan will be to
                    gallop on with history as fast as possible &amp; then cross the seas. by the time of my return the profits of these running works
                    will surely be enough to furnish a house, &amp; then I will settle within a mornings ride of town. My regular work is first &amp;
                    foremost before all others to write these pages of history &#8211; such pages as when printed will extend honestly to five in quarto. a
                    year at this rate will well nigh finish my materials.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of
                        Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> writes me word of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Newtons<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Newton (1749&#8211;1804), the sister of Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), was the principal
                        beneficiary of the sales of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803), which Southey and <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref> edited to relieve Chatterton&#8217;s family from financial
                        distress.</note> death, who it seems would have wanted bread but for what we have done for her. she had received &#163;184&#8211;15&#8211;
                    &amp; more than as much again remains yet to be received when the remainder of the subscribers shall have paid for their copies,
                    &amp; the copies unclaimed shall have been sold. I was more successful for her than I ever have been for myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun a letter to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> to beg a drawing from him for one of the
                        vignettes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to his plan for engravings for <title>Madoc</title> (1805);
                        see Southey to John King, [1]&#8211;5 March 1804, Letter 904.</note> &#8211; you will see by it that it is my design to make them useful &#8211;
                    as for mere pictures from the story of the poem they usually do more harm than good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref> is quite happy with his map. He grows up as unlike all other boys as
                    he was unlike all other children. It is very diverting to hear him talk of his children whenever any thing displeases him. when he
                    is called to his book &#8216;well I am determined that my children shall never read when they have not a mind to,&#8217; &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; his
                    children are never to learn to spell &#8211; never to be washd &#8211; never to be denied any thing they want. When <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> offends him he shakes him by the arm saying &#8216;you little ridiculous
                    fellow.&#8217;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I continue well &#8211; but still at times vexed with these weak eyes. somebody to walk with in the morning &amp;
                    somebody to talk to in the evening would relieve them.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-03-01">Wednesday. March 1. 1804.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>