<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.958</idno><idno type="nines">rce2080</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4847 .  Previously  published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), A Memoir
                            of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                    506–512.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="958" type="letter"><head>958. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1804-07-01">1 July
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 6 July<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4847 <lb/>Previously published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir
                            of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                    506–512.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> It is time to tell you how after having talkd &amp; walkd &amp; travelled away the little flesh which can be spared
                    from my bones, quiet &amp; plenty of sleep have restored it. how <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my little Edith</ref>
                    is a large &amp; thriving child of two months old – &amp; how happily I have relapsed into all those habits &amp; occupations
                    which were so completely dislocated by a journey to London. – At Newington I met D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir James Edward Smith (1759–1828; <title>DNB</title>): botanist, botanical author, founder of
                        the Linnean Society, a man of Norwich, like Taylor.</note> &amp; was pleased to find that his sister remembered me as well as
                    I remembered her. I had also the good fortune to meet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably Samuel Henley D.D. (1740–1815; <title>DNB</title>): clergyman, antiquarian, man of letters and regular contributor to
                        the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> – &amp; as of course I mentioned your name to him, &amp; he spoke of you in
                        <del>which</del> &lt;a way&gt; which it did me good to hear, this puts me upon making my defence about <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref>. I do’nt call him a dim eyed son of blasphemy as <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> did in his days of intolerant unitarianism; – he may blaspheme
                    &amp; wear spectacles in peace for me. But when such a man says ‘take my word for it there’s nothing at all in <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W.T.</ref>’ I certainly do take his word for it that he believed what he said – &amp;
                        <del>xxx</del> was a blockhead for his pains. &amp; the private anger that <del>this</del> such a circumstance excited, added
                    to that <del>which</del> &lt;produced by&gt; his weathercock instability of opinion, &amp; the odium which it brought upon the
                    best principles &amp; the best cause, &amp; the want of all feeling in stripping <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">his
                        dead wife</ref> naked as he did,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Godwin’s publication of <title>Memoirs of the Author
                            of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</title> in 1798, revealing Wollstonecraft’s unorthodox lifestyle, had
                        inadvertently destroyed her reputation.</note> &amp; such a wife – &amp; taking such another home<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Godwin married his second wife, Mary Jane Clairmont (1766–1841; <title>DNB</title>), in December 1801.</note>
                    when the picture of <del>xxxx xxxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;that first&gt; hung up over his fire place, – indeed indeed my flesh is not
                    made of such Quaker fibre, nor my blood of such toad temperature as not to be irritated by these recollections. You know how much
                    I hope for the human race – but you do not know how deeply that hope is rooted, &amp; how it leavens all my feelings &amp;
                    opinions. To see these two such men as Godwin &amp; Malthus come to such an issue upon such a question – did make me feel bitter
                    anger &amp; bitter contempt; &amp; notwithstanding even your dissatisfaction I cannot wish one syllable that expresses or enhances
                    such sentiments were cancelled.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Godwin’s argument, in <title>An Enquiry Concerning
                            Political Justice</title> (1793), that human society might advance towards perfectibility was opposed by Thomas Malthus
                        (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), in <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the future improvement of
                            Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803). Southey’s review of
                        Malthus appeared in <title>The Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292–301.</note> The reviewal is imperfect – very
                    imperfect. such things never lie by me for correction, &amp; I have here <del>x</del> no one to help me by immediate criticism. It
                    might have shown that his detail is full of blunders – &amp; that his ultimate plan would inevitably provoke, &amp; ought to
                    provoke, rebellion &amp; revolution.</p><p rend="indent1"> It was a sore disappointment that you did not come to London. We should have had some pleasant hours at <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>, who would every hour have continued to rise in your estimation, &amp; he
                    would have brought together a few men whom you would have liked to know. – You are doing good in the Annual Review – that is
                        certain.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor was a regular reviewer for this periodical.</note> one article
                    supports another, &amp; your opinions come together as much in a body as is possible in such a shape. – Henley said you were the
                    best statistic in Europe, not even excepting some German whose name I could not shape to my eye when I knew it, &amp; it has
                    escaped my auricular memory. I can only say that you have taught me so thoroughly the extent of my own ignorance that I shall not
                    venture to praise. – In the poetical &lt;department&gt; &amp; <hi rend="ital">belles letters</hi> (Oh give me <hi rend="ital">English</hi> for that phrase!) <del>departme</del> it is to be wishd that you were my coadjutor, instead of <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> B.</ref> &amp; those other <del>xxxx</del><hi rend="ital">curmudgeons</hi> (according to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ashs <del>inter</del> excellent interpretation of the word, &lt;in his
                    dictionary&gt;, <hi rend="ital">which see</hi>, if you do not know the jest already.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Ash (1724–1779), a Baptist minister who included many provincial words in his <title>New and Complete Dictionary</title>
                        (1775). Ash’s ridiculous derivation of ‘curmudgeon’ from the French for ‘unknown correspondent’ stemmed from a naive reliance
                        on Samuel Johnson’s (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Dictionary of the English Language</title> (1755) in which
                        ‘curmudgeon’ is derived from ‘cœur méchant’– a derivation that Johnson credits to an ‘unknown correspondent’.</note> one
                    reviewal directly contradicts the radical system of the other. it is pull-Devil, pull-Baker all thro.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> An old English proverb meaning they are both as bad as each other.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has not yet made his appearance. his walk must have
                    extended farther than I thought his finances could have carried him. I am labouring to set <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> affairs in order, &amp; if that were once done there would be certain
                    &amp; sufficient allowance for him. I wish he were come. the expectation forces upon me a remembrance how many years have passed
                    since we lived under the same roof, &amp; with that thought comes a long train of melancholy associations. God send me independent
                    leisure enough to leave behind me my domestic history! It would be a picture of society in a <del>new</del> light wherein it had
                    never before been painted. – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will have a pleasant summer here – &amp; a
                    profitable one. A few friends will drop in in the course of the season to whom I wish him introduced, – &amp; my overflowing of
                    Portugueze information will supply him with a stock of new knowledge for Edinburgh.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am passionately &amp; exclusively engaged in history<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected,
                        but never finished, ‘History of Portugal’.</note> – nor shall I be able to extricate myself till the sight of the first proof
                    from <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> reminds me that I have half Madoc to rewrite.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> was published in 1805.</note> Do not accuse me of presumption in again
                    running races. <hi rend="ital">this</hi> is all mature for parturition, &amp; without imposing upon myself such a necessity I
                    should still have lingered in Portugal &amp; Portugueze Asia – perhaps till I had past the age of writing poetry. I have written
                    more than the amount of three honest quartos, &amp; there are yet years of labour before me. You ask who will read? I have two
                    grounds of hope. that the books will be read for the amusement they contain – &amp; that I shall by other means have made such a
                    reputation that it shall one day be thought a thing of course to have read them. The objection of bulk will be obviated by
                    dividing it into many separate works; a division made necessary by the divi[MS torn] subjects, &amp; exampled by the Portugueze
                    themselves.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> will soon be here on his way towards Scotland. he is I hope
                    recovering from the baneful effects of fashionable company, &amp; of fame too early acquired. there is a notion of getting <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> to deliver Lectures on Poetry at the Royal Institution next year –
                    &amp; Davy has askd me if I would do it, as he will not be returned from Malta. I have no inclination for the task, &amp; am glad
                    that the exceeding inconvenience of the journey is sufficient to outweigh the only motive that could induce me to think such a
                    thing possible – the wish of preoccupying a situation in which the old mumpsimus<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        traditional notion that is obstinately held although it is unreasonable.</note> faith will else be delivered <hi rend="ital">ex cathedra</hi>?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning with the authority derived from one’s office or
                        position.</note> My labouring days are over. And to preach in a London Lecture Room upon poetry! to talk of all that is
                    connected with the highest part of our nature to Ladies &amp; Gentlemen – would be a profanation like making the Eleusinian
                        mysteries<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Initiation ceremonies into the cult of the goddesses Demeter and
                        Persephone, the rituals of which were kept secret, held every year for two thousand years from c. 1600 BC, at Eleusis in
                        Greece.</note> into a puppet show at Athens.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">Owen</ref> is translating the Mabinogion.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was reading a manuscript translation by William Owen Pughe of the Welsh romances dating from the eleventh to the
                        thirteenth centuries, collected in fourteenth-century Welsh manuscripts and known as the Mabinogi; see Southey to John
                        Rickman, 6 June 1804, Letter 948, Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 11 June 1804, Letter 951, and Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, 16 June 1804, Letter 955. Some of these were published in the journal edited by Pughe, <title>The Cambrian
                            Register</title> (1796, 1799), where they are entitled <title>The Mabinogion, or Juvenile Amusements, being Ancient Welsh
                            Romances</title>.</note> I have seen three tales. they are even more curious than I expected. as barbarous as possible,
                    &amp; what is most extraordinary, strikingly like the Arabian Nights in their character of fiction. princes subsisting by making
                    shoes &amp; saddles better than any one else could do, – a mouse who is the Magicians wife &amp;c &amp;c.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The mouse appears in the story entitled ‘Manawyddan Son of Llyr’.</note> the translation is to the very letter
                    – just as it should be, Welsh idiom &amp; Welsh syntax nothing so curious has yet appeared. how old the composition is I cannot
                    tell – but the traditions themselves seem to me certainly older than the Conversion of Britain<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The arrival of Christianity in Britain, c. AD 597.</note> – &amp; I am no credulous believer in antiquity.</p><p rend="indent1"> What proofs have you that Blue Beard<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had printed his poem on
                        Bluebeard (‘Barbablao’) in the newspaper he edited, <title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title>, on 17
                        March 1804. A revised edition appeared three weeks later. It was later published in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 38
                        (1814), 437–440.</note> is Henry 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>? I ask anxiously because it is so apparently true, &amp; I am
                    collecting what relates to the conduct of the Catholicks at that period, which will make a very curious chapter in my
                        history.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 9.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I shall soon send you more rhymes for the Iris – &amp; a monodrama which has to my feeling something good in
                        it.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Six poems by Southey have been identified in <title>The Iris</title>, although he
                        may also have been the author of several anonymous epigrams published there in 1803–1804. The poems are: ‘A Lamentation’,
                        published on 12 November 1803; ‘Doris can find no taste in tea’, 19 March 1803; ‘To a Lock of Delia’s Hair’, 23 April 1803;
                        ‘Cool Reflections during a Midsummer Walk’, 13 August 1803; ‘Queen Urraca’, 3 November 1804: the ‘Monodrama. Florinda’, 21
                        July 1804.</note> if you think them worth criticising tell me how to mend them.</p><closer><salute> God bless you</salute></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1804-07-01">July 1. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>