<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1116</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2238</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        101&#8211;103.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1116" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1116" type="letter">
        <head>1116. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1805-11-01">1 November 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ NOV 4/ 1805; 10o&#8217;Clock/ NO.4/ 1805F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 113 1805 / Robert Southey / Keswick 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Nov / rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published:
                        Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        101&#8211;103.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1805-11-01">Nov. 1. 1805.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is so long since we have written to each other, that I know<del>x</del> not to whose charge the silence is to be
                    laid, tho rather suspecting it to be on your side than mine. I have been absent from home fifteen days, &#8211; for me an extraordinary
                    event; three days of that time were spent at <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Walter Scotts</ref>
          <del>in xxx</del> on the banks of the Tweed, a week in Edinburgh, &amp; the rest upon the road. I went to accompany my friend <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &amp; am heartily glad to find myself again by my own fire side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, I find, being from home when his remittance arrived, has not
                    acknowledged its receipt, which I therefore now do for him. It is not fitting that there should be any secrets respecting him on
                    my part towards you. He has entangled himself, or been entangled by the daughter of Colonel Noel, member of Rutlandshire.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emma Noel (d. 1873), daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes of Exton Park, Rutland (1759&#8211;1838;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who adopted the surname Noel in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in 1813 to become the 2nd Baronet
                        Barham.</note> the affair took place while he was visiting <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> &amp; it seems has proceeded pretty far in a short time. The father viewing the
                    matter with very natural feelings, such as any other father in similar circumstances would needs have, &amp; assuredly such as I
                    cannot blame or wonder at, has acted very foolishly &amp; very blameably. He has treated his daughter with great severity, &amp;
                    of course provoked her into a settled &amp; steady perseverance. What her mother<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Diana
                        Noel (n&#233;e Middleton) Baroness Barham (1762&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>).</note> may do will decide the matter, &#8211; as she uniformly
                    has said that she will do nothing which would afflict her &amp; endanger her weak health. But the mother is of an affectionate
                    &amp; therefore yielding disposition, methodistically inclined &amp; therefore not much regarding inequalities of birth, &amp;
                    being herself unhappily married may probably set a higher value upon the chances of happiness, than people in high rank are apt to
                    admit into their calculations. So that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; the young Lady herself
                    think they have more to hope than to fear. The father bluntly &amp; honestly says he never will give her anything, but that that
                    is of little consequence &#8211; for he never should have done more &#8211; <del>xxx then</del> than just to &lt;have&gt; rendered things
                    pleasanter at first. When of age she has fifteen hundred pounds of her own, &amp; as much more at his death; <del>of her</del>
                    &amp; may have whatever more Lord Barham her grandfather<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Middleton, 1st Baron
                        Barham (1726&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and administrator.</note> may leave her. These are her prospects &amp;
                    this the state of the business.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have never seen the young Lady. they who have tell me it is no wonder that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has been thus attached, &#8211; &amp; I who know him think it as little
                    extraordinary on her part. I wish it had not happened, but having happened would, as far as can be, render my own plans
                    subservient to their well-doing; &amp; if they should marry, when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> sets
                    up to practise, I shall not be unwilling to reside for some years wherever he may fix, to assist him with a home. You will of
                    course perceive how uncertain all this is, nor should I have communicated any speculations upon, or account of, an affair which
                    may very likely end in nothing, but for a sense of something like duty, &#8211; at least of impropriety in concealment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now for myself. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> advises me to visit Portugal the sooner
                    the better, &#8211; advice which I have every inclination to follow. In the spring I shall be ready, &#8211; it is my hope that <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will consent to accompany me, in which case I would not hurry back; if she will
                    not I shall make the best use of my time, &amp; work the harder for the sake of speedily returning. I have much to do before my
                    departure. At least as large a proportion of the Review to supply as in any former year<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806): James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>),
                            <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title> (2nd edn, 1804&#8211;1805), 2&#8211;16; Thomas Lindley
                        (dates unknown), <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ... with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of
                            the City and Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto Seguro</title> (1805), 27&#8211;32; Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Present State of Peru, Comprising its Geography, Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and
                            Manners of its Inhabitants; Embellished by ... Engravings of Costumes</title> (1805), 49&#8211;60; John Griffiths (dates
                        unknown), <title>Travels in Europe, Asia Minor and Arabia</title> (1805), 67&#8211;77; James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 1; 1805), 99&#8211;100; Charles
                        Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title>
                        (1805), trans. B Lambert (dates unknown), 177&#8211;187; William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de
                            Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467; Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848), <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805), 477&#8211;483;
                        Dieudonn&#233; Thi&#233;bault (1733&#8211;1807), <title>Original Anecdotes of Frederic the Second, King of Prussia, and of his Family, his
                            Court, his Ministers, his Academies, and his Literary Friends: Collected During a Familiar Intercourse of Twenty Years
                            with that Prince</title> (1805), 488&#8211;495; William Parr Greswell (bap. 1765&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of
                            Angelus Politianus, Joannes Picus of Mirandula, Actius Sincerus Sannazarius, Petrus Bembus, Hieronymus Fracastorius,
                            Marcus Antonius Flaminius, and the Amalthei: Translations from their Poetical Works: and Notes and Observations Concerning
                            Other Literary Characters of the Fifteenth and Sixteenth Centuries</title> (1805), 509&#8211;515; George Ellis, <title>Specimens
                            of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805), 536&#8211;544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Works of Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544&#8211;555; William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Spirit of Discovery</title>
                        (1804), 568&#8211;573; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals,
                            with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title> (1805), 575&#8211;576; John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810), <title>Oriental
                            Tales: Translated into English Verse</title> (1805), 576&#8211;578; Francis Burroughs (dates unknown), <title>A Poetical Epistle
                            to James Barry Esq.</title> (1805), 578&#8211;579; Vincenzo Monti (1754&#8211;1828), <title>Penance of Hugo: A Vision</title> (1805),
                        trans. Henry Boyd (1748/9&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), 581&#8211;588; James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Sabbath</title> (1805), 588&#8211;591; Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rhymes on Art, or, The
                            Remonstrance of a Painter</title> (1805), 592&#8211;596; Samuel Whitchurch, (dates unknown), <title>Hispaniola, a Poem</title>
                        (1804), 596&#8211;597; Matthew Rolleston (dates unknown), <title>The Anti-Corsican, A Poem</title> (1805), 597&#8211;598; Charles Grant,
                        Baron Glenelg (1778&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poem on the Restoration of Learning in the East</title> (1805), 598;
                        Edward Coxe (dates unknown), <title>Miscellaneous Poetry</title> (1805), 598&#8211;600; Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian, Containing the Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with
                            Notes and Illustrations</title> (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald Macdonald (1739&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>),<title> Some of
                            Ossian&#8217;s Lesser Poems Rendered into Verse [from Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s
                            Critical and Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Philip Massinger (1583&#8211;1640;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Plays</title> (1805), ed. William Gifford, 625&#8211;634; Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781),
                            <title>Nathan the Wise; a Dramatic Poem in Five Acts</title> (1805), trans. William Taylor, 634&#8211;639; John Collett (dates
                        unknown), <title>Sacred Dramas: Intended Chiefly for Young Persons</title> (1805), 639; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the
                            Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805), 679&#8211;699; Hannah More, <title>Hints Towards Forming the
                            Character of a Young Princess</title> (1805), 708&#8211;713; Joseph Lancaster (1778&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Improvements in Education as it Respects the Industrious Classes of the Community</title> (3rd edn, 1805), 732&#8211;736;
                        Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of
                            Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary Friends and Select Re-publications</title>
                        (1805), 736&#8211;738; William Henry Ireland (1775&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Confessions of William Henry Ireland
                            Containing the Particulars of his Fabrication of the Shakespeare Manuscripts</title> (1805), 743&#8211;745.</note> &#8211; which is
                    only this day begun, &#8211; &amp; another work, which is about a third part done, to compleat. Upon this I must for a time enjoin
                    secrecy, &#8211; observing none to you. It will appear as Letters from England, translated from the Spanish.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807).</note> being a faithful picture of society in England, to the best of my talents, coloured only by the feelings of a
                    Spaniard &amp; a Catholic. You will I hope like the book, &amp; I am sure heartily approve the whole feeling which will pervade
                    it. I wish for secrecy merely because it will serve the sale.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey wanted to preserve
                        his anonymity as the author of <title>Letters from England</title>, because he believed negative reviews by his enemies
                        affected sales of his work.</note> it is quite certain that such a book must excite attention, &amp; the suspicion which may
                    very probably arise, will stimulate curiosity. You need not be told that the only motive which could induce me to suspend my
                        history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> for the
                    time this has employed &amp; will employ, is a very urgent one. &#8211; I have not heard from Evans how <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> affairs are going on.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The lawyer hired by Hill, on <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa&#8217;s</ref> recommendation, to untangle
                            the payment of revenues that he derived from the clerical livings he held in Herefordshire.</note> He writes to me from Lisbon that if they are going
                    on as they should do there would be enough for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> &amp; for me. I am not
                    idle, &#8211; but the system of refusing to sell copy-right subjects me to present inconvenience &#8211; may I ask you to remit me forty
                    pounds? &#8211; to be repaid when the next Annual Review<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual</title> usually
                        appeared in March or April of the year.</note> is published &#8211; for I would rather ask it of you than of my bookseller, to whom
                    it is never advisable for an author to be under pecuniary obligation however trifling. My reviewing will discharge this debt &amp;
                    set me fairly even with the world &#8211; by spring too Madoc &amp; the Metrical Tales may have produced something, &amp; then Letters
                    &amp; the Specimens<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> and <title>Metrical Tales and Other
                            Poems</title> were both published in 1805. <title>Letters from England</title> and <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> were in preparation and were both published in 1807.</note> (which <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> delay has there most unreasonably <del>xxx</del> retarded, &amp;
                        <del>therefore</del> thereby amerced me of the profits of a whole years sale &#8211;) will in the course of the next two years, in
                    all human probability set me fairly beforehand with the world, &amp; make me perfectly at ease in my circumstances.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> sent books by the last convoy both to you &amp; to <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref>, &amp; I am uneasy at receiving no tidings of either consignment. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Little Edith</ref> is cutting her eye teeth, which makes her restless at night &amp;
                    irritable by day: of course I feel some anxiety, tho every thing promises well. I could tell you how sweet a child she is, how
                    forward in speech &amp; in intellect &amp; how winning in all her ways &#8211; but these are things not to be talked of beyond ones own
                    fireside &#8211; I am only afraid of loving any thing too well whose existence &#8211; or rather continuance here is so precarious.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have seen the Edinburgh review of Madoc<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Jeffrey&#8217;s review
                        appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> &#8211; <hi rend="ital">&amp;</hi> I have seen <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">the reviewer</ref> since it was printed &#8211; met him in Scotland &#8211; travelled with him, &amp;
                    entertained him here at supper. In all matters of taste he is so mere a child that the absolute contempt I felt when we measured
                    each others strength in conversation &#8211; effectually prevents any feeling of resentment for the language of contemptuous superiority
                    affected over me by an homunculus<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning a little or diminutive man; a mannikin.</note> of five feet two &amp; a half. So we are very good friends!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>