<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.970</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2092</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 299&#8211;302 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.970" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="970" type="letter">
        <head>970. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-07-30">30 July
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Galatea/ Barbadoes/ or
                        elsewhere/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ AUG/ 1804<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 299&#8211;302 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-07-30">Monday July 30. 1804.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your three letters of April 26. May 20 (the large sheet) &amp; June 11. have arrived together this evening, &amp;
                    relieved me from very considerable anxiety. mine I find are <del>xxx</del> consigned to the Atlantic without bottle,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey means that they have been lost. The reference is to his request to Thomas that he send
                        him messages in bottles from the West Indies &#8211; several of which did indeed reach Keswick. For an account of these experiments;
                        see Southey to the Editor of the <title>Athenaeum</title>, [April 1807], Letter 1314.</note> &amp; the books of Madoc<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and since then had
                        been intermittently revising. It was completed in October 1804 and published in 1805.</note> which <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> copied in them, gone to edify the Sharks &#8211; gentlemen who will digest them far
                    more easily than the Critics. However there must be yet some other letters on the way &amp; I trust you will have learnt before
                    this can reach you that I have now two Ediths in family, the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> (who was
                    born on the last of April) continuing to do well &#8211; only that I am myself somewhat alarmed at that premature activity of eye &amp;
                    spirits, &amp; those sudden startings which were in her poor sister the symptoms of a dreadful &amp; deadly disease. However I am
                    on my guard, &amp; the child has in her favour an excellent digestion which was not the case with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">the other</ref>. I did not mean to trust my affections again on so frail a
                    foundation &#8211; &amp; yet the young one takes me from my desk &amp; makes me talk nonsense as fluently as you perhaps can imagine.
                    Both <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; I are well. indeed I have weathered a rude winter &amp; a ruder
                    spring bravely. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is here &amp; has been here about three weeks, &amp;
                    will remain till the end of October. he is a very excellent companion &amp; tempts me out into the air &amp; the water when I
                    should else be sitting at home. I have seldom or never seen a young man promise better. For <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Scapegrace</ref> I have at last got an appointment &#8211; by means of Dickinson,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dickinson (1771&#8211;1837), a pupil at Westminster School, who later went on to Christ Church,
                        Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795) and was Civil Lord of the Admiralty, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> one of the new Lords of the Admiralty, to
                    whom as an old schoolfellow I applied thro <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. it is but just done &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is to go on board the Salvador del Mundo,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Salvador del Mundo</hi> was a 112-gun ship of the line, captured from the Spanish at the
                        battle of Cape St Vincent in 1797.</note> &amp; Admiral Colpoys<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Colpoys (c.
                        1742&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), British naval officer who achieved notoriety for inciting the mutiny at Spithead in 1797. He
                        was promoted to full Admiral in 1801 and appointed as Commander-in-Chief at Plymouth in 1803. In 1804 he gave up his command
                        to take a seat in the Admiralty.</note> will then ship him off to some foreign station, so you have a fair chance of seeing
                    Hopeful in the land of pine apples &amp; land crabs. So much for ourselves; &amp; thank God nothing but what is well. We have made
                    our way well in the world Tom, this far, &amp; by Gods help we shall yet get on better. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles of Antwerp</ref> is coming to see me &#8211; &amp; we look every day for
                    the letter which is to tell me to meet him. by his last it appears that Joe<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles
                        Danvers&#8217;s dog, formerly Thomas Southey&#8217;s.</note> was recovering from an indisposition &amp; a course of physic. Make your
                    fortune &amp; Joe may yet live to share its comforts as he stands upon his Majestys books in my name,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is stating that he has paid the &#8216;dog tax&#8217; for Joe; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 27 June 1804, Letter
                        956: &#8216;your right title to his Jacobship is still preserved, as the tax is paid in my name by Danvers &#8211; my Agent
                        Plenipotentiary&#8217;.</note> tho degraded by the appellation of mongrel. &#8211; Madoc is in a Scotch Press &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> who printed the Minstrelsy of the Scottish Border,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott, <title>Minstrelsy of the Scottish Border</title> (1802).</note> a book which you
                    may remember I bought at Bristol. he runs pretty hard. two proofs to day the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    &#8211; containing exactly those parts of the story which <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> copied for you. I shall be
                    hurried by him &#8211; for my work is by no means done, tho all the difficulty is over. I am finishing the last section of the new part
                    &#8211; indeed should have finished it this evening, if your letters had not happily arrived &#8211; for I should not have had heart to write
                    again till some tidings of you arrived. This insertion which contains above a thousand lines brings me to the old eighth book &#8211;
                    but thenceforward all is plain sailing &#8211; &amp; I have only to correct &amp; ornament a story which requires but little alteration.
                    &#8211; You ask of Amadis. it has been well received both in the Annual &amp; the Edinburgh by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 600&#8211;603, and in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 5 (October 1803), 109&#8211;136.</note> who in both has been very civil to me, tho he has miserably
                    misrepresented the arguments of the preface which prove Vasco Lobeira<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vasco de Lobeira
                        (d. 1403) a troubador knighted after the Battle of Aljubarrota (1385).</note> to have been the author. Of all my later
                    publications this has been the most successful &#8211; more than 500 of the 1000 having sold within the year, so that there is a fair
                    chance of the 50 &#163; dependant upon the sale of the whole. Thalaba has been very admirably reviewd in the Critical by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor&#8217;s review of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) appeared in <title>The Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 39 (December
                        1803), 369&#8211;379.</note> but it does not sell &amp; will not for some years reach a second edition, till the current of my
                    reputation sets in full, as it one day will do, &amp; then it will be carried down. Tomorrow I send off the two Anthologies that
                    the best <del>x may</del> pieces then may be reprinted in a seperate form, revised &amp; arranged.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poems from the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) reappeared in his <title>Metrical Tales
                            and Other Poems</title> (1805).</note> 500 will sell certainly, &amp; tho my profits will not exceed 30 &#163; &#8211; still even
                    that sum is to me worth having, especially as it requires no labour. My last letter will have told you of a more promising
                    speculation &#8211; the Specimens of the Later English Poets &#8211; who have died between the year 1688 &amp; 1800 &#8211; designed as a supplement
                    to <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis&#8217;s</ref> book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The project that
                        Southey undertook with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>. It was a
                        companion work to George Ellis&#8217;s <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn 1801, 3rd edn 1803).
                        Southey&#8217;s last surviving letter to his brother Tom (27 June 1804; Letter 956) did not mention the <title>Specimens</title>;
                        the previous one (1 June 1804; Letter 947) did.</note> this is sure to sell, &amp; is the main hope of my Ways &amp; Means.
                    Reviewing is coming round again! One parcel arrived! another on the road! a third ready to start. &#8211; I grudge the time thus to be
                    sold, sorely &#8211; but patience! it is after all better than reading the Athanasian Creed<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        That is, becoming a priest in the Church of England. The Athanasian creed is a Christian statement of belief, focusing on
                        Trinitarian doctrine, attributed to St Athanasius (c. 293&#8211;373) and used by Christian churches since the sixth century
                        AD.</note> &#8211; pleading in a stinking court of Law &#8211; or being called up at midnight to a patient. it is better than being a
                    soldier or sailor &#8211; better than calculating profit &amp; loss in a counter, &#8211; better in short than any thing except independence.
                    Have you yet got the Second Volume? there are two famous articles on Malthuss Essay, &amp; the History of the Methodists in which
                    you will trace my gall.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), Southey
                        reviewed Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it affects the
                            future improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title>
                        (1803), 292&#8211;301, and William Myles (1756&#8211;1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People called Methodists ... With an
                            Appendix, Containing Two Lists of the Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of the Rev. J.
                            Wesley</title> (1803), 201&#8211;213.</note> &#8211; Henry has never arrived,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Henry
                        (1718&#8211;1790), <title>The History of Great Britain, From the First Invasion of it by the Romans under Julius C&#230;sar</title>
                        (1771&#8211;1793), was delayed in the post, its despatch having been entrusted by Southey&#8217;s brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref> to a bookseller in Cork; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 1 February 1804,
                        Letter 892.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Owen Rees</ref> is going to Ireland &amp; I have requested him to enquire
                    for it, which he can do well as his business lies with the booksellers. &#8211; July is indeed a lovely month at the Lakes, &amp; so the
                    Lakers seem to think, for they swarm here. We have been much interrupted by visitors &#8211; among others young Roscoe,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Stanley Roscoe (1782&#8211;1843): poet, and eldest son of <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William Roscoe</ref>. Educated at Peterhouse, Cambridge, he became a partner in his
                        father&#8217;s bank but was also a student of Italian literature.</note> &#8211; &amp; more are yet to come. A friend of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> is hourly expected. these are not the only interruptions. we have been &#8211;
                    or rather are manufacturing black currant rum for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &amp; black currant
                    wine for ourselves &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I chief workmen, pounding them in a wooden
                    bowl with a great stone, as the acid acts upon a metal mortar. We have compleated a great work &#8211; that of bridging the river Greta
                    at the bottom of the orchard, by piling heaps of stones so as to step from one to another. many a hard hours sport half knee deep
                    in the water. <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> has been here, &#8211; stark mad for angling. this is our history. Yours
                    is rather busier, &amp; has been hitherto more profitable &#8211; your prize came in time, &amp; I hope the second will not prove a
                        disappointment.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Southey's letter to Charles Danvers, 2 August 1804, Letter 971, he
                        reports Tom&#8217;s news of &#8216;a recapture which will give him &#163;120 &amp; set him on his legs for he was behind-hand &#8211; &amp; a ship
                        from Hambro [Hamburg] detained, which if it be condemned (&amp; they say there is every reason to suppose it will) will double
                        his half pay.&#8217;</note> You cannot tell how earnestly we have looked for the Galateas<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate.</note> name in the papers &#8211; &amp; how
                    earnestly I shall continue to look for it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for news the packet which conveys this will convey later intelligence than is in my power to communicate. <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis</ref> may &amp; probably will lose his election. but it is evident that he has not
                    lost his popularity.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burdett&#8217;s election victory in Middlesex in 1802 alarmed the
                        government and the election was subsequently voided. A new contest took place in 1804 and Burdett was narrowly defeated as a
                        result of misconduct by the Middlesex sheriffs. The results were subsequently overturned and Burdett sat in parliament for
                        Middlesex in 1805&#8211;1806 (<title>DNB</title>).</note> Pitt will go on blundering till every body by miserable experience shall
                    at last think him the despicable dog that I always did.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>) had become Prime Minister for the second time on 10 May 1804.</note> As for Emperor Bonaparte<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821) was Emperor of the French from 1804 to 1814.</note> &#8211; damn
                    him &#8211; he furnished me with a piddling pun yesterday night &#8211; looking in the Cookery book I saw a receipt for making Imperial Water
                    &amp; could not help remarking that that was what Bonaparte made now.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My journey to London almost knocked me up. the fatigue was excessive. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> is an excellent house for me. I worked hard at the book of Specimens, &amp; still harder in visiting as many
                    of the Thousand and One persons who expected me to visit them, as possible. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>
                    talks of coming here in the autumn &#8211; in the hope of carrying me back with him to Wales &#8211; an expedition for which I cannot
                    conveniently spare time, yet did not willingly give it up, as I shall travel with every possible advantage. You doubted whether we
                    should be at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. I have no intention of removing till upon some definite plan, &amp;
                    it will certainly not be desirable to settle till my journey to Portugal be over. perhaps I may be able to go by the winter of
                    next year. certainly not before &#8211; &amp; till then, for certainly I shall have no means of removing any where till then, shall
                    remain where I am, a situation in every way desirable were it not quite so far from London, &amp; my books. Whensover the great
                    change of ministry to which we all look on with hope takes place I shall have friends in power able to serve me, &amp; shall in
                    fact without scruple apply to <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> thro one or two good channels. this may be very
                    remote &amp; yet may be very near. &#8211; When Madoc is published I mean to send Fox a copy with such a note as may be proper for me to
                    address such a man. I love Homer, &amp; I do not think this poem unworthy <del>to offer</del> &lt;of being offered&gt; to a lover
                    of the Odyssey. &#8211; I will also send one to the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">Old Boy</ref>. taking care to pay carriage
                    &amp; frank the letter which announces it. The Scotch reviewers<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>.</note> are grown exceedingly civil to me &#8211; partly influenced by <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> who has lived intimately among them, partly by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> who is
                    enlisted among them &amp; is disposed to be very courteous, &amp; partly perhaps because they know <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, who makes his talents felt among the Edinburgh literati, having lived
                    &amp; learnt from <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">Wm T.</ref> a man who has more guts in his brain than all the Scotchmen
                    ever had or will have from the day of Creation to the Day of Judgement. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you Tom. it grows late &amp; I have two proofs to correct for this nights post. once more God
                        bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>