<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1459</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2581</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Victoria and Albert Museum, National Art Library, MS Forster 48 D.32
                        MS 2.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 145&#8211;147.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1459" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1459" type="letter">
        <head>1459. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1808-05-20">20 May
                    1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 1. Albemarle
                        Row/ Hotwells/ Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Victoria and Albert Museum, National Art Library, MS Forster 48 D.32
                        MS 2<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 145&#8211;147.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have bound me to the completion of Kehama,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &amp; if I have health &amp; eye-sight, compleated it will be within twelvemonths. Want of
                    practice has not weakened me, &#8211; I have ascertained this, &amp; am proceeding.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will use such materials as have stood the test, &#8211; those materials are the same in all languages, &amp; we know
                    what they are. With respect to metre it is otherwise. there we must look to English only, &amp; in English we have no other great
                    poem than Paradise Lost. Blank verse has long appeared to me the noblest measure of which our language is capable, &#8211; but it would
                    not suit Kehama. there must be quicker &#8211; wilder movements &#8211; there must be gorgeousness of ornament also, &#8211; eastern gem work; &#8211;
                    &amp; sometimes rhyme must be scattered upon rhyme till the reader is half dozing with the thundering echo. My motto must be
                    &#928;&#959;&#953;&#954;&#953;&#955;&#959;&#957; &#949;&#953;&#948;&#959;&#962; &#949;&#967;&#969;&#957;, &#959;&#964;&#953;
                    &#960;&#959;&#953;&#954;&#953;&#955;&#959;&#957; <del>&#948;&#953;</del> &#965;&#956;&#957;&#959;&#957;
                        &#945;&#961;&#945;&#963;&#963;&#969;.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Nonnus, <title>Dionysiaca</title>, Book 1,
                        line 15: &#8216;having a diversity of shapes, since I twang my harp to a diverse song&#8217;.</note> This is not from any ambition of
                    novelty, but from the nature &amp; necessity of the subject. I am well aware that novelty in such things <del>in</del> is an
                    obstacle to success, &#8211; Thalaba<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> has
                    proved it to be so. The mass of mankind hate innovation, they hate to unlearn what they have learnt wrong, &amp; they hate to
                    confess their ignorance by submitting to learn any thing right. I would tread in the beaten road <del>th</del> rather than get
                    among thorns by turning out of it, but the beaten road will not take me where I want to go. What seems best to be done is this, to
                    write mostly in rhyme, &#8211; to slip into it rather than out of it, &amp; then generally into some metre so strongly marked as to
                    leave the ear fully satisfied.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One inference I think must be drawn from the obscurity of Pindars<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Greek lyric poet (ca. 522&#8211;443 BC).</note> metre that be what it may, the pleasure which it gave did not result from the
                    rhythm. Indeed the whole system of Classical metres seems to have been that of creating difficulty for the sake of overcoming it.
                    We mis-read sapphics without making them worse, &#8211; we misread pentameters &amp; make better; &amp; the hexameter remains the most
                    perceptible of all other measures tho in our pronunciation we generally distort four feet out of six.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A great deal more may be done with rhyme than has yet been done with it &#8211; there is a crypto-rhyme which may often
                    be introduced with excellent effect, the eye has nothing to do with it, but the ear feels it without perhaps perceiving any thing
                    more than the general <del>effect</del> &lt;harmony&gt;, &amp; not knowing how that <del>effect was</del> &lt;harmony is&gt;
                    produced. Sometimes the sparing inter mixture of rhyme in a paragraph may be so managed as to satisfy the ear, &amp; give greater
                    effect to their after profusion. These are not things which one thinks of in composition, but they are thought of in correcting.
                    They are the touches in finishing off, when a little alteration produces a great difference</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your dislike of the ballad metre is perhaps because you are sick of a tune which has been sung so often &amp; so
                    badly. It is not as capable of dignity, but there is a sort of language which usually goes with it &amp; <del>seems to</del> has
                    the effect of making it so. Kehama is pitched in too high a key for it. I shall weed out all uncouth lines, &amp; leave the public
                    nothing to abuse except the strangeness of the fable, which you may be sure will be plentifully abused. The mythology
                        <del>will</del> explains itself as it is introduced, &#8211; yet because the names are not familiar people will fancy there is a
                    difficulty in understanding it. Sir William Jones has <del>not</del> done nothing in introducing it so coldly &amp; formally as he
                    has done.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The linguist and judge (1746&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), founder of the
                        Asiatic Society of Bengal, who had introduced the poetry and mythology of Hindu India to Europe in its journal <title>Asiatick
                            Researches</title>, by his translation of Kalidasa&#8217;s <title>Sacontal&#225;</title> (1789) and by poems such as his &#8216;Hymn to
                        Durga&#8217; (1788).</note> They who read his poems do not remember them, &amp; none but those who have read them can be expected to
                    have even heard of my Divinities. But for popularity I care only as it regards profit, &#8211; &amp; for profit only as it regards
                    subsistence. The praise of ten would have contented you, often have I said that you did not underrate the number of men whose
                    praise was <del>des</del> truly desirable. Ten thousand persons will read my book, &#8211; if five hundred will promise to buy it I
                    shall be secure of all I want, &#8211; You shall have it in large portions as fast as it is written.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did send Landor further extracts from the poem; see Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 26
                        November 1808 (Letter 1543), 13 July 1809 (Letter 1653), 30 September [1809] (Letter 1688), and [25/26 November 1809] (Letter
                        1715).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1808-05-20"> May 20. 1808.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>