<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1108</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2230</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    401&#8211;404.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1108" type="letter">
        <head>1108. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-10-01">1 October
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Amelia/ Barbadoes./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ OCT 4/ 1805<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    401&#8211;404.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-10-01">October 1. 1805.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is quite vexatious to see with what rascally negligence your West Indian post is managed. My last will have told
                    you that Extract 3. had arrived<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 22 August 1805, Letter
                        1095.</note> &#8211; above a month afterwards came that marked Ext. 2. &amp; the next day N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5. 1 &amp; 4
                    therefore <del>are</del> have miscarried, or as yet are missing. I thank you heartily for these &amp; for all your letters, &#8211; they
                    are full of interesting matter &amp; you will yourself think so, when you look them over collectively. let me set you more work.
                    If ever you happen to see a Planters books cast your eye along the backs &amp; give me an idea of what a Planters library may
                    consist. How are their houses built? how furnished? their dinners. in what are they like or unlike English meals? What sort of
                    churches? meeting houses if <del>xxx</del> any? There has been a magazine lately published in Jamaica bring this home if you can
                    get it, &amp; a bunch of Jamaica or any other papers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your last letter startled me &#8211; I hoped you were climate proof before this time. About exchanging to come to Europe
                    you best know what is professionally best &#8211; &amp; it is worth while to sacrifice something to get <del>nearer</del> into a
                    wholesome air. besides I heartily &amp; hourly wish you were nearer &#8211; not at that dismal distance. I am going to Lisbon in March
                    or April next. whether or not <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> goes is quite uncertain as yet &#8211; you will easily
                    conceive how much I wish I could then get upon the Lisbon station &#8211; or even at Gibraltar for I would go on to see you. Of peace
                    there is no prospect, tho it may yet come suddenly. a change at home is more probable, from the great strength of the opposition
                    &amp; the miserable state of the King,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great Britain
                        1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). During his latest outbreak of madness, the King was making inappropriate sexual remarks in
                        public; he again declared his desire for Elizabeth Herbert, Countess of Pembroke and Montgomery (1737&#8211;1831;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> who like Solomon in his old years is backsliding, being led astray by strange women.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Old Testament king of Israel, whose propensity for foreign princesses as wives and
                        mistresses, was supposed to have led him away from his religious faith.</note> In case of such a change of administration as
                    is to be expected, &amp; indeed sooner or later must take place I have good hope of doing something for you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now to the subject of the prize money. I wrote two articles in the Courier putting the case fairly &amp; forcibly
                    before the public.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804, the naval ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of
                        which Thomas Southey was a lieutenant, had captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with
                        cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict,
                        but in this case the prize money was contested because the ships were captured before war was officially declared. Southey
                        took up his brother&#8217;s cause to have his share reinstated in <title>The Courier</title> which published a paragraph supporting
                        the sailors&#8217; claim to the prize-money on Saturday 24 August 1805. This was followed by a longer defence of their position in
                            <title>The Courier</title> on 31 August 1805 under the title &#8216;Indemnification to the Spanish Merchants&#8217;.</note> In a few
                    days comes a reply from a Spanish Merchant stating that as the prizes taken <hi rend="ital">before</hi> the Declaration of War are
                    droits of the crown, &amp; only given in former cases by special favour to the navy, there was no injustice in withholding from
                    them what they never had any <hi rend="ital">right</hi> to. To this I replied, &amp; yesterday the Courier in their leading
                    article assert that their Correspondent (meaning me) has been greatly mistaken, for that the sailors are not to receive one
                    farthing less than in former cases.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A &#8216;reply from a Spanish merchant&#8217; appeared in
                            <title>The Courier</title> for 4 September 1805, and Southey&#8217;s response, that the prize money was being withheld from the
                        sailors in a measure that was &#8216;impolitic, ungenerous and unjust&#8217; was published in <title>The Courier</title> of 25 September
                        1805, p. 2. This was refuted by an editorial article in <title>The Courier</title> of 28 September 1805, where it was stated
                        that there was no truth in Southey&#8217;s assertion.</note> If this be true you may thank me for it, &#8211; for the Spanish Merchants
                    themselves understood the matter as I understood it. I believe Government has been puzzled by its first blunder of stopping the
                    frigates in that buccaneering &amp; infamous manner, &#8211; that by way of making out a better story they resolved to give them to the
                    Merchants, then finding that was not enough tost your prizes into the bargain, &#8211; then fearing the unpopularity of this, thought to
                    halve it, &#8211; for <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> knows a Captain who had received half his share &amp; was to
                    have no more, &#8211; &amp; lately that they have given the matter up &amp; you will have your full due. I do not know that any one
                    besides myself has stirred publicly in the business.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tomorrow I am going to Edinburgh with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> for a fortnight, just to
                    see the place &amp; the people, the city itself being by general consent one of the finest in the world. On my return I have a
                    world of business to get thro. What with <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &amp; other visitors my whole
                    summer has been almost wholly consumed in walking or boating on this lovely lake.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Derwentwater.</note> There lie untouched upon the shelf as many books for the Annual Review as will make a full sixth of the
                    next volume, to which I must fall unintermittingly to work without delay.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed
                        in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806): James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>), <title>Travels to
                            Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title> (2nd edn, 1804&#8211;1805), 2&#8211;16; Thomas Lindley (dates unknown),
                            <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ... with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and
                            Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto Seguro</title> (1805), 27&#8211;32; Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The Present
                            State of Peru, Comprising its Geography, Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and Manners of its
                            Inhabitants; Embellished by ... Engravings of Costumes</title> (1805), 49&#8211;60; John Griffiths (dates unknown),
                            <title>Travels in Europe, Asia Minor and Arabia</title> (1805), 67&#8211;77; James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 1; 1805), 99&#8211;100; Charles
                        Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title>
                        (1805), trans. B Lambert (dates unknown), 177&#8211;187; William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de
                            Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467; Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848), <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805), 477&#8211;483;
                        Dieudonn&#233; Thi&#233;bault (1733&#8211;1807), <title>Original Anecdotes of Frederic the Second, King of Prussia, and of his Family, his
                            Court, his Ministers, his Academies, and his Literary Friends: Collected During a Familiar Intercourse of Twenty Years
                            with that Prince</title> (1805), 488&#8211;495; William Parr Greswell (bap. 1765&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of
                            Angelus Politianus, Joannes Picus of Mirandula, Actius Sincerus Sannazarius, Petrus Bembus, Hieronymus Fracastorius,
                            Marcus Antonius Flaminius, and the Amalthei: Translations from their Poetical Works: and Notes and Observations Concerning
                            Other Literary Characters of the Fifteenth and Sixteenth Centuries</title> (1805), 509&#8211;515; George Ellis, <title>Specimens
                            of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805), 536&#8211;544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Works of Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544&#8211;555; William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Spirit of Discovery</title>
                        (1804), 568&#8211;573; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals,
                            with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title> (1805), 575&#8211;576; John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810), <title>Oriental
                            Tales: Translated into English Verse</title> (1805), 576&#8211;578; Francis Burroughs (dates unknown), <title>A Poetical Epistle
                            to James Barry Esq.</title> (1805), 578&#8211;579; Vincenzo Monti (1754&#8211;1828), <title>Penance of Hugo: A Vision</title> (1805),
                        trans. Henry Boyd (1748/9&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), 581&#8211;588; James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Sabbath</title> (1805), 588&#8211;591; Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rhymes on Art, or, The
                            Remonstrance of a Painter</title> (1805), 592&#8211;596; Samuel Whitchurch, (dates unknown), <title>Hispaniola, a Poem</title>
                        (1804), 596&#8211;597; Matthew Rolleston (dates unknown), <title>The Anti-Corsican, A Poem</title> (1805), 597&#8211;598; Charles Grant,
                        Baron Glenelg (1778&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poem on the Restoration of Learning in the East</title> (1805), 598;
                        Edward Coxe (dates unknown), <title>Miscellaneous Poetry</title> (1805), 598&#8211;600; Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian, Containing the Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with
                            Notes and Illustrations</title> (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald Macdonald (1739&#8211;1814; DNB), <title>Some of Ossian&#8217;s Lesser
                            Poems Rendered into Verse [from Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s Critical and
                            Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Philip Massinger (1583&#8211;1640;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Plays</title> (1805), ed. William Gifford, 625&#8211;634; Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781),
                            <title>Nathan the Wise; a Dramatic Poem in Five Acts</title> (1805), trans. William Taylor, 634&#8211;639; John Collett (dates
                        unknown), <title>Sacred Dramas: Intended Chiefly for Young Persons</title> (1805), 639; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the
                            Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805), 679&#8211;699; Hannah More, <title>Hints Towards Forming the
                            Character of a Young Princess</title> (1805), 708&#8211;713; Joseph Lancaster (1778&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Improvements in Education as it Respects the Industrious Classes of the Community</title> (3rd edn, 1805), 732&#8211;736;
                        Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of
                            Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary Friends and Select Re-publications</title>
                        (1805), 736&#8211;738; William Henry Ireland (1775&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Confessions of William Henry Ireland
                            Containing the Particulars of his Fabrication of the Shakespeare Manuscripts</title> (1805), 743&#8211;745.</note> Besides this
                    I have the preface for the Specimens to write<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s joint project with Bedford,
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>
                        in 1807 as a companion work to George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn 1801, 3rd edn
                        1803) (1807).</note> &amp; to get Espriella ready for the press,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &amp; now
                        <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> has thus applied to me to furnish the Spanish &amp;
                    Portugueze literary biography for the remaining volumes of his great biographical dictionary.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin&#8217;s <title>General Biography: or, Lives, Critical and Historical, of the Most Eminent Persons of all
                            Ages, Countries, Conditions, and Professions, Arranged According to Alphabetical Order</title> was published in 10 volumes
                        between 1799&#8211;1815. According to Kenneth Curry (<title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, p. 403) Southey contributed the following entries to volumes VI (1807), VII (1808) and VIII (1813): Volume VI:
                        &#8216;Vasco Lobeira&#8217;, 314&#8211;317; &#8216;Francisco Rodrigues Lobo&#8217;, 318; &#8216;Fernam Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Gregorio Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Francisco de Losa&#8217;,
                        344&#8211;345; &#8216;Joam de Lucena&#8217;, 371&#8211;372; &#8216;Miguel de Luna&#8217;, 388; &#8216;Fr. Francisco de Santo Agostinho Macedo&#8217;, 434&#8211;435, &#8216;El Enamorado
                        Macias&#8217;, 437&#8211;438; &#8216;P. Fr. Pedro Malon de Chaide&#8217;, 506; &#8216;D. Jorge Manrique&#8217;, 523&#8211;524; &#8216;Don Juan Manuel&#8217;, 529&#8211;530; &#8216;Ausias
                        March&#8217;, 542&#8211;543; &#8216;Juan de Mariana&#8217;, 555&#8211;557; &#8216;Vicente Mariner&#8217;, 558; &#8216;Luis de Marmol Carvajal&#8217;, 569; &#8216;P. M. Fr. Juan Marquez&#8217;,
                        574&#8211;575. Volume VII: &#8216;Juan de Mena&#8217;, 28&#8211;30; &#8216;Don Inigo Lopez de Mendoza&#8217;, 37&#8211;38; &#8216;D. Diego Hurtado de Mendoza&#8217;, 38&#8211;39;
                        &#8216;Menezes&#8217;, 41&#8211;42; &#8216;Christoval de Mesa&#8217;, 59&#8211;60; &#8216;George de Montemayor&#8217;, 174&#8211;175; &#8216;Ambrosio de Morales&#8217;, 194&#8211;198; &#8216;Alonso de
                        Castro Nunez&#8217;, 466; &#8216;Antonio de Naxara&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Abraham Nehemias&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Florian de Ocampo&#8217;, 471&#8211;472; &#8216;Fr. Diego de Olarte&#8217;,
                        487; &#8216;Fr. Andres de Olmos&#8217;, 497; &#8216;Jerome Osorio&#8217; [with Thomas Morgan (1752&#8211;1821)], 530&#8211;533; &#8216;Alonso de Ovalle&#8217;, 548; &#8216;Andres
                        de Oviedo&#8217;, 555&#8211;556; &#8216;Gonzalo Fernandez de Oviedo&#8217;, 556&#8211;557; &#8216;Lorenzo de Padilla&#8217;, 578; &#8216;Pedro Paez&#8217;, 578&#8211;580; &#8216;D. Juan de
                        Palafox y Mendoza&#8217;, 585. Volume VIII: &#8216;Josef de Ossau, Salas y Pellicer&#8217;, 25&#8211;26; Bartholom&#233; Pereira&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Luys Pereyra&#8217;, 46;
                        &#8216;Antonio Perez&#8217;, 46&#8211;47; &#8216;Ruy de Pina&#8217;, 173; &#8216;Juan de Pineda&#8217;, 175; &#8216;Fernam Mendes Pinto&#8217;, 178&#8211;179; &#8216;Thome Pires&#8217;, 182&#8211;184;
                        &#8216;Fernando de Pulgar&#8217;, 385.</note> Did I also tell you that Joan of Arc being again in the press <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has put the Vision <del>at</del> at the end of the poem, so that there is a
                    gap in the second vol. of Poems to be filled up, which gap I must supply with pieces from the very first volume of all, &amp;
                    tinker them for the purpose.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> was
                        published in 1806, with the &#8216;Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217; &#8211; originally published in the second volume of
                            <title>Poems</title> (1799) &#8211; printed at the end of the poem. Southey now wished to fill the gap made by the removal of
                        the &#8216;Vision&#8217; in the new 1806 edition of <title>Poems</title> that he was preparing for the press. He filled it with &#8216;The
                        Retrospect&#8217;, originally published in <title>Poems</title> (1795). For the alterations, see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical
                            Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols. (London, 2004), I.</note> All this will fully occupy me till March,
                    &amp; as soon as all this is cleared off I shall start for London, where I must needs pass a few days previous to my departure,
                    then go for Bristol, &amp; sail in a Portugueze vessel, the Captain of which is well known to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &#8211; a good ship, well fitted for passengers at about half the price of the
                        Packet.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not make his intended trip to Portugal as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> did not wish to go and he did not want to be separated from her. See Southey
                        to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 20 October 1805, Letter 1113.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These are my plans, &amp; I hope they will not be disappointed. You I think had better get removed if you can,
                    &amp; if the disadvantages be not very great, for it is worth some sacrifice to get a little nearer us, &amp; a little farther
                    from the land crabs.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> is lodging at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Did I ever tell you that soon after you left Bristol he wrote a letter to me soliciting a reconciliation? that
                    I sent him up to &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> who crammed him with so much surgery that he got a
                    birth in the army &#8211; &amp; that he gave up this to go &amp; live with a Polish Count in Poland as Librarian? &#8211; the sequel is &#8211; that
                    he is just come back over head &amp; ears in love with a Polish Princess who happens to be the said Counts Wife!!! &#8211; I think Tom
                    you will shake your sides at this. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Little Edith</ref> goes on excellently well &#8211; she
                    makes herself understood about every thing, &amp; <hi rend="ital">Pappa</hi> is the favourite. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> herself has been very well till last night she was taken with a sore throat,
                    which tho it does not threaten any thing may possibly for a day or two delay my departure. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is very well. <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> has
                    at last carried into effect her promised visit. she has been here about a week, &amp; is making drawings of this noble scenery. &#8211;
                    Long ere this you must have received Madoc, &amp; I hope the Reviews are by this time arrived also.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey sent copies of the <title>Annual Review</title> containing his articles to his brother.</note> Madoc
                    has not yet &#8211; to my knowledge, been reviewed, &#8211; but I am out of the way of knowing these things here. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> still at Malta. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> I hear is going into the Caermarthensh. Militia. he has been to Lisbon &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> thinks him the most impudent &amp; worthless coxcomb that ever disgraced
                    his relations, &#8211; &amp; so he is in plain truth. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>