<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1233</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2355</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1233" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1233" type="letter">
        <head>1233. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1806-11-03">3 November
                    1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/ Staffordshire<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: No. 3. J.f. Bath<lb /> MS: MS untraced; text from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                        Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 208&#8211;212.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Senhora you mistake the orthography of Aballiboozobanganorribo.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A word
                        used in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847), I, p. 165, in humorous imitation of &#8216;certain letters of unknown
                        signification&#8217; in the &#8216;Koran&#8217; (Qur&#8217;an), whose &#8216;commentators say that the meaning of these initials ought not to be
                        inquired&#8217;.</note> you write it as if it were two words making the first syllable an interjection &amp; the remainder either
                    noun or adjective. In common cases the Ladies must be allowed their privilege of having but one rule for spelling &amp; for every
                    thing else, &#8211; that is &#8211; their own pleasure; &amp; of treating his Magistys English with the same omnipotent caprice as they do his
                    male subjects. But this prerogative does not extend to Aballiboozoganganorribo, which is no part of the Kings English, but is
                    music &amp; music alone. The mysteries of that word, as <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcote</ref> says of
                    one of her books,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>A Continuation of Prophecies, by Joanna Southcott, from the
                            Year 1792, to the Present Time March, 1802</title>, Southcott declares of her former predictions, &#8216;the last eight pages of
                        the book of Letters are hastening on. The prophecies in that book are deeper than any man can imagine&#8217;.</note> are deeper than
                    any one can conceive.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have added half a dozen lines to make a hasty conclusion to those upon the death of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John S.</ref>  &amp; will at no very distant time send them you, &#8211; but
                    do not you let them be seen by any who may talk of them again, as that would not be so well.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;For the lines on John Southey, see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 17&#8211;18 October 1806, Letter 1228.</note>
                    Except this finish they were literally thrown off the evening that the news reached me &#8211; I read the letter &#8211; drank tea &#8211; &amp;
                    having less matter to think of than I should have had had he left me a rich man, wrote verse to his memory which most likely I
                    should never have done as his heir. Some evening when my conscience &#8211; both that which is I know not where, &amp; that other one
                    whose seat is in the purse, &amp; which touches one sometimes in the breeches pocket &#8211; when these two will let me feel that I can
                    honestly afford the leisure &#8211; I will draw a picture of the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">old man</ref>  in
                    blank verse, &#8211; &amp; perhaps (the thought strikes me now when talking about it with the slow tongue of this soft Keswick-quill)
                    perhaps go on &amp; make a set of family portraits. in truth if I had leisure enough &amp; could call up heart to speak of the
                    dead, this idea might lead to some thing very delightful to myself &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, &amp; worth something when he &amp; I shall have rejoined those who are gone before us, &amp; all our generation shall
                    have past away also. I could say something about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>  in
                    a plain tale which should go to the heart of thousands, &amp; reach no heart without leaving some good feeling behind it. But here
                    I am Senhora working six hours at every sheet of Palmerin,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was preparing for
                        the press an English translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title>, published in 4 volumes in
                        1807.</note> &amp; resting from that only to turn to something else. It is very well as it is, but it might be better. It is
                    better than law &#8211; better than physic &#8211; better than divinity, &#8211; in short better than any thing else that I could have done, &#8211; but
                    it may be better yet; &#8211; &amp; till it is I shall say Aballiboozobanganorribo, &amp; when it is better I shall say so still &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your last letter gave me some uncomfortable thoughts &#8211; tho it did not much surprise me. I fear you will have some
                    domestic trouble in store. Your father<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Barker (dates unknown).</note> like a bad
                    government still kept his family together &#8211; the tie between brother<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick Barker
                        (dates unknown).</note> &amp; sister is easily broken. Like to like is not merely true in the loving sense<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the left margin beside this sentence a large &#8216;S&#8217; is written in pencil in Barker&#8217;s
                        hand.</note> but in the moral &amp; intellectual &#8211; the value of a human being as if a jewel, must be understood or it will not
                    be appreciated at its worth. I wish your interest &amp; Fredericks were bound together by the plan you told me of. Without some
                    such legal bond natural ones are too weak &#8211; what he said in his cups he may resolve upon afterwards &#8211; &amp; literally turn
                    soldier; &#8211; still more likely he may marry, &#8211; &amp; then unless his wife be a rare woman indeed, she will fancy her interest &amp;
                    yours clash, &amp; there is no dependence upon any thing except moral or intellectual strength, &#8211; of which it seems to me you have
                    monopolized what, if it had been divided between you, would have made a whole family far above par. &#8211; I could tell your fortune
                    without looking in the stars for it &#8211; but I will not, for tho it ends in content there is a dark middleground to be past over.
                    However it is better not to be quite happy enough in this world, than to be too happy &#8211; trees that must be transplanted suffer
                    most when their roots are deepest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I am a Cock-Simorg<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Persian mythology, a fabulous undying bird;
                        it features in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 11.</note> I beg &amp; desire you will be pleased to come
                    &amp; perch by me, in the vale of my repose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is at last arrived<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Coleridge had travelled abroad to Malta for his health in 1804, taking up a temporary post there as Public Secretary to the
                        British Civil Commissioner. He arrived back in England in August 1806 and though he returned to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> at the end of October, he did not stay to live there.</note> &#8211; little improved
                    in health of body &amp; not at all so in health of mind. He is grown very fat &#8211; which he attributes to disease &amp; his wife
                    believes it &#8211; the fact is that he is always eating &amp; drinking &#8211; morning noon &amp; midnight, &#8211; hardly ever without rum &amp;
                    water beside him sugared to the utmost, &#8211; if he is not talking he must be eating &#8211; his mouth seems incapable of being at rest. If
                    he does not sleep at night &#8211; up he gets for cold meat &amp; spirits &amp; water. If all this does not kill a man it must needs
                    fatten him &#8211; &amp; if he goes on he will be brought to as many stone as Peter<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A pet
                        pig owned by Barker.</note> was &amp; by the same process. He came on Thursday last &#8211; a heap of letters which awaited him lies
                    still unopened upon his table &#8211; increasing every day. He has begun to teach the two boys<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> Coleridge.</note> Greek! &amp; I think it very possible that he may go on with them three days more. As you
                    may suppose he is very entertaining, &#8211; but whether it be that he is really worsened, or that after so long an absence this thing
                    becomes more striking &#8211; I never saw a human countenance express such intense &amp; loathsome arrogance of self admiration. It is
                    at times quite fiendish. His humour is now to be orthodox because he has made out some metaphysical arguments for the Trinity &#8211; In
                    short I feel more than ever admiration &amp; astonishment at his intellect &amp; more than ever grief &amp; indignation at all
                    that it is coupled with. He goes to London to lecture.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was to lecture at the
                        Royal Institution upon &#8216;the Principles common to the Fine Arts&#8217;; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 18 October 1806, Letter 1229.
                        He did not in fact lecture there until 1808, on the subjects of the Principles of Poetry, Shakespeare and Milton.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs C</ref>  I fancy has little wish to accompany him. &#8211; as I hope <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> may winter here I wish him gone. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">He</ref>  &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> dislike one another heartily, &#8211; as you may
                    imagine; &amp; I had rather they did not meet. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">young one</ref>  goes on well. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>  talks of you very often &amp; with great delight. that
                    child has all good seeds in her nature &#8211; she is slow to like &#8211; &amp; still slower to leave liking &#8211; If she were not to see you
                    these seven years your name would always excite in her pleasant recollections.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Mrs. Peachey</ref>  is very ill &#8211; &amp; there is no alarming the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref>. He never will believe her in danger for half an hour at
                    a time till she is in her coffin &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> comes I will tell him to call at <ref target="places.html#Congreve">Congreve</ref> for the Evangelicals.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Copies of the
                            <title>Evangelical Magazine</title> unwanted by Barker.</note> Such a cargo ought to secure him from overtures &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-11-03">Nov. 3. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>