<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1109</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2231</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    339&#8211;341.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1109" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1109" type="letter">
        <head>1109. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1805-10-03">3
                        October 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.
                        P. / Wynnstay/ Wrexham &lt;Shrewsbury&gt;<lb />Stamped: OSWESTRY/ 163<lb />Endorsement: Be so good as direct the enclosed to
                            Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Thomas Coutts &amp; Co Strand London [Thomas Coutts (1735&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), banker and
                        head of the successful company Coutts &amp; Co.]<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    339&#8211;341.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall take your advice respecting <del>xxxx</del> Madoc, &amp; confine myself to correcting the parts as they
                    are. About the catastrophe when my thoughts acquire any thing like a definite form &#8211; you shall be consulted.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In an earlier letter, Southey had suggested various alterations to his poem for its next edition,
                        including omitting the volcanic eruption that occurs at the end; see Southey to Charles Watkins Williams Wynn, [September
                        1805], Letter 1107.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To day I start with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> for Edinburgh, &amp; shall be home within
                    three weeks. I have a world of reviewing to do, which with Espriella,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> will keep
                    me hard at work till April, &#8211; &amp; then, as soon as I have cleared off these incumbrances I design once more to cross the seas,
                    &amp; pay my last visit to Portugal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not make his intended trip to Portugal as
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> did not wish to go and he did not want to be separated from her. See
                        Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 20 October 1805, Letter 1113.</note> Concerning this I will write at large hereafter. Now of course we are in haste, &amp; have
                    besides something to say which &lt;you&gt; will be glad to hear.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Froude, a clergyman of Devonshire,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Hurrell Froude (1770/71&#8211;1859;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Church of England clergyman of Dartington, South Devon, and later Archdeacon of Totnes.</note>
                    happened some little time ago to tell me that a Lady in Nottinghamshire had an old MSS volume of poems, which nobody could make
                        out.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Sherbrooke family of Oxton, Nottinghamshire had owned a manuscript volume
                        containing rare medieval metrical romances since the sixteenth century. It was compiled by one Richard Heege in the fifteenth
                        century. Southey later arranged for its purchase, through the good offices of Scott, by Scott&#8217;s friend Thomas Thomson
                        (1768&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), an Edinburgh advocate, record keeper and editor of medieval manuscripts. See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 11 January 1806, Letter 1146. From Thomson the manuscript went to the Advocates Library, Edinburgh. It remains in their collection today
                        (National Library of Scotland, Advocates MS 19.3.1).</note> I expressed a wish to see it, &#8211; &amp; in short &#8211; have it now lying
                    on my desk. It contains all sort of things &amp; among others three metrical Romances. Sir Ysumbras<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Isumbras</title> is a metrical romance, written in Middle English, and surviving in at least nine manuscripts and
                        five prints. It is a secularized retelling of the legend of Saint Eustace (a 2nd-century AD Christian martyr) which circulated
                        widely in England in martyrologies, legendaries and homilies.</note> &#8211; Sir Gowther<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Gowther</title> is a metrical romance, written in Middle English, that survives in one other fifteenth-century
                        manuscript, British Library Royal MS 17.B.43.</note> &#8211; &amp; Sir Amadas.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Amadas</title> (or <title>Sir Amadace</title>) is a medieval English chivalric romance found in one other
                        fifteenth-century manuscript, Taylor MS 9, otherwise known as MS Ireland Blackburn in the Robert H. Taylor Collection,
                        Princeton University Libraries.</note> The first you will recollect by the title of Isembras, whether that was known to exist
                    or not I cannot tell. The two latter are discoveries, I believe, &amp; Amadas, being known to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> only by name, was suspected by him in the Edinburgh Review as being
                    possibly the original of Amadis.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1803) was reviewed by Walter Scott in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 5 (October 1803), 109&#8211;136.</note> The copy of
                    these is imperfect at the beginning, but nothing of any importance is lost. The story this. Amadas has spent all his property
                    except forty pounds. With this he sets out to seek his fortune &#8211; he finds a widow sitting by a bier in a lonely chapel with two
                    tapers burning, &amp; her husbands body, which was rotting above ground, because a cruel creditor would not permit it to be
                    buried. Amadas pays 30&#163; to redeem it, &amp; spends the other ten upon the funeral. As he rides on close thro a forest bewailing
                    his poverty aloud, a knight in white armour upon a white horse overtakes &amp; overhears him; &amp; then advises him to go &amp;
                    marry the Emperors daughter by his help, covenanting to have half of whatever he shall chuse for this assistance. Accordingly he
                    supplies him with cloaths from a wreck &amp; bids him say that his retinue have perished in the storm. Amadas marries the Princess
                    &amp; has a child. The White knight comes &amp; sends up word of his arrival in a <del>sort of</del> suspicious way, as if he
                    doubted whether the promise would be kept; he is most joyfully &amp; gratefully received but demands to have the Princess &amp;
                    the child cut in half. The Lady on no account will permit her husband to break his promise &amp; prove a false knight, &amp; lays
                    down on a table to submit to the operation. It then appears that the White Knight is the Spirit of the Merchant who does this only
                    to prove Sir Amadas.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Sir Gowther &#8211; <hi rend="ital">the Son of the Devil</hi> &#8211; is equally wild in story &#8211; but I have no time now for
                    more. Each is about 800 lines long. the rest of the volume contains many curious things with much devotional poetry. I shall show
                    it to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, &amp; get the owners permission to take measures for publishing
                    such of its contents &lt;as&gt; are worthy.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-10-03">October 3. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>