<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1600</idno><idno type="nines">rce2722</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bertram R. Davis Collection, University of Waterloo Library,
                        Ontario.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 502–505.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1600" type="letter"><head>1600. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-03-14">14–15 March
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey,/ H. M. S. Dreadnought,/
                        Plymouth-Dock<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Bertram R. Davis Collection, University of Waterloo Library,
                        Ontario<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 502–505.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-03-14">Tuesday March 14. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> This evening I have sent off a book of Kehama,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (London, 1810). Southey was sending his brother drafts of the poem via Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford.</note> &amp; shall follow it up quickly while I fancy myself somewhat at leisure, having no immediate pressure of
                    employment. The 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> section is begun – one &amp; twenty will compleat it. I feel therefore as
                        near<del>ly</del> the end of my journey as we did when we reached Lancaster on our way home, &amp; had the mountains once more
                    in sight. Lorrinite &amp; Arvalan are disposed of in Padalon,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events in Southey’s
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book 17.</note> Kehama is come down just too late to save his son, – his offers to
                    Kalyal, <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events in Southey’s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book 18.</note> Ereenias
                    appeal to Seeva,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Book 19 of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>.</note> their journey to
                    the throne of Yamen,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Books 20–23 of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>.</note> &amp; the
                    final scene before the Throne are all that remain to be written.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Book 14 of <title>The
                            Curse of Kehama</title>.</note> And then <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> in what metre shall I write
                        Pelayo?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s early name for the poem published as <title>Roderick the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly Review has been published a fortnight. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> has been the
                    main contributor, – a good one in the lighter articles of miscellaneous literature, but in prose &amp; poetry wherever it is
                    necessary to see into the life &amp; essence of things there he fails.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed in
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809): Robert Hartley Cromek (1770–1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques
                            of Robert Burns, Consisting Chiefly of Original Letters, Poems, and Critical Observations on Scottish Songs</title>
                        (1808), 19–36; Southey’s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808), 117–134; John Barrett (1753/4–1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Earlier Part of the Life of Swift, by the Rev. John Barrett, D. D. and Vice
                            Provost of Trinity College, Dublin. To which are Subjoined Various Pieces Ascribed to Swift, Two of his Original Letters,
                            and Extracts from his Remarks on Bishop Burnett’s History</title> (1808), 162–177; [with <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref>] Sir John Carr (1772–1832; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Caledonian Sketches, or a Tour through Scotland in 1807</title> (1808), 178–193. Scott also had a hand in William
                        Erskine’s (Lord Kinneder; bap. 1768–1822; <title>DNB</title>), review of John Philpot Curran (1750–1817),<title> Speeches of
                            the Right Honourable John Philpot Curran, Master of the Rolls in Ireland, on the late very Interesting State
                            Trials</title> (1808), 96–107.</note> He has made poor work of the Cid. <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> has written sensibly upon Sanscrit literature.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon Turner [with John
                        Shore, 1st Baron Teignmouth (1751–1834; <title>DNB</title>)] reviewed Charles Wilkins (bap. 1749–1836; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>A Grammar of the Sanskrîta Language</title> (1808); William Carey (1761–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A
                            Grammar of the Sungskrit Language, Composed from the Works of the Most Esteemed Grammarians; to Which are Added Examples
                            for the Exercise of the Student, and a Complete List of the Dhatoos or Roots</title> (1804); and Henry Thomas Colebrooke
                        (1765–1837), <title>Grammar of the Sanskrit Language</title> (1805), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February
                        1809), 53–69.</note> It is on the whole a respectable number. I have suffered grievously from mutilation,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747–1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the
                            Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his
                            Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the
                            Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity… By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776–1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the
                            Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to
                            India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193–226.</note> partly inflicted to
                    shorten what is still the longest article in the book, <del>far</del> more frequently for the sake of weeding out whatever
                    savoured of heresy, political or religious, no very easy operation to perform upon a man who weaves it in the very warp of his
                    discourse. I amuse myself with writing it into my own copy as carefully as <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>
                    had cut it out. As soon as the number was published I received a letter of flattery from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">the
                        bookseller</ref>, &amp; a very handsome one from <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, inclosing goodly
                    guerdon <del>t</del>h in the shape of 21 – 13 – good pay for a single article. I am at work upon the South Sea Missions for the
                    second number, &amp; shall <del>t</del> go to the South African in the third.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title> in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2
                        (August 1809), 24–61, but there is no review by him of the South African missions.</note> If these essays be executed as much
                    to my own liking, &amp; with as much effect as the first, it may very probably be advisable to republish them in a seperate
                    volume.</p><p rend="indent1"> I knew your motions before your letter arrived. The end of this adventure will probably be that you will blockade
                    the French till your hearts ache, then comes a gale which blows you off, &amp; the <del>F</del> enemy escape.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not believe the news that Zaragoza has fallen.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second siege of
                        Zaragoza ended, after ferocious defence, great bloodshed, starvation and disease, in the French taking the town, on 20
                        February 1809. For Southey’s accounts of the affair, see the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810),
                        306–321; and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508–527.</note> very probably it may fall, but
                    the accounts are <del>not</del> contradictory, &amp; neither of them looks like truth. War with Austria <del>&amp; if not
                        imp</del> (with Russia too perhaps) will do no harm by destroying what is now the worst existing government of Europe (except
                    Sicily) – &amp; will do good by giving the Spaniards time. It is now March, – they will be at Madrid by Midsummer: &amp; we might
                    catch Joseph,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph-Napoléon Bonaparte (1768–1844) was the elder brother of Napoleon
                        Bonaparte who made him King of Spain as Joseph I in 1808. Joseph had returned to Madrid, after French troops put down a
                        Spanish uprising, at the beginning of 1809.</note> if ministers were not too busy in their shameful &amp; most impudent
                    defence of the D of Y<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763–1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798–1809, but was forced to resign in the wake
                        of allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776–1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept
                        money from army officers, in return for which promotion was arranged.</note> – to think of any thing else. What a kettle of
                    stinking fish it is! – Do you remember Speddings story?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Spedding (1770–1851) of
                        Mirehouse, the house and estate near Bassenthwaite lake , north of Keswick. Spedding was a schoolfriend of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at Hawkshead. For Spedding’s story about the Clarke/York affair,
                        see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 28 February 1809, Letter 1590.</note> he never understood the whole history till it
                    appeared in the newspapers.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thalaba has been finished about a fortnight;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> was published in 1809.</note> in two or three weeks I expect to see it advertised,
                    &amp; will then order off your copy with the Annual.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809): <title>Tour Through Spain and Part of Portugal</title>, Volume 3 of
                        Richard Phillips, <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages and Travels</title> (1805–1810), 56–57; Christian
                        Augustus Fischer (1771–1829), <title>A Picture of Madrid: Taken on the Spot. Translated from the German</title> (1808), 57–60;
                        Thomas Clarkson, <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by
                            the British Parliament</title> (1808), 127–148; <title>Report of the Committee of the African Institution, Read to the
                            General Meeting on the 15th July, 1807, Together with the Rules and Regulations which were then Adopted for the Government
                            of the Society</title> (1807); Thomas Zouch (1737–1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of
                            Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224–235; Robert Drury (1687–1734?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Adventures of Robert
                            Drury, During Fifteen Years Captivity on the Island of Madagascar; Containing a Description of that Island; an Account of
                            its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; With an Account of the Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion, and Civil Policy of
                            the Inhabitants: to Which is Added, a Vocabulary of the Madagascar Language. Written by Himself, and now Carefully Revised
                            and Corrected from the Original</title> (1807), 253–263; John Finlay (1782–1810), <title>Scottish Historical and Romantic
                            Ballads: Chiefly Ancient with Explanatory Notes and a Glossary</title> (1808), 457–462; Charles Kirkpatrick Sharpe
                        (1781?-1851), <title>Metrical Legends</title> (1807), 473–473; Francis Douce (1757–1834), <title>Illustrations of Shakespeare,
                            and of Ancient Manners: with Dissertations on the Clown and Fool of Shakespeare; on the Collection of Popular Tales
                            entitled Gesta Romanorum; and on the English Morris Dance</title> (1807), 554–562; Charles Lamb, <title>Specimens of
                            English Dramatic Poets, who Lived about the Time of Shakespeare</title> (1808), 562–570; [Howard Luke (1772–1864)],
                            <title>A Brief Apology for Quakerism, Inscribed to the Edinburgh Reviewers</title> (1808), 354–356.</note> This said
                    Annual I expect in my next parcel – on Thursday – &amp; be it known unto you that I have the happiness of expecting three parcels!
                    – theres joy! one from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref> containing a present of the first volume of Ld Somers’s
                        Tracts<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809 Scott published the first volume of Baron John Somers (1651–1716;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Scarce and Valuable Tracts on the Most Interesting and Entertaining Subjects
                            But Chiefly Such as Relate to the History and Constitution of These Kingdoms, Selected from an Infinite Number in Print
                            and Manuscript in the Royal Libraries</title> (1809–1815).</note> &amp; one from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> the publisher of the Quarterly, with Vancouvers voyages which I wish<del>ed</del> to read for my article upon
                    the S Sea Islands.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Vancouver (1757–1798; <title>DNB</title>) had been a midshipman
                        on Captain Cook’s third voyage to Tahiti. In 1791–1795 he commanded an expedition that surveyed America’s northwest coast,
                        wintering at Hawaii. His record of <title>A Voyage of Discovery to the North Pacific Ocean and Round the World,
                            1791–1795</title> (1798) was completed by his brother, John Vancouver (bap. 1756–1829).</note> I am to review Ld
                    Valencia’s Travels for the said Q. when they come out.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed George Annesley,
                        Viscount Valentia (1770–1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in the Years
                            1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 88–126.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> We thought it was all over with poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref>, – never did man seem
                    nearer the grave than he did ten days ago, – but there has been an inward abscess, &amp; there is now some hope<del>s</del> of his
                    recovery, – tho I confess I am not very sanguine in this expectation. He is however materially better, – or indeed he would not
                    now have been alive – In the way of improvements, we have ordered stuff the same as my curtains for a bed &amp;c in the wing room.
                    The bordering for the study is come, &amp; I shall write in my next letter to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref><note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> This does not appear to have survived.</note> for half a ream of such
                    paper as the Athenæum<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Athenæum, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807–1809) was edited by <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> and published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> covers, to paper it with. The next operation will be to build a grand Pavillion at the back of the
                    coal-shed, so constructed as that the winds of Heaven may not visit ones rump too roughly <del>which we</del> &lt;which&gt; Heaven
                    knows they do at present, &amp; I never heard that taking the air at that end was wholesome. I shall be glad when the edifice is
                    erected.</p><p rend="indent1"> Four &amp; twenty sheets of Brazil are printed<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of
                        Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note> – copy for as much more was sent off ten days ago to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> ; &amp; he as soon as he has looked it thro will send it to <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref>. For the remainder of the volume there is scarcely any thing more than mere
                    transcription. it will be a thick book – not less I believe than 650 pages. I have now lying on the table a portion of Arrowsmiths
                    great map of America,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750–1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of
                        Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith’s other productions were <title>A Map of
                            America</title> (1804), which depicted North and South America.</note> to correct <del>x</del> as much as possible for
                    that which he is about to prepare for me. My map will be the best that has yet appeared of Brazil, &amp; <del>one</del> as
                    beautifully executed as possible, – for this art is now carried to perfection.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second
                        volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1817) contained Arrowsmith’s <title>Map of Brazil and Paraguay with the
                            Adjoining Countries</title>.</note><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Burney</ref>, both great map-makers take much interest in this part of my business. The <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</ref> has bespoken place in the Monthly Review for a reviewal of the Cid by <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Bedford
                        to write a review of his <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) for the <title>Monthly Review</title>; see Southey to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 28 February 1809, Letter 1590. The book was reviewed in complimentary terms in the <title>Monthly
                            Review</title>, 63 (1810), 131–144.</note><ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon"> Sharon Turner</ref> performed the office
                    in the Annual.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sharon Turner’s review of Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        (1808) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 91–99.</note><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has promised, &amp; probably will perform something about it in
                    the Courier,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge did not review the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> in <title>The
                        Courier</title>.</note> which will be of more effect than either, for no literary journal produces half the effect of a
                    popular newspaper. Is not <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> doing his duty about the D York?<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of
                        the army. He held the post from 1798–1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by
                        allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776–1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for
                        which promotion was arranged. Stuart’s coverage in the <title>Courier</title> was critical of the Duke.</note> Love from all
                    quarters &amp; the regular allowance of kisses from your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">eldest niece</ref> – </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1809-03-15">Wednesday 15.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>