<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1563</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2685</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 207&#8211;210 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1563" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1563" type="letter">
        <head>1563. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-01-10">10 January
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 207&#8211;210 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-01-10">Tuesday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 10. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> A book of Kehama, after a long interval, was sent off four or five days ago, which will introduce you to Lorrinite
                    the Enchantress.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 11.</note>
                    I have had a cold which for the last fortnight has made me lie in bed till breakfast time &amp; so the poem has stood still. It
                    has not however proved one of my wicked cattarhs &amp; is I believe pretty well gone off, so that I am rid of it cheaply.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> wishes you were at Portsmouth, where he will at any
                    time go to see you, if you cannot go to see him, &amp; where he has friends to whom he shall be glad to introduce you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have corrected five sheets of the Brazil, &amp; am now hard at work in transcribing &amp; filling up skeleton
                    chapters, that in particular contains every thing concerning my friends the Tupinambas that has not been inadvertently said
                        before.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published
                        in 1810. The Tupinamba, one of the main ethnic groups of Brazilian indigenous people, are described in chapter 7.</note> I
                    wish you were here to hear it as it gets on. There is a great pleasure in reading these things to any one who takes an interest in
                    them, &#8211; &amp; like our toast at <del>the morning</del> &lt;breakfast&gt; they seem the better for coming in fresh &amp; fresh. I
                    made an important discovery relative to De Lery,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613), <title>Histoire
                            d&#8217;un Voyage fait en la Terre du Bresil</title> (1578), was no. 1709 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> one
                    of my best printed authorities, this morning. This author who tho a Frenchman was a very faithful writer, translated his own
                    French into Latin, &amp; I used the Latin edition in De Bry&#8217;s Collection, &#8211; you remember the book with those hideous prints of the
                    savages at their cannibal feasts.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The collection of travel narratives published by Theodor
                        and Johann Israel De Bry (1528&#8211;1598), <title>Peregrinationes</title> (1598&#8211;1613).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> laid hands on the French book &amp; sent it to me, &#8211; it
                    arrived last Thursday only, &#8211; &amp; I in transcribing with my usual scrupulous accuracy, constantly referred to the original,
                    because I knew that when an author translates his own book he often alters it, &amp; therefore it was probable that I might
                    sometimes find a difference worthy of notice. Well &#8211; I found my own references to the number of the Chapter wrong, &#8211; for the first
                    time it past well enough for a blunder, tho I wondered at &lt;it&gt; a little, being remarkably exact in these things &#8211; the second
                    time I thought it very extraordinary, &#8211; &amp; a third mistake made me quite certain that something was wrong, but that the fault
                    was not in me. Upon examination it appeared that a whole chapter, &amp; that chapter the most important as to the historical part
                    of the volume, had been omitted by De Bry, because he was a Catholick, De Lery a Hugonot, &amp; this chapter exposed the villainy
                    of Villegagnon<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Durand, de Villegaignon (or Villegagnon) (1510&#8211;1571), who invaded
                        Brazil in 1555 to claim it as a French colony, with a group of Huguenots who were escaping Catholic persecution and some
                        Catholics. Disgusted by disputes between the Protestant and Catholic colonists, Villegagnon condemned some of the Calvinists
                        to death, withdrew his support, and returned to France. In 1558 the colonists were defeated by the Portuguese.</note> who went
                    to Brazil expressly to establish an asylum for the Hugonots, when there was won over by the Guises, apostatized, &amp; then ruined
                    a colony, which must else inevitably have made Rio de Janeiro now the Capital of a French, instead of Portugueze Empire. The main
                        fact<del>s</del> I had collected before, &amp; clearly understood, &#8211; but the knavery of a Roman Catholick Editor had thus
                    nearly deprived me of my best &amp; fullest authority, &amp; of some very material circumstances, for nobody has ever yet
                    suspected this collection of being otherwise than faithful, tho it is now more than two hundred years old. See here the necessity
                    of tracing every thing to the fountain head when it is possible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your niece</ref> who is collecting all the seals which come to me requests
                    that you will be pleased to make a very fine impression upon your next letter. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> never sees a ship in a picture without saying that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Uncle Tom</ref> lives
                    in a ship. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> just tottles alone for a few steps, but is afraid to set off, &#8211; &amp;
                    there will be another by Gods blessing <del>early</del> in the spring, who is to be called Danvers if a boy, &#8211; if a girl I know
                    not what.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref> was born 27 March
                        1809.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you <del>xx</del> said about transports I reported to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 20 December
                        1808, Letter 1557.</note> he made enquiry &amp; understood the objection came from the Navy Captains, who did not like ever to
                    have their ships encumbered, or to <hi rend="ital">feel</hi> as if they were transports. I repeated this to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>,
                    &amp; thro them it has reachd <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>, &amp; got into the Courier,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Courier</title> for 5 January 1809 laments the fact that merchant ships are used to
                        convey troops, when &#8216;we have upwards of 1100 ships of war, one-fourth of which are at least always in our ports or our
                        coasts&#8217;.</note> whether or not with effect time will show, &#8211; but there is nothing like sending so obvious a truth afloat, &#8211; it
                    will find its way sooner or later. I see the Captains are petitioning for an increase of pay, &#8211; they will get it to be sure, &amp;
                    then the increase must extend to you also.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Things in Spain look well. Bonapartes bulletins<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">French bulletins and decrees
                        by Napoleon were published in <title>The Courier</title> newspaper at regular intervals.</note> prove beyond all doubt that
                    every heart is against him, &amp; his threat of taking the crown himself is the perfect frenzy of anger. Sir John Moores<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and varied
                        military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was
                        given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna.</note>
                    movements backwards &amp; forwards, have been mere moves at chess to <del>get</del> gain time, &amp; wait for a blunder on the
                    part of the adversary &#8211; so <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> tells me, &#8211; &amp; his intelligence is
                    good coming from <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> &#8211; who is <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> Secretary, &amp; <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> who is in <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref> confidence. Moore<del>s</del> is a very able man, &amp; is acting with a
                    boldness which gives every body confidence that knows him. He will beat twice his own number of Frenchmen, &amp; I do not think
                    greater odds can be brought against him. It bodes well that in this fresh embarkation the officers are desired not to take more
                    baggage than they can carry themselves. At him Trojan! &#8211; We shall beat him <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> upon
                    Spanish ground. Let but our men fairly see the faces of the French in battle, &amp; they will soon see their backs too. The
                    Grenvilles &amp; Foxites are likely to seperate upon the question of peace.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Factions
                        within the Whig party who were followers of the policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James Fox</ref>
                        or <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>.</note> Canning hankers after the Grenvilles, &amp;
                    would do much to bring them in with him instead of his wretched associates. They are not popular, but if they had courage to
                        <del>xx</del> make a home charge upon the Duke of York,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of
                        York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army.</note> &amp; insist upon his removal as a
                    preliminary &amp; sine qu&#226; non of their going in, &#8211; that measure would win them a popularity which would carry them in in spite of
                    every obstacle. God bless you. We have been dining upon a <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> goose, &#8211; a better
                    never was eaten, &#8211; &amp; have a Turkey from the same quarter in the house.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> yrs RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>