<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.992</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2114</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4848 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 520&#8211;523.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="992" type="letter">
        <head>992. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1804-11-23">23 November
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb />Stamped: KENDAL/ 261<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 3 Jan<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4848 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 520&#8211;523.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> A half written letter, begun immediately on the receipt of your last, is lying in my desk at home, (&#8211; for I am now
                    visiting <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>) &#8211; it
                    is better to begin anew than to protract a delay which has already been too long continued. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is gone back to Edinburgh. he has past a chearful summer, &amp; if not a
                    very profitable one in the way of study I readily excuse him, remembering what my own habits were when something younger. As you
                    may suppose he left behind him a very favourable impression with every body; with me also tho I wish him more perseverance, &amp;
                    enough self-denial to secure his own permanent comfort &amp; self-complacency. Advice usually excites dislike &#8211; I therefore never
                    offered it. <del>or xxxxx for xxxx xxx xxxxxx</del> he knew what I thought right, &amp; to have told him when I thought he was
                    wrong would only have provoked him to a defence. Our time passed easily, &amp; should we remain here next summer I shall be glad
                    when the time for his return arrives, &amp; he will not be sorry. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letters, like Gibbons<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>): the
                        author of <title>The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1788).</note> sentences, all go to one
                    tune &amp; would furnish as pretty specimens of egotism as the Memoirs of P.P.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Memoirs of P. P. Clerk of this Parish</title>, a satire on the self-importance of autobiographers, was published in
                        1727 in the <title>Miscellanies in Prose and Verse</title> authored by Jonathan Swift (1667&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>) and
                        Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Twas a vile trick of Akenside to strip the personal pronoun of its
                    honest importance, dwarfing &amp; dotting it, as if I was not the most consequential word in the language.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mark Akenside (1721&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>): poet, author of <title>The Pleasures of the Imagination</title>
                        (1744). In his <title>Odes on Several Subjects</title> (2nd edn, 1760), Akenside had the pronoun &#8216;I&#8217; printed in lower case as
                        &#8216;i&#8217;, among other typographical innovations.</note> An Englishman does think himself somebody, &amp; has good reason to think
                    himself so: our great I is in character. &#8211; The news of my microcosm is not very important just at present. the best is that the
                    last sheet of Madoc is on the table &#8211; that is of the poem. the notes will take up another month &#8211; &amp; then without much delay it
                    shall be delivered into your hands.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correcting proofs of <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805) even while still revising the sections of the manuscript not yet sent to the printer.</note> I had prefaced it with a
                    story of its birth &amp; progress, thereby accounting for sundry faults, but on consultation &amp; farther thought I was convinced
                    that nobody likes <del>his</del> egotism in his neighbours &#8211; that the least said is the soonest mended. So my preface contains
                    nothing more than what is necessary to state the historical foundation of the poem, said as briefly as possible in some twenty
                    lines.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have commenced my campaign against the Authors,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, his reviewing
                        work for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> with a resolution to censure for the future as gently as possible. in fact
                    your remark has risen in my conscience, &amp; I fairly confess that the pride of saying a good thing is but a bad motive for
                    saying an ill natured one. You perhaps have sinned on the other side &#8211; Pinkerton &amp; Maurice are instances.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>): Scottish antiquarian and cartographer whose many
                        publications earned him a reputation for irreligious views, arrogant irritability and personal immorality. Thomas Maurice
                        (1754&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), Orientalist author of <title>Indian Antiquities</title> (1793&#8211;1800). Taylor reviewed
                        Pinkerton&#8217;s <title>Modern Geography, a Description of the Empires, States, and Colonies, with the Oceans, Seas and Islands in
                            all Parts of the World</title> (1802) in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 37 (March 1803), 265&#8211;273 and the
                            <title>Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 39 (December 1803), 58&#8211;69. He reviewed Maurice&#8217;s <title>Indian
                            Antiquities</title> in the <term>Critical Review</term>, 2nd series, 31 (March 1801), 295&#8211;300.</note> It is well that the
                    last escaped my hands! he is the worst putter together of a book of all men living &#8211; except Vallancy<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> General Charles Vallancey (1731&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), military surveyor and author of much-derided works
                        on the history and antiquities of Ireland, including a <title>Vindication of the Antient Kingdom of Ireland</title> (1786) and
                        the <title>Antient History of Ireland proved from the Sanscrit Books</title> (1797).</note> &#8211; &amp; moreover a very good for
                    nothing &amp; unprincipled fellow.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers</ref> Essay will interest me. we have however a school of
                    poetry of our own, &#8211; &amp; of the present race of poets &amp; poetasters very many discover no traces of German taste.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frank Sayers traced the Scandinavian influence on English poetry and rejoiced that the recent
                        fashion for German poetry was passing in a &#8216;Sketch of the rise and progress of English poetry&#8217; in his <title>Miscellanies,
                            Antiquarian and Historical</title> (Norwich, 1805), pp. 45&#8211;58.</note> the Wordsworth who chuses to add one article more to
                    the nine &amp; thirty is brother to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William W</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Wordsworth (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), William&#8217;s youngest brother, a clergyman in the Church
                        of England, had, in 1802, defended the argument of Granville Sharp (1735&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) against Unitarians that the
                        use of the definite article in the New Testament demonstrated Christ&#8217;s deity.</note> has lately married <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> sister,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Wordsworth married
                        Priscilla Lloyd (d. 1815) in 1804.</note> &amp; is settled on his living between Yarmouth &amp; Norwich. I do not know him,
                    but know that he is a good man, very studious, very sincere, thoroughly bigotted, &amp; holding <del>as thorough a</del> in
                    thorough contempt all persons who differ from his own orthodox standard. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William
                        Wordsworth</ref> is very desirous of seeing you. pray pray come up to us, if (as we have reason to hope) we should remain here
                    next summer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My plans are sadly unsettled by the great evils in the world. this piratical war with Spain may very probably
                    occasion our expulsion from Lisbon &#8211; &amp; that city is also perilously near this dreadful pestilence.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Yellow fever was epidemic in Iberia in 1804, and killed an estimated 60% of Gibraltar&#8217;s population.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, who would willingly end his days there, feels himself very insecure,
                    &amp; thinks he may soon be driven here; &#8211; else I should certainly migrate in the next winter, &amp; remain abroad as long as <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> would be contented to forego her own country. I must wait &amp; see how things
                    turn out. meantime life is running on &#8211; I have been married nine years &#8211; &amp; it is time that I should have a settled resting
                    place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are very uneasy about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. <hi rend="ital">if</hi> there was a
                    frigate lost in the hurricane at Dominica, it was the Galatea. &amp; besides that ship has suffered dreadfully in attempting to
                    cut out a sloop.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> was not sunk in the hurricane. On 14
                        August 1804, the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>&#8217;s boats made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near
                        Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission, 65 were killed or wounded, and Southey suspected that his brother Thomas was
                        among the dead.</note> no official accounts have arrived. the private letters do not mention <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> name &#8211; what most alarms me is that he has not written himself. I fear the fever
                    worst of all these chances. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">My younger brother</ref> is turned vagabond again &amp; must
                    be left to his fate. few candidates for Tyburn<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The place where criminals were executed in
                        west London.</note> have started with a better chance. my best hope for him is that he may turn strolling player &#8211; if not, if
                    he only attains to transportation his destiny will be better than his deserts. happily he has no mother, &amp; I know how to
                        <del>take</del> &lt;give&gt; these evils no more their proper weight.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-11-23">Nov. 23. 1804.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>