<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1507</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2629</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington
                        Library, RS 132.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 169&#8211;170 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1507" type="letter">
        <head>1507. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1808-09-13">13 September
                    1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Christ Church/
                        Hampshire<lb />Endorsement: RS./ 13 Sept. 1808 <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ SEP 16/ 1808<lb />MS: Huntington
                        Library, RS 132<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 169&#8211;170 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-09-13"> Sept. 13. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The book concerning which the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Captain</ref>  enquires proves to be
                    thoroughly &amp; entirely worthless I believe it to be fabulous altogether, &amp; am quite sure that tho there should happen to be
                    any truth in it, it is good for nothing. When you convey this information to him, let him know that <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has been instructed to send him a copy of my Cid the Campeador,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> to the end that
                    he make enquiry for it in case of its non appearance in due time. Your copy I hope will have reached you before then.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Portugueze have a better story to make out than you have made for them. The conscription certainly had been
                    enforced, but it was before any stir began in Spain, &amp; consequently before there was any probability of resisting to good
                    purpose. The business at Porto may not have been upon a great scale, but perhaps you are not aware that there is in the large
                    towns a French party in opposition to an English one, &amp; therefore the true Portugueze have had more to contend with than the
                    Spaniards. Besides they certainly lost no time in stirring: long before Duponts surrender<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre-Antoine, Comte Dupont de l&#8217;&#201;tang (1765&#8211;1840), the general who led the Napoleonic army to its first major defeat,
                        at the Battle of Bail&#233;n, in July 1808.</note> the whole of Algarve had risen, &amp; you may see what Alentejo has suffered for
                    rising, exposed as it was to troops from Lisbon on the one side &amp; from Elvas on the other. The French had more troops there in
                    proportion than in Spain, &amp; better distributed. There is also this remarkable difference between the two countries. In the one
                    the higher you ascend in rank the better the people are, &#8211; that is till you come to royalty which is necessarily worthless
                    everywhere. But in Portugal the reverse holds good, &amp; nothing can be worse than the nobility &amp; the fidalgos. This is only
                    to be accounted for physically. The kingdom is very small, &amp; as these casts intermarry only among themselves the breed has
                    degenerated, &#8211; syphilis too has probably in many or most instances left a taint in the blood &amp; helped on the process of
                        kakkerlakkenism.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Literally, &#8216;cockroachism&#8217;.</note> Spain has been preserved from
                    this by its greater size. You are not to receive this as a mere speculation of mine, invented by my own fire side, &#8211; I find it so
                    represented by some of the Portugueze themselves, &#8211; &amp; the fact is certainly so.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your estimate of Spain is right. the difference between our age &amp; that of Elizabeth is that the bulk of the
                    people are better in no respect, &amp; worse in some: that the middle classes are fineered instead of being heart of oak, &#8211; &amp;
                    the higher ones are better classics &amp; worse in every other possible point of view. Ours is a degrading &amp; dwarfing system
                    of society I believe as you do that the Spaniards have displayed more spirit than we should have done, &amp; that the peacemongers
                    were ready to have sacrificed the honour of England for their looms &amp; brew-houses,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        A hit at Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), brewer, Whig politician and advocate of a negotiated peace with
                        Napoleon.</note> &#8211; in what light I regard it you will see by the Introduction to the Cid, written six years ago, &amp; only
                    remodelled now, &amp; that before these late events took place. But much has also been done by that awakening recollection of the
                    deeds of their forefathers, which every Spaniard felt &amp; delighted to feel. The very ballads of the Cid must have had their
                    effect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have seen my old Letters advertised &#8211; 2 weeks close work has thoroughly expurgated them, &amp; by the addition
                    of such pertinent matter [MS torn] &amp; local history as my later knowledge enabled me to bring forward they have been recast
                    into a respectable book, &#8211; as you will in due time behold.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters
                            written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797) were being reprinted in an expanded form as
                            <title>Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very idle, &#8211; boating &amp; walking about &amp; laying in health &amp; exercise <del>from</del> for the next
                        <del>xx</del> season of hybernation. Right glad shall I be when you come &amp; help me in this laudable &amp; needful part of
                    my years work. &#8211; The last odd thing which has turned up in my reading is &#8211; that the Merino sheep were originally English &amp;
                    transported from hence into Spain, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">ergo</hi>, the quality of wool depends upon the climate or pasture, &amp;c.
                    few generations may be expected to bring it back to what it originally was.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain had
                        first obtained the merino sheep, long jealously guarded by the Spanish because their fine wool commanded high prices, at the
                        end of the eighteenth century. Now, in 1808, with the two countries allies against France, a further 2000 Paula merinos were
                        obtained. Southey&#8217;s notion that the merino originated in Britain is supported by historians only to the extent that in the
                        13th and 14th centuries, the Arab-descended sheep of Spain were improved by the import of British bloodstock.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your mode of sending MS news is not a very safe one. I paid for a gazette one day in consequence: there had been
                    old scrawling on the cover which was visible thro &amp; probably induced an examination. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know how the Eastern jugglers<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A troop of Indian jugglers including
                        Kia (or Khia) Khan Khruse and Ramo Samee performed in Britain in the early decades of the nineteenth century.</note> &amp; the
                    Psylli of old<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Psylli were a North African tribe reputed by Roman writers to be
                        immune to snake bites.</note> are proof against animal poisons. The discovery of their secret would be worth more than all the
                    European atchievements in the East <del>xxx xxxxxx</del> have produced. It is not probable that they have <del>xxxxxxed xxx</del>
                    discovered something which renders the system unsusceptible of each poison, in the manner that the vaccine prevents variolous
                    infection? &#8211; I am writing to an infidel I know. but that matters not. The thing is worth enquiry. Are these men equally proof
                    against hydrophobia? &#8211; here is another <del>thing</del> thing which deserves investigation also. &#8211; Ira furor brevis est<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Anger is a brief madness&#8217;. Horace (Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65 BC&#8211;8 BC)),
                            <title>Epistles</title>, 1.2.62</note> is true in a wider sense than perhaps Seneca himself suspected.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anger was the subject of &#8216;<title>To Novatus on Anger</title>&#8217;, by Lucius Annaeus Seneca (c.
                        4 BC&#8211;AD 65).</note> Do you know that Hydrophobia, or a species of it, has been occasioned by the peck of a furious game cock
                    &amp; by the bite of a man, in a paroxysm of anger?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now going to hurry thro a letter to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> concerning
                    the lost books.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter has not been traced.</note> &gt; &#8211; It goes by the same
                    post, &amp; I have made out a list of the desiderata, give him a helping hint. the old books are of value, &amp; so are the
                    sketches&gt;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8212;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>