<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1457</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2579</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 371&#8211;374 [misdated
                        1806].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1457" type="letter">
        <head>1457. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-05-06">[c.
                    6 May 1808]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./
                        London<lb />Postmark: FREE/ 6 MY 6/1808<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D <lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 371&#8211;374 [misdated
                        1806].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Peter Elmsley</ref> had not lived so far from town that we were four
                    hours on the way to his house, &amp; as long in returning, you &amp; I should scarcely have seen each other during my long absence
                    from home. This is always the case when I visit London. In the endless hurry &amp; fatigue which it is impossible to avoid, I
                    scarcely ever see my friends, except in large parties, which is almost as bad as [illegible word] seeing them at all; &amp; even
                    in that way I have no opportunity of falling &lt;in&gt; with you. My head too was always full of what I had just done, or what I
                    had next to do: always weary, always in haste, always restless, &amp; with a sense of discomfort produced by the detestable
                    composition of fog, smoke &amp; pulverized horse dung which serves the Londoner for an atmosphere. &#8211; I can truly say that the
                    pleasantest minute I past in the capital, was when I seated myself in the stage coach to depart from it. I spent four days with
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Mr T. Southey</ref> at Taunton. He behaved as well as is in his nature to do,
                    &amp; gave me a 25&#163;, &#8211; for him an act of great liberality. He walked me over fields in which I could neither feel nor feign an
                    interest, &amp; showed me the plan of an estate in Devonshire for which he had just paid 7,000&#163;, &amp; made five per cent by the
                    purchase. I left him in good humour with me &amp; generally am much in his good graces, &#8211; but what hold can there be upon the good
                    will of a man who is growing fond of money, &amp; who by shunning all better society lays himself open to the artifices of low
                    flatterers &#8211; just as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">his brother</ref>  did before him. Whatever expectations
                    there may be from him have more reference to my children than to me, for he is not yet sixty, &amp; never was there a haler man of
                    his age &#8211; my head has more grey hairs in it than his. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Lord Somerville<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s distant relation by marriage John Southey
                        Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>) had lost a case concerning <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey&#8217;s</ref> estate, which passed to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref>.</note> is selling his estates, &amp; by all that I can learn is doing this in my wrong. How can I
                    ascertain this? I am Cannon Southey&#8217;s heir at law,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cannon Southey (dates unknown), the
                        son of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> and the heiress Mary Cannon.</note> &#8211; &amp; if the last
                    decision be what you supposed it to be, these estates devolve to me in default of issue male from the present heir. The truth is
                    that I know nothing about the matter, &amp; were I to say care nothing about it, it would not be far from the truth. This too
                    concerns my children more than me, &#8211; my worldly wealth will be no hindrance to me when I appear at Heaven&#8217;s gate: - if it
                    &lt;should&gt; be a turnpike gate it will be well if I have enough to pay Peter for letting me through.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The warm weather after so long a winter began on May day, &amp; I can not <del>xxxx</del> keep within doors, but it
                    draws me like an insect from its hole. &#8211; we have launched our boat, &amp; made our first voyage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I did not see you after I had seen Frere, who promised to let me print some translations of his from parts of the
                    old poem of the Cid<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Hookham Frere (1769&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>): poet, diplomat,
                        Hispanist, Frere had parodied Southey&#8217;s radical ballads in &#8216;The Friend of Humanity and the Knife-grinder&#8217; in the
                            <title>Antijacobin</title> (1797). Three of Frere&#8217;s translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to
                        Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>. Frere had been Britain&#8217;s ambassador to Portugal while Southey&#8217;s
                        uncle had lived there; from 1808&#8211;1809 he was ambassador to Spain.</note> &#8211; wonderful translations they are, &amp; will
                    increase the value of the book very considerably, as well as aid the sale of it. &#8211; The <del>xxxx</del> dearth of paper put a stop
                    to every thing &#8211; I can put nothing to press while it continues at its present enormous price, &amp; Heaven knows when it will be
                    abated. No material abatement can take place till the old state of commerce is restored.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is there any hope of seeing you in Cumberland this year? &#8211; Now that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> is settled in Herefordshire I shall be more likely to pay you occasional visits in Wales, for my way to him will
                    be thro Shrewsbury. Will you direct the enclosed to him the [MS obscured] <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert
                        Hill</ref>, <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton upon Wye</ref>, Hereford.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You urged me not to go see Horne Tooke.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Horne Tooke (1736&#8211;1812;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the political radical and etymologist, tried for treason in 1794.</note> Had it been prest upon me to
                    go I should probably have gone, because nothing could be so unpleasant to me as to have it supposed that I was afraid of visiting
                    him. For this reason I did not promise you to the contrary. But because of your wishes I kept out of the way of the person with
                    whom the thing would have been arranged &#8211; or to speak more accurately did not get in his way. Any gratification I might have felt
                    in seeing so remarkable a man was willingly given up, &#8211; but I could not bear to have it supposed that I am bound with a treasury
                    chain, &amp; must not go beyond my tether. Independent as relates to money, it is not possible that I shall ever be, &#8211; but blessed
                    be God this dependence brings with it no other curse to me than a few worldly cares. &#8211; without which I should not have my share of
                    evil in the world. It is too late in the day for me to walk in trammels: &amp; I never shall <del>xx xxx</del> learn to consider
                        <del>whether</del> &lt;in what light&gt; what I say or do may appear to others &#8211; till after it is done. I believe too that you
                    overrated the importance of a thing which in itself <del>ha</del> is of none. To strike off my pension would be making me of
                    consequence, &amp; my life for it no body in power ever thinks about me or my pension. Why should they? I think nothing about
                    them, &amp; have literally more to do with any times than <del>xx</del> my own. The worst offence I commit is probably <del>that
                        of</del> when I receive my quarter &#8211; &amp; swear at the deduction instead of being thankful for the net sum.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>