<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1332</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2454</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891. Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
               (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 100&#8211;103.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1332" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1332" type="letter">
        <head>1332. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1807-06-13">13
                  June 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: For/ Hartley Coleridge/ with Thomas Poole Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Stowey/
                  Bridgewater/ Somersetshire<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ JUN16/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: Entertaining letter from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey &#8211;/ to Hartley Coleridge, Then, 10 years old./ On a visit at/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. Pooles/ nether
                  Stowey<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 100&#8211;103.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1807-06-13">June 13. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Nephew Job</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First I have to thank you for your letter &amp; your poem, &amp; secondly to explain why I have not done this sooner.
               We were a long time without knowing where you where, &amp; when news came from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss
                  Barker</ref> that you were in London, by the time a letter could have reached you, you were gone, &#8211; &amp; lastly <ref type="m" target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Mr Jackson</ref> wrote to you to Bristol. I will now compose an epistle which shall follow you
               farther west, &amp; tell you all the news of <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bona Marietta hath had kittens, they were remarkably ugly, all taking after their father Thomas, who there is reason to
               believe was either Uncle or Grandsire to Bona herself, the prohibited degrees of consanguinity which you will find at the end of the
               Bible, not being regarded by cats. As I have never been able to persuade this family that catlings, fed for the purpose &amp; smothered
               with onions, would be rabbits to all eatable purposes, Bona Mariettas ugly progeny no sooner came into the world than they were sent
               out of it; the River Nymph Greta conveyed them to the River God Derwent, &amp; if neither the eels nor the Ladies of the Lake have
               taken a fancy to them on their way, Derwent hath consigned them to the Nereids: you may imagine them converted into sea cats by favour
               of Neptune, &amp; write an episode to be inserted in Ovids Metamorphoses. Bona bore the loss patiently &amp; is in good health &amp;
               spirits. I fear that if you meet with any of the race of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mary Rowes cat<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Coleridge is recorded as reciting children&#8217;s verses of his own composition about &#8216;Miss Mary Rowe, Tity Mouse Brim, Dr. Daniel Dove,
                  of Doncaster, and his Horse Nobbs&#8217; during a walking tour in Germany in 1799. Southey later developed some of these stories in
                     <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> at Ottery<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ottery St Mary, Devon, the
                  birthplace of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref> and the home of his mother and
                  brothers.</note> you will forget poor Marietta. &#8211; Do&#8217;nt bite your arm <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Job</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have been out one evening in the boat <ref type="m" target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Mr Jackson</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs Wilson</ref> &amp; the children &amp; kindled our fire upon the same place where you
               drank tea with us last autumn. The boat has been painted, &amp; there is to be a boathouse built for it. &#8211; Alterations are going on
               here upon a great scale. The parlour has been transmogrified &#8211; that Hartley was one of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mothers</ref> words, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">your Mother</ref> will
               explain it &lt;to&gt; you, &amp; then you may tell her what it is in Ejectian. The masons are at work in my study, &amp; on the shaving
               room; &#8211; the garden is inclosed with a hedge, some trees planted behind it, a <del>shrubbery</del> few shrubs, &amp; abundance of
               currant trees. We must however wait till the autumn before all can be done that is intended in the garden. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> White
               the Belligerent is settled in the Generals<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Peche (dates unknown), who had served in the
                  East India Company&#8217;s army, gazetted as Colonel in 1796 and Major-General in 1798.</note> house &#8211; find out why I give him that
                  appellation.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The aggressive and paunchy Mr White (unidentified) had tried to buy Greta Hall
                  in 1804.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There has been a misfortune in the family. We had a hen with five chickens, &amp; a gleed<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A kite.</note> has carried off four. I have declared war against the gleed &amp; borrowed a gun, but since the gun
               has been in the house he has never made his appearance. Who can have told him of it? Another hen is sitting, &amp; I hope the next
               brood will be luckier. Mr Jackson has bought a cow: but he has had no calf since <hi rend="ital">you</hi> left him. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has taken your place in his house, &amp; talks to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilson by
               the hour about <hi rend="ital">her</hi> Hartley. She grows like a young Giantess, &amp; has a disposition to bite her arm, which you
               know is a very foolish trick. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> is a fine fellow. I call him the Boy of
                  Basan<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Basan/Bashan is an area on the east side of the river Jordan renowned in the Bible for
                  its strong bulls. See <title>Isaiah</title> 2.3; <title>Psalms</title> 22.12.</note> because he roars like a young bull when he is
               pleased. &#8211; indeed he promises to inherit his fathers verbal powers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The weather has been very bad, &#8211; nothing but easterly winds which have kept every thing back. We had one day hotter
               than had been remembered for fourteen years: the glass was at 85 in the shade, in the sun in <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Calverts</ref> Garden at 118. The horses of the mail died at Carlisle. I never
               remember to have felt such heat in England, except one day fourteen years ago, when I chanced to be in the mail coach, &amp; it was
               necessary to bleed the horses or they would have died then. In the course of three days the glass fell forty degrees, &amp; the wind
               was so cold &amp; so violent that persons who attempted to cross the fells beyond Penrith were forced to turn back.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your friend <del>xx</del> Dapper,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s dog.</note> who is I believe your
               god-dog, is in good health, tho he grows every summer graver than the last. This is the natural effect of time, which as you know has
               made me the serious man I am. I hope it will have the same effect upon you &amp; your mother, &amp; that when she returns she will have
               left off that evil habit of quizzing me &amp; calling me names. It is not decorous in a woman of her years. Tell her we often think of
               her, &amp; of the state she was in this time twelvemonth. Long tongues are deceitful. That <del>name</del> saying is for you, the
               meaning is for her. I speak darkly, after the manner of the wise men of old.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PooleThomas">Mr Poole</ref>, &amp; tell him I shall be glad when he
               turns Laker. He will find tolerable lodging at the Hill;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, the &#8216;Aunt Hill&#8217; &#8211; one of
                  Southey&#8217;s nicknames for <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> &#8211; a boat for fine weather, <del>no</del> good
               stores of books for a rainy day, &amp; as hearty a shake by the hand on his arrival as he is likely to meet with between <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> &amp; <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. &#8211; Some books of mine will soon be
               ready for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">your father</ref>. Will he have them sent anywhere, or will he pick
               them up himself when he passes thro London on his way Northward? &#8211; Tell him that I am advancing well in South America,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> appeared in three volumes from 1810&#8211;1819.</note> &amp; shall
               have finished a volume by the end of the year. the Chronicle of the Cid is to go to press as soon as I receive some books from Lisbon
               which must first be examined.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the
                     Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica Particular del Cid</title>
                  (1593), with additions from the <title>Cro&#769;nica de Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and <title>Romancero e Historia del
                     Cid</title> (1632).</note> This <del>is for</del> intelligence is for him also.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am desired to send you as much love as can be inclosed in a letter. I hope it will not be charged double on that
               account at the post office, &#8211; but there is <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs Wilsons</ref> love <ref type="m" target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Mr Jacksons</ref>, your <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Aunt Southeys</ref>,
               your <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Aunt Lovells</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref>, with a purr from Bona Marietta, an open-mouthed kiss from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, &amp; three wags of the tail from Dapper. I trust they will &lt;all&gt; arrive safe, &amp; remain</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> dear Nephew <del>Job</del> Job,</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> your dutiful Uncle</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>