<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1670</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2792</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.73.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 155&#8211;159 [with
                        omissions].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1670" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1670" type="letter">
        <head>1670. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-08-17">17 August
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Durham.<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.73<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 155&#8211;159 [with
                        omissions].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Last night a letter from <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">Thomas Rees</ref> communicated to me the intelligence
                    of the death of the Annual Review. The Long<del>men</del> Men of the Row<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman&#8217;s</ref> publishing firm in <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref>, London.</note> were long in making up their minds to discontinue it; &#8211; it is not above ten days
                    ago that a large parcel of books designed for another volume arrived here, &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">King
                        Thomas</ref> told me he should send off one to you in a few days.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now then supposing that you will seriously set about the Crusades I will give you such directions in the art of
                    historical book-keeping as may save time &amp; facilitate labour.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey
                        did conduct research on the crusades.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Make your writing books in foolscap quarto &amp; write <del>onl</del> on only one side of a leaf; draw a line down
                    the margin, marking off space enough for your references, which should be given at the end of every paragraph, &#8211; <del>min</del>
                    noting page, book or chapter of the author referred to. This minuteness is now demanded, &amp; you will yourself find it useful,
                    for in transcribing, or in correcting proofs it is often requisite to turn to the original authority. Take the best author, that
                    is to say the one who has written most at length of all the original authors upon the particular point of time on which you are
                    employed; &#8211; &amp; draw up your account from him, &#8211; then on the opposite page correct &amp; amplify this from every other who has
                    written upon the same subject, this page should be divided into two columns, one of about two thirds of <del>th</del> its breadth,
                    the other the remaining one; &#8211; you are thus enabled to <hi rend="ital">add</hi> to your <hi rend="ital">additions</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of these books you should have for your geography, &#8211; that is to say for collecting descriptions of all the
                    principal scenes of action, &#8211; which must be done from books of travels &#8211; their situation, their strength, their previous history,
                    &#8211; &amp; in the notes their present state. These descriptions you can insert in their proper place when you transcribe. Thus also
                    you should collect accounts of the different tribes &amp; Dynasties whom you have occasion to mention. In this manner the
                    information which is only to be got at piece meal, &amp; oftentimes incidentally when you are looking for something else, &#8211; is
                    brought together with least trouble, &amp; almost imperceptibly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All relative matter, not absolutely essential to the subject, should go in the form of supplementary notes, &amp;
                    these you may make as amusing as you please, the more so &amp; the more curious the better. Much trouble is saved by writing them
                    on separate bits of paper, each the half of a quarter of a foolscap sheet, numbering them, &amp; making an index of them; &#8211; in
                    this manner they are ready for use when they are wanted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was sometime before I fell into this system of book-keeping, &amp; I believe no better can be desired. A Welsh
                    Triad might comprehend all the rules for style, say what you have to say as <hi rend="ital">perspicuously</hi> as possible, as <hi rend="ital">briefly</hi> as possible, &amp; as <hi rend="ital">rememberably</hi> as possible, &amp; take no other thought
                    about it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Welsh sayings collected in groups of three lines, the earliest of which predate
                        Saxon times. Preserved in different versions, partly in the fourteenth century White Book of Rhydderch and Red Book of
                        Hergest, the triads were associated with bardic recitation. Southey cited the triads in the preface to <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805) from the translation of Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg; 1747&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>) in his <title>Poems, Lyric and
                            Pastoral</title> (1794).</note> Omit none of those little circumstances which give life to narration, &amp; bring old
                    manners, old feelings &amp; old times before your eyes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Gibbon will supply you with the names of the main authorities.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward
                        Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1789),
                        chapters 58&#8211;61.</note> The <hi rend="ital">Gesta Dei per Francos</hi>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 1193 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was <title>Gesta Dei per Francos, siue Orientalium Expeditionum et Regni Francorum
                            Hierosolimitani Historia a Variis, Sed Illius Aeui Scriptoribus, Litteris Commendata, etc,</title> edited by Jacques
                        Bongars (1554&#8211;1612).</note> must be one of the <hi rend="ital">first</hi> importance quoad order of time. This Gibbon refers
                    to for the best account of the state of Jerusalem from the time of Heraclius<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Heraclius (c.
                        575-641), Byzantine Emperor 610&#8211;641.</note> (i.e. the beginning of Mahommedanism) to the Crusades. He refers <del>to</del>
                    also to a memoir of M de Guignes <hi rend="ital">sur le Commerce des Francois dans le Levant avant les Croisades</hi>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph de Guignes (1721&#8211;1800).</note> &#8211; in the <hi rend="ital">Mem de l&#8217;Academie des Inscriptions
                        7. 37. p 467&#8211;500</hi>).<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Acad&#233;mie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres
                        (renamed Acad&#233;mie royale des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres in 1716) was founded in 1663 and published its scholarship in the
                        form of <title>Memoires</title>.</note> Your first Chapter will be the most difficult &amp; should be written last, &#8211; I would
                    advise you <del>to begin with the xxxx xxxxx xx xx</del> not &lt;to&gt; think of introductory matter till you are far advanced in
                    the work &amp; find your stock of knowledge of considerable amount.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the first crusade you will want the Geste Dei,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 5.</note> &#8211; the
                    Acts of the Council of Clermont, which are in the great collection of Council T. 12.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        first Crusade (1095&#8211;1099) was instigated during a meeting of the Church Council, presided over by Pope Urban II (c.
                        1035&#8211;1099), in a field in Clermont, France. Southey derives his reference to the Acts of this Council from Gibbon,
                            <title>Decline and Fall</title>, chapter 58.</note> &#8211; Anna Comnena<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Comnena
                        (1083&#8211;1153), daughter of Alexios I Komnenos (1048/1056&#8211;1118), Byzantine emperor 1081&#8211;1118. She wrote the
                            <title>Alexiad</title>, a history of her father&#8217;s reign. Southey may have read her narrative in the French-compiled dual
                        Latin/Greek edition of Byzantine texts, <title>Byzantinae Historiae Scriptores</title> (1645&#8211;1711).</note> &#8211; I dare say the
                    Byzantine Historians are in the College library. Look at Gibbons 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> note to his 58<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    chapter for his authorities. His 41<hi rend="sup">st</hi> to the same chapter is full of minute references,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 4.</note> &#8211; but you must not be contented with merely following his references, &#8211; unless
                    you read with your own eyes you will do nothing. Do not be dismayed at the sight of a large book, &#8211; <unclear>but</unclear> read on
                    manfully, &amp; you will find &lt;in&gt; the accumulation of knowledge quite as great a pleasure as the veriest miser finds in the
                    accumulation of gold. Read half a dozen authors at once, &amp; thus you never need dwell upon one till you are tired of it, &#8211;
                    &amp; begin the history of two or three Crusades at once, &#8211; that you may be able to go on with one part of the narration when you
                    are in want of materials for another. When you have done enough to <hi rend="ital">give security</hi> to yourself that you will do
                    more, I will put in requisition all my means of obtaining books, &amp; borrow for you from <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> whatever his library contains. Read every traveller that has ever<del>y</del> written upon Syria, Egypt or
                    Palestine, &#8211; in the worst of them you may chance to find something which will throw light <del>&amp;</del> upon history, &amp;
                    make you fully understand circumstances which else you might imperfectly have comprehended. &#8211; I can be of some use to you in the
                    way of annotations, &#8211; &amp; nothing in the course of my reading which bears upon your subject shall be let slip. Go to work with a
                    good heart &amp; you will soon find yourself the happier for having <del>so</del> such a work in hand.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have undertaken to write for <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> Edinb. Annual Register
                    the history of affairs in Spain &amp; Portugal last year, &#8211; for which I shall be well paid, but hard worked being pressed for
                        time.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; section to the <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register</title> for 1808&#8211;1810.</note> If <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> can tell me any
                    anecdotes of Junots character &amp; conduct,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Andoche Junot, Duc d&#8217;Abrantes
                        (1771&#8211;1813) was the commander of the French invasion of Portugal in 1808.</note> &#8211; or of the state of Lisbon during his reign
                    there, I dare say I shall be able to make good use of them. to day I am going to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>, from whence I return on Saturday. Yesterday I took <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref>,
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Coleridge</ref> up <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> being their first appearance upon that stage. They walked
                    it, &amp; did it well by half of meat &amp; drink on the way. Coming home M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C. got into a bog some way above
                    her knees, &amp; I saved her life! I wish you had been there to have assisted in it. Afterwards I washed her pettycoat in one of
                    the <del>becks</del> gills, &amp; carried it home upon my stick. Oh Domine Doctor<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s nickname for Henry Herbert Southey.</note> if you had but been there!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My lease for 21 years is executed; &#8211; that&#8217;s well. Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> is
                    alive but will hardly outlive this month. I know not which will carry him off <del>x</del>, diarrh&#339;a or dropsy. His brothers have
                    been to see him &amp; his sister from London. He however happily does not seem to apprehend that his end is so near. Our love to
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-08-17">
              <del>Aug</del> August 17. 1809.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>