<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1317</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2439</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library,
                        RS 111.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 4&#8211;5 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1317" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1317" type="letter">
        <head>1317. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-05-04">4 May 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Right Honble/ The Speaker/ &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c/ Westminster
                        <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 4 May 1807.<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK/2<lb />Postmark: D/ MAY 7/ 1807<lb />MS: Huntington Library,
                        RS 111<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 4&#8211;5 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The proof sheet consists of 24 pages &amp; may be cut into as many pieces of needful &#8211; tho I formerly understood
                    otherwise, but Taylor<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), whose firm was
                        printing <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note>
                    undeceived me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In order to keep the author&#8217;s name a secret, Southey had been forwarding
                        the proofs of his <title>Letters from England</title> via Rickman; see Southey to John Rickman, 29 April [1807], Letter
                        1312.</note> Place them in the shape which they will retain when <del>xxx</del> put together in a book, <del>double</del> fold
                    them like <hi rend="ital">a note</hi>, &amp; chuse that page which has most blank paper for the directing. &#8211; but do not let me see
                    any more post marks in <hi rend="ital">red ink</hi> till the Tantara-raras<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        disparaging term for the noisy MPs in the House of Commons. <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786
                        play by John O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Dramatic Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1798), III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All Fools All&#8217; was also a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754;
                            <title>DNB</title>) play <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> return.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman
                        was unable to frank letters when Parliament was not in session.</note> There is a great fitness in your franking my proofs, &#8211;
                    none in your paying for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is out of town, &#8211; as bad for our purpose as being out of office he writes me
                    from Chester. Being got into the last volume this failure of franks is of less consequence. The fair sheets may very well
                        <del>xxxx</del> wait till a more convenient season, &#8211; they are matters of luxury, not of necessity, &#8211; rather for my pleasure
                    than my use. If any continuous work it would be otherwise, <del>&amp;</del> in this there is rarely or never occasion for me to
                    refer to what is said before.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In reading Amadis of Greece<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Feliciano de Silva (1491&#8211;1554), <title>Noveno
                            Libro de Amad&#237;s de Gaula, Cr&#243;nica del Muy Valiente y Esforzado Pr&#237;ncipe y Caballero de la Ardiente Espada Amad&#237;s de
                            Grecia, Hijo de Lisuarte de Grecia, Emperador de Constantinopla y de Trapisonda, y Rey de Rodas</title> (1530).</note>
                    (lent me by <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>) I have found Spensers Mask of Cupid,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Edmund Spenser (1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title>, Book 3, Canto 12.</note>
                    Sir P. Sidneys Zelmane,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Arcadia</title> (1593).</note> &amp; Shakesperes Florisel.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Florizel, whom
                        Shakespeare dramatised in the <title>Winter&#8217;s Tale</title>, is the subject of de Silva&#8217;s <title>Don Florisel de Niquea</title>
                        (1532).</note> Was there ever other book honoured by three such borrowers! The father of Tasso<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernardo Tasso (1493&#8211;1569), author of <title>L&#8217;Amadigi</title>, an epic inspired by the Amadis narratives and
                        published by his son Torquato under the title <title>Florindante</title> in 1587.</note> also has borrowed an adventure from
                    it. &#8211; Palmerin<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (London,
                        1807). Southey noted the borrowings from &#8216;Amadis of Greece&#8217; referred to here in his &#8216;Preface&#8217; (pp. xliv&#8211;xlv).</note> will show
                    you the change of manners since the days of Vasco Lobeira<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vasco de Lobeira (died 1403),
                        reputed author of the first of the prose romances of Amadis of Gaul.</note> &#8211; His Princesses are prudes. The book is worth
                    reading, tho every way inferior to Amadis it has much merit, &amp; that merit quite of a different character. There is this
                    remarkable difference in the impression which the two books leave behind them. &#8211; for Lobeira I have a great love, &amp; when I
                    arrive among the worthies of old times, my predecessors, I am inclined to think he will be among the first whom I shall be
                    ambitious of meeting. But for Francisco de Moraes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Moraes Cabral
                        (1500?-1572), author of <title>Libro del Muy esforzado caballero Palmerin de Inglaterra</title> (1547).</note> I have neither
                    respect nor liking; throughout his book there is not a single passage which gives me any love for the author. he knows what virtue
                    is only from what he has been taught, not from what his own heart teaches him, &amp; <del>from</del> represents no character well
                    but such as are marked by some obliquity of mind. And never did I discover in any writer such an ill opinion of womankind, &#8211;
                    learnt I presume from the French Court, where he was for many years attendant on an Embassy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Good news from Portugal. A MSS. has been discovered of Poems, certainly older than the oldest Collection as it had
                    till now been esteemed &#8211; that is certainly older than 1480, &#8211; &amp; supposed by the best antiquarians there to be nearly two
                    centuries older. I shall endeavour to procure a transcript of it; &#8211; &amp; in return part of my business when I next become your guest will be to see to the
                    transcribing of certain Port. MSS. in the Museum,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> that I may
                    have the satisfaction &amp; credit of returning them to their own country, where they will be most thankfully received by the
                    learned. Of men learned in their own literature, Portugal &amp; Spain have a greater proportion than England. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1807-05-04"> May 4. 1807.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I direct in implicit obedience to the <hi rend="ital">Speaker</hi>, tho suspecting that he ought now to be
                            Abbotized.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> On Parliament&#8217;s resumption after the election, the Speaker&#8217;s chair
                            would be taken by <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>; Rickman was his secretary.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>