<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1174</idno><idno type="nines">rce2296</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888 .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 38–39.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1174" type="letter"><head>1174. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-04-12">12 April
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Mrs Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland./
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: NORWICH/ 110<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888 <lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 38–39.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1806-04-12">Saturday. April 12. 1806.</date> 
                        <address><placeName>Norwich</placeName></address></dateline><salute>My dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I write, tho literally with nothing to say, merely because you will be wishing to receive a letter. My place is
                    taken for tomorrow, &amp; I hope to be in London by – noon on Monday, some five or six hours before this can reach you.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your letter arrived the day on which my last was written,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to
                        Edith Southey, 5 April 1806, Letter 1172.</note> tho from the lateness of the post I had concluded there would be none till
                    the morrow. When the morrow came I was sorry that I had it not still to look for. You will not I suppose be more comfortable in
                    your feelings till this intolerable weather changes: intolerable it may truly be called. The wind seems determined to get a new
                    character, &amp; make the weathercock an emblem of immutability. My fingers ache while writing &amp; I do not stir out without the
                        bearskin<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s name for his greatcoat.</note> – which thick as it is is hardly
                    sufficient to keep me warm, even with exercise. Spring however will come on rapidly whenever this blasting wind is at an end.</p><p rend="indent1"> My adventures here are such as you might guess – a mere repetition of visits &amp; dinners. Tuesday a dinner party
                    here <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">Dr Sayers</ref> – Pitchford<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitchford
                        (1772/3–1839), one of the Norwich intellectuals with religious and literary interests who had gathered around Sayers and <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>.</note> &amp; two other men. Wednesday we dined with <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">Dr Sayers</ref>, &amp; the day was the pleasanter because he could get nobody to meet us.
                    Thursday with a walk &amp; called on John Gurneys family<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Gurney (1749–1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), merchant and banker of Norwich, the father of Elizabeth Fry (1780–1845; <title>DNB</title>), the
                        Quaker prison reformer.</note> – the tribe who were once at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, dined with
                    Pitchford – &amp; had droppers in to the tray at home. Yesterday a sumptuous dinner with Joseph Gurney.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Gurney (1757–1830), a member of the Quaker banking family and brother to John Gurney.</note> The two
                    impossibilities for a stranger at Norwich, are to find his way about the city – &amp; to know the names of the Gurneys. They
                    talked about <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, &amp; seemed to fear his book would not sell as he expected
                    it to do.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> His fears were unfounded. In 1806 Thomas Clarkson published <title>A Portraiture
                            of Quakerism</title>, which met with great success.</note> Not more than twenty subscribers having been procured among the
                    Quakers there. <del>Today we dine with Dr. Sonxxx with Mr. John Taylor</del> – &amp; tomorrow I sup at Newmarket on my way to London &amp; sleep in the coach – &amp; then have you
                    my whole history thus far.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall write soon from London &amp; as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> is fond of a
                    letter will frank down a book for her with a great-seal which I think will delight her. It is now thirteen days since my departure
                    from home – the time seems thrice as long – so much ground have I gone over, &amp; seen so many new scenes &amp; fresh faces. You
                    may be well assured that I will lose no time in London, but get thro my business as rapidly as possible – &amp; off for
                        Herefordshire<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref> had the living of a parish at Staunton-on-Wye, Herefordshire, which, while
                        he was in Lisbon, he had left in the care of <ref target="people.html#ThomasDr">Dr Thomas</ref>, father of his business agent
                            <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">William Bowyer Thomas</ref>, who had died in 1802. Southey was visiting the
                        estate on his uncle’s behalf to investigate the payment of tithes’; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 17 March 1806, Letter
                        1166.</note> without going an inch out of my way to right or left. </p><p rend="indent1"> The Annual does not seem to be quite published – <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthurs</ref> weekly
                    numbers coming out a fortnight or three weeks asunder. He has I see been playing his usual editorial tricks with me, &amp; has
                    left off <del>some</del> a defence of Bruce<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed James Bruce’s
                            (1730–1794;<title> DNB</title>), <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768–73</title>, 2nd edn.
                        (1804–1805), in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 2–16.</note> against Pinkerton<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>): Scottish antiquarian and cartographer whose many publications
                        earned him a reputation for irreligious views, arrogant irritability and personal immorality.</note> – because he did not
                    chuse to have Mr Pinkerton contradicted, &amp; some remarks upon the infamous blunders of the printer because he did not chuse to
                    insert anything which was not agreable to the booksellers.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of Bruce’s
                            <title>Travels</title> was printed by the firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> for the
                        booksellers Archibald Constable &amp; Co. (1774–1827; <title>DNB</title>), Manners and Miller, and Longman (the publisher of
                        the <title>Annual Review</title>).</note> And yet Miss Lucy Aikin<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy Aikin
                        (1781–1864; <title>DNB</title>), the daughter of <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> and sister of Arthur
                        Aikin.</note> says her brother is by nature of an intrepid character, – &amp; alleges as a proof of this intrepidity that he
                    puts his name to the Annual Review. The whole of the theology is written by a Mr. Wellbeloved<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Wellbeloved (1769–1858; <title>DNB</title>), Unitarian minister and theology tutor. As well as having
                        responsibility for reviewing religious and metaphysical works for the <title>Annual Review</title>, he published <title>Devotional
                        Exercises for Young Persons</title> in 1801.</note> of York whose qualification for reviewing is – that his mother is Mrs Aikins
                    sister – so he is not only our Wellbeloved cousin, but also in consequence of this cousinship becomes our Wellbeloved brother in
                    the Review. – Charles Aikin<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Rochemont Aikin (1775–1847; <title>DNB</title>), son
                        of <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref>, and brother of Arthur and Lucy, who was adopted by his aunt, <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Anna Letitia Barbauld</ref>, and trained to be a surgeon.</note> is going to
                    marry Miss Wakefield,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Wakefield (d. 1821), daughter of Gilbert Wakefield (1756–1801;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the biblical scholar, religious dissenter and political radical, who was a friend of the Aikin
                        family. Anne’s father was indicted for seditious libel in 1798 and imprisoned until 1801, dying shortly after his
                        release.</note> he is said to be a truly amiable man – but a more unlovely one you never saw. There is a certain pitch of
                    ugliness to which it is inconceivable how either man or woman can make up their minds, &amp; poor Charles Aikin is unfortunately
                    at that pitch.</p><p rend="indent1"> I begin to think that my expedition to Lisbon may be disconcerted – that since Bonaparte has succeeded in making
                    Prussia shut her ports against us, he may think to compleat his project by ejecting us from <del>xxxxx</del> Portugal – at least
                    this is more probable than it was a fortnight ago. – Tell me if you would like to see Patch’s trial,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 5 April 1806, Richard Patch (1770?-1806; <title>DNB</title>) was tried for the murder of Isaac Blight (d.
                        1805). He was found guilty and hanged on 8 April. Shortly afterwards an account was published, by Joseph Gurney (1744–1815)
                        and his son, William Brodie Gurney (1777–1855), of <title>The Trial of Richard Patch for the Wilful Murder of Isaac Blight, at
                            Rotherhithe, on the 23rd of September 1805: at the Session House, Newington, Surrey, on Saturday the fifth of April
                            1806</title>.</note> &amp; in that case I will frank it down to you.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have got a clue to the state of the Catholicks here of which some use may be made by D Manuel.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807).</note> Pitchford is the head of the sect here &amp; loves to talk about them, &amp; from him I
                    have borrowed a sort of Catholick Almanac which explains their present state. I shall purchase one in London &amp; turn it to good
                    account. He tells me the Jesuits exist in England as a seperate body, &amp; have even a chapel in Norwich<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> A small Jesuit chapel was built in St Swithin’s, Norwich, towards the end of the eighteenth century. It was
                        rebuilt on a grander scale after the Catholic Emancipation Act of 1829.</note> – but how they exist, or whence their funds are
                    derived? is a secret to him himself. This is a highly curious fact, &amp; to me particularly – a very interesting one. I shall
                    make farther enquiry. St. Winifred has lately worked a miracle at her Well, &amp; healed a paralytic woman.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saint Winifred was a 7th-century Welsh noblewoman, who died rather than lose her chastity. She
                        was canonised, and a shrine was established at the place of her death, in Holywell, Flintshire, where a spring on the site was
                        said to have healing powers.</note> These Catholicks want only a little more success to be just as impudent as they were three
                    centuries ago.</p><p rend="indent1"> Some hope I have of finding a letter in London – if you have not written however, let me have by the first post –
                    if it merely tells me that you &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the child</ref> are as when I left you it will
                        <del>xxx xx</del> lighten my heart of a sort of weight which is daily growing heavier. I have seen the fire safeguards, or
                    whatever they are to be called. They <del>are</del> perfectly answer their purpose, do not obstruct the heat, rather improve than
                    hurt the look of the grate &amp; are of such utility that I think no fire ought to be without one.</p><p rend="indent1"> My first business in London must be to send for Hyde,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        tailor frequented by Southey when he was in London; his first name and dates are unknown.</note> &amp; to buy a hat – for the
                    journey to London is an excuse for my old one here.</p><p rend="indent1"> And I shall the first walk I take buy a book for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>, that
                    I may have this pleasure of sending it her in a letter which is to be for her own self, &amp; to be given into her own hand. Give
                    her a kiss – &amp; fifty more added to it – &amp; remember that all you give her you lend me – &amp; that I shall soon repay every one with interest.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear dear Edith</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>