<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1121</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2243</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Manuscripts and Archives Section, New York
                        Public Library.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and
                        New York, 1965), I, pp. 407&#8211;409.Dating note: Despite the postmark, the contents of this letter suggest it was written
                        before that to Rickman of 19 November 1805.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1121" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1121" type="letter">
        <head>1121. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard Duppa</ref>, <date when="1805-11-19">[started before 19
                        November 1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [insertion in another hand] To/ Richard Duppa
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 13. Poland Street/ Oxford Street/ London./ Single/ &lt; N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 51 Great <hi rend="ital">Marlboro</hi> Street&gt;<lb />Postmark: E/ NOV22/ 1805<lb />MS: Manuscripts and Archives Section, New York
                        Public Library<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and
                        New York, 1965), I, pp. 407&#8211;409.<lb />Dating note: Despite the postmark, the contents of this letter suggest it was written
                        before that to Rickman of 19 November 1805.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Duppa</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our succession of visitors is over, the summer birds have all taken flight. The Islanders are gone, the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> is gone. &amp; our in door circle also is contracted, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> have left
                    us, the season for reviewing is begun &amp; I have put on my winter cloaths &amp; commenced my hybernation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Scotch excursion with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> was a pleasant one. We saw Melrose on
                    our way, if not the most picturesque ruin, certainly the finest architectural one in the whole island.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Melrose Abbey is a picturesque ruin located in the Scottish borders. It was founded in 1136 by Cistercian
                        monks. Southey visited the Abbey, which is close to Walter Scott&#8217;s then home, <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Ashestiel</ref>, on his trip to Edinburgh in October
                        1805.</note> We staid three days with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> at his <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">home</ref> on the banks of the Tweed. One morning was given to salmon-spearing &#8211; with a heavy
                    trident about twelve feet long I had to manage one <del>side</del> end of a flat bottomed crazy boat as she floated sideways down
                    a rapid stream, &amp; to keep her even, &amp; prevent her from striking against the rocks &amp; so upsetting. I did my part well,
                    &amp; having no evil designs upon the salmon came home quite innocent, &amp; sufficiently instructed in a very singular
                    &lt;savage&gt; sport. Scott is a pleasant man, of open &amp; friendly manners, so full of topographical anecdote that having seen
                    him you would be perfectly well satisfied how well history may be preserved by tradition. We saw much classic ground besides the
                    Tweed. The Yarrow with Newark Castle, Branksome overlooking the Tiviot &amp; Johnny Armstrongs strong hold on the Esk.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey visited Newark Castle (a ruin in the valley of the Yarrow Water, three miles west of
                        Selkirk in the Scottish Borders); Branxholme Castle (owned by Charles William Henry Montagu-Scott, 4th Duke of Buccleuch and
                        6th Duke of Queensberry (1772&#8211;1819), friend and relation of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, who used
                        the castle as a setting for his work <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805)); Gilnockie tower on the Esk
                        river, built by John (or &#8216;Johnny&#8217;) Armstrong (d. 1530), who was an outlaw in the Scottish borders.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At Edinburgh <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> was invited to meet me. Before he would venture
                    to do this he sent me his reviewal of Madoc, then printed but not published.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey&#8217;s
                        review of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> A man
                    who has been reviewed above fifty times, which is my case is hardened to such things &#8211; besides by Gods blessing such praise or
                    such censure as can be bespoke for five guineas a sheet can neither help nor harm me now. <del>xxxxx xxxxxxxxxxxx</del> they who
                    fling dirt at me will only dirt their own hands &#8211; for I am out of reach. So <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>
                    &amp; I met courteously &amp; are very good friends. In fact I am not very irascible, &amp; if I had been so &#8211; found him too
                    little to be angry with. he is not above five foot one. a man of ready wit, no taste &amp; so little knowledge that it would have
                    been scarcely <del>xxxxx</del> inaccurate to have said none. Bating the very immoral trade which he has set up, of
                    &lt;publicly&gt; speaking ill of books which he makes no scruple to commend in private, a good-natured man, who only writes
                    malignantly because it gratifies his vanity &amp; sells his review. He has since been to the Lakes &amp; supt with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of all the Scotch reviewers who have fallen in my way, &amp; with the exception of Sidney Smith<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founder members of the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, in 1802. He was a frequent contributor of reviews on a wide range of subjects, including philosophy,
                        travel, drama, and theology.</note> I have seen all of any celebrity, I think little, perhaps too little. But having lived
                    with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> it is impossible not to perceive that
                    these Scotch men are very feeble indeed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> sleeps over the unhappy Specimens,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly-compiled anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (1807).</note> &amp; will I verily believe oblige me to come to town to compleat in two weeks what he
                    &lt;will&gt; have been two years about! The inconvenience which this delay <del>hav</del> occasions me is more than he conceives.
                    I am vexed &#8211; but have learnt to rely upon myself next time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> the journey of D Manuel to London, &amp; have another
                    large cargo ready to send, from which you will be able to form an adequate idea of the tone &amp; temper of the work.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807). For the two letters to Rickman mentioned here; see Southey to John Rickman, 27 October 1805
                        (Letter 1115) and 19 November [1805], (Letter 1122).</note> In the course of three months I shall be ready for your part,
                        <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa wrote several passages of <title>Letters from England</title>. The description
                        of the monuments in Westminster Abbey, in Letter 23, is an example of his contributions. Southey notes in his own copy of
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807),
                        that Duppa&#8217;s contributions were included in I, pp. 264, 268 and 273&#8211;275.</note> &amp; hope to have the book in the press. To
                    the best of my judgement it is likely to sell well, but the sale of books is almost a lottery. You will have heard if you have
                    seen any of my correspondents that I go for Lisbon next year, certainly unless any unforeseen public or private mishap should
                    prevent. That I may do my business thoroughly &amp; not be hurried <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the child</ref> go with me, &amp; I shall remain two or even three years.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected visit to Portugal did not take place.</note> In fact once there I shall not
                    wish soon to return, but when returned may confidently look to a permanent settlement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have seen the Monthly Review of Madoc, some wretched man who either has been reviewed by me with deserved
                    severity, or fancies that he has &#8211; has been permitted to vent his spleen there, which he has done very clumsily. It is stupid
                    &amp; blunt ill nature. A blue-bottle fly wriggling his tail &amp; fancying he has a sting in it.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish physician who practised medicine in Manchester and
                        often contributed articles to the <title>Monthly Review</title>, including this one on <title>Madoc</title> (1805). See
                            <title>Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 48 (October 1805), 113&#8211;122.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Edinburgh is the finest city I have ever seen. having had no new coat since I was in London &amp; no new hat except
                    a seven shilling white one of felt, it was judged proper by Edith that I should beautify my appearance in Scotland, &amp; also
                    adorn myself with new boots &amp; new pantaloons. But when I was there, &amp; contemplated the very respectable figure I made,
                    considering the vanity of externals, &amp; moreover that as learning was better than house &amp; land it must be much better than
                    new cloathes &#8211; I laid out all my money in books, &#8211; &amp; have in consequence the pleasure of laughing at the man&#339;uvre &amp;
                    reading the books.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How goes on Michael Angelo?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa&#8217;s <title>Life and Literary Works of
                            Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> was published in 1806 and contained translations by Southey
                        and <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William Wordsworth</ref>.</note> I beseech you publish while I may have it in
                    my power to review.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Duppa&#8217;s <title>Heads from the Fresco Pictures of
                            Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802) in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 918&#8211;923, as well as
                            <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806) in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 411&#8211;425.</note> If you will send more translations I will do my best.
                    After this year I have done with reviewing at all events for ever.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey continued his
                        reviewing work when his trip to Portugal did not occur.</note> My apprenticeship has been a long one, &amp; heartily glad
                    shall I be to leave off the trade.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How are our friends at Stockwell?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stockwell Park, Surrey, residence of
                            <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">Thomas Woodroffe Smith</ref>, a wealthy Quaker merchant, and his second
                        wife, Anne Reynolds. The Smiths were friends of <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> and his family
                        as well as Duppa.</note> I do not ask without some uneasy anticipations, for an English winter is trying for an invalid. There
                    are warm baths in Portugal which restored to Lady Errol<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Alicia Eliot (d. 1812),
                        wife of William Hay, 17th Earl of Errol (1772&#8211;1819).</note> the use of her limbs, &amp; which might perhaps be serviceable to
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 13.</note> I could wish he would try change of
                    climate, &amp; will urge him to it if he finds himself no better in the spring.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> We go on well. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">little Edith<del>s</del>
            </ref> very forward with
                        her tongue. All desire their remembrances.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>