<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1679</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2801</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library, In 74 A. L. S. to
                        various correspondents. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 161&#8211;164.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1679" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1679" type="letter">
        <head>1679. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-09-08">8
                        September 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Durham
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Watermark: T BOTFIELD<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library, In 74 A. L. S. to
                        various correspondents. <lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 161&#8211;164.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not sure whether I said any thing respecting a material part of your work, &#8211; which is its Bibliography.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter is largely concerned with Henry Southey&#8217;s proposed history of the
                        Crusades.</note> Have a book for this express purpose &#8211; &amp; allowing every author his leaf or <del>x</del> more, as need may
                    be, put down every thing concerning him &amp; his works, as <del>x</del> you meet with it in the work itself, or stumble upon
                    &lt;it&gt; accidentally elsewhere, &#8211; minuting down your own remarks, so that these Collectanea may be formed into a
                    Bio-bibliographical &amp; critical <del>x</del> account. This is what Gibbon<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Gibbon
                        (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), author of the <title>History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title>
                        (1776&#8211;1789).</note> regretted not having done, &amp; what every historian should do &#8211; I shall do it volume by volume in my
                    great opus.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s History of Portugal, never completed, of which his <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) was a part.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have long coveted &amp; desired a set of the Byzantine Historians above all other books, &amp; am not without
                    hopes of being able to compass my wishes in the course of another year or two. <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is
                        probably referring to the French-compiled dual Latin/Greek edition of Byzantine texts, <title>Byzantin&#230; Histori&#230;
                            Scriptores</title> (1645&#8211;1711). He eventually owned the <title>Corpus Scriptorum Histori&#230; Byzantin&#230;</title> in 40 volumes,
                        no. 740 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> My last told you of an engagement with <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> to write the history of Spanish affairs for 1808 &#8211; in his Ed. An.
                    Register; &#8211; I have since consented to take the whole historical department, for which he is to pay no less a sum than 400 &#163;.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed to the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for 1808&#8211;1810 in James
                        Ballantyne&#8217;s <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. For Southey&#8217;s previous letter to Henry, see Southey to Southey to Henry
                        Herbert Southey, 17 August 1809, Letter 1670.</note> &#8211; &amp; if I do this <del>x</del> a second year (he wishes me to
                    undertake it regularly) it will enable me to purchase this enormous set of books, in which the whole of your Greek authorities
                    will be contained. There is a French Hist. of the Crusaders which you must lay your hand on whenever you find it in a Catalogue.
                    it is by P. Maimbourg<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Maimbourg (1610&#8211;1686), <title>Histoire des Croisades pour la
                            Deliverance de la Terre Sainte, par le P. Louis Maimbourg, de la Compagnie de Jesus</title> (1682).</note> &#8211; &amp; I dare
                    say bad enough, &#8211; but it will be of use, by sometimes showing the bearing &amp; relation of facts to each other which might have
                    escaped you, &amp; more frequently by <del>xxxxx a</del> explaining the names of places, which are often utterly inexplicable
                    without some such help.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must acquaint yourself thoroughly with the whole grievous history of the Mahommedans, &amp; this will best be
                    done by the Universal History,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is probably referring to the 26 volume
                            <title>Universal History, Ancient and Modern, from the Earliest Account of Time to the Present, Compiled from Original
                            Authors, with the Additions, Maps and Plates</title> (1740&#8211;1765), no. 2888 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
                    which is far better in <del>its</del> this branch than <hi rend="ital">in</hi> any other, &#8211; or than any other. It is an
                    interesting history, but the Propria qu&#1237; maribus<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A schooltext Latin phrase, here meaning
                        &#8216;things which are deemed appropriate to males&#8217;.</note> of the Arabians renders it almost impossible to remember the actors who
                    figure in it. your introduction should contain a view of the moral &amp; political system of the Koran, i-e Islam as Mohammed
                    taught it; &amp; an account of its mythology as held by his followers, for the Christianity of the Vatican is not more unlike that
                    of the Gospel in its mythology, than that of the present Mufti is to what Ali fought for.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        A mufti is a Sunni Islamic scholar who interprets Islamic law. Al&#299; ibn Ab&#299; &#7788;&#257;lib (c. 599&#8211;661) was the son-in-law of Muhammad
                        (570&#8211;632) as well as his cousin and supporter. After his death he became one of the first four leaders of Islam, but as
                        Muhammad&#8217;s closest male relative he believed he should have had sole leadership. His murder in 660 led to a division between
                        Sunni and Shiite Moslems.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your first chapter must have an account of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernard.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bernard of Clairvaux (1090&#8211;1153), a French abbot who was instrumental in setting up the Cistercian religion order, as well as
                        preaching support for the Second Crusade (1146&#8211;1149). The Second Crusade took place after the Christian defeat by the Seljuk
                        Turks at the Siege of Edessa (1144), which was a Crusader state established after the First Crusade (1096&#8211;1099).</note> I can
                    send you an Italian life of him of the date 1614,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey owned a copy of <title>Battista
                            Vita di San Bernardo</title>, published in Turin in 1618. It was no. 180 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; if
                    you can find no other at hand, but there will probably be one prefixed to his works, which there can be little doubt of finding in
                    one of your Cathedral Libraries. I have <del>a certain</del> a copy out of which all the prolegomena, including <del>xx
                        xxxxx</del> &lt;the Table of Contents&gt; have been torn,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 247 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was St Bernard&#8217;s <title>Opera</title> (n.d.), wanting title.</note> &#8211; &amp; which by this
                    mutilation is almost rendered useless, &#8211; for life is not long enough to read such authors thro. &#8211; before turning to it I perceive
                    a Latin life which will doubtless be the best authority, &amp; a seperate account of his miracles. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> S Bernard was a far greater man than any of his Biographers will lead you to suppose, &#8211; they make him a Saint &amp;
                    a Thaumatourgos.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> One who works wonders or miracles.</note> &#8211; &amp; that is all. but he
                    was a farseeing statesman, &amp; a main agent in that grand scheme of the Benedictines of uniting all Xtendom into a sort of
                    federal government under the Pope. &#8211; at that time the grandest &amp; most beneficial scheme that could possibly be devised. The
                    Epistles must be examined,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Epistles of St Bernard, published after his death.</note>
                    &#8211; I have occasion to hunt them thro for the chance there may be of finding any thing relating to Alfonso Henriquez,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Afonso I, or Afonso Henriques (c. 1109&#8211;1185), was the first King of Portugal (1112&#8211;1185).</note>
                    a great admirer of the Saints, &#8211; &amp; I will mark what they contain for your purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> _______</p>
        <p rend="indent1" />
        <p rend="indent1"> Since writing the above I have looked thro S Bernards works, &#8211; a note or two (which I have marked) may be gleaned
                    from them. &amp; this is all which you will find for your purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Another plan which I can from experience recommend, is to have a common place book in which <del>you</del> to enter
                    such passages in the work you read as have no immediate bearing to what you have in hand &#8211; &amp; yet may be of use hereafter, &#8211;
                    either entering the passage itself, the substance of it, or merely the subject with a reference to <del>th</del> the exact place,
                    &#8211; according to the length &amp; nature of the passage. I do this now to every book I read, &amp; the advantage is very great. When
                    your extracts are not in Greek or Latin you have an amanuensis at hand. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    transcribes many of my notes for me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have two articles in the third Quarterly. The S Sea Missions &amp; Ld Valentia.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809):<title> Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title>, 24&#8211;61; George Annesley, Viscount Valentia (1770&#8211;1844), <title>Voyages
                            and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt in the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title>
                        (1809), 88&#8211;126.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R S.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address> &#8211; <date when="1809-09-08">Sept. 8. 1809</date>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>