<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1465</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2587</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 67&#8211;69.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1465" type="letter">
        <head>1465. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1808-06-11">11
                        June 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M
                        P./ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb />Postmark: FREE/ 14 JUL 14/ 1808<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 67&#8211;69.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have something to thank you for, &#8211; but it is not for a letter, &#8211; if you neglect your gospel duties as much as you
                    do your epistle ones &#8211; heaven help you! &#8211; I have to thank you for your amendment to Ld Castlereaghs bill,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Stewart, 2nd Marquess of Londonderry (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) became Secretary of State for War
                        and the Colonies in 1807. In 1808 Castlereagh introduced a Local Militia Bill designed to improve the nation&#8217;s defences by
                        requiring men to join local militias for up to 28 days per year. The amendments proposed by Wynn in the Commons debate of 30
                        May concerned exemptions from service and the administering of an oath &#8211; a procedure with which Southey, as an objector to the
                        39 articles of the established church, would, in common with many radicals and dissenters, have been reluctant to comply. Thus
                        Hansard: &#8216;Mr. C. Wynne observed that in this case a strong temptation to perjury existed, and there was every opportunity for
                        evasion; he therefore objected to the oath. He contended that the frequency with which oaths were administered had much
                        diminished their influence on the public mind, especially when they were administered in cases where there was every
                        temptation to perjury. &#8211; Mr. Windham, Mr. W. Smith, Mr. Wilberforce, sir S. Romilly, sir T. Turton, and Mr. Stephens, joined
                        with Mr. Wynne, in his representation of the mischievous effects that resulted to the community from the frequency of
                        appointing oaths to be taken in improper cases, and declared their conviction of the soundness of the common law principle,
                        which prohibits oaths being taken by persons strongly interested in the cause. &#8211; Lord Castlereagh agreed that the oath should
                        be left out, and that the clause should remain with the provision that a declaration to the same purport should be signed by
                        the volunteer, with a penalty of 20<hi rend="ital">l.</hi> if false. In the twenty second clause, exempting persons who shall
                        have served four years in the local militia from being liable to serve therein again for four years after, two amendments were
                        proposed. One was, that instead of the term of the exemption for four years, the exemption should be till the turn came by
                        rotation. The other, proposed by Lord Milton, was, that one who served four years in the local militia should be for two
                        years, subsequent to the close of that period, exempt from the regular militia ballot. Both were agreed to&#8217;.</note> &#8211; whereby
                    you have exempted me from the Local Militia. There is one good consequence resulting from your speaking in the house &amp; taking
                    an active part there, of which you are not aware at the time; &#8211; it lets your friends in the country know you are alive, when they
                    might otherwise be ignorant of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor Conway Shipley!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Conway Shipley (1782&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), a
                        member of a North Wales clerical and landowning family in Wynn&#8217;s circle, was killed on 23 April while on a mission to &#8216;cut
                        out&#8217; an enemy ship from its moorings on the river Tagus.</note> Sir R Barlow<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert
                        Barlow (1757&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), a naval officer famed for having, as captain of a frigate in the 1790s, captured
                        French frigates after close range actions.</note> used to say his was the finest set of midshipmen in the fleet, &#8211; there were
                    seven of them. Shipley, Betterworth,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> Hanfield,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Jon Hanfield (dates unknown) who Southey refers to in a letter to Thomas Southey, 27 September 1808,
                        Letter 1512.</note> &#8211; a son of Sir Roger Curtis,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> 1st Baronet (1746&#8211;1816;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer. Curtis&#8217;s son, also named Roger (?-1802) was a post captain by 1802.</note> a son of
                    Sir J B. Warren,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Borlase Warren, Baronet (1753&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), naval
                        officer. The son joined the Coldstream Guards and was killed at Abu Qir in 1801.</note> Prowitt<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> &amp; my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Curtis, a lad of genius,
                    died of consumption.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 12 July 1802.</note> Warren was taken out of the navy to please
                    his mother &amp; transferred into the army, &#8211; he fell in Egypt. Hanfield, Betterworth &amp; Shipley all rose to the same rank,
                    were all among the most promising men in the British navy, &amp; have all fallen within a few weeks of each other, &#8211; &amp; what is
                    vexatious all fallen unprofitably. Prowitt &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> both old lieutenants have often
                    half envied the better fortunes of their old messmates, &amp; now they are the only survivors. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">little boy</ref> has been very ill, &amp; <del>x</del> I had many days
                    anxiety about him. Thank God he is now recovering &amp; able again to walk. I have <del>xxxx</del> &lt;such a&gt; rooted &amp;
                    habitual sense of the precariousness of life, <del>xxx</del> that what is to be done with him hereafter, scarcely ever passes
                    across my mind, &amp; never so as to excite a moment of care. I only resolve that if possible he shall be neither soldier nor
                    sailor, &#8211; &amp; wish I could breed him a Quaker, &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How much of Kehama<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> did I send you? &#8211; I am borrowing hours from sleep to go on with it, &amp;
                    &lt;have&gt; made some progress. If five hundred subscribers could be found for every such poem <del>xxx</del> &lt;which&gt; I
                    should produce, I should wish for no better fortune. &#8211; because there would be no occasion to allow the booksellers the Lions
                    share. However by thus creating the time so employed, whatever it may produce will be gain &#8211; tho but another five &amp; twenty
                    pounds; &#8211; &amp; I am rigorously resolved to allow it no <del>other</del> time <del>than</del> &lt;but&gt; what is thus fairly won.
                    If you can tell me the last line of what you already have, I will send you the rest as it pro[MS obscured] It is more than
                    probable that I should never have written verse again had it not been for an accidental meeting with <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, the author of Gebir.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor&#8217;s
                        oriental poem of 1798.</note> I had told him of the whole series which I have planned, &#8211; &amp; that they were stopt because
                    Thalaba &amp; Madoc<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s earlier mythological poems <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) and <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> lay <del>upon</del> in the publishers cellars &#8211; &amp; he
                    said to me write them &#8211; as many as you will, &amp; I will pay for the printing. This stung me. &#8230; &amp; I believe a strong desire
                    to show him that if the time could anyway be afforded I cared nothing for present popularity or present emolument, but would
                    willingly cast my bread upon the waters, &#8211; has been the main, almost the only motive, for my resuming an amusement which I had
                    totally disused for the last three years. Perhaps I may do more than I have yet done. &#8211; as soon as I have determined between the
                    subject of Pelayo<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project would eventually become Southey&#8217;s 1814 epic,
                            <title>Roderick Last of the Goths</title>.</note> &amp; the first deliverance of Portugal from Castile,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The battle of Aljubarotta of 1385, repelled, and largely annihilated, Castilian invading forces,
                        to establish John of Avis (1358&#8211;1433) firmly on the Portuguese throne. He ruled as John I, 10th king of Portugal and the
                        Algarve from 1385&#8211;1433. This plan was not adopted.</note> I shall probably begin another blank verse poem in the morning
                    hours; &#8211; because it will save time to carry on two poems at once, &#8211; when the thread of ready thought is run out in one &#8211; I may
                    then turn to the other, &#8211; &amp; reap the <del>ben</del> harvest of one field while the other is lying fallow. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-06-11">June 11. 1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>