<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1542</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2664</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 185&#8211;189
                        [with omissions, and mis-dated 17 November]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1542" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1542" type="letter">
        <head>1542. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, [started before, and
                    continued on]<date when="1808-11-24"> 24 November 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C.
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Endorsement: 24 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1808<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ NOV 28/ 1808<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 185&#8211;189
                        [with omissions, and mis-dated 17 November]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have taken what I said a little too seriously, &#8211; that is you have given it more thought than it deserved.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had expressed reservations about writing for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>;
                        see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 18 November 1808, Letter 1536.</note> The case stands thus you wish to serve the
                    public, ministers wish to serve themselves, &#8211; &amp; it so happens that just at this time the two objects are the same. I am very
                    willing to travel with them as far as <del>xxx</del> we are going the same way, &amp; when our roads seperate shall of course
                    leave them. Meantime that suppression which there certainly will be upon certain points is of little consequence to me,
                        <del>xxx</del> who shall have nothing to do with those points. <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me
                    materials for the Missionary article, which <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> wishes to <del>have</del> enter
                    upon the subject generally, &#8211; my intent was to have confined myself to the Hindoo question &#8211; but I am master of the whole subject
                    &amp; will therefore take the wider view.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed missionary activities generally
                        in his review of <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> There are three reviewals of mine upon this very topic in the three first Annuals,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> (1800&#8211;1801), in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207&#8211;218. In the <title>Annual Review
                            for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), he reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (Vol. 1, 1803), 189&#8211;201. In
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805) he reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (Vol. 2,
                        1804), 621&#8211;634.</note> which are well done, &#8211; &amp; there were the first which ever appeared concerning them. I am strong here
                    &amp; shall do well, God willing, &#8211; yet how much better could I do if nobody but Robert Southey was responsible for the opinions
                    expressed, &amp; I could speak out concerning the corruptions of Xtianity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> that he reviews the Cid,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott reviewed Southey, <title>Chronicle of the Cid Rodrigo Diaz de Bivar, the Campeador, from
                            the Spanish</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1.1 (1809), 117&#8211;134.</note> &#8211; it is not a text for entering
                    directly upon the present Spanish affairs, &#8211; tho a fair one for <hi rend="ital">touching</hi> upon them. Two things are required
                    for the review of that book which will not be found in one person &#8211; a knowledge of Spanish literature, &#8211; &amp; of the manners of
                    chivalry, &#8211; so as to estimate the comparative value of any Chronicle. The latter knowledge <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> possesses better than any body else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About Cevallos<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Cevallos Guerra (1760&#8211;1840) was Sectretary of State in
                        Spain when the country was taken by the French. He fled to London in 1808, returning to Madrid in 1814, after the war.</note>
                    you best know your own stock of materials, &#8211; authors may be divided into silkworms &amp; spiders, those who spin because they are
                    full, &amp; those who spin because they are empty. <del>What fact</del> It is not likely that there are any facts of importance
                    which are not known to the public, &amp; indeed if I undertook the task I should have little to do with the past history of <hi rend="ital">these</hi> transactions &#8211; but state as summarily &amp; <del>xxx</del> strongly as I could what the conduct of
                    France had been, hold up the war as a crusade on the part of us &amp; the Spaniards (I love &amp; vindicate the Crusades &#8211;) show
                    why I expected this from their character, &amp; also why I &lt;now&gt; expect<del>ed</del> in full faith a glorious termination at
                    last, tho prepared to <del>expect</del> &lt;hear of&gt; heavy reverses for a time, &#8211; possibly the recoronation of Joseph<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Bonaparte (1768&#8211;1844), the eldest brother of Napoleon, who made him King of Spain
                        (1808&#8211;1813).</note> at Madrid. Finally I would represent the thought of peace with Bonaparte as high treason against all
                    honourable feelings &#8211; &amp; all liberty &#8211; <del>&amp; xxx xxx Europe. I have some</del> Of the Spanish frigates I would say
                    nothing<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">At issue was whether the British, since July 1808 allied with the Spanish people in their war against the French invaders of their country, should have restored to Spain frigates captured shortly before the alliance, when Spain was still formally an ally of Napoleonic France.</note>
                    &#8211; Would to God that they who issued orders for their capture were turned in the deep with them! &#8211; There is a sort of methodical
                    writing <del>xxx</del> carrying with it an air of official imposingness which does better in such cases than better things,
                        (<del>&amp;</del> tho I would not be supposed to imply that it necessarily excludes them) &#8211; &amp; of this style I should guess
                    that <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> is the master.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> may be applied to, &amp; I think with success. As for Davy, he <hi rend="ital">is </hi>
          <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry"> Humphrey Davy </ref>
          <hi rend="ital"> Esq<hi rend="sup">r </hi>
          </hi>
          <del> &amp;</del> Mr Professor Davy, &#8211; &amp; may far better be applied to thro the great than by one who knew him before the world
                    knew him, &amp; who has kept himself uncontaminate from the world. I know not whether the prize which he received from Bonaparte
                    sticks to his fingers or no &#8211; I would sooner have cut mine off than have accepted it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Davy
                        travelled to Paris in 1806 to accept at the Institut de France a prize offered by the Emperor Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821),
                        in recognition of his scientific discoveries.</note> It is likely to cooperate with <del>his</del> some of his Royal Institute
                    associates<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Since 1801 Davy had been Director of the Laboratory at the Royal Institution of
                        Great Britain. His associates there included the President, George Finch, 8th Earl of Winchilsea (1752&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in making him cry out for
                    peace &#8211; yet <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy&#8217;s</ref> heart is sound at the core, &amp; his <del>all- xxx</del>
                    all-grasping, all-commanding genius must have redeemed him. The best channel to him is thro Sotheby,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s acquaintance.</note> &#8211; a man on whom you may
                    calculate. &#8211; I am particularly anxious that my hint about <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> should be adopted. One
                    article from him about the Poor will be worth its weight in gold.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Poole did not
                        write for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note>
          <del>As for</del> I hope Malthus<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rev. Thomas Robert Malthus (1766&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Southey had reviewed <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future
                            Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), in
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292&#8211;301.</note> will not infect the review, &#8211; it would wither my hand if
                    the thought came across me that any truths of mine could lend their sanction to his blasphemies. By that mans <hi rend="ital">first</hi> book moral restraint was pronounced impracticable, by his <hi rend="ital">second</hi> it is relied upon as the
                    remedy for the poor rates, which are to be abolished to prevent the poor from marrying, &amp; moral restraint &amp; the Parson are
                    to render them contented in celibacy. <del>xxx</del> His main principle is that God makes men &amp; women faster than he can feed
                    them, &#8211; &amp; he calls upon government to stop the breed. As if we did not at this moment want men for our battles! <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> name should stand in the place of his, &#8211; Rickman has ten fold his knowledge,
                    ten-thousand fold his ability. There is no man living equal to Rickman upon the subject of political economy. <del>His</del> He
                    too is a crusader <del>in</del> to this war, Malthus will <del>probably</del> prove a peace-monger.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would attract much notice &amp; carry with it much recommendation if an account of the Welsh Archaiology could
                    be procured. <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> may be asked for it, <del>tho</del> I am afraid he is too busy.
                    <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref> alas is one of <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcotes</ref> four &amp; twenty Elder. &amp; Bard
                        Williams<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg) (1747&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), scholar and
                        forger of Welsh literature, reviver of bardism.</note> is God knows where, &amp; nothing is to be got out of him except by
                    word of mouth. There is however the chance of Turner. There is Davies of Olveston the author of the Celtic Researches.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin,
                            Traditions and Language of the Ancient Britons</title> (1804).</note> there is <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> Welshman &#8211; Peter Roberts.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1760&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), a Welsh
                        cleric and author of <title>A Sketch of the Early history of the Cymry (700 BC&#8211;AD 500)</title> (1803).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Farewell. I finish my Annualizing<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">That is, reviewing for the
                        <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> in a few days &amp; shall then set about the Missions</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-24">Thursday night Nov. 24. 1808.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Let not <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> suppose me a troublesome man to deal with,
                        pertinacious about trifles, or standing upon punctilios of authorship. No Grosvenor I am a quiet, patient, easy-going hack of
                        the mule breed, &#8211; regular as clock work in my pace, sure footed, bearing the burthen which is laid on me, &amp; only obstinate
                        in chusing my own path. If Gifford could see me by this fire side where like Nicodemus one candle suffices me in a large
                            room,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rembrandt van Rijn (1606&#8211;1669) etched a picture of Jesus and Nicodemus, the
                            Pharisee who, in John&#8217;s gospel (3.1&#8211;21) visited Jesus by night. In the etching, the figures are illuminated only by one
                            candle.</note> &#8211; he would see a man in a coat &#8216;still more thread bare than his&#8217; when he wrote his <del>ode</del>
                        imitation, working hard &amp; getting little, &#8211; a bare bare maintenance &amp; hardly that, &#8211; <del>yet</del> writing poems
                        &amp; history for posterity with his whole heart &amp; soul, &#8211; &amp; &lt;having&gt; more heart &amp; soul <del>left</del> to
                        spare for inferior occupations, than go to the composition of five hundred ordinary men, or five thousand Scotchmen, &#8211; one
                        daily progressive in learning, &#8211; not so learned as he is poor, not so poor as proud, not so proud as happy. By the Lord
                        Grosvenor there is not a lighter-hearted nor a happier man upon the face of <del>xxx</del> this wide world.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Your godson</ref> thinks that I have nothing to do but to play with him, &#8211; &amp;
                        anybody who saw what reason he has for his opinion would be disposed to agree with him. I wish you could see my beautiful
                        boy!</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>