<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1471</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2593</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        283&#8211;287..  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 73&#8211;76.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1471" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1471" type="letter">
        <head>1471. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1808-06-22">22 June 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        283&#8211;287.<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 73&#8211;76.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-06-22">Wednesday June 22. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Senhora,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I had leisure to enter into a new correspondence I would thank Mr Walhouse for his curious paper by letter,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward John Walhouse (1791&#8211;1862), <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward
                            Littleton&#8217;s</ref> nephew and heir. He assumed the name of Littleton on Sir Edward&#8217;s death in 1812, and became MP for
                        Stafford. The &#8216;paper&#8217; has not been traced.</note> &#8211; but you know how very much I am employed, &amp; that it is not possible
                    for me to write with tolerable regularity to the friends already on my list. Almost every letter that reaches me brings with it a
                    complaint, &amp; every one which goes from me has occasion to begin with an apology. Do you say this for me, &amp; excuse me in
                    the handsomest manner you can. Part of the paper I had seen in a Birmingham Newspaper, &amp; easily guessed who was its author. It
                    is very odd &amp; ingenious, &#8211; tho it is not to be supposed that I am who am both Whig &amp; Dissenter can assent to its
                    philosophy. Mr Walhouse speaks in parables; &#8211; seeing things vividly &amp; combining them rapidly, he expresses himself as if the
                    type &amp; the thing typified were the same: thus because those principles which would be beneficial to our body politic may be
                    likened to the constituent parts of Lemington Water,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mineral water from Leamington
                        Spa.</note> he says Lemington water will save the King; &#8211; not that he can possibly mean that the King &amp; the body politic
                    are one, &#8211; or that good political principles are the same things as carbonate of iron &amp;c &#8211; or even that Lemington water,
                    drastic as it may be, can purge away political corruption, or natural stupidity. There are some persons whose ideas are so vivid
                    as to produce all the effect of actual impressions, &amp; to be mistaken for such. You have heard me relate a remarkable instance
                    in my own case, before I went last to Lisbon. The phantoms produced by laudanum are of this description. When the body is weak,
                    &amp; the patient makes the mistake he is what is called light-headed, &amp; it is beyond a doubt in this state of mind that so
                    many ghosts have been seen, &#8211; which did really exist in the sight of the beholder, &#8211; &amp; had no other existence. These peoples
                    perception differs from that of others in its excessive vividness, &#8211; so if I am not mistaken, do the reasoning powers of Mr
                    Walhouse. He passes so rapidly from his premises to his conclusions, that you know not by what process he has got there. If I am
                    in the top of one tree, &amp; want to get to another, I must descend the first &amp; then climb the second, &#8211; but he jumps from
                    one to the other like a squirrel, &amp; they who are not like squirrels in their understanding cannot follow him. &#8211; It is plain
                    that he is a very ingenious man, &amp; I have no doubt a very interesting one. If his inclination should ever lead him to the
                    lakes, I shall be glad to show him all the attention in my power, &amp; to talk with him upon matters on which I have no time to
                    write. As he is an amateur of waters, you may tell him that there is some of the finest &amp; purest in the world at poor old
                    Peter Crosthwaites<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey adds an asterisk by the name and then a note at the bottom of
                        the page: &#8216;he was buried last week&#8217;. Peter Crosthwaite (1735&#8211;1808), a <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
                        inventor, mapmaker and showman, who established a museum there in 1780.</note> pump. &amp; that in Borrowdale there is a well
                    which I dare be sworn will out-stink Lemington Water, let Lemington water stink as it will.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have lost <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. He was unexpectedly summoned by an appointment to the
                    Dreadnought, &#8211; Admiral Sotheby&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was a 98-gun second
                        rate ship of the line launched in 1801. She had fought at Trafalgar (1805) and was now under the command of Rear Admiral
                        Thomas Sotheby (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s
                        acquaintance.</note> ship, &amp; set off on Sunday to join her. In all probability he past thro <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Penkridge</ref> yesterday, &amp; certes cast a wistful eye towards <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley</ref>, cursing his evil fortune that would not let him halt there. But that
                    Admiral-Ty is an Admiral whose orders must be immediately obeyed. I suppose Senhora that absolute peremptoriness is because of the
                        <hi rend="ital">Ty</hi>-ship &#8211; for Time &amp; Tide &amp; that Admiral-Ty will wait for no man &#8211; Honour &amp; praise be to the
                    first wise man that ventured to talk nonsense.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> More books. <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> has sent me Sir Wm Jones&#8217;s works<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Listed in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library thus: Sir William Jones (1746&#8211;1794;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Works, with his Life by Lord Teignmouth, portrait, 13 vol. Presentation Copy, calf extra,
                            marbled leaves, from J. Neville White, with an extract from Landor in the autograph of the Poet Laureate</title>
                        (1799&#8211;1806).</note> in some of the best binding I have ever seen. They are the handsomest volumes in my whole library, &amp;
                    thirteen of them. I have told him that if he were rich enough to give me books by the cart load I should gladly accept them, &#8211; but
                    that it gives some little pain, as well as pleasure, &#8211; to receive so costly a present from one who can have so little to
                        spare.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this letter, see Southey to Neville White, 20 June 1808, Letter
                        1470.</note> So it is that there always seems the greatest disposition to be generous when there are the least means: it is an
                    old observation that street beggars receive more alms from servant-maids than from any other class. You will admire these books
                    very much, &#8211; they are in excellent taste; &#8211; &amp; it is not <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville&#8217;s</ref> fault that the
                    inside is not as perfect as the out. He followed public opinion in supposing Sir Wm Jones a very great man: &#8211; I look upon him as
                    one of the show[MS obscured]<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Word partially covered by seal. Warter supplies
                        &#8216;books&#8217;.</note> of fashion. However, there is something there which I wanted &amp; the magnifico bookcase is greatly increased
                    in ricosity.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">From the Portuguese, meaning &#8216;costly&#8217;, &#8216;well-off in appearance&#8217;.</note> Great
                    is the grandeur Senhora which you have to behold.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">H. Senhouse</ref> &amp; his wife<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Senhouse had married Elizabeth Frances Greaves (b. 1779) in 1803.</note> called here this morning on their return at last to
                    Cumberland &#8211; I was heartily glad to see them. &#8211; farewell &#8211; I have plenty of love &amp; remembrances to send you, &#8211; things that
                    travel without paying postage, &#8211; even without a frank.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I wish you would write me the particulars of your story about the mad-dogs &amp; the geese. I shall not write
                        now to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir E. L.</ref> because a second letter of thanks would be too formal,
                        &amp; somewhat obtrusive, when I have the opportunity of thanking him through you. My Cid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> I suppose will be published in
                        six or seven weeks, &#8211; &amp; than I shall order a copy to be sent him, &amp; will take the occasion of returning him thanks
                        myself, when I wrote to apprise him of it.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>