<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1517</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2639</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1517" type="letter">
        <head>1517. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-10-09">9&#8211;11 October
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <date when="1808-10-09">Sunday. Oct. 9. 1808</date>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your M.S. will go by tomorrows carrier, &#8211; Pimentel<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manoel Pimentel
                        (1650&#8211;1719), whose navigational aid was translated and updated by Hill as <title>The Brazil Pilot; or, a Description of the
                            Coast of Brazil, Translated from the Portuguese of Manoel Pimentel &#8230; to which are added, Charts, of some of its most
                            Considerable Ports</title> (1809). This was no. 2331 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> came with it,
                    &amp; also the extracts from Falkner.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose
                        papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774). Southey
                        cites him in volume 1 of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810), pp. 320 and 630.</note> His account of the Jacare is
                    curious, &amp; I shall make mention of it in its place. I shall also say something of the Lago de Xarayes from one of your MSS.
                    The descriptions of the Iguassu falls you can insert. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> shall send back the
                    papers here for revision, &amp; I will take especial care to <del>xxxx all</del> &lt;correct every&gt; ambiguity of expression.
                    Carelessly it has most certainly not been written, &#8211; as the sight of the first copy would convince you. The pamphlet, intitled
                    OBreasil, of which mention is made in one of the notes, I have lately discovered at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> in this neighbourhood, &#8211; &amp; it turns out to be altogether worthless, &#8211; a feeble &amp; wretched fiction,
                    introductory to a clumsy satire upon the Welsh.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See volume 1 of <title>The History of
                            Brazil</title> (1810), p.22, where Southey cites the pamphlet concerning an imaginary island, Richard Head (c.1637&#8211;1686?),
                            <title>O Brazile, or the Inchanted Island, Being a Perfect Relation of the Late Discovery of an Island on the North of
                            Ireland</title> (1674).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By the time you should have received the Cid, &amp; the new edition of my Letters, purged of much base matter,
                    &amp; amplified with pertinent historical &amp; antiquarian information.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) and the expanded edition of his <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence
                            in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797, 1798) published in 2 volumes as <title>Letters Written During a Journey in Spain, and
                            a Short Residence in Portugal</title> (1808).</note> But they were in too much haste for the publication to allow time for
                    sending the proofs here, &amp; I anticipate many provoking errors of the press. That life of D Luisa de Carvajal, which is now
                    added, is the most curious piece of Catholick biography that has yet fallen in my way.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                            <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, I, pp. 259&#8211;302, Southey included a
                            <title>Life of Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title>, taken from <title>Vida y Virtudes de la Venerable Virgen Do&#241;a
                            Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza, su Jornada a Inglaterra y Sucessos&#8217; en aquel Reyno. Por el Licenciado Luis Mu&#241;oz</title>
                        (1632).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of the books to be still sought after at Lisbon the Life of R. Almeyda is by far the most important &#8211; bad as it
                    must needs be coming from such a biographer: &#8211; but it was written <del>pre</del> before his Life of Anchieta &amp; is referred to
                    in that later work for information relating to the savages, &amp; it must unavoidably contain some facts respecting that
                    particular period of Brazilian history for which there is the greatest scarcity of <del>xx</del> documents.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos (1596&#8211;1671), <title>Vida do Padre Joam d&#8217;Almeida da Companhia de Jesu, na
                            Provincia do Brazil</title> (1658); <title>Vida do Vener. Padre Joseph de Anchieta, &#8230; Taumaturgo do Novo Mundo, na
                            Provincia do Brasil</title> (1672).</note> I find these works mentioned in the Mem. para e Hist. de S. Vincente,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fr. Gaspar da Madre de Deos (1715&#8211;1800), <title>Mem&#243;rias para a Hist&#243;ria da Capitania de
                            S&#227;o Vicente</title> (1797).</note> &#8211; Anno Historico de P. M. Francisco de Santa Maria,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> P. M. Francisco de Santa Maria (dates untraced), <title>Anno historico, Diario portuguez, noticia abreviada de
                            pessoas grandes, e cousas notaveis de Portugal</title> (1744).</note> &#8211; Chron. da Provincia d S. Antonio do Brazil. by P.
                        Jaboata&#333;,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de Santa Maria Jaboatao (1695&#8211;1763/1765), <title>Novo Orbe Serafico
                            Brazilico ou Chronica dos Frades Minores da Provincia do Brazil</title> (1761).</note> a name uncouth enough to look as if
                    it were Tupinamban.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, as if Jaboatao was a name derived from Indian heritage, from
                        the Tupinamb&#225; people of Brazil.</note> &#8211; Hist. da Prov. de S Cruz for Pedro de Magalhaens Guandavo.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Magalh&#227;es Gandavo (1540-c. 1580), <title>Hist&#243;ria da Prov&#237;ncia Santa Cruz</title> (1576), the first
                        historical survey of Brazil to be published by the Potuguese.</note> &#8211; Santuario Mariano do P. Fr. Agostinho de Santa
                        Maria<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Agostinho de Santa Maria (1642&#8211;1728), <title>Santuario Mariano e Historia das
                            Imagens milagrosas de nossa Senhora e das milagrosamente apparecidas</title> (1707&#8211;1723), no. 3222 in the sale catalogue
                        of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; this is a work of considerable extent it seems. None of these books did I ever see mentioned
                    before, except that of P. de Magalhaens.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are a few miscellaneous books which will be procured without difficulty &#8211; Obras do Antonio Pinheiro<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Pinheiro (fl. 1541&#8211;1583), Bishop of Miranda and Leiria. His writings were
                        published in 1785 as<title> Colleccao das obras portuguesas do sabio Bispo de Miranda c de Leiria</title>.</note> &#8211; Vida do
                        <del>xx R</del> Bartolomieu dos Martires by Fr. Luis de Sousas<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel de Sousa
                        Coutinho (1555&#8211;1632), <title>Vida de D. Fr. Bertolameu dos Martyres da Ordem dos Pregadores, arcebispo, &amp; senhor de
                            Braga</title> (1619).</note> &#8211; &amp; the Sermons &amp; whatever other works may exist of Fr. Antonio das Chagas<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio da Fonseca Soares (1631&#8211;1682), a soldier who became a Franciscan friar under the
                        name Antonio das Chagas. Southey later acquired a seven volume edition of his <title>Obras</title> of 1763, no. 3257 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> except his unpublished poem of Filis &#8211; of which I have a beautiful
                        manuscript,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3837 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was the quarto
                        manuscript Soares/Chagas, <title>La Filis Obra Heroica y Tragica</title>.</note> &#8211; &amp; his life by Manoel Godinho which I
                    also possess.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3474 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was Manuel Godinho
                        (1630&#8211;1712), <title>Vida do Ven. Padre Fr. Antonio das Chagas</title> (1762).</note> This was a very remarkable man, &#8211; you
                    will see a sketch of his history in the first packet of my Letters which <del>xxx</del> reaches you, &amp; I am very curious to
                    see <del>x</del> what the eloquence was which produced such <del>remarkable</del> &lt;extraordinary&gt; effects upon his
                    auditors.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of scarcer books there is the Chronica do Inf. Santo De Henrique por Jeronymo Lopez.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jer&#243;nimo L&#243;pez (16th century), <title>Cr&#243;nica do infante Santo Don Henrique</title> (1529).</note> 1527. &amp;
                    the Comedias de Gil Vincente.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese playwright Gil Vicente (c.1465 &#8211; c. 1536)
                        wrote many comedies and farces including <title>Auto da &#205;ndia</title> (1509) and <title>Farsa de In&#234;s Pereira</title> (1523).
                        Their rarity in print was caused by their suppression by the Inquisition.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are so many which I <hi rend="ital">wish</hi> from Spain that it is tantalizing to think of them &#8211; what I <hi rend="ital">want</hi> most particularly is the Orinoco Ilustrado of Gumilla<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jose
                        Gumilla (1686&#8211;1750), <title>El Orinoco ilustrado y defendido. Historia Natural, Civil, &amp; Geografica de este gran rio y de
                            sus caudalosas vertientes</title> (1791), no. 3488 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> the Chronica del Rey
                    D Enrique 4.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry IV (1425&#8211;1474), King of the Crown of Castile, nicknamed the Impotent
                        (ruled 1454&#8211;1474). The chronicle of his reign was written by Diego Enriquez del Castillo (1443&#8211;1503).</note> &amp; all the
                    particular Chronicles anterior to that of Alonso II,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ruy de Pina, <title>Chronica de D.
                            Sancho I, D. Afonso II, D. Sancho II, D. Afonso III, D. Diniz, D. Afonso IV</title> (1726&#8211;1728). King Afonso II of
                        Portugal (1185&#8211;1223), ruled from 1212.</note> of which I have two copies.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        owned a series of chronicles bound as a set: no. 3258 of the sale catalogue of his library was <title>Chronica de D. Alfonso
                            et onceno de este nombre de los Reyes que Reynaron en Castilla y Leon, por Fr. Cerd&#225; y Rico</title>, vol. 1, uncut,
                        Madrid, 1787 &#8211; <title>Chronica de San Luis, Rey de Francia, nieto del Rey D. Alonso et VIII, por Senor de Jonville traducida
                            por J. Ledel</title>, uncut, ib. 1794 &#8211;<title> Coronicas de los Reyes de Castilla Don Pedro, Enrique II &amp; III, Juau I,
                            e de D. Alvaro de Luna, par D. Pedro Lapez de Ayala, &amp;c.</title> portrait, 5 vol. half bound together 7 vol.</note> O
                    for the Catalan Historians! especially the histories written by K Jayme el Conquistador, &amp; K Pedro.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3591 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was <title>Historia de la Vida de Don Jayme de Aragon,
                            primero deste Nombre Ilamado el conquistador</title>, portrait, fine copy, in calf Valencia (1584). No. 3194 was
                            <title>Chronica del Rey D. Pedro I</title>, por J. Pereira Bayam (1735).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Most likely Waddings <del>Gr</del> great work would be forthcoming from some of the Convent libraries. Wadding (not
                    Waddington) is the name, &#8211; the title I do not know &#8211; probably Historia Seraphica &#8211; of Franciscana.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luke Wadding (1588&#8211;1657; <title>DNB</title>), an Irish Catholic historian educated in Portugal. Wadding&#8217;s
                        Latin verses and epigrams were published by Francisco de Susa in his <title>Sanctorale Seraphicum</title> (1623). His magnum
                        opus was <title>Annales Minorum</title>, a history of the Franciscan order from 1208 to 1540, in eight folio volumes
                        (1625&#8211;1654).</note> The book which I covet &amp; desire above all others is the great Acta Sanctorum.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 152 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (Antwerp and Brussels,
                        1643&#8211;1794).</note> &#8211; &amp; this would be likely enough to turn up now. I would joyfully give five and twenty guineas for
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a <hi rend="ital">chart</hi> of Maranham in Barl&#339;us<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caspar
                        Barlaeus (1584&#8211;1648), <title>Rerum per octennium in Brasilia et alibi nuper gestarum sub praefectura</title> (1647), a work
                        containing many maps and charts, including this of the Maranham river. Southey&#8217;s library, on his death, contained an edition
                        of 1660.</note> but it has no soundings marked &amp; I should not think it worth copying. No doubt the book is in the Museum
                    &amp; there Arrowsmith<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of
                        Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map
                            Exhibiting All the New Discoveries in the Interior Parts of North America</title> (1795 rev. 1801, 1802, 1804),
                            <title>Chart of the South Pacific</title> (1798), <title>A New Map of Africa</title> (1802).</note> may examine it &amp;
                    judge for himself. As for my map &#8211; would it not be best to have the whole of S. America, &#8211; Brazil &amp; Paraguay as full as the
                    size will admit, &#8211; &amp; only the <del>xxx</del> outline of the rest. Vespuccis earlier voyage was with Ojeda<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alonso de Ojeda (c. 1466&#8211;1515), on whose Caribbean voyage of 1499 Vespucci sailed.</note> &amp;
                    had nothing to do with Brazil.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amerigo Vespucci (1451&#8211;1512), explorer who made three or
                        four voyages to the east coast of South America at the start of the sixteenth century; that which he made with Ojeda sighted the
                        coast of Venezuela.</note> That book of Bandinis<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Angelo Maria Bandini (1726&#8211;1803),
                            <title>Vita e Lettere di Amerigo Vespucci</title> (1745).</note> about him is a bad one, &amp; Lady Hollands MS.
                        eulogy<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> This eulogy, which <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady
                            Holland</ref> had introduced to Southey, denying that Columbus discovered America and promoting the navigational and
                        astronomical achievements of Vespucci (1451&#8211;1512), aroused great controversy. It was given by Florentine librarian Father
                        Stanislaus Canovai (1740&#8211;1811) and published as <title>Elogio d&#8217;Amerigo Vespucci che ha riportato il premio della nobile
                            Accademia Etrusca di Cortona nel d&#236; 15. Ottobre dell&#8217;anno 1788. Con una dissertazione giustificativa di questo celebre
                            navigator</title> (1788).</note> is worse. Did I tell you that these Florentines attempt to show that he discovered the
                    [MS obscured] unless I am greatly mistaken, the letter on which this discovery rests, has been forged by them for the purpose &#8211;
                    But you shall see my critical catalogue before it is printed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I could have wished that the history of the Mother country had appeared before that of Brazil, because it is full
                    of beautiful circumstances, &amp; is as rich in all that can interest common readers, as that of Brazil is deficient. You will I
                    think be pleased to see in the succeeding chapters the quantity of information collected, concerning the native tribes, &amp; the
                        <del>saturation</del> state [MS torn] <del>xxxxx xxx xxxxxx xxxxxxxxxxxx xxxxx xxx xxxxxxxx</del> [MS torn] The Licencas to
                    Pimentel are dated 1709. [MS torn]</p>
        <p>assigned him to Joan 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> time.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> John V the Magnanimous (1689&#8211;1750),
                        king of Portugal.</note>
        </p>
        <p>I entirely agree with you in preferring the Portugueze to the Castillian dialect. Your neighbour the Desembargador told me that a
                    great proportion of the words were derived from the Basque, &#8211; far more he said than was generally supposed. Etymology is the key
                    to history, &amp; yet no branch of knowledge, not even theology has been more absurdly handled. The gradual absorption of Moorish
                    words &amp; sounds into the Castillian may be traced easily enough, &#8211; but I do not understand <del>xxx</del> how a difference
                    should have arisen in such common &amp; every day words as <hi rend="ital">feca</hi>, <hi rend="ital">garfo</hi> &#8211; <hi rend="ital">rapaz</hi>, &amp; others such, which you will readily call to mind. It would be of some use to hunt out the origin of these
                    words if it could be done. The definite article in Portugueze is Greek, &#8211; in Castilian, Arabick &#8211; the indefinite in both Latin. I
                    wish I had the Origenes de las lingua Castellana &#8211; by Mayans y. Siscar<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gregorio May&#225;ns y
                        Siscar (1699&#8211;1781), <title>Or&#237;genes de la lengua espa&#241;ola</title> (1737).</note> &#8211; It would be difficult to say which dialect
                    is the richest in works of real value, &#8211; this I am sure of &#8211; that either of them outdoes the Italian &amp; French put together. In
                    Chronicles, which are the best of all books when they are good, the Portugueze have the advantage. Beautiful as the Chronica del
                        Cid<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043&#8211;1099), <title>Chronica de la
                            Famoso Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593) was about to be published.</note> is (&amp; in parts, nothing can
                    be finer) it is yet on the whole exceeded by the greater work of Fernan Lopes.<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fernao
                        Lopes (c. 1385&#8211;after 1459), chronicler of Portugal.</note> When my whole history is published I think I could with great
                    pleasure translate his three Chronicles, the two printed<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Cr&#243;nica del-rei D. Pedro</title> (1735); <title>Chronica del Rey D. Ioam I de Boa Memoria, e dos Reys de Portugal o
                            Decimo, Primeira Parte, em Que se contem A Defensam do Reyno at&#233; ser eleito Rey &amp; Segunda Parte, em que se continuam
                            as guerras com Castella, desde o Principio de seu reinado ate as pazes</title> (1644).</note> &amp; the ms. one.<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors"> The manuscript &#8216;Cronica del Rei Dom Fernando o Noveno Rei de Portugal&#8217;, which was listed
                        as no. 3829 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library after his death.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
          <date when="1808-10-11">Tuesday Oct. 11.</date>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>