<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1226</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2348</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 94.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                        53&#8211;55 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1226" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1226" type="letter">
        <head>1226. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1806-10-13">13 October
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 13 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1806<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 94<lb />Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                        53&#8211;55 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my child</ref> proves to be of the more
                    worthy gender, &#8211; he is as stout-limbed &amp; as strong-voiced as I could wish him. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> going on excellently well. The boy was born a quarter after six in the morning, the alarm having been given at
                    three; his name is <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I would do a good deal to please poor <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref> (&#8211; indeed it is doing a
                    good deal to let him inflict an argument upon me &#8211;) but to write an epilogue is doing too much for any body.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tobin had asked Southey to write an epilogue, probably to <title>The Curfew: a Play</title>
                        (1807), the posthumously-published work of Tobin&#8217;s brother John Tobin (1770&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>), a London solicitor and
                        playwright whose comedy <title>The Honey Moon</title> had been a success in 1805; see Southey to John Tobin, 22 September
                        1806, Letter 1218.</note> Indeed were I ever so well disposed to misemploy him; paper &amp; rhymes, it would be as much out of
                    my reach as the moon is, &amp; I bless my stars for the incapacity, &#8211; believing that a man who can do such things well cannot do
                    anything better. I am also thoroughly busy. Summer is my holyday season, in which I lay in a store of exercise to serve me for the
                    winter, &amp; leave myself as it were lying fallow to the influencies of heaven. I am now very hard at Palmerin,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published an English translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco
                            Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> &#8211; so troublesome a business that a look before the leap would have prevented
                    the leap altogether. I expected it would only be needful to alter the Propria quae maribus<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        A schooltext Latin phrase: &#8216;things which are deemed appropriate to males&#8217;.</note> to their original orthography, &amp; restore
                    the costume when the old translators had omitted it as being to them foreign or obsolete; &#8211; but they have so mangled, mutilated
                    &amp; massacred the &lt;manners&gt; so vulgarized impoverished &amp; embeggared the <del>story</del> &lt;language&gt;, so lopt
                    cropt &amp; <del>xxxxxxx</del> dockt <del>all</del> the ornaments, &amp; so castrated the virility of the style &#8211; that I was fair
                    to set my shoulder stiffly to the wheel, &amp; retranslate about the one half. As this will not produce me one penny more than if
                    I had reprinted it with all its imperfections on its head, the good conscience with which it is done reconciles me to
                        <del>xxxx</del> the loss of time &#8211; &amp; I have moreover such a true love of romance that the labour is not irksome. the
                    labour of hand it is. To correct a sheet, 16 pages of the square sized black letter &#8211; is a days work, that is from breakfast till
                    dinner, allowing an hours walk, &amp; from tea till supper. &amp; the whole is about sixty sheets.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly Espriella<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> is regulated by the Printer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who would go on to establish the
                        publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with his son William Francis (1817&#8211;1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> who seems
                    as little disposed to hurry me as I am to hurry him. he has half a sheet yet to finish the first volume, &amp; copy for three
                    sheets more. In a few days I shall have the start in Palmerin sufficiently to put three more in readiness for him, having little
                    more than to transcribe them. Indeed there is not above half a volume more to write.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thirdly the reviewing is come round of which in the shape of Missionaries, Catholick Miracles, Bible &amp;
                    Religious Societies &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#MooreThomas">Little
                        Moore</ref> (not forgetting the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> )<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to Cochin China, in the Years 1792, and 1793: Containing a General View of the
                            Productions, and Political Importance of this Kingdom; and also of such European Settlements as were Visited on the
                            Voyage, with Sketches of the Manners, Character, and Condition of their Inhabitants</title> (1806), 2&#8211;16; James Burney,
                            <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title>
                        (Vol. 2; 1806), 16&#8211;30; James Stanier Clarke (1765?&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of
                            Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 2; 1806), 71&#8211;72; <title>Report of the British and Foreign Bible Society</title> (1805), 155&#8211;160;
                        Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A New and Appropriate System of Education for the Labouring
                            People</title> (1806), 278&#8211;282; John Wooll (bap. 1767&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of the late
                            Revd. Joseph Warton, Master of St. Mary Winton College; Prebendary of Winchester Cathedral; and Rector of the Parishes of
                            Wickham and Upham, Hants: to which are added, a Selection from his Works; and a Literary Correspondence Between Eminent
                            Persons, Reserved by him for Publication</title> (1806), 298&#8211;305; Lucy Hutchinson (<title>n&#233;e</title> Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title>
                        (1806), 361&#8211;378; James Grant Raymond (1771&#8211;1817), <title>The Life of Thomas Dermody</title> (1806), 383&#8211;397; Henry Richard
                        Fox, 3rd Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Life and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1806), 397&#8211;411;
                        Richard Duppa, <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806),
                        411&#8211;425; George Chalmers, (bap. 1742&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Sir David Lyndsay</title>
                        (1806), 482&#8211;494; Thomas Moore (1779&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epistles, Odes and Other Poems</title> (1806), 498&#8211;499;
                        [Society of Friends of Pennsylvania], <title>Accounts of Two Attempts Towards the Civilization of Some Indian Natives</title>
                        (1806), 589&#8211;593; Thomas Clarkson, <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline,
                            Peculiar Customs, Religious Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title>
                        (1806), 594&#8211;607; Thomas Jarrold (1770&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological and
                            Political; in Answer to Mr. Malthus&#8217;s &#8216;Essay on the Principle of Population&#8217;</title> (1806), 607&#8211;615.</note> I have more
                    to do than I at first designed, yet not more than will make a reasonable item on the right side of the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">King of Persias</ref> books.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Fourthly I have done half the Cid,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation <title>The
                            Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> &amp; wherever I seem sufficiently ahead of other employment to
                    lie to for awhile &#8211; this is what I go to.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Lastly for the Athen&#230;um alias Fool&#230;um<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The short-lived <title>Athen&#230;um, A
                            Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (1807&#8211;1809), which was owned by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> and edited by <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John
                        Aikin</ref>.</note> &#8211; for I abominate such titles I am making some preparations, meaning among other things to print there
                    certain collections of unemployed notes &amp; memoranda under the title of Omniana, for the sake of being paid for them now, &amp;
                    meaning them to use them hereafter as required,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey gathered many of the miscellaneous
                        short pieces that he contributed to the <title>Athenaeum</title> in the book he compiled with Coleridge in 1812,
                            <title>Omniana: or Horae Otiosiores</title>.</note> &amp; taking care to secure them to myself by omitting the
                    references.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By Gods blessing I shall have done all this by the end of the winter, &amp; come to town early in spring, to
                    inspect certain books for the Cid at the Museum &amp; at Holland House &#8211; &amp; to proceed to Lisbon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I rejoice to hear of <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R&#8217;s</ref> recovery.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Susannah Rickman had suffered a miscarriage in May and was subsequently unwell; see Southey
                        to Mary Barker, 26 May 1806, Letter 1187.</note> pray you remember me to her &#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-10-13">Monday October 13. 1806</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>