<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1724</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2846</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New
                        York Public Library, In 74 A. L. S. to various correspondents. .  Previously  published: M. Betham-Edwards, &#8216;Letters of
                        Coleridge, Southey and Lamb to Matilda Betham&#8217;, Fraser&#8217;s Magazine, ns 18 (July 1878), 73&#8211;84. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1724" type="letter">
        <head>1724. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Mary Matilda Betham</ref>], <date when="1809-12-27">27 December
                    1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [MS torn]hirty [MS illegible]/ [MS torn]m Cavendish St<hi rend="sup">t</hi>/ London [in another hand]<lb />Stamped: WREXHAM<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New
                        York Public Library, In 74 A. L. S. to various correspondents. <lb />Previously published: M. Betham-Edwards, &#8216;Letters of
                        Coleridge, Southey and Lamb to Matilda Betham&#8217;, <title>Fraser&#8217;s Magazine</title>, ns 18 (July 1878), 73&#8211;84. </note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Pictures<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Betham visited Keswick in September and October 1809 and
                        painted portraits of Southey, <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah
                            Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref> and <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref>; see Southey
                        to Charles Danvers, 14 October 1809, Letter 1694. The frames for these had been bought for Southey by Bedford, see Southey to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter 1669) and 4 September 1809 (Letter 1675).</note> arrived this day &lt;having
                    come&gt; by the Mail Coach &#8211; <del>xx xxxx xxxxx xxxxxx xx xxxx xxx xxx</del>, &#8211; &amp; as was to be expected the large glass broken
                    into fifty pieces. All the others by good fortune have escaped. It is well for the frame-maker that I am not Buonaparte, &#8211; as I
                    should think cutting his ears off not too severe a punishment for the absurdity of sending such things by such a conveyance, when
                    the waggon would have brought them with perfect safety, at one fourth of the cost. Unquestionably the loss ought to fall upon him,
                    &amp; if <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has not paid him, I shall remonstrate upon the subject, &#8211;
                    tho I am a bad hand at such disputes myself, &amp; in conscience one cannot expect a friend to dispute for one. The worst of the
                    business is the great inconvenience it occasions, &#8211; for how is another glass to be sent, when the frame is here? &#8211; however I must
                    make enquiry as to the possibility of getting one of that <del>xxx</del> size <del>here</del>, &lt;upon the spot&gt; &amp;
                    endeavour to do the enamelling myself. But it is as vexatious as I ever permit a thing of no greater moment to be, because it has
                    been occasioned by a piece of folly not to have been calculated upon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">Dyers</ref> picture is a most happy likeness. He does me wrong if he supposes that I do not
                    set great value upon it, for I have a great regard for him, &amp; so much respect for his better part, that I never lose sight of
                    it even when his oddities &amp; weaknesses provoke a smile. It is melancholy to <del>think</del> see so many of the ingredients
                    both of genius &amp; happiness existing in that mans mind, &amp; spoilt in the mixing, &#8211; to think how trifling an alteration in
                    his character would have made him as useful as he is good, &amp; as happy as useful. &#8211; The frames look well, but by no means so
                    well as they would have done if the gilding had been broader. It was a bitter disappointment not to find <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moons</ref>  picture among them, &#8211; because we remembered it as the
                    happiest likeness, &#8211; the better way of sending it will be in a frank, sufficiently enveloped. Dyer will convey it to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>, &amp; then no matter what may be the weight. It is hardly possible that he
                    should lose a second charge of the same kind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Kehama has been finished this month,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title>, published in 1810.</note> is half transcribed, gone to the printers, &amp; I expect the first proof in the
                    course of the week. Early in the spring I hope to send it to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is written hastily, &#8211; hereby to announce the arrival of the box &#8211; alas that it should not be the safe arrival!
                    &#8211; I must not forget thanks from below stairs for the feathers. The children often talk of you, &#8211; when will she come again &#8211; is the
                    constant question. &#8211; I shall be likely to see you in the course of next year. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My
                        Uncle</ref>  has the living of <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>  given him, &amp;
                    will reside there. He gives up for it some Herefordshire preferment, &amp; I do not think the exchange in any other degree
                    advantageous, than that his &lt;new&gt; residence will be more conveniently situated for my visits than his old one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent nobody to give you any other trouble than that of exhibiting the family groups. Nor have I heard who has
                    taken the pains of <del>xxxx</del> going to see them &#8211; except <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> (<ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henrys</ref> brother) &#8211; He thought the last years picture of myself <del>a mor</del> a better likeness than this.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> When visiting London in March 1808, Southey had sat to Betham for a portrait; see Southey to Mary Matilda
                        Betham, [late March 1808], Letter 1435.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> very truly yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-12-27">Dec. 27. 1809.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I am afraid my letter did not reach John Dolignon,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Dolignon
                            (1774&#8211;1856), son of <ref target="people.html#DoliognonLouisa">Louisa Dolignon</ref>. He was a clergyman, later Rector of
                            Wimbish in Essex 1816&#8211;1838 and Hilborough in Norfolk 1838&#8211;1856. Southey regularly visited Mrs Dolignon&#8217;s house when he was
                            at school at Westminster and was very close to her son, John, who was at Charterhouse and then Trinity College, Cambridge
                            (BA 1797, MA 1800).</note> &#8211; for it has received no answer; &#8211; &amp; it was such a letter concerning old times,
                            <del>&amp;</del> remembered intimacy &amp; friends who are gone, &#8211; that I am sure he must have replied to it had it
                        reached him.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>