<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1657</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2779</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
                        1996.5.72.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1657" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1657" type="letter">
        <head>1657. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-07-18">18
                        July 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        Durham.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 43<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
                        1996.5.72<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Major Chamberlain<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Thomas Chamberlin (d. 1828), Major in the 24th
                        Foot Regiment, April 1809 to May 1811.</note> of the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> has written to me from Lisbon, to say that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> was then a private in that Regiment, &#8211; that he would endeavour to get him a
                    commission in some Portugueze battalions which he was organizing, &amp; to which he expected to be appointed Colonel, that Colonel
                        Drummond<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant Colonel George Duncan Drummond (d. 1811), commander of the 2nd
                        24th Foot Regiment in the Peninsular war, from April to November 1809.</note> of the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> would assist him
                    in this endeavour, &amp; that Lord John Fitzroy<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord John Fitzroy (1785&#8211;1857), attach&#233; at
                        the British Embassy in Lisbon and son of Augustus, 3rd Duke of Grafton (1735&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister
                        1768&#8211;1770.</note> would <del>pro</del> furnish him with his necessary equipments. &#8211; A few days after this letter comes one
                    from Edward himself to tell me he was a Lieutenant &amp; Adjutant in the Port. Reg of Oliveira, &amp; that he obtained it by his
                    own good conduct! &#8211; not does he mention one word of these officers who raised him from the ranks, &amp; equipped him. &#8211; The same
                    intelligence which Major C sent me, he sent also to Dalrymple the surgeon, of Norwich,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Dalrymple (1772&#8211;1847).</note> thinking his letter might fail of finding me &#8211; I have of course written to thank him,
                    &amp; sent my letter to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> that it may reach him free.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the letter to May, see Southey to John May, 15 July 1809, Letter 1655. The other does not appear to have
                        survived.</note> When <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> writes to her father<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Sealy (dates unknown) a wealthy Lisbon merchant who was Harry&#8217;s father-in-law.</note> I should be
                    obliged to her if she would beg him to make my respects to Major Ch. (if he happens to see him) &#8211; express my thanks to him, &amp;
                    likewise say that I have written to express them myself, &#8211; this is a fit sort of precaution in case my letter should be as long
                    kicking to windward as his has been. God knows what this precious youths adventures have been since he was in the Northampton
                    Militia! He writes from Abrantes, tells me he has 8 Shillings a day, &amp; that his regiment is to be the advanced guard of the P.
                    army when it enters Spain. Never had man more chances for redeeming himself than he has had, &#8211; but I confess I am altogether
                    hopeless about him. There is a species of moral derangement as well as of intellectual madness, &#8211; an idiotcy of the heart; &#8211; a
                    deficiency of the moral sense, &amp; this is his case.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Almost ever since my return I have had my obstinate summer catarrh upon me. <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">Losh</ref> turned me over at Newcastle to a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Doubleday<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably
                        George Doubleday (dates unknown), manufacturer of soap, tallow and sulphuric acid, and father of Thomas (1790&#8211;1870), who went
                        on to become a radical politician and writer.</note> to show me the town &amp; as we were peripateticating, who should we meet
                    but <ref target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Adamson</ref>, <del>whom</del> who may be called A-dam-son of the
                    Muses. By his guidance we got on the old Castle. Our old acquaintance M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Turner<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably William Turner (1761&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), Unitarian minister of the Hanover Square chapel,
                        Newcastle. Turner was a teacher and scholar, a founder of the Newcastle Literary and Philosophical Society, and one of James
                        Losh&#8217;s circle.</note> dined with us. I got off at one the next day, &amp; was well pleased with the road to Carlisle which
                    lies thro a striking country for the greatest part of the way. On the Wednesday I walked to Heskett to breakfast &amp; reached
                    home about two o clock, being so fresh after my nine &amp; twenty miles, that I <del>should</del> could have marched on another
                    stage with great ease &amp; comfort.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> has been here about ten days, &amp; we minutely expect <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> who is to stay here &#8216;one day &amp; a half&#8217;. The Liddells<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> made their appearance duly &amp; I sent them to Waswater, but I did not see the
                    females of the party. Walsh<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Untraced.</note> &amp; his poney are not yet arrived. We have
                    had <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> here, &amp; Dickinson<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Dickinson (1771&#8211;1837), a pupil at Westminster School, who later went on to Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795). He was
                        Civil Lord of the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806.</note> the Member for Somersetshire, a schoolfellow of mine whom I had not seen for
                    seventeen years. A Cambridge fellow with his pupil has also been here, whom <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles</ref>
                    &amp; I met the next day in their gig &amp; picked up a pocket full of Methodistical Tracts which they were dropping along the
                    road, &#8211; as seed by the way side.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly the Revd Samuel Tillbrook (1784&#8211;1835),
                        evangelical cleric, fellow of Peterhouse, Cambridge and later also rector of Freckenham, Suffolk. Tillbrook soon made
                        Southey&#8217;s acquaintance and also that of Wordsworth, near whose home at Rydal he subsequently purchased a cottage.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I perceive that an abridgement of Francisco Alvares<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Alvarez (c.
                        1465&#8211;1541?) was a Portuguese missionary and explorer, who published in Lisbon in 1540 an account of his travels entitled
                            <title>Yerdadera Informacam das terras do Preste Joam</title>. It was translated into English and included in part 2 of
                        Samuel Purchas (c. 1577&#8211;1626; <title>DNB</title>), <title>His Pilgrimage, or Relations of the World</title> (1625).</note> is
                    inserted in Purchas, &#8211; to reabridge it would therefore be <del>useful</del> useless but do you examine whether or no it be much
                    shortened (Purchas is in the Bishops Library) &#8211; for <del>it</del> in that case one might advise <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to give a full translation, &amp; translating is of all work the easiest. &#8211;
                    Some leisure hour I will write to you vehemently about the Crusades, &#8211; being assured that you can in no way add so materially to
                        <del>your</del> present enjoyment &amp; future happiness, as by having some work of importance in hand, &amp; some pursuit of
                    a higher nature than the ordinary ones of the world. You are well situated for books, &#8211; many of those which are of most importance
                    being at hand, &amp; you may make the whole skeleton of the work with your present stock of languages; &#8211; it will be time enough at
                    the end to incorporate Arabian documents, if any of importance remain untranslated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref>, &#8211; whom we heartily wish to see here. I will
                    send you Cullens Materia Medica,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Cullen (1710&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish
                        chemist and physician who published his <title>Lectures on the Materia Medica</title> (or properties of medicines) in
                        1773.</note> &amp; put a copy of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Whites</ref> Remains<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White of Nottingham with an Account of his Life</title>
                        (1807).</note> for her in the parcel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Miss Wood<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isabella Wood (dates unknown), cousin of <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>.</note> informs us that <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> by the last accounts was confined to her bed, &amp; the physicians had desisted from
                    giving her any thing except laudanum. No doubt she is at rest ere this. [MS obscured] am glad they were not here last summer, but
                    in spite of the slow weening the Island will always be to me a melancholy place, &amp; the &#8216;what has been&#8217; will frequently come
                    across me in moments of enjoyment upon yonder Lake, to sadden what <hi rend="ital">is</hi>!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to Derwent Isle, a melancholy place because of the untimely death of its summer resident <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachey</ref>, wife of its owner <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General
                            William Peachey</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-07-18">July 18. 1809.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> We are likely to have <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">a cousin</ref> in the course of next month</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>