<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1722</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2844</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    522&#8211;524.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1722" type="letter">
        <head>1722. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#StandertHughChudleigh">Hugh Chudleigh Standert</ref>, <date when="1809-12-14">14 December 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. C. Standert Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Taunton/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: [illegible]<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    522&#8211;524.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter<del>s</del> reminds me of some pleasant days which I had not forgotten, &amp; which it gives me
                    pleasure to perceive that you remember also. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Eltons volume of poems,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Abraham Elton (1778&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, translator, theologian and occasional reviewer for the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, who like Southey was Bristol-born. In 1804 he had published an edition of<title>
                            Poems</title>.</note> as well as those which appeared in the Athen&#230;um<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elton
                        published the following poems in <title>The Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>: &#8216;Lines
                        Written on the Banks of the Thames&#8217;, 1 (March 1807), 278&#8211;279; &#8216;Lines on a Favourite Retirement&#8217;, 1 (May 1807), 501&#8211;502; &#8216;The
                        Rose&#8217;, 2 (July 1807), 50.</note> I have read &amp; admired, &#8211; as containing many beautiful <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;passages&gt;
                    &amp; always affording the promise of greater things hereafter. His Hesiod<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elton&#8217;s
                            <title>The Remains of Hesiod the Ascraean: Translated from the Greek into English</title> (1809).</note> I have never
                    seen. I wished to have reviewed it in the Quarterly, being fond of Hesiod &amp; fancying I had something to say upon the
                        Theogony,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Theogony</title> is a poem by Hesiod (8C&#8211;7C BC), which
                        describes the origins and genealogies of the Greek gods, composed c. 700 BC.</note> &#8211; but for some reason unknown the book was
                    not sent me, &#8211; perhaps because it had been published too long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My knowledge of the trade of literature has I am sorry to say, never been very profitable either to myself or my
                    friends. Perhaps no poor author ever acquired so little pudding in proportion to his praise. There are only two branches in which
                    a man of letters can obtain any adequate remuneration for his labour, &#8211; by writing for reviews, or for the stage. I need not say
                    how grievously the stage is in want of poets, &amp; every thing which I have seen of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Eltons induces me to
                    think that he would succeed in this line, which is paid as much above its due proportion as all other kinds of poetry are under
                    paid. He might offer a play thro <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to Covent Garden &#8211; or I would willingly
                    &amp; zealously exceed my influence for him at a new theatre which is in preparation at Edinburgh,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The New Theatre Royal in Edinburgh.</note> where I have been urged to try my own fortune.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Reviewing also is well paid, even at the inferior price of the monthly Reviews. The Annual<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey wrote for the <title>Annual Review</title> from 1801 to 1808.</note> in which I could have been of
                    service to your friend is defunct. I bear a part in the Quarterly, but have no personal knowledge either of the <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Editor</ref>  or <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Publisher</ref>
                    , &amp; doubt the efficacy of my interference. Nevertheless if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Elton thinks his prose as good
                    as his verse (&amp; our best poets are our best prose-writers) &amp; if he be disposed to amuse himself in this manner, I will
                    mention his name there. Halham who, if I mistake not is related to him by marriage, has written in the Edinburgh, &amp; could
                    perhaps introduce him <del>xxxx</del> in that direction.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Elton&#8217;s sister, Julia
                        Maria (1807&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), married the historian Henry Hallam (1777&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>) in 1807. Between
                        1805 and 1809 he contributed articles to the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> Reviewing is not an unpleasant task. <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>  introduced me to the Critical<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Critical Review</title>, founded in 1756 and continuing until 1817.</note> in 1798, &amp; I
                    wrote some years for it at the low rate of three guineas per sheet, &#8211; my work was not worth more, &#8211; it brought me from 50 to 100 &#163;
                        <del>xxxxxxxx</del> &lt;yearly&gt; a very acceptable addition to my very straitened income. it made me look for my opinions
                    upon many subjects which had not occupied much of my attention before, &amp; it made me acquire more knowledge of contemporary
                    literature than I should else have possessed. For the Annual I received four guineas, &#8211; as much as the concern could afford, but
                    greatly below the value of my work, for the former apprenticeship had made me a skilful workman. Two years ago I refused ten
                    guineas per sheet with the promise of a great advance for the Edinburgh, &#8211; upon the ground of my total dissent from all its
                    principles of morals &amp; politics as well as taste. &#8211; I have since had that sum for the Quarterly, &amp; have this very evening
                    been offered twice that sum for a specific article in it.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref> offered Southey 20 guineas a sheet for his review of John
                        Charnock (1756&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord Viscount Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.; with
                            Observations, Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d. 1847), <title>The Life of Lord Nelson</title>
                        (1806); T. O. Churchill (fl. 1800&#8211;1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount Nelson, Duke of Bront&#233;, &amp;c</title> (1808); and
                        James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur (1755&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of
                            Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title> (1809), see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February
                        1810), 218&#8211;262. It was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; These facts will show
                    you the relative prices &amp; the nature of the employ. The ordinary pay of the Monthly<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Monthly Review</title>, a periodical founded in 1749 and continuing until 1845.</note> is five guineas, &#8211;
                    the Critical &amp; British Critic rather less.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The British Critic</title> was a
                        Tory periodical, established in 1793, and published until 1843.</note> This latter is likely to depart in peace &#8211; may the dust
                    be heavy upon its pages of bigotry, intolerance &amp; dullness!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But it is to the drama that I should especially advise M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Elton to direct his thoughts, as a
                    pursuit congenial to his taste &amp; worthy of his talents. There is a natural flow of feeling &amp; of language in his poems
                    (&amp; this which you have done me the favour to send <del>it</del> is an instance of it) which is excellently adapted to dramatic
                    verse. We want to have the mixed drama of Shakespeares age restored. Poor John Tobin attempted it,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Tobin (1770&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>) was a London solicitor and playwright whose comedy <title>The
                            Honey Moon</title> had been a success in 1805.</note> &amp; would have done much if he had lived, &#8211; but in the higher
                    requisites I do not think he was equal to what might be expected from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Elton. I knew him, &amp; speak
                        <del>as much</del> from what was in him, as well as from what came out <del>from</del> &lt;of&gt; him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for the intelligence you give me concerning <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref>,
                    to whom in consequence of thus knowing where to direct I have written, tho as the letter has to make a tour in search of a frank
                    it will be a day or two longer upon the road than this. If any chance should lead you to our Lakes it will give me great pleasure
                    to be your guide in this neighbourhood, &#8211; or if at any time you have a friend travelling this way, a line from you shall be
                    honoured as a draft for all serviceable civilities in my power. Remember me to my Taunton friends when you see them &amp; believe
                    me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> truly &amp; respectfully yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-12-14">Dec. 14. 1809</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>