<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1241</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2363</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1241" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1241" type="letter">
        <head>1241. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1806-12-12">12 December 1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: 12 Dec 1806<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of all the proof sheets which ever travelled to me in the course of twelve years hard authorship this is the most
                    infamously incorrect.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correcting the proofs for his and Bedford&#8217;s jointly
                        edited anthology, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> You had better send me the revise that I
                    may not be made to talk as much nonsense in the preface, as the poor Poets are in the Specimens &#8211; If you do not think I have said
                    enough now of Isaac Reed<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Reed (1742&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>), literary editor and
                        book collector, whose library Southey made use of for his anthology. He died before the <title>Specimens</title> were
                        published. Southey says of him &#8216;The worthy heart of Mr. Isaac Reed would have rejoiced to have known the advantages I have
                        derived from his rare Library, and still rarer knowledge; but while I am adding one more testimony of esteem and thanks to the
                        many due to him, I hear of an event, which places him beyond my praise or my gratitude&#8217;, <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (London, 1807), I, p. v.</note> &#8211; alter it to your own taste. In speaking well of living men I am apt to
                    feel a modesty for them with which I have no business.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the Index it need be nothing more than a chronological one prefixed to the first volume with reference to
                    the pages &#8211; &amp; an alphabetical one of the authors at the end of the last. Send me by favour of his Honour a set of the sheets
                    &amp; I will make out a list of Errors. three poems I know must be cancelled &#8211; that upon Felton as not being Buckinghams<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Villiers, 2nd Duke of Buckingham (1628&#8211;1687; <title>DNB</title>): politician, wit
                        and writer, whose father, also George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham (1592&#8211;1628; <title>DNB</title>), favourite of James I
                        (1566&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>), was murdered by John Felton (c. 1595&#8211;1628), an army officer, in Portsmouth. The 2nd Duke&#8217;s
                        poems are included in the <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 29&#8211;32. Here
                        Southey is arranging to omit a poem about Felton. For the text of the poem, see <title>Poems and Songs Relating to George
                            Villiers, Duke of Buckingham; and his Assassination by John Felton, August 23, 1628</title>, ed. Frederick W. Fairholt
                        (London, 1850), pp. 77&#8211;78.</note> &amp; two by Gildon<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Gildon (c.1665&#8211;1724;
                            <title>DNB</title>): poet and critical writer, slated in Alexander Pope&#8217;s (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) <title>The
                            Dunciad</title> (1728) and <title>Epistle to Arbuthnot</title> (1735). See <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title>, I, pp. 243&#8211;246.</note> &amp; Amhurst<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Amhurst (1697&#8211;1742;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a poet and political writer, who published the satirical <title>Terr&#230; Filius; or, the Secret History
                            of the University of Oxford</title> (1726). A selection from his works is featured in the <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, I, pp. 394&#8211;398.</note> &#8211; because no woman could read them aloud, &amp; no man in a womans presence.
                    &#8212; </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref> was born in 1766<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amos Simon Cottle,
                        author of <title>Icelandic Poetry, or, The Edda of Saemund, Translated into English Verse</title> (1797) which included a
                        dedicatory poem by Southey. Cottle&#8217;s work was not included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> &#8211; If
                    I do not get Churcheys<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Churchey (1747&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), a Welsh poet who
                        published <title>Poems and Imitations of the British Poets</title> in 1789. He is not included in <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (1807). Southey had asked for information on him from Joseph Cottle; see Southey to Joseph Cottle, 11 August
                        1806 (Letter 1210) and 2 November 1806 (Letter 1232).</note> Biog. in time omit him as well as poor Botch<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Botch Hayes&#8217; was Samuel Hayes (d. c. 1795), a master at Westminster School during Southey&#8217;s time
                        there. He was renowned for being lax on discipline, so much so that Southey later recorded that pupils used to &#8216;stick his wig
                        full of paper darts&#8217;. Hayes was also a writer of poems and sermons, and co-author of a tragedy, <title>Eugenia</title>
                        (1766).</note> &#8211; &amp; Sir John Moore<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Henry Moore, 2nd Baronet (1756&#8211;1780;
                            <title>DNB</title>), published a volume of poems entitled <title>The New Paradise of Dainty Devices</title> in 1777, reissued in 1778
                        with some new pieces as <title>Poetical Trifles</title>. His poetry was not included in <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title>.</note> also. <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury</ref> promised to send me his po[MS torn]
                    &amp; they may perhaps arrive &#8211; if not no matter</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot tell how to alter the Title page &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My dear Grosvenor about those ballads<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably, poems derived from Spanish
                        and Portuguese books, which Southey intended to include in a volume of poems on Spanish and Portuguese history: &#8216;Garci
                        Ferrandez&#8217;, which was published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor
                            Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838); &#8216;Queen Urraca and the Five Martyrs of
                        Morocco&#8217;, which had been published in the newspaper that <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>
                            edited,<title> The Iris</title>, on 3 November 1804. See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, pp. xxiv and 517; 406&#8211;413.</note> you talk as if there were originals instead of
                    imitations. One is in an artificial metre &#8211; because it is an artificial poem &#8211; full of prettinesses &amp; nothing more, &#8211; &amp;
                    Englished in the manner &amp; spirit of the original &#8211; merely doing for a newspaper &#8211; not because it was worth doing &#8211; but because
                    I am obliged to do something. The others are equally in the manner of the originals &#8211; &amp; <del>one of them</del> the conclusion
                    of one of them one of the finest specimens of that sort of bold personification which I have ever seen &#8211; had it been in Greek you
                    would have had it for ever instanced as the true sublime. To put such a ballad into polished rhyme would <del>be an</del> show as
                    utter <del>as</del> a want of all feeling &amp; all sense of the character &amp; merit of the original as Pope shows of
                        Homer.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Pope&#8217;s (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) translation of Homer&#8217;s
                            <title>Iliad</title>
                        (1715&#8211;1720) and <title>Odyssey</title> (1726).</note> The merit of these translations is that they are faithful representations of the
                    original both in manner &amp; matter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you knew <del>how</del> &lt;the inconvenience&gt; you have <del>incon</del> occasioned &amp; the vexation by
                    keeping D. Luisa<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza (1568&#8211;1614), was a Spanish missionary who devoted herself to the cause of the
                        Catholic faith in England during the reign of James VI and I (1566&#8211;1625, King of Scotland, England, and Ireland 1603&#8211;1625;
                            <title>DNB</title>). An account of her life was written by Luis Mun&#771;oz (d.1646) as <title>La Vida y Virtues de la
                            Venerable Virgin Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title> in 1632, and was summarised by Southey in the third edition of
                        his <title>Letters from Spain and Portugal</title> (1808).</note> so long it would give you the belly ache &#8211; therefore I hope
                    you will not know it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Vale</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1806-12-12">Friday. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 12 1806</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>