<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1186</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2308</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 380&#8211;385 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1186" type="letter">
        <head>1186. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-05-22">22 May
                        1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Amelia<lb />Postmark:
                        [illegible]<lb />Seal: [illegible] <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 380&#8211;385 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1806-05-22">May 22. 1806.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letters often miscarry, &amp; those which reach me come very irregularly. I had one of Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 10 &#8211; (the mere news of Duckworths action<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Thomas Duckworth, 1st Baronet
                        (1748&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, created Vice-Admiral in 1804, who defeated a French squadron off San Domingo
                        on the 6 February 1806.</note>) before my departure for London, &amp; some three or four weeks after during my absence came
                    one of Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; but I discover March 10 in the Post Mark which is, like the date, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kitts.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of the Leeward Islands of the West Indies.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> must have had later news as he tells me you have received the Reviews.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had sent his brother the <title>Annual Review</title> for 1803 and 1804, together
                        with a set of <title>Couriers</title>, courtesy of Charles Danvers; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806, Letter
                        1140.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Before this you will have seen that a million of the Spanish prize money goes towards the Ways &amp; Means of the
                    year. This is from beginning to end so rascally a piece of business that I lose all patience to think of it; &#8211; the remainder has
                    been shared among the Royal Family &#8211; part to the Prince of Wales, part to pay the Princess of Wales&#8217;s debts, part to pay for the
                    new Palace which the King has built at Kew, not as a nautical building &#8211; but to be the Queens.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This palace was unfinished when in 1810 King George III (1738&#8211;1820, reigned 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>)
                        lapsed into madness; his son George IV (1762&#8211;1830, reigned 1820&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>) not wishing to continue the work, it
                        was demolished in 1828.</note> The million given to the nation stops all inquiry, &amp; the rest is thus quietly pouched. And
                    so goes the money villainously taken from the Spaniards first, &amp; secondly from the captors &#8211; a very pretty piece of secret
                    history &#8211; on the truth of which you may rely. My articles were stopt by a positive assurance in the Courier that I was mistaken
                    &amp; that the prize money would be disposed of as usual: this assurance <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> told
                    me was inserted directly by some person in the confidence of government, &amp; it was as you see, neither more nor less than a
                    direct falsehood. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I could not see your defence at the Admiralty, without certain formal permissions which it would have been
                    unpleasant to have requested.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In January 1805 Southey learned that Thomas Southey had been
                        found guilty at court martial of contempt of a senior officer and dismissed his ship. The circumstances of the offence were
                        such that Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), who was in command of the
                        fleet in which his brother served, promptly appointed him to a finer ship.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry
                        Bedford</ref> however who is employed there, got it pretty well by heart &amp; repeated for me the whole substance. he said
                    the whole transaction was to your credit, &amp; that even what you had written about Williams<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> perjury would be rather serviceable than otherwise. I shall send the letter thro him, hoping
                    that you will receive it more speedily, &amp; that its chance of reaching you will be the greater, &#8211; but God send that it may pass
                    you on your passage to England with the convoy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now for my own affairs. Still in the same uncertainty about the fate of Portugal, but if it is not shut against us,
                    almost certain of Secretaryship there.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had expected an official position in the
                        legation at Lisbon owing to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn&#8217;s</ref> being appointed Under
                        Secretary of State in the Home Office under the administration of his uncle, <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William
                            Wyndham Grenville</ref>, who was Prime Minister 1806&#8211;1807.</note> Madoc has been reviewed in the Critical &amp; Monthly
                    very unjustly. the former, which I have not seen, was written by Le Grice, who is supposed to have so done because he hates <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, having always envied him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was negatively reviewed by Charles Valentine Le Grice (1773&#8211;1858) in the <title>Critical
                            Review</title>, ns 7 (1806), 72&#8211;83.</note> who did the latter I know not, &#8211; but if you can conceive a blue bottle fly
                    wriggling his tail &amp; trying to sting with it, you have a <del>xx</del> good emblem of the writers clumsy malice.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) wrote a hostile review of <title>Madoc</title> in
                        the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 48 (October 1805), 113&#8211;122.</note> Of <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffreys</ref> article in the Edinburgh I have before spoken,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Jeffrey&#8217;s
                        review appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> &amp; I believe told you, how
                        Windham<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Windham (1750&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary for War and the
                        Colonies, 1806&#8211;1807.</note> was induced to read the book by the merit of the extracts there given to be censured.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 7 December 1805, Letter 1130.</note> I perceive he said very
                    clearly that he who wrote the review knows nothing of poetry, &amp; that he who wrote the poem does. This which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> had told me was repeated by <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord
                        Holland</ref>. <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady H</ref>. added that it was the rule at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Anns Hill (<ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Fox&#8217;s</ref>) to read &lt;aloud&gt; after supper, &amp; shut the book
                    at eleven to retire to bed. But while Madoc was in reading, they went on till after midnight. Fox&#8217;s letter concerning which you
                    enquire was a civil one, written before he had read the book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fox&#8217;s letter acknowledging
                        Southey&#8217;s presentation of a copy of the poem is not extant.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> said to
                    me, the one poem was all that my warmest friends could wish it to be. But tho it has thus fairly made its fortune with those who
                    can discriminate, the main part of readers take their opinion from reviews, &amp; the dullest malignity can for a time do
                    mischief. 188 remain unsold &#8211; I gave away 28 &#8211; &amp; upon the rest my profits amount to &#8211; 3 &#8211; 17 &#8211; 1. the remuneration in 1806 for
                    the best poem except Paradise Lost in the English language &#8211; after a years sale &#8211; &#8216;O sweet remuneration!&#8217; But do not you suppose
                    that I am fool enough complain, or even really to feel dissatisfied. In the long run fame will be fortune to me if I live, &amp;
                    if I die secure a fit pension to my family. Besides the profits do not end here. Of the remaining quartos every one which sells,
                    adds 15/<hi rend="sup">s</hi> to my creditor account with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &amp; we are
                    going to print a small edition in two vols<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805) was published in 1807.</note> which will I suppose in the course of seven years send me in a hundred pounds &#8211; but if
                    the wind of fashion should set in in my favour, a thing always possible &#8211; I shall reap tens instead of units.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Metrical Tales have netted me about 22&#163;. pure profit this as it was no labour.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey republished his contributions to the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800) under his own name in
                            <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805).</note> I have put Espriella in the press, &amp; have received four
                        proofs.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella;
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) was being printed by Richard Taylor, (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), printer
                        and naturalist, who would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with his son William Francis
                        (1817&#8211;1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> It will make three small volumes in a type rather larger than that of
                        Amadis,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> or
                    rather a page less crowded. I have sold the first edition for &#163;100. without which I had been behind hand, &#8211; &amp; am now beginning
                    a race with the printer, as you know I like to do; &amp; if I do not keep pace with him, the Constable will not keep pace with me.
                    This then is my first &amp; main business in hand. Secondly I am preparing the Chronicle of the Cid for publication, in which I
                    shall dispose of much matter originally collected for preliminary chapters to my History: <hi rend="ital">there</hi> there will be
                    no room for <del>them</del> it &amp; here it may be advantageously set forth.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        used the materials from his unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; in the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> This is
                    a very favourite work with me, &amp; is I think likely to please a certain degree of readers much. Thirdly I am going to reprint
                    Palmerin of England, correcting the old translation when it requires it, restoring the original orthography of the names, &amp;
                    writing a preface.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert
                            Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807).</note> These are all stipulated engagements, concluded on with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. In my own mind I think of making from time &lt;to time&gt; more stories like
                    Queen Orracca,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Queen Urraca and the Five Martyrs of Morocco&#8217; had been
                        published in the newspaper that <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> edited,<title> The Iris</title>,
                        on 3 November 1804. See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), V, pp.
                        406&#8211;413.</note> Garci Ferrandez<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Garci Ferrandez&#8217;, was published in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838). See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda
                        Pratt (London, 2004), V, pp. xxiv and 517.</note> so as to fill a volume; &amp; of proceeding with Kehama in the winter,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, published in 1810.</note> if I should be in
                    England, instead of reviewing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Henrys History is safe &#8211; I had given it up as lost, but found that it was in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> possession.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Henry
                        (1718&#8211;1790), <title>The History of Great Britain, From the First Invasion of it by the Romans under Julius C&#230;sar</title>
                        (1771&#8211;1793). Southey had asked Tom to buy him a cheaper copy of this work in Ireland. He had entrusted its despatch to a
                        bookseller in Cork but it had been delayed in the post; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 1 February 1804, Letter
                    892.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> direction is now <hi rend="ital">Whitehall</hi>, he being one of
                    the Under Secretaries of State. he is married to a very good-natured unaffected woman.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Wynn married Mary Cunliffe (d. 1838), daughter of Foster Cunliffe, 3rd Baronet (1755&#8211;1834) on 9 April 1806.</note> If you ship
                    him a Turtle his house is N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 6. Great George Street, Westminster. The former one died performing quarantine at
                        Cork.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had sent his brother a turtle from the West Indies; see Southey
                        to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 24 November 1805 (Letter 1125) and Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806 (Letter
                        1140).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will expect some politicks, but in truth I like all that is going on so little that I had rather talk about any
                    thing else. It is such a damnd scramble for place &#8211; so completely every thing <del>that</del> which it ought not to be &#8211; that I am
                    out of heart, &amp; have lost all hope of any beneficial change to any extent. Yet Windhams army bill<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Windham (1750&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary for War and the Colonies, 1806&#8211;1807, introduced a
                        bill designed to limit the term for which soldiers could enlist.</note> is certainly a noble improvement, &#8211; &amp; the people
                    are so intolerably stupid that no measure seems to have excited more dislike or more opposition. Let me go to pleasanter subjects
                    &amp; tell you how <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref> has had two silver cups given her one by her
                    godmother <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref>, one by <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>, &amp; a noble cargo of barley sugar from <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, besides some fine clothes from her
                    godfather <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>: that she talks of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">her Uncle</ref>
                    who lives in a great ship upon the great waters, &amp; regularly receives a kiss in his name for every letter which arrives from
                    him, &#8211; &amp; let me also tell you that I hope she will have either brother or sister in the autumn:<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, the Southeys&#8217; first son, was born on 11 October
                        1806.</note> tho that piece of news should have been kept till the end of the letter, as I have nothing else half so
                    interesting to add.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have again suffered in the painters chair, having sate to Opie for a picture for <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s portrait was
                        painted for William Taylor by John Opie (1761&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>), while he was in London in April.</note> the likeness
                    is said to be a very strong one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The fourth Annual was published while I was in town: my portion in it is rather greater than in any of the
                    foregoing volumes,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4
                        (1806): James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>), <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years
                            1768&#8211;73</title> (2nd edn, 1804&#8211;1805), 2&#8211;16; Thomas Lindley (dates unknown), <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ...
                            with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto
                            Seguro</title> (1805), 27&#8211;32; Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The Present State of Peru, Comprising its Geography,
                            Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and Manners of its Inhabitants; Embellished by ...
                            Engravings of Costumes</title> (1805), 49&#8211;60; John Griffiths (dates unknown), <title>Travels in Europe, Asia Minor and
                            Arabia</title> (1805), 67&#8211;77; James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical
                            Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 1; 1805), 99&#8211;100; Charles Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay
                            on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title> (1805), trans. B Lambert (dates unknown), 177&#8211;187;
                        William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467; Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848),
                            <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805), 477&#8211;483; Dieudonn&#233; Thi&#233;bault (1733&#8211;1807), <title>Original Anecdotes
                            of Frederic the Second, King of Prussia, and of his Family, his Court, his Ministers, his Academies, and his Literary
                            Friends: Collected During a Familiar Intercourse of Twenty Years with that Prince</title> (1805), 488&#8211;495; William Parr
                        Greswell (bap. 1765&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of Angelus Politianus, Joannes Picus of Mirandula, Actius
                            Sincerus Sannazarius, Petrus Bembus, Hieronymus Fracastorius, Marcus Antonius Flaminius, and the Amalthei: Translations
                            from their Poetical Works: and Notes and Observations Concerning Other Literary Characters of the Fifteenth and Sixteenth
                            Centuries</title> (1805), 509&#8211;515; George Ellis, <title>Specimens of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805),
                        536&#8211;544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544&#8211;555;
                        William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Spirit of Discovery</title> (1804), 568&#8211;573; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals, with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title>
                        (1805), 575&#8211;576; John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810), <title>Oriental Tales: Translated into English Verse</title> (1805), 576&#8211;578;
                        Francis Burroughs (dates unknown), <title>A Poetical Epistle to James Barry Esq.</title> (1805), 578&#8211;579; Vincenzo Monti
                        (1754&#8211;1828), <title>Penance of Hugo: A Vision</title> (1805), trans. Henry Boyd (1748/9&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), 581&#8211;588;
                        James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Sabbath</title> (1805), 588&#8211;591; Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769&#8211;1850;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rhymes on Art, or, The Remonstrance of a Painter</title> (1805), 592&#8211;596; Samuel Whitchurch,
                        (dates unknown), <title>Hispaniola, a Poem</title> (1804), 596&#8211;597; Matthew Rolleston (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Anti-Corsican, A Poem</title> (1805), 597&#8211;598; Charles Grant, Baron Glenelg (1778&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poem
                            on the Restoration of Learning in the East</title> (1805), 598; Edward Coxe (dates unknown), <title>Miscellaneous
                            Poetry</title> (1805), 598&#8211;600; Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian, Containing the
                            Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with Notes and Illustrations (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald
                            Macdonald</title> (1739&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Some of Ossian&#8217;s Lesser Poems Rendered into Verse [from
                            Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s Critical and Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity
                            of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Philip Massinger (1583&#8211;1640; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Plays</title> (1805), ed.
                        William Gifford, 625&#8211;634; Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781), <title>Nathan the Wise; a Dramatic Poem in Five Acts</title>
                        (1805), trans. William Taylor, 634&#8211;639; John Collett (dates unknown), <title>Sacred Dramas: Intended Chiefly for Young
                            Persons</title> (1805), 639; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the
                            Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805),
                        679&#8211;699; Hannah More, <title>Hints Towards Forming the Character of a Young Princess</title> (1805), 708&#8211;713; Joseph Lancaster
                        (1778&#8211;1838), <title>Improvements in Education as it Respects the Industrious Classes of the Community</title> (3rd edn, 1805),
                        732&#8211;736; Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of
                            Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary Friends and Select Re-publications</title>
                        (1805), 736&#8211;738; William Henry Ireland (1775&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Confessions of William Henry Ireland
                            Containing the Particulars of his Fabrication of the Shakespeare Manuscripts</title> (1805), 743&#8211;745.</note> &amp; with
                    this thank Heaven I close my reviewing, as a regular employment, for ever. What I shall do hereafter will be merely a few things
                    by choice, either to help a friends book, or to take up a subject in which I am particularly interested, &#8211; nothing more. If I do
                    not lose money by the experiment I shall be satisfied; nothing took me so much time, &amp; nothing was done with so little
                    pleasure, &#8211; there was certainly a great pleasure in receiving a large parcel, &amp; looking over its contents, but there the
                    pleasure ended, &amp; all else was mere drudgery. I shall however by this abdication of my seat at the Round Table<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> A jokey reference to the <title>Annual Review</title> based on Southey&#8217;s nickname for its editor,
                        &#8216;King Arthur&#8217; <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Aikin</ref>.</note> have 80&#163; upon the average, to supply between October
                    &amp; April. Now if in that time I can compleat Kehama,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                        was not published until 1810.</note> that will about hit the mark: I can raise enough upon a first edition to supply this
                    deficit, &amp; there will remain <del>to me</del> the contingency of after profits to myself, or to my family the certain value of
                    the copy-right.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should &lt;you&gt; be on your passage to England as your letter teaches me to hope, you will yet be able to lend
                    Don Manuel a helping hand. I wish to write a letter upon the state of the navy,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> The navy
                        is discussed in <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (London,
                        1807), Letter 76.</note> representing in what manner <del>in what manner</del> that has partaken of the universal change which
                    has taken place during the present reign; &#8211; how, even there, men can no longer rise from the ranks, except by some lucky accident,
                    &#8211; men being now born to be Captains as they are to be Members of Parliament. If you were within reach you should tell me what
                    ought to be said of the blockading system &#8211; of the discipline &amp;c &amp;c. Without you I shall only venture to speak of the very
                    little which I think myself competent to understand: but the subject shall remain for the latest place possible in the hope that
                    you may come within reach, or that you may perhaps have sent me a letter to this purpose. You will be well pleased with this book.
                    its tone is not unlike that of my Letters from Spain &amp; Portugal,<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal,</title> first published in 1797.</note> but it will
                    be better done as I am better acquainted with that of which I write &amp; am also ten good years older.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your account of the insects on board delights me greatly. Scatter a little camphor among your letters to keep away
                    the weevils. I believe all insects dislike it, &amp; the experiment may be tried at little expense. I have no doubt that every
                    insect might be kept at due distance by some perfume or other &amp; a series of experiments upon this subject would be of great
                    importance. &#8211; I do not know the pronunciation of Trafalgar. It is always called Traf&#257;lgar in England, but I suspect the accent
                    ought to be on the last syllable &#8211; however Traf&#257;lgar it will be called &amp; as it the English who have made it famous, I think
                    they may be allowed to pronounce it as they think proper.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British victory at the
                        Battle of Trafalgar took place in October 1805; Horatio, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233; (1758&#8211;1805;
                            <title>DNB</title>), was killed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> have quarrelled, P. as usual, having behaved like a scoundrel.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillips established the<title> Monthly Magazine</title> in 1796. It was edited by John Aikin until they quarrelled in 1806,
                        when the editorship was taken over by George Gregory (1754&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>) until his death in 1808.</note> the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> has made terms with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, who only wanted an Editor to
                    start a Magazine upon a plan of my suggestion, &amp; they begin with the next new year.<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Aikin became editor of the short-lived <title>Athenaeum</title> magazine (1807&#8211;1809), published by Longman. For Southey&#8217;s
                        plan; see Southey to [Thomas Norton Longman], [10 January 1806], Letter 1144.</note> I must lend a hand at the launch, &amp;
                    indeed not leave the new ship till she is fairly under weigh. If my plan be in the main adhered to, the book will be a very good
                    one, &amp; supply a gap in the literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> I have just heard has a letter as late as March 13 from
                    you &#8211; much later than my latest. I cannot account for the great irregularity of the post. <hi rend="ital">all</hi> letters <hi rend="ital">to</hi> England ought to arrive with certainty, unless captured, &#8211; &amp; yet it is plain that very many of yours
                    have never reached me &#8211; we are going next week both I <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> to pass a few days at <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>, who has five children, &amp; lives at a very sweet place, eighteen miles off.<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles
                        Lloyd lived at Low Brathay, near <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>.</note> I begin to indulge so much hope
                    that it is possible you may be with us before the autumn is over, that if you are not it will be a disappointment &amp; that in
                    indulging more hope than is reasonable. If that be the case this letter will be written in vain. So much the better. God bless you
                    my dear Tom. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211; &amp; as much of a kiss from the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">young one</ref> as can be transferred up by letter &#8211; paper currency being a worse
                    substitute for kisses than for gold.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>