<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1669</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2791</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1669" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1669" type="letter">
        <head>1669. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1809-08-12">12 August 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You were perfectly right in all you said respecting the Stewardship, &amp; I only wish your information had arrived
                    a little sooner. Set on by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref>, &amp; encouraged by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref> &amp; by <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211; who thought it
                    the most desirable thing could be devised for me, I proceeded so far in quest of it, &#8211; that had I been fit for the situation,
                    there is very little doubt <del>that</del> &lt;but&gt; it must have been mine<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In July
                        1809, Southey was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the stewardship of the
                        Derwentwater Estates (which were owned by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the incumbent. Southey
                        asked several friends to intercede on his behalf for this position, including <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humprey Senhouse</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">George Beaumont</ref>, but in the end it was
                        considered unsuitable for him. See letter 1671 of this edition.</note> &#8211; &amp; in consequence I must now next week pay <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> a visit (at an expence of time which I can just now less than ever
                    afford) to thank him for assisting me in to get &#8211; what I am not qualified to accept. So much for place hunting! &#8211; Now that you
                    &amp; I may perfectly understand one another, or rather that you may perfectly understand me, &#8211; what I want is to succeed Dutens
                    whenever he vacates the situation which never ought to have been given him, &amp; I want also to have the salary increased t so as
                    to make it net its nominal amount.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), a French
                        Protestant, held the post of Historiographer Royal until his death on 23 May 1812. Southey&#8217;s campaign for the post proved
                        unsuccessful and it went to one of his particular <hi rend="ital">b&#234;tes noires</hi>, James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> This I have told Scott, &amp; he &amp; <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref> will
                    tell <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, who thinks proper to express a great deal towards me, &#8211; tho whether he
                    will ever do me any other service than inducing me to make other interest, I confess myself very doubtful. I believe however that
                    if Dutens would do me the favour to die, (&amp; you know that for a Frenchman this would be great stretch of politeness for &#8211; bid
                    him go to Hell &#8211; to Hell he goes) &#8211; I could obtain <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdales</ref> interest, &amp;
                    the Duke of Northumberlands,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hugh Percy, 2nd Duke of Northumberland (1742&#8211;1817), army
                        officer and politician.</note> &#8211; both weighty men with this ministry: Upon this subject you will say to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> as much as you think proper, &#8211; not implying on my part any suspicion of the
                    sincerity of <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref> professions, &#8211; &amp; if you can give me any better advice, for
                    at present I have according to an old proverb a fool for my counsellor<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The way of a fool
                        is right in his own eyes: but he that listens to counsel is wise&#8217;, Proverbs 12: 15.</note> you know ready I shall be to
                    receive it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just undertaken, &amp; that too upon miserably short notice, to write the history of Spanish affairs during
                    the last year, for the Edinburgh Annual Register, which the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> are
                    starting. They calculated its fit length at fifteen sheets &amp; want it by the middle of October &#8211; I do not think the narrative
                    will extend to more than ten, &amp; it will be hard work to furnish that; &#8211; but if it take up more so much the better. This is a
                    thing which I shall do with great good will, &#8211; if it be possible to procure a good series of documents. From the two accounts by
                    Neale &amp; the Officer of Sir John Moores extract,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Adam Neale (1778?-1832),
                            <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain: Comprising an Account of the Operations of the Armies under their Excellencies Sir
                            Arthur Wellesley and Sir John Moore</title> (1809). Possibly Robert Ker Porter (1777&#8211;1842), <title>Letters from Portugal
                            and Spain: Written During the March of the British Troops under Sir John Moore. By an Officer</title> (1809).</note> &amp;
                    by some letters to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> from an Officer nearly connected with him, my
                    own opinion of that retreat is confirmed, &#8211; &amp; it is so strongly &amp; decidedly against Sir John Moore that I must not as an
                    honest man express my opinion till I have seen his brothers book.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Moore
                        (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs
                        1784&#8211;1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the
                        Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna on 16 January 1809. James Moore (1762&#8211;1860;
                            <title>DNB</title>), surgeon and biographer, author of <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British Army in
                            Spain</title> (1809), incorporating letters and extracts from his elder brother&#8217;s journals to defend his actions.</note>
                    Be sure that I will in sure justice make full allowance for all his difficulties, &amp; in courtesy to you (even if there be no
                    other motives) speak with due honour of his death, &#8211; but indeed Grosvenor it is well for him that he was compelled to fight at
                    last, &amp; that such a death has thrown some lustre about his memory, for there is not such another <hi rend="ital">flight</hi>
                    upon record.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell me, that is explain to me so as I may be able to explain, why the subscription for the Spaniards produced so
                    little, &#8211; &amp; give me any other hints &amp; information that may be of use.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For his
                        contribution to the history pages for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> &#8211; This business, saving the hurry,
                    is in every respect agreable to me, I can do it with comparative ease &amp; great pleasure, for you know how deeply it has
                    interested me, &amp; I shall receive for it a sum which will be very acceptable &amp; come in good time &#8211; ten guineas per sheet &#8211;
                    at the Quarterly measure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Mss herewith is for my Uncle &#8211; Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert
                        Hill</ref>, <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton upon Wye</ref>, Hereford. &#8211; in the absence of the Grand
                        Parleur.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s name for the Speaker of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>, for whom Rickman worked as secretary.</note> you will get it
                    franked for me by some hand potential. 424 pages of my history are printed, &#8211; the volume will extend to more than 600 &amp; I am
                    working hard at transcribing the remaining chapters.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford that you have remained so long at Southampton, because it shows me that on
                    an occasion you can be absent for some time from the Exchequer, &amp; I call <del>you</del> upon you to show cause why coming to
                        <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> should not be held a lawful occasion next summer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now Grosvenor I must trouble <del>xxx</del> you with a commission which will not be very troublesome, &#8211; for which
                    you will be the most convenient pay master, as you can deduct the amount from my next payment. I want four frames for miniatures
                    the exact size of the pattern below;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Towards the bottom of the page, Southey has drawn a
                        square captioned &#8216;Site of the Picture&#8217; and has written the remainder of the letter around this.</note> they are to be of black
                    pannel with a little raised black rim in the inside, the breadth of the frame two inches; the glasses black &amp; gold
                        <del>enamel</del>, but the gold on the glasses <hi rend="ital">broad</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">plain</hi> next the picture.
                    Back boards &amp; every thing ready so as there may be no difficulty in putting in the pictures when they arrive here. Myers in
                        Strand<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> will be a fit man to order them of, &amp; as
                        <del>little</del> likely to be in your way as any one, &#8211; but go wherever is most convenient, the glasses must be convex. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want also another frame &lt;for a picture&gt; two foot wanting a quarter of an inch long, &amp; one foot
                        <del>xxxx wide</del>. four inches wide. The frame tho perhaps it must be of <hi rend="ital">different</hi> materials (that is
                    to say of common black wood) <del>to the same pattern as the others,</del> flat like the others, &amp; 3 &#189; inches wide, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">no</hi> interior rim. the glass black &amp; gold &amp; in gold black-letters (for which you know my partiality) on
                    the glass, the words Mars &amp; L&#8217;Hercule.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was a print owned by Southey of the
                        battle in 1798 between HMS <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> (a 74-gun third-rate ship of the line) against the French seventy-four
                        gun <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi>. After a bloody battle, <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi> surrendered, having lost over three
                        hundred men. On <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> 31 men were killed and 60 wounded, including the captain. Southey&#8217;s brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref> was a participant in the battle.</note> &#8211; the dimensions given are of the
                    picture, &amp; the frame must allow for the additional breadth of the glass.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These must be carefully packed, &amp; sent to me by the waggon which goes from the Bull &amp; Mouth. The Mars print
                    explains its own story. for the others I will gratify your curiosity. We have in this house a visitor by name <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref>, who is a miniature painter, &#8211; &amp; who has drawn me two of the best
                    likenesses &amp; best pictures that ever were seen, &#8211; one of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; the other of
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>. &#8211; I &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">young Edith</ref>
                    are also under her hands &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you Grosvenor &#8211; </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-08-12">August <hi rend="ital">12</hi>
              <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1809 </date>
          </p>
          <p>I am 35. this day. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>