<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1129</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2251</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 355&#8211;357.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1129" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1129" type="letter">
        <head>1129. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-12-06">6 December 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 6 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        1805<lb />Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 355&#8211;357.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Williams<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William is a fictional character, one of Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s
                        comic inventions, originating in schoolboy stories at Westminster.</note> iron gray had his advantages &amp; disadvantages. He
                    never required shoeing &#8211; for as the hoof is harder than the flesh, so in just proportion to his metallic muscles he had hoofs of
                    adamant, &#8211; but then he was hard mouthed. There was no expence in feeding him but he required scouring least he should grow rusty.
                    &#8211; Instead of spurs William had a contrivance for touching him with aqua-fortis.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aqua
                        fortis is a corrosive solution of nitric acid in water.</note> It was a fine thing to hear the rain hiss upon him as he
                    gallopped. William has a way of cooling him by affusion, but it was only a temporary relief at the expence of his asbestos
                    breeches.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Butler wore a chest of drawers, sometimes a bureau.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Recipe for the Readers of your Book if they cannot see its meaning. Euphrasy &amp; rue<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In John Milton&#8217;s (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667), the angel Michael
                        purges Adam&#8217;s eyes, which have been blinded by the &#8216;false fruit that promis&#8217;d clearer sight&#8217; with &#8216;euphrasy and rue&#8217; (Book 11,
                        lines 413&#8211;414).</note> may fail, or may not be at hand or they may not exactly understand the mode of applying them &#8211; but <hi rend="ital">Zibethum Occidentale</hi>, dried &amp; pulverized &amp; blown into the eye, is a sovereign remedy for film, &amp;
                    the medicine every man can make for himself.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Because it is dried human excrement.</note>
                    Tis John Wesleys prescription.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Primitive Physic: Or, An Easy and Natural Method of Curing Most Diseases</title>, 21st edn (London, 1785), p.
                        55.</note> If you did not know what Zibethum Occidentale is, go to your apothecary, if he cannot supply you &#8211; (for it as
                    antiquated as a drug) &#8211; ask a physician. You may if baffled there insert a query in the Gentlemans Magazine<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title> was founded in London, in 1731, by Edward Cave (1691&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>).
                        Correspondents frequently posted factual queries in the magazine.</note> &#8211; But if you are willing to be spared all this trouble go to the necessary
                    &amp; you may nose it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bedford I will break off all acquaintance with you if you do not publish the Butler.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Though urged on by Southey, their comic inventions were never published by Bedford. However they provided the
                        hint for Southey&#8217;s comic novel/miscellany <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> Who the Devil would keep a Phoenix
                    with a spaniels ears, a pigs tail, <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combes</ref> nose &amp; Wingfields wig, all naturally
                    belonging to him &#8211; in a cage only for his own amusement, when he might show it for five shillings a piece, &amp; be known all over
                    the world as the man who hatched it himself!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You shall send it me in Letters &amp; I will return my comments. It is not in my way to help you in your own, for
                    your way is your own exclusively &amp; pre-eminently. But now &amp; then I can perhaps fling in a stroke of politics, &amp; give a
                    seasoning of out-of the way erudition which will make the learned stare.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hints for the Butlers descent into Hell where he went to learn <del>what was</del> the best way of dressing soles.
                    The Devil received him in full dress &#8211; that is he had put his tail in a bag, &amp; he entertained him with a concert in which
                    every man played upon his neighbours fistula. Scotchmans corner I believe you know &#8211; it is that part of Hell where there is all
                    fire &amp; no brimstone.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A joke about the Scots&#8217; lack of cleanliness: brimstone (sulphur) was used for fumigating rooms to kill fleas and lice.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>The</del> By the first January send me the first chapter &#8211; being the Mythology of the Butler &#8211; or else by the Lord I will for
                    ever more call you Sir when I speak <hi rend="ital">to</hi> you &amp; <hi rend="ital">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </hi> Bedford when I
                    speak of you, &#8211; &amp; moreover will always pull off my hat when I meet you in the streets.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish I could see the European critique.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was hoping that
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) would be reviewed in the <title>European Magazine</title>, because his wealthy uncle, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref>, would see it there and it might benefit him financially.</note> Hang
                    all the others! &#8211; that <del>xx</del> really may be of some importance to me. &#8211; By certain phrases you seem to imply that I ought
                    to have profited by the reviewals of Thalaba,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reviews of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) were: <title>British Critic</title>, 18 (September 1801), 309&#8211;310; <title>Monthly Mirror</title>,
                        12 (October 1801), 243&#8211;247; Francis Jeffrey, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1 (October 1802), 63&#8211;83; <title>Monthly
                            Review</title>, 39 (November 1802), 240&#8211;251; Anna Seward, <title>The Poetical Register, and Repository for Fugitive
                            Poetry, for 1801</title> (London, 1802), pp. 475&#8211;486; William Taylor, <title>Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 39
                        (December 1803), 369&#8211;379.</note> for <del>xxx of</del> which I never <del>xxx</del> &lt;entertained&gt; any <del>thing</del>
                    other feeling than that of a very thorough contempt. If you had them to refer to you would perceive that they imagine
                        <del>xxxx</del> absurdities in the story which only existed in their misapprehension &lt;of it&gt;, &amp; that they object to
                    the metre, not upon any principle, not for any defects real or supposed, but merely because it is not what they had been used to.
                    Saving in the Critical (which <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> wrote) there was not a
                    single remark &lt;among them&gt; which originated in thought, or could lead to anything. I perceive also that the reviewals of
                    Madoc have in a certain degree influenced you, which they will not do if you look at them when they are three months old, or if
                    you recollect that a review is the opinion of one man upon the work of another, &#8211; &amp; that it is not very likely that any man
                    who reviews a poem of mine should know quite so much of the mechanism of poetry, or should have thought quite so much upon the
                    nature of poetry as I have done. The Monthly<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 48 (October 1805), 113&#8211;122.</note> is mere malice &amp; beneath all
                    notice &#8211; but look at the Edinburgh &amp; you will perceive that <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> himself
                    does not know what he is about.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Jeffrey, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7
                        (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> He talked of Virgil &amp; Pope &amp; Racine<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius
                        Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), author of the <title>Aeneid</title> (19 BC); Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>); Jean
                        Racine (1639&#8211;1699), French dramatist.</note> as <del>the opposite to xx the poetry of Madoc</del> &lt;what I have set up
                    against&gt;. I told him Pope was a model for satire, &#8211; that, he said, was a great concession &#8211; no, said I, if his stile be a model
                    for satire how can it be for serious narration? &amp; he did not attempt to hold up his Homer<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pope&#8217;s translation of Homer&#8217;s <title>Iliad</title> (1715&#8211;1720) and <title>Odyssey</title> (1726).</note> for
                    imitation, but fairly &amp; unequivocally declared he did not like it. And yet <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> attacks me for not writing in Madoc like Pope! &#8211; The passages which he has quoted for praise or for censure may
                    just as well change places &#8211; they are culled capriciously, not with any sense of selection. The real faults of Madoc have never
                    been pointed out. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> has criticised it for the
                        Annual,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor reviewed <title>Madoc</title> in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1805</title>, 4 (1806), 604&#8211;613.</note> very favourably &amp; very ably. there are remarks in his critique to set one
                    thinking &amp; reconsidering, &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> is a man who
                    fertilizes every subject he touches upon. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Don Manuel.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> How could you
                    not understand it was a secret? do you not remember how covertly I enquired of you the text in Fields Bible?<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Field (dates unknown) printed a pocket-sized edition of the Bible, known as the &#8216;Pearl
                        Bible&#8217; due to its diminutive size, but also referred to as &#8216;Field&#8217;s Bible of 10,000 Errors&#8217; (1653) owing to the number of
                        misprints in it. One of the most famous errors was in 1 Corinthians 6.9: &#8216;Know ye not that the unrighteous [instead of
                        &#8216;righteous&#8217;] shall inherit the kingdom of God?&#8217; Field was rumoured to have accepted a bribe from the Presbyterians to alter
                        Acts 6.3 to read &#8216;Wherefore, brethren, look ye out among you seven men of honest report, full of the Holy Ghost and wisdom,
                        whom we [instead of &#8216;ye&#8217;] may appoint over this business&#8217;, so that it confirmed men&#8217;s right to choose their own priests.
                        Biblical translations are discussed in Letter 54 of <title>Letters from England</title>, but there is no reference to
                        Field.</note> &amp; was not my very phrase that they were to be shown to you under the seal of silence? &#8211; The use of secresy
                    is to create curiosity, &#8211; &amp; <hi rend="ital">perhaps</hi> to pass thro the reviews under cover. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> particularly commends the foreign cast of remarks thro the whole of the
                    journey. thus do Doctors differ. I make blunders sometimes, but am cautious of overdoing it. Do you make more, &amp; if they do
                    not suit my conception of the Spaniards character they can be omitted or modified.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bedford had suggested that &#8216;the remarks did not seem foreign enough&#8217;; see Southey to John Rickman, 28 November [1805], Letter
                        1128.</note> On many subjects you will know necessarily more than I can do, &amp; I shall expect some whole letters &amp; many
                    interpolations from you. You see the plan admits of every thing. I get bravely on with it, &amp; feel no doubt of producing a book
                    which will be thought very amusing now, &amp; very valuable hereafter when I &amp; the author of the Butler shall be considered as
                    antients. &#8211; Have you ever been to Margate? I want much to have a journey into Kent for him.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s fictional traveller does not go to Kent in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> &#8211; As for the
                    queerities let them stay &#8211; it is only they who know me pretty nearly, know what a queer fish I am. The world conceives me to be a
                    very grave sort of person. Besides I have not the least intention of keeping the thing concealed, after the purpose of secresy has
                    been answered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That wretch Mack<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant Field Marshal Mack von Leiberich (1752&#8211;1828),
                        commander of the Austrian forces defeated and captured by the French army at the Battle of Ulm in October 1805.</note> &#8211; who
                    must be the veriest wretch that ever tainted Gods air, as he has not blown out his own brains, &#8211; has very likely spoilt my voyage
                    to Lisbon. If there be not peace Bonaparte will show himself master of the continent &amp; turn us out of Portugal if only to show
                    that he is <del>as</del> &lt;more&gt; powerful in that peninsula than Charlemagne<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Charlemagne (742&#8211;814) was King of the Franks 768&#8211;814 and Holy Roman Emperor (800&#8211;814).</note> was &#8211; I am afraid of peace,
                    &amp; wish for single-handed war carried on steadily &amp; systematically. we ought to have Egypt, Sicily &amp; the Cape, if we do
                    not France will. But nothing good ever will be done while that wretched minister is at the head of affairs.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801,
                        1804&#8211;1806.</note> In my conscience I do not think him capable of one good feeling, or one grand conception.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Write me the first chapter of the Butler. Once begin &#8211; &amp; the whole will be done in six weeks.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> tui favoris studiossimus<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;most eager for your goodwill&#8217;.</note>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-12-06">December 6. 1805</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>