<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1704</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2826</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I,
                        Box 1, folder 7.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 261&#8211;265.Dating note: the letter can be dated 28 October 1809
                        from internal evidence. Southey is writing in reply to a letter from Coleridge dated 20 October 1809, in which he requested
                        him to &#8216;look over the eight numbers&#8217; of The Friend and to write a letter &#8216;in a lively style&#8217; on the obscurity
                        of the material within them. See Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 259&#8211;260 [in part]. The first letter Southey wrote in answer to this request is Letter 1702
                        (dated Thursday 26 [October 1809]) in which he says he will write on &#8216;Saturday&#8217;, the day Southey gives at the bottom of this
                        letter.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1704" type="letter">
        <head>1704. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, [<date when="1809-10-28">28 October 1809</date>]<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ S. T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.<lb />Endorsements: [mathematical calculations on address sheet]<lb />MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I,
                        Box 1, folder 7<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 261&#8211;265.<lb />Dating note: the letter can be dated 28 October 1809
                        from internal evidence. Southey is writing in reply to a letter from Coleridge dated 20 October 1809, in which he requested
                        him to &#8216;look over the eight numbers&#8217; of <title>The Friend</title> and to write a letter &#8216;in a lively style&#8217; on the obscurity
                        of the material within them. See Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 259&#8211;260 [in part]. The first letter Southey wrote in answer to this request is Letter 1702
                        (dated Thursday 26 [October 1809]) in which he says he will write on &#8216;Saturday&#8217;, the day Southey gives at the bottom of this
                        letter.</note>
        </head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>To the Friend.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, was published in 26
                            numbers from 1 June 1809 to 15 March 1810. This letter of Southey&#8217;s was solicited by Coleridge for publication but not
                            published, Coleridge himself writing and publishing, in the eleventh number, 26 October 1809, an answer to a critical
                            letter from an imaginary friend. The text is given in S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2
                            vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp. 149&#8211;153.</note>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <opener>
          <salute>Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not whether your subscribers have expected too much from you, but it appears to me that you expect too much
                    from your Subscribers, &amp; that however accurately you may understand the diseases of the Age, you have certainly mistaken its
                    temper. In the first place Sir your Essays are too long. &#8216;Brevity, says a contemporary journalist, is the humour of the times; a
                    tragedy must not exceed fifteen hundred lines; a fashionable preacher must not trespass above fifteen minutes upon <del>xxxxxx
                        xxx</del> his congregation. We have short waistcoats &amp; short campaigns; every thing must be short, &#8211; except law suits,
                    speeches in Parliament &amp; Tax Tables.&#8217;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is quoting himself in his review of
                        William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de Medici</title> (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1805</title>, 4 (1806), 449&#8211;467 (467).</note> It <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; expressly stated in the prospectus of a
                    collection of Extracts called the Beauties of Sentiment, that the Extracts <del>would</del> &lt;shall&gt; always be complete
                    sense, <hi rend="ital">&amp; not very long</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Instructive Selections: Or, The
                            Beauties of Sentiment being Striking Extracts from the Best Authors, Ancient and Modern, in Prose and Verse, on a Great
                            Variety of Subjects, Divine, Moral, Literary, and Entertaining, on a New Methodical Plan. Also, a List of the Best Books
                            on the Principal Subjects, and the Names of the Authors Annexed to these Extracts by the Rev. G. G. Scraggs [dates
                            unknown] in Two Volumes</title> (1st edn, 1801; 2nd edn, 1802). A contemporary advertisement of &#8216;New Books Printed for
                        Sherwood, Neely and Jones&#8217;, contained in the back pages of many books stated that &#8216;the extracts are always complete sense, not
                        very long, and yet not too short&#8217;.</note> Secondly, Sir, though your Essays appear in so tempting a shape to a Lounger, &#8211; the
                    very Fiends themselves were not more deceived by the <hi rend="ital">Lignum Vit&#230;</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Meaning &#8216;wood of life&#8217;, a tropical American tree with blue or purple flowers.</note> apples when</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> They fondly thinking to allay</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Their appetite with gust, instead of fruit</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Chewd bitter ashes.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Paradise Lost</title>, Book 10, lines
                            564&#8211;566.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">than the <del>fashionable</del> reader is who takes up one of your Papers from <del>the</del> &lt;breakfast table,
                    parlour window, Sofa, Ottoman or Chaise-longue, thinking to amuse himself with a few minutes light-reading. We are informed upon
                    the authority of no less a man than <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Sir Richard Phillips</ref>, how &#8216;it has long been a
                    subject of just complaint among the lovers of English Literature that our Language has been deficient in Lounging or
                    Parlour-window books&#8217; <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>London Chronicle</title>, 106 (7 September 1809),
                        237.</note> &amp; to remove this opprobrium from the Language Sir Richard advertises a list mostly ending in <hi rend="ital">ana</hi>; under the general title of &#8216;Lounging Books, or Light Reading.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Also in the
                            <title>London Chronicle</title>, 106 (7 September 1809), 238.</note> &#8211; I am afraid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friend that your
                    predecessors <del>would never</del> &lt;would never have&gt; obtained their popularity <del>because they</del> unless their essays
                    had been of this description, &#8216;&#927;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#959;&#957; &#959;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#968; &#966;&#953;&#955;&#959;&#957;;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> From a longer Greek saying: &#8216;&#972;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#959;&#962;
                        &#959;&#956;&#959;&#943;&#969; &#945;&#949;&#943; &#960;&#949;&#955;&#940;&#950;&#949;&#953;&#8217;, meaning &#8216;like is pleasing to like&#8217;.</note> &amp; this is a light age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have yourself observed that few converts were made by Burke,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        politician and author, Edmund Burke (1729/30&#8211;1797;<title> DNB</title>).</note> but the cause which you have assigned does not
                    sufficiently explain why a man of such powerful talents &amp; so authoritative a reputation should have produced so little an
                    effect upon the minds of the people. Was it not because he neither was, nor could be generally understood? Because instead of
                    endeavouring to make difficult things appear easy of comprehension, he made things which were easy in themselves difficult &lt;to
                    be comprehended&gt; by the manner in which he presented them, evolving their causes &amp; involving their consequences, till the
                    reader whose mind was not habituated to <del>logical reasoning &amp;</del> metaphysical discussions, neither knew in what his
                    arguments began nor in what they ended. You have told me that the straightest line must be the shortest, &#8211; but do not you yourself
                    sometimes <del>nose out your</del> nose out your way hound-like in pursuit of truth, turning &amp; winding &amp; doubling &amp;
                    running roundabout, when the same object might be reachd in a tenth part of the time by darting straight forward, like a
                    greyhound, to the mark? &#8211; Burke failed of effect upon the people for this reason; &#8211; there was the difficulty of mathematics
                    without the precision in his writings; &#8211; you looked thro the process without arriving at the proof. It was the fashion to read
                    him, because of his rank as a political partizan; otherwise he would not have been read. Even in the House of Commons he was
                    admired more than he was listened to, &#8211; not a sentence came from him which was not pregnant with seeds of thought, if it had
                    fallen upon good ground; &#8211; yet his speeches convinced nobody, while the mellifluous orations of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitt<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note>
                    persuaded his majorities of whatever he wished to persuade them, <del>the orations</del> &lt;because they&gt; were easily
                    understood &amp; <del>as easily forgotten</del> what mattered it to him that they were as easily forgotten? &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Reader Sir must think before <del>you</del> he can understand you; &#8211; is it not a little unreasonable to require
                    from him an effort which you have yourself described as so very painful a one? &amp; is not this effort not merely difficult
                    &lt;but&gt; in many cases impossible? All brains Sir were not made for thinking; &#8211; modern philosophy has <del>thought</del> taught
                    us that they are galvanic machines, &amp; <hi rend="ital">thinking</hi> is only an accident belonging to them. Intellect is
                        <del>in our day</del> not essential to the functions of life, &#8211; in the ordinary <del>purposes</del> &lt;course&gt; of
                        <del>life</del> &lt;society&gt; it is very commonly dispensed with; &amp; we have lived M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friend, to
                    witness experiments for carrying on Government without it. This is surely a proof that it is a rare commodity, &#8211; &amp; yet you
                        <del>are xxxxxxxxxx enough to</del> expect <del>that</del> &lt;it&gt; in all your subscribers? &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Give us your moral medicine in a more &#8216;elegant preparation&#8217;.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An oft-used
                        advertising slogan for patent medicines.</note> The Reverend J Gentle administers his physic in the form of tea,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Reverend J. Gentle&#8217;s cordial tea was a patent medicine advertised in newspapers.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Solomon prefers the medium of a cordial,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Solomon
                        (1745&#8211;1819), who devised patent medicines such as his &#8216;Cordial Balm of Gilead&#8217; with great commercial success.</note> &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ching exhibits his in Gingerbread nuts,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> J. Ching&#8217;s (d. 1800) worm
                        lozenges and Waite&#8217;s (first name and dates unknown) gingerbread nuts were patent medicines used for the removal of
                        worms.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Barton in wine.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Barton&#8217;s Vital Wine was
                        another commonly advertised quack medicine.</note> But you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friend come with a tonic bolus,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A large pill.</note> bitter in the mouth, &lt;difficult to swallow,&gt; &amp; hard of
                    digestion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> ___</p>
        <p>My dear <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All this were it not for the Sir &amp; the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friend &#8211; is like a real letter from me to you, &#8211;
                    I fell into the strain without intending it, &#8211; &amp; would not send it were it not to show you that I have attempted to do
                    something. <del>xxxx</del> From jest I got into earnest, &amp; trying to pass from earnest to jest, very nearly became seditious.
                    It was against the grain &amp; would not do. I had reread the <del>ten</del> eight last numbers, &amp; the truth is they left me
                    no heart for jesting or for irony. &#8211; In time they will do their work, &#8211; it is the form of publication only that is unlucky, &amp;
                    that cannot now be remedied. But this evil is merely temporary, &#8211; Give two or three amusing numbers &amp; you will hear of
                    admiration from every side &#8211; Insert a few more poems, &#8211; any that you have except Christabel,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s poem &#8216;Christabel&#8217; was composed in 1797&#8211;1800 but not published until 1816.</note>
          <del>which</del>
                    &lt;for that&gt; is of too much value, &#8211; There is scarcely any thing you could do which would excite so much notice as if you were
                        <hi rend="ital">now</hi> to write the character of Buonaparte, announced in former times for &#8216;tomorrow&#8217; &amp; tomorrow &amp;
                        tomorrow;<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>The Friend</title> of 11 January 1810, Coleridge promised an
                        analysis of the character of Napoleon in a future number. See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E.
                        Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, p. 283. It did not appear. &#8216;Tomorrow, and tomorrow, and tomorrow&#8217;,
                            <title>Macbeth</title>, Act 5, Scene 5, line 19.</note> &amp; I think it would do good by counteracting that base spirit
                    of condescension towards him, which I am afraid is gaining ground; &amp; by showing the people <del>on</del> what grounds they
                    have for hope.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I send you a letter of <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuarts</ref> &#8211; written in reply to an application
                    which I made to him for the foreign papers.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Daniel Stuart, 22 October
                        1800, Letter 1699.</note> &#8211; What is become of Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pasley?<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir
                        Charles William Pasley (1780&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), an acquaintance of Coleridge&#8217;s in Malta and author of <title>Essay on
                            the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810), which was much admired by Southey and reviewed
                        by him in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811), 403&#8211;457.</note> I look with fear &amp; trembling for his name in
                    the Newspapers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Saturday morning</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>