<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1569</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2691</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 121&#8211;124.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1569" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1569" type="letter">
        <head>1569. Robert Southey to Neville White, <date when="1809-01-20">20 January 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 121&#8211;124.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-01-20">January 20. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am the most punctual of men in replying to a letter of business; but when a letter of luxury (as it may be
                    called) is to be written, it is so often deferred till a more convenient season, that what would at first have been a matter of
                    pleasure is at last considered with the feeling of debt. Your last letter is five weeks old. I have during that time been absent
                    from home three days. I have been invalided for a week by a cold, and something worse than invalided, after my recovery, by some
                    of those little family sicknesses which bring with them more disquiet than is reasonable to one who is apt to be anxious overmuch upon such occasions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask me whether you shall write again to &#8211;&#8211;?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Capel Lofft (1751&#8211;1824;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Whig landed gentleman, lawyer and poet, notoriously testy of disposition. Lofft was the patron and
                        editor of Robert Bloomfield (1766&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Kirke White and a number of other writers from poor backgrounds.
                        He was a regular contributor to the <title>Monthly Mirror</title>. For further details, see Southey to Neville White, 28
                        November 1808, Letter 1545.</note> Better advice cannot be given upon that subject than what <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry</ref> gives you in one of his earliest letters. In this case I think the question
                    entirely depends upon the pleasure which you derive from his correspondence. Mr. &#8212;, I believe, is a man not happy in his
                    circumstances; and fits of irritation against you, or me, or anybody else, serve to divert a certain portion of uneasiness which
                    is always fermenting in him, and which becomes more tolerable by finding its object abroad than at home. I respect his learning
                    and his benevolence, and regard his infirmities of temper with pity, because they are symptomatic of what is still more to be
                    pitied. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not by you, <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref>, that a monument to <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">your brother</ref> should be erected. His works are his monument, and you have done your
                    part in preserving them. Leave it to others to do themselves honour by thus honouring him. He will, perhaps, have one at
                    Nottingham before Chatterton has at Bristol.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A statue to Chatterton&#8217;s memory was placed in
                        St Mary Redcliffe churchyard, Bristol. A bronze bust of Kirke White is located in the colonnade of Nottingham castle.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My opinion respecting the affairs of Spain remains unshaken. Every blunder which it is possible to commit our
                    ministry and our generals have committed, and, I suppose, will continue to commit: if, however, they will but (as <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> says, in a letter which I lately received from him,) &#8216;fight on like
                    mastives, &#8211; boldly, blindly, and faithfully,&#8217; even that will do.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott wrote to Southey:
                        &#8216;Alas! we want everything but courage and virtue in this desperate contest. Skill, knowledge of mankind, ineffable
                        unhesitating villany, combination of movement and combination of means, are with our adversary. We can only fight like
                        mastiffs, boldly, blindly, and faithfully&#8217;; see Walter Scott to Robert Southey, 14 January 1809, <title>The Letters of Sir
                            Walter Scott</title>, ed. Sir Herbert Grierson, 12 vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), II, p. 151.</note> We have only to keep the
                    field till the Spaniards have been beaten with soldiers, as they were at Buenos Ayres;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        British invasions of the Spanish territories around the R&#237;o de la Plata took place between 1806 and 1807 when Spain was an
                        ally of France. Buenos Aires was occupied by the British for 46 days in 1806 before they were forced to retreat; in 1807
                        another British force was repulsed when the citizens defended their town from rooftops and behind barricades.</note> they are
                    a slow nation, but of unconquerable perseverance. Meantime, the temporary success of Bonaparte will end in good, because he is
                    abolishing the Inquisition, and other grievances, which it might not have been easy for the Patriotic Government to abolish, but
                    which certainly they will not renew.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That &#8216;Life of Sydney&#8217; is indeed a meagre book.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas
                        Zouch (1737&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 224&#8211;235.</note> I have been reviewing it very gently, because, as we are
                    never compelled either to buy a book or to read one, the public ought to be obliged to every person who takes the pains to write
                    even a bad one for their use, provided there be no evil in it. Dr. Z. is a bigot in all things; there is nothing so pestilential
                    to my feelings as the fog of bigotry in which all our cathedral establishments are enveloped. Enthusiasm has the glory of the sun
                    to kindle up mists and clouds with beauty; fanaticism has thunders, and lightning, and meteors in its darkness; but bigotry,
                    especially that which is found about deans and chapters, is like one of your London fogs. Dr. Z. is bigoted in his religion,
                    bigoted in his politics, bigoted in his taste. His very admiration of Sydney is bigotry, for by his censure of the &#8216;Arcadia&#8217; he
                    proves that he has not the slightest perception of Sydney&#8217;s real excellence.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Philip
                        Sidney (1554&#8211;1586; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Countess of Pembroke&#8217;s Arcadia</title> (1590).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have lately been much delighted with the &#8216;African Memoranda&#8217; of Captain Beaver: it is the history of the
                    disastrous settlement, Bulama, where Beaver himself did all that it was possible for man to do, and, I believe, more than it would
                    have been possible for any other man in the world to have done.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip Beaver (1766&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, who in 1791 participated in a scheme for colonizing the island of Bulama, near Sierra
                        Leone. The scheme failed and he returned in 1794, publishing his Bulama experiences in <title>African Memoranda</title>
                        (1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I have a pretty frequent correspondence with the printers; for &#8216;Thalaba&#8217; is reprinting at
                        Edinburgh,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801) was published in 1809. It was printed by <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref>.</note> and
                    my &#8216;History of Brazil&#8217; is in the press at London.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810. The printer was <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">William
                            Pople</ref>.</note> I hope to finish my Hindoo poem early in the spring.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> I have also written for a Review, not yet published, nor even announced, and
                    of which I do not yet know the name, a long vindication of the Baptist Mission in Bengal, which I am about to follow, in the
                    succeeding numbers, with a view of the other missions to the South Seas, and to Africa.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794);
                        [John Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend
                            Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical
                            Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity&#8230; By a
                            Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East
                            India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the
                            British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1
                        (February 1809), 193&#8211;226. <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226. He also reviewed <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South
                            Sea Islands</title>, in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61, but a review by Southey of the
                        African missions was never written.</note> Remember me kindly to <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>