<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1412</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2534</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 20768.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        467&#8211;469.Manuscript note: No address sheet &#8211; text is from a typed copy of the letter.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1412" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1412" type="letter">
        <head>1412. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#GrahameJames">James Grahame</ref>, <date when="1808-01-04">4 January
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 20768<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        467&#8211;469.<lb />Manuscript note: No address sheet &#8211; text is from a typed copy of the letter.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry to hear so bad an account of your health. To me who in the South of England am called a West-countryman
                    it seems strange that any one should think of removing into Cumberland for the sake of climate. Yet certainly it must be a great
                    change from the bleak Edinburgh winds which I remember with a sort of shivering antipathy to the long cheerless streets of your
                    new town. Do you suffer most from cold, or from damp weather? We have more rain than they have at Penrith &#8211; but are much warmer;
                    our mountains stop the clouds which come from the coast &amp; manufacture plenty of their own &#8211; but they also screen us from
                    bitter East winds, &amp; our side of <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> is green for many weeks before that which
                    looks towards Carlisle has lost its winter covering. In our neighbourhood there is no house of the description that would suit
                    you. I am making enquiry round about, &#8211; the neighbourhood of Cockermouth would suit you best in point of climate, as neither too
                    near the sea, nor the mountains; &#8211; but any place on that side the mountains will be preferable to the Penrith side. Heartily glad
                    shall I be to have you within such a distance that you may often see <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> Lake, &amp;
                    receive ocular proof that there are times when neither pen nor pencil can convey ought but a faint idea of its awefulness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Espriella<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> is so
                    generally ascribed to me that I must console myself by the persuasion that the public had no good reason for suspecting me,
                    unknown as I am to them in any other character than that of a poet. Nothing renders England more remarkable to a Spaniard than the
                    variety of religious sects which it contains: &amp; few subjects appeal to me more worthy of attention than the aberrations of
                    human intellect upon the most momentous object which can ever employ it. You &amp; I seem to hold different opinions upon that
                    subject &#8211; &amp; our points of difference probably appear to me of less importance than they do to you. I regard those letters as
                    some of the most curious in the whole work. there is more research in them than you would imagine, &amp; if I am not mistaken some
                    valuable observations. As to my own faith I am what would have been called a Seeker in former times; &#8211; belonging to no flock yet
                    not without a shepherd. I incline to Quakerism, &amp; if the present Quakers abstained from insisting on articles of faith, &amp;
                    left those points which are not explained in the Gospel, untouched, with the same reverence as their fathers did &#8211; I should
                    perhaps call myself a Quaker. But I have no Quaker superstitions, &amp; can see their errors with a strong eye. All sects appear
                    to think unworthily of man &amp; his maker. You may recognise their opinions thro the assumed character of a thorough Papist. &#8211; As
                    for <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcote</ref> surely that such a woman can find believers is an
                    extraordinary fact in the history of the present times. <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref> the Welsh
                    Scolar is one of her four and twenty elders! Bedlam is the place for such half lunatic half-imposters because they infect others.
                    I have seen instances of the mischief Brothers did in making tradesmen leave their business &amp; their families, all that relates
                    to him &amp; Bryan<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> included sections on the visit of the copperplate engraver and religious visionary William
                        Bryan (dates unknown) to the Soci&#233;t&#233; des Illumin&#233;s d&#8217;Avignon, and of his subsequent relationship with the self-proclaimed
                        prophet Richard Brothers (1757&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>). For these sections see <ref type="l" target="/editions/southey_prophecy/">
              <title>Robert Southey and Millenarianism:
                            Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic Era</title>
            </ref>, ed. Tim Fulford.</note> is
                    written from personal knowledge. I knew Bryan &amp; heard the whole system from his own mouth, &amp; he it was who went with the
                    knife to stab Brothers &amp; told me the fact himself. The main value of the book is its thorough veracity. To the best of my
                    knowledge I have good authority for every single thing which it asserts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your opinion of the moral &amp; political opinions which pervade it, is highly gratifying to me. It is time that
                    there should be a Sect of Moral Economists in the world &amp; let you &amp; I do our best to establish it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There needed no explanation concerning the coincidence in one of your poems &amp; mine, &#8211; the passage has that
                    dissimilitude which no imitator could ever have given it. You have elsewhere noticed another such which is wrongly imputed to me
                    (unless my memory fails me) but is I believe to be found in a poem of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> upon the Princess of Wales, published many years ago in the Monthly Magazine.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s poem &#8216;On a late Connubial Rupture in High Life&#8217; was published in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 2 (September 1796), 647.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am much obliged to you for procuring Vieyra, &amp; very much
                    rejoiced at it. Have the goodness to send it by the Carlisle Coach, directed to be forwarded from Carlisle by the <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> carrier. You will be interested by the history of that Vieyra,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Viera (1608&#8211;1697), the Brazilian-born Jesuit renowned for his preaching and as the
                        architect of the Jesuit missions (Reductions) there. In his <title>History of Brazil,</title> Southey cites both Viera&#8217;s
                            <title>Todos sus Sermones y Obras diferentes que de su original Portugu&#233;s se han traducido en Castellano</title> (1734)
                        and Andr&#233; de Barros (1675&#8211;1754), <title>Vida do Apostolico Padre Antonio Vieyra da Companhia de Jesus, Chamado por
                            Grande</title> (1746).</note> &#8211; he is one of our heroes &#8211; had Popery canonized him I could have knelt before his altar. It
                    will be well for <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> if his abuse of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Jeffrey had negatively
                        reviewed Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11 (October 1807),
                        214&#8211;231.</note> does not draw down vengeance upon his head. I know a man who wants neither the power nor the inclination to
                    inflict it, &#8211; only the leisure: &#8211; &amp; who for every flea bite of his animalcular malice could repay him with a scorpion
                    sting.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I beg my remembrance to Mrs Grahame &amp; am</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours very truly,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-01-04">Jany. 4. 1808</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>