<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1506</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2628</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 86&#8211;89.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1506" type="letter">
        <head>1506. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-09-12">12 September
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 86&#8211;89.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Uncle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Men who have little to do with the Press seem to be so fond of it when they are once in, that there is no getting
                    them out of it. <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> has made a months business of what ought to have been only
                    a week; the proofs travel Heaven knows where to hunt him thro M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hammond,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably George Hammond (1763&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), a fellow diplomatist of Frere&#8217;s.</note> revises after
                    proofs &amp; cancels after revises.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Proofs of Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of
                            the Cid</title> (1808), which contained three of Frere&#8217;s translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> in an
                        appendix.</note> However I am very much &amp; very truly obliged to him, &amp; my book is greatly increased in value by his
                    communications. I look daily to see it advertised. You may have seen my old letters announced<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797), reissued in a 3rd expanded edition
                            as<title> Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title> (1808).</note> &#8211; I devoted
                    a week to the corrections, weeding them with righteous relentlessness, &amp; inserting such pertinent matter of fact &amp;
                    antiquity as the books at hand supplied. A supplementary chapter about the Bierzo will show you what we lost by not halting a day
                    or two at Villafranca &amp; Ponferrada. But I live in hopes to see Spain &amp; Portugal once more, &amp; go where I will to know
                    what is to be looked for in the neighbourhood. Landor is gone as a volunteer among the Spaniards.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, who is acquainted with my old schoolfellow <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, has been talking to him upon the fitness of my being sent to
                    Spain, to write the history of what is going on there; &#8211; &amp; the first intimation I had of this was that he had undertaken to
                    speak about it to <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frere had been Britain&#8217;s ambassador to Portugal while Southey&#8217;s uncle
                        had lived there; from 1808&#8211;1809 he was ambassador to Spain.</note> I have no wish to go, especially for that specific purpose,
                    having history enough in prospect; &#8211; but if an offer were made me which it would be expedient to accept, the desire of seeing the
                    country once more, &amp; of picking up books would induce me to go I believe, great as the sacrifice would be of departing from
                    home. There is little probability that any thing will come of this, nor am I desirous that it should. Yet if any thing
                    advantageous should be offered, my own comforts shall not stand in the way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made a discovery which would interest Lord Somerville<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        distant relation by marriage John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; the
                    Duke of Bedford,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). It
                        was, however, his father, Francis Russell, 5th Duke of Bedford (1765&#8211;1802) who was famed as a sheep breeder and member of the
                        Board of Agriculture.</note> &#8211; that the merino sheep were originally exported from England. Here is the passage, which occurs
                    in the Centon Epistolario del Bachelles Fernan Gomez de Cibdareal. Ep. 73.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter in
                        question was one of one hundred written by the personal physician of John II (1405&#8211;1454), King of Castile from 1406 to 1454.
                        The letter contains gossip about the turbulent politics of Castile at that period, and the passage in question is a debate
                        about which of two nominees should be sent to carry assurances of safe passage from the king to a third party. <title>Centon
                            Epistolario del Bachiller Fernan Gomez de Cibdareal: Y Generaciones y Semblanzas del Noble Caballero Fernan Perez de
                            Guzman</title> (1790).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two persons are quarelling before Juan 2 of Castille, &amp; one of them says in scorn que non fuera figo de juez de
                    pastores. E esto dixo por motejo, ca Juan Sanchez de Tovar deriva de Fernan Sanchez de Tovar, Juez de la Mesta e Pastoria Real. E
                    Fernan Sanchez el de Berlanga le respuso en la presencia del Rey, que bien le entendia la punta, mas que no era buen ballestrero,
                    e fablaba contra de si mesmo; ca Fernan Sanchez que a locallado ser Juez de pastores motejaba, tanto bueno como el era ca era
                    primo del aguelo del Fernan Sanchez de Berlanga, e fuera Vasallo del Rey de que se pasaba en el tiempo antes, a Richohome: e el
                    cargo de la Juzgaduria e Alcaydia de Mesta fue habido siempre de Fidalgos de honor e a Fernan Sanchez de Tovar se lo dio el Rey
                    Don Pedro, levandolo a Juan Tenorio su Repostero mayor, e su Alconera mayor, que era tan bueno como Gomez Carrillo; e que el Rey D
                    Alfonso, quando se traxeron la primera vez en las naves carracas las pecoras de Ingalaterra a Espana, principio este oficio en
                    Inigo Lopez de Orozco, de quien vienen por <del>x</del> parte de madre el mismo Pedro Laso e su padre Inigo Lopez de Mendoza; e
                    que sabido quell mesmo deriva de Juez de pastores, moteja como querra.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the letter from
                        which this passage is taken the writer reports on an incident in the never-ending upheavals of John II&#8217;s reign. It is written
                        after John II had arrested Pedro Manrique de Lara, Adelantado and second-placed counsellor in the royal council. Manrique&#8217;s
                        sons then began to stir up their followers to revolt. The King then sent for Fadrique Enriquez de Mendoza, Admiral of Castile,
                        who was an ally of the arrested Adelantado. The admiral refused to come unless the king sent a third party to make a sworn
                        oath to the Admiral that he would ensure his safe passage to and from the court. The King referred the matter to the Council.
                        The Council recommended that Gomez Carrillo should be sent to the Admiral. The King had named Juan Sanchez de Tovar. A debate
                        ensued as to which of the two men should go, particularly involving Fernan Sanchez el de Berlanga and Pedro Laso de Mendoza,
                        who were related to one another. Pedro Laso said in the King&#8217;s presence that Gomez Carrillo was a son of a royal doncel [a man
                        who began serving as a royal page and then passed into the military amongst whom the donceles were a corps with certain
                        privileges] and grandson of the cup-bearer of King Enrique, connected to Lope de Carrillo &#8211; a doncel and master of the hunt
                        for King John I &#8211; and that he [here begins the passage quoted by Southey:] &#8216;was certainly not descended from a judge of
                        shepherds. This was said because Juan Sanchez de Tovar is descended from Fernan Sanchez de Tovar, judge of la Mesta &#233; Pastor&#237;a
                        Real. [The Spanish Honrado Concejo de la Mesta/ Honored Council of the Mesta was a powerful association of sheepbreeders and
                        shepherds in the medieval Kingdom of Castile.] And Fernan Sanchez el de Berlanga answered him, in the presence of the king,
                        that he understood by the point that he was not a good crossbow man and spoke against him thus. That the Fernan Sanchez who he
                        was censuring by identifying him as a judge of shepherds was also a cousin of the grandfather of Fernan Sanchez de Berlanga,
                        who was a royal vassal and had become a wealthy man: and the offices of the courts of the Mesta were always held by honourable
                        gentlemen but the King Don Pedro had given this office to Fernan Sanchez de Tovar, raising him to offices in the royal house
                        including that of his chief falconer, which was just as good as Gomez Carillo; and when the carracks brought the sheep first
                        from England, the King Don Alfonso, first conferred this office on Inigo Lopez de Orozco, from whom the mother of the same
                        Pedro Laso is in tenth part descended and his father Inigo Lopez de Mendoza; and the same is descended from a juez de
                        pastores&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Which Alfonso is meant I do not know, perhaps I shall be able to hunt it out.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alfonso XI (1311&#8211;1350), King of Castile, Le&#243;n and Galicia.</note> The fact is curious because it seems to
                    prove that the quality of the wool has been affected by the climate, &amp; that consequently a few generations in this country
                    will bring <del>xxxx</del> &lt;these sheep&gt; back to what they originally were.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Paper will now fall in price, since the ports of Holland are open for exportation. This revolution in Spain has so
                    effectually destroyed Bonapartes plans of war upon our commerce, that he will probably let things <del>xxxx xxx</del> fall into
                    their old course as soon as he decently can do it. I have scarcely a fair weeks work to come to the Acclamation,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The acclamation in 1640 of Joam IV (1603&#8211;1656), as King of Portugal and the Algarves.</note>
                    &amp; the volume<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note>
                    had perhaps better conclude with the subsequent treaty. This is my idle season, when I see friends, acquaintances &amp; strangers,
                    boat about on the Lake, &amp; lay in exercise &amp; health <del>for</del> to last me during my long <hi rend="ital">hybernation.</hi> If it were possible to get to Lisbon, I would forego the advantage of earlier publication for the sake of
                    seeing Anchietas grammar,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was eventually sent a copy from Brazil of this book:
                        Joseph de Anchieta (1534&#8211;1597), <title>Arte de Grammatica da Lingoa mais usada na Costa do Brasil</title> (1595).</note> &amp;
                    getting the Life of Almeida,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos (1596&#8211;1671), <title>Vida do Padre
                            Joam d&#8217;Almeida da Companhia de Jesu, na Provincia do Brazil</title> (1658).</note> &#8211; his life ought to furnish some
                    account of the first migration to Paraguay, &amp; of the first descent of the Aymares, a dreadful race of savages who are
                    described in your <del>MSS</del>. MS. of Ribeiro<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Xavier Ribeiro Sampaio
                        (1741&#8211;1812?), colonial official, wrote a manuscript <title>Di&#225;rio da Viagem que em Visita e Correi&#231;&#227;o das Povoa&#231;&#245;es da Capitania de S. Jos&#233; do Rio Negro Fez o Ouvidor e Intendente Geral da Mesma, no Ano de 1774 e 1775</title> (1775).</note> as <del>xxxx</del> frequently desolating the
                    settlements on the S of the Orellana, &amp; <del>on</del> the great rivers on that side. Muris, he calls them, but they must be
                    the same people. One volume of your Relacam Annual<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit Relations of their missions
                        in South America, published annually from 1632 in Latin, French and Italian. On the Aymores see volume 1 of the <title>History
                            of Brazil</title> (1810), p. 378.</note> gives the best account of them; &#8211; Every thing we want will now be turning out at
                    Lisbon, &amp; I verily believe as mere matter of speculation it would answer to go over &amp; buy <del>xxx</del> books to make an
                    auction of in London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ought long ere this to have had your large <del>copies</del> paper copies, &amp; with them, Whites
                        Remains.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had arranged for Hill to be sent the new 1808 edition of his 1797
                            <title>Poems</title>, the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800), and <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of
                            Nottingham</title> (1807); see Southey to Herbert Hill, 9 August 1808, Letter 1488.</note> His tutor M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Catton<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Catton (1758&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), tutor of St John&#8217;s
                        College, Cambridge, praised in Southey&#8217;s <title>Remains</title> for his fatherly solicitude towards White.</note> dined with
                    me yesterday. You would be surprized to know how much credit I have got for that book, &amp; how many friends it has made me. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Catton talks of putting up a tablet to his memory. He had no notion how deeply the poor fellow was infected
                    with Calvinism till his letters appeared, &amp; has no doubt that it contributed to wear him out, &amp; hastened his end. What is
                    to stop this dry rot in the Establishment!</p>
        <p>&#8211; It appears by the Old Spanish Poems that their pronunciation had none of those sounds which now distinguish it from the
                    Portugueze. It is curious how they should have adopted them. Ximena for instance is spelt with Sc instead of X. &amp; the <hi rend="ital">ll</hi> is unknown.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I more than half wish that the Factory<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1792&#8211;1807 Hill had been
                        chaplain to the British factory at Lisbon.</note> may take you back with them, &amp; that I may get something to take me over
                    with you &amp; settle me there.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-09-12">Sept. 12. 1808</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>