<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.929</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2051</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 56.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 273&#8211;275 [in part; minus
                        postscript].Dating note: year from JR&#8217;s endorsement</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.929" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="929" type="letter">
        <head>929. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-04-29">29 April
                        [1804]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ Ap. 29:/ 1804<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 56<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 273&#8211;275 [in part; minus
                        postscript].<lb />Dating note: year from JR&#8217;s endorsement</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>Bonaparte</del> &lt;The Grand Consul&gt; may be Emperor of the Gauls<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; First Consul 1799&#8211;1804; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814).</note> &#8211; but I say that the Grand
                    Parleur is Emperor of the Franks.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A jokey reference to <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>, the Speaker of the House of Commons. Rickman, who was his
                        secretary, extended his right to frank letters to Southey.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> ______</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have waited too long to tell you that I am not coming yet, &amp; yet you will excuse me for having so long waited
                    when it was probable that every day would give me cause to write. Indoors we are just as we were a month ago, save that the curst
                    March winds are over &amp; we can be very comfortable by the fireside at night. &amp; at the window by day. However <del>if this
                        be no strange deviation from the ordinary course of nature a few days must lighten <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> of her load</del>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Southeys&#8217; second child, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, was born on 30 April 1804.</note>
          <del>&amp;</del> I <del>will
                        then</del> give you <del>quit</del> notice enough to prorogue my coming should it not be convenient, &#8211; for my delay amounts to
                    a fair forfeiture &#8211; &amp; when you offered me a bed in April &#8211; you may have needed the reversion for somebody else in May. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Meantime I have transcribed the first part of Madoc for the Press,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem
                            <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in
                        1805.</note> &amp; done as much towards my specimens<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, jointly edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
                            Bedford</ref> and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807.</note> as can be done from
                    accessible materials. At this I have been working hard, &amp; having now finished, return to my old Monks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I conceived of a book the other day. <del>xx</del> the main &amp; sole object of it is utility. nothing more than
                    to collect what I can remember &amp; what I shall read that can be of any practical use, or is fit subject for experiment or
                    speculation. to arrange the facts under different heads, &amp; comment upon them when they require any comment that I can bestow,
                    &amp; so furnish hints <del>for</del> to cooks &amp; chymists, Physicians &amp; Philosophers.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early reference to the project that culminated in Southey&#8217;s and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge&#8217;s</ref> jointly authored volume <title>Omniana; or Horae
                            Otioisiores</title> (1812).</note> taking however due care that some wiser eye than my own oversee the manuscript &amp;
                    hunt out such gross blunders as would be very likely to creep in.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Alexander the Great went down into the sea in a glass case to see the wonders of the deep. I have found this in an
                    old Spanish romance,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The romance was the <title>Libro de Alexandre</title>, a Spanish epic
                        poem written between 1178 and c.1250. It is attributed to several authors, including Joan Lorenzo Segura de Astorga (dates
                        unknown). Southey refers to this work in <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, Book 11. See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works
                            1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, pp. 304&#8211;306.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> found it before me in an old German one,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In the German epic poem <title>Alexanderlied</title>, which was composed in the twelfth century by Lamprecht (der Pfaffe [the Priest]).</note> &amp; in all probability it will be found in Adam Davies poem.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803), the English version
                        of the collection of stories and legends which originally appeared in Greek between AD 200&#8211;300 and is attributed to
                        Pseudo-Callisthenes &#8211; the <title>Romance of Alexander</title> &#8211; was ascribed to Adam Davy (fl. early 14th century). Davy,
                        author of a verse account of five prophetic dreams (in Bodleian MS Laud misc. 622) described himself as &#8216;Adam, the marshal&#8217; of
                        &#8216;Stratford-atte-bowe&#8217; (London) (<title>DNB</title>). The story of the diving bell does appear in the
                        <title>Romance</title>.</note> for all old fictions are cosmopolitan. But is this only mere fiction, or had they in the
                    Romancers days any second sight of the diving bell? Roger Bacon can answer the question, either by <del>xx xxx xxxxxxxx</del> his
                    Brazen Head or his <hi rend="ital">Opus Majus</hi>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In fact the use of the diving bell
                        had been known since classical times: it is discussed by Aristotle (384&#8211;322 BC) in his <title>Problemata</title>. It is also
                        described by Roger Bacon (c.1220&#8211;92) in <title>Frier Bacon his Discovery of the Miracles of Art, Nature, and Magick Faithfully
                            Translated out of Dr. Dees Own Copy by T.M. and Never Before in English</title> (London, 1659), p. 18 (a translation of
                            <title>De Mirabili Potestate Artis et Naturae</title> (1542)), who notes that Alexander used one. Bacon&#8217;s brazen head was
                        a mechanical device supposedly able to give answers to any questions asked of it; his <title>Opus Majus</title> was written in
                        1267 and published in 1733.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My eyes continue weak &#8211; I suspect from general debility &#8211; for when I take steel they mend, &amp; when I leave it
                    off they become blood-shot, &amp; the lids discharge. the sight of one is certainly much weaker than the other. objects which are
                    distinct to the other become quite dim to that. <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> must put me in tune or in
                    tone. Man is an <hi rend="ital">organic</hi> being, &amp; as long as the bellows are not out of order, I shall not mind a little
                    relaxation of the strings.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-04-29">April 29. Sunday.</date>
          </p>
          <p>
            <del>I should not have inclosed that letter of <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Frickers</ref> had we then known
                            any other direction it was breach of principles on my part</del>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>