<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1098</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2220</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1098" type="letter">
        <head>1098. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-08-26">26 August 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ AUG29/ 1805<lb />Endorsement:
                        26 Aug 1805<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-08-26">Monday. Aug. 26. 1805</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Many are the reasons, &amp; as weighty as they are manifold which have prevented me from answering your letter. it
                    may suffice to mention one &#8211; that within the last five weeks I have walked between 4 &amp; 500 miles. I am in search of Relph,
                    &amp; have been disappointed in finding him where he ought to have been found, but now point by point to your letter.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Josiah Relph (1712&#8211;1743; <title>DNB</title>): a Cumberland poet who published <title>A Miscellany
                            of Poems</title> (1747; 2nd edn 1798). He features in Southey&#8217;s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3
                        vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 418&#8211;429. In his letter Southey is advising Bedford on the collection and transcription of texts
                        for inclusion in this jointly edited publication.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Certainly I never saw the Topographica Britannica,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Bibliotheca Topographica Britannica</title> appeared in fifty-two numbers between 1780 and 1790. It was a collaborative
                        publishing project undertaken by the antiquarian Richard Gough (1735&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), and the printer and publisher,
                        John Nichols (1745&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), to publicize antiquities and sites of historic interest.</note> but should
                    conjecture that the specimen of Wesley<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Wesley (&#8216;the younger&#8217;) (1690/91&#8211;1739;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was a Church of England clergyman and poet. His poetry is included in <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, I, pp. 369&#8211;375.</note> would be found by referring there to the place of his birth &#8211; Epworth in
                    Lincolnshire.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Millers specimen I myself looked out at <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Hills</ref>, from some satire
                    published separately &amp; bound up with other miscellanies.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Miller (1704&#8211;1744;
                            <title>DNB</title>), playwright and satirist who features in the <title>Specimens</title>, II, pp. 21&#8211;33.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And for Sheffields Epitaph &#8211; do you suppose that I wanted to give it as he wrote it? or as the Dean thought proper
                    to correct it? The words omitted are precisely those which mark the Dukes sentiment &amp; character of mind.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Sheffield, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Normanby (1647&#8211;1721; <title>DNB</title>), politician
                        and author who is included in the <title>Specimens</title>, I, 219&#8211;222. Southey is complaining that Bedford has omitted, from
                        the Duke&#8217;s epitaph for his own tomb, the words &#8216;Christum adveneror&#8217; (&#8216;venerator of Christ&#8217;); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford, 26 July 1805, Letter 1086. Bedford had copied the inscription as it appeared on Buckingham&#8217;s monument, rather than as
                        originally written. According to William Betham, <title>The Baronetage of England: or The History of the English
                            Baronets</title>, 5 vols (London, 1801&#8211;1805), III, 251, &#8216;the words, &#8220;Christum adveneror,&#8221; are omitted, at the desire, as
                        is said, of bishop Atterbury, who thought the verb <hi rend="ital">adveneror</hi> not full enough, as applied to Christ. Great
                        clamours were raised against this epitaph, many asserting that it proved the Duke a sceptic; and as great a trifle as it may
                        seem, his grace&#8217;s orthodoxy became the subject of a controversy: it was, however, defended in form by Dr. Fiddes, in &#8220;A Letter
                        to a Freethinker,&#8221; 1721&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Send me the names of the 80 because it is very likely that I may be shortly at Edinburgh, &amp; there I would look
                    for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps I may get Relph to day &#8211; at least there is now a person seeking it for me in Keswick. As soon as it comes I
                    shall transcribe the extract, &amp; you may correct the press from it confidently, because as <del>the</del> it will be in the
                    Cumbrian dialect I shall take especial care to be accurate. Add any thing you like to his biography, his religion was of too
                    ascetic a cast certainly &#8211; but he was a good &amp; an interesting man &#8211; The book is come &#8211; I fell to &amp; have transcribed
                    without a minutes delay &lt;a full&gt; <del>xxx</del> sheet <del>xxx xxxxxx</del> Add to the account that the character as well as
                    the imagery of the Cumbrian pastorals were from real life &#8211; there was hardly a person in the village who could not point out those
                    who had sate for his Cursty &amp; Peggy.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Characters in Relph&#8217;s poem &#8216;Hay-time, or the
                        Constant Lovers&#8217;, <title>Specimens</title>, I, pp. 420&#8211;424.</note> The Amorous Maiden was well known, &amp; died a few years
                    ago at a very advanced age.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The subject of Relph&#8217;s poem &#8216;St. Agnes&#8217;s Fast, or the Amorous
                        Maiden&#8217;, <title>Specimens</title>, I, 424&#8211;427.</note> &#8211; You may remark if you please that his poems have not the slightest
                    indication of his ascetic disposition,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s additions to Relph&#8217;s biography were
                        included, see <title>Specimens</title>, I, p. 419.</note> &#8211; &amp; you may insert the epigrams or not, according as there shall
                    be room or not in the last page.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> An epigram was included. See <title>Specimens</title>, I,
                        p. 429.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford &#8211; look at p236. &amp; tell me whether the name on the top is an error &#8211; or the whole
                    page out of place? &#8211; what a beautiful extract is that from the Countess of Winchelsea!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Anne Finch (n&#233;e Kingsmill), Countess of Winchilsea (1661&#8211;1720), courtier and poet who features in the
                        <title>Specimens</title>, I, pp. 223&#8211;226.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Little did you think when you spoke so freely of the Colonel in your letter that the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref> himself was to frank
                    it! &#8211; I never had the pleasure of receiving his superscription before.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Government have thought proper to appropriate all the Spanish prizes taken before a certain day to indemnify the
                    merchants whose property has been confiscated in Spain. I am trying to make a noise about this in the Courier, &#8211; because by this
                        <del>xxxx</del> unprecedented measure my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> loses 2000&#163;, a tax a little
                    too hard upon an individual.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804, the naval ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas Southey was a lieutenant, had captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and
                        the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden
                        with cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed
                        conflict, but this award of prize money was contested because it was claimed that the ships were captured before war was
                        officially declared. Southey took up his brother&#8217;s cause to have his share reinstated. It was presumably Southey&#8217;s influence
                        that caused <title>The Courier</title> to publish a paragraph supporting the sailors&#8217; claim to the prize-money on Saturday 24
                        August 1805. This was followed by a longer defence of their position in <title>The Courier</title> on 31 August 1805 under the
                        title &#8216;Indemnification to the Spanish Merchants&#8217;.</note> It is not impossible but the measure may be given up if the matter be
                    taken up strongly &amp; decorously in the newspapers. I beg you will admire my policy in chusing a ministerial paper &#8211; &amp; allow
                    that I am beginning to know something of the way of the world.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did you ever discover the cause of the Butlers prolapsus?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> There are
                        several jokey references to &#8216;Butler&#8217; in Southey&#8217;s letters to Bedford. These comic inventions, originating in schoolboy stories
                        at Westminster, were never published by Bedford but provided the hint for Southey&#8217;s comic novel/miscellany <title>The
                            Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> &#8211; Nature instead of a <hi rend="ital">colon</hi>, had only given him a <hi rend="ital">comma</hi>, &amp; that stop was not long enough.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want to frank up the Relphian sheet. <del>x</del> how is this to be done? for <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is God knows where &amp; so is <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; the Emperor of the Franks.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Speaker of the House of Commons,
                            <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>, who had the power to frank mail, a power Rickman, his
                        secretary, used on Southey&#8217;s behalf.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a world of business to do, &#8211; &amp; my time day after day is taken up by some dropper in or other, &#8211; for
                    every body seems to come to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. my review-shelf is so full that I groan in spirit at
                    the prospect of so much labour. The life of Leo is among them<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de&#8217;
                            Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467.</note> &#8211; I have just found time to read it &#8211; with sufficient pleasure. <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoes</ref> mind is <del>xx</del> truly pure &amp; all his feelings <del>xxx</del>
                    instinctively right. his chapters on the Reformation are therefore the finest that I have yet seen on that subject. The literary
                    chapters are rather curious &amp; useful than interesting. mere critical characters in general language lay little hold on the
                    memory. analysis &amp; specimens are wanting &#8211; &amp; for these there was not room.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for seeing me in London &#8211; if I come it will be your fault, &amp; I shall be sorry for it, neither liking the
                    trouble nor the expence of the journey nor the fatigue of seeing my thousand &amp; one acquaintances. Neither in fact can I
                    without great &#8211; a really serious inconvenience, spare the time &#8211; for my sixth journey with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> will leave me little time enough for all that I have to do. My removal seems adjourned sine die,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;without a date&#8217;.</note> &#8211; unless I can recover <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> prize money.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> My eyes are miserably weak.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>