<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1388</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2510</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D..  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    30&#8211;33.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1388" type="letter">
        <head>1388. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-12-03">3
                        December 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W WilliamsWynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        M. P./ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    30&#8211;33.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> arrived in the convoy, &#8211; &amp; this is all I know about him, for by a
                    mistake sufficiently provoking he directed to me a letter of business which was written to some person at Falmouth. It is by no
                    means unlikely that I may shortly set out to meet him in London, this of course depends upon his movements.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am a <hi rend="ital">little</hi> surprized at the charge of irreverence. Few men have more of what Hartley<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> David Hartley (1705&#8211;1757; <title>DNB</title>) employs the concept of theopathy in
                            <title>Observations on Man, his Frame, his Duty, and his Expectations</title> (1749).</note> calls theopathy in their
                    nature than I have: few men have a firmer faith in the truths of Christianity. There is nothing more in quoting scripture in such
                    a case as that of Ossian than there is in quoting any other book.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Letter 19 of
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) Southey has his
                        narrator regret that popular preachers indulge in trite moralising rounded off with a quotation from scripture or from
                        Ossian.</note> &#8211; As for the Rabbinical story I found it in a Catholick writer (Feyjos<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library lists Benito Jer&#243;nimo Feyj&#243;o y Montenegro (1676&#8211;1764), <title>Obras</title> (1769).
                        Letter 63 of <title>Epriella</title> discusses the Jews in England and their beliefs.</note>) &#8211; &amp; to a Catholick I gave
                    it: &amp; surely Espriella is in no danger of the Inquisition for repeating what had been told by the General of the Benedictines.
                    &#8211; The book sells. 700 are gone &amp; the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> think it probable that it must be
                    reprinted in a few weeks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On the duty of spreading Christianity you know my opinions &#8211; which perfectly coincide with your own. My
                        <del>religious</del> views of religion approach very nearly to Quakerism, as the Annual Review may perhaps have led you to
                    suspect. The Quakers err in prohibiting things which it is sufficient to despise; &#8211; they err in their principle of preaching; &#8211;
                    &amp; their conduct about tythes is foolish &amp; troublesome. &#8211; Their opinions concerning war go against the instinct of self
                    defence; &#8211; just now that sort of religion which the Maccabees held upon this subject is more called for;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">In the Bible the Books of Maccabees set out a series of moral limitations upon the conduct of war: these include making war only in self-defence and by legitimate authority, sparing women and the survivors of sieges.</note> &#8211; there can however be no
                    question but that the Quaker system were it general would produce the greatest possible good; it never can spread so rapidly as to
                    lay any part of the world at the feet of a conqueror, &#8211; &amp; if it were not for Bonaparte I should have with little hesitation in
                    declaring my conviction that it is the true system of the gospel. &#8211; that is my reason is convinced, but I want to have the
                    invasion over before I allow it to be so. Their morality is perfect. I should not have agreed with George Fox<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1624&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>), founder of the Society of Friends.</note> if he had made his
                    creed, &#8211; but I entirely agree with him in reverentially abstaining from attempting to define what has been left indefinite, &amp;
                    in rejecting all those disputed terms which are not to be found in the scriptures, &#8211; not as false, but as not being there &amp; as
                    unnecessary provocations to disputes &amp; doubts. Were there a meeting in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> I
                    should silently take a seat in it, but I should not alter my language nor my dress, &#8211; should pay my Easter dues, &#8211; &amp; stand in
                    no fear of a pack of cards. Did you ever read Sir Th. Brownes Religio Medici?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas
                        Browne (1605&#8211;1682; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Religio Medici</title> (1643), a rambling discussion of Browne&#8217;s faith which
                        contained so many unorthodox views that it was placed on the Papal Index of proscribed books.</note> &#8211; if ever I can afford to
                    write what I should not think it prudent <del>x</del> to publish, it will be the Religio Poetae.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Overtures have been made me to write in the Edinburgh Review. They came thro <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref>, who takes some pains to satisfy me of <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> &#8216;high
                    consideration&#8217; &amp; tells me I may &lt;add&gt; one or even two hundred a year to my income, chusing my own books &amp; expressing
                    my own opinions.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s letter to Scott regarding this offer, see Southey to Walter
                        Scott, 8 December 1807, Letter 1392.</note> It so happens that I have no opinions in common with that Review &#8211; I am greatly in
                    hopes that it may not be necessary for me to review at all after this year. &#8211; It is work which I abominate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> had no copy of M. Arthur<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas Malory (1415/18&#8211;1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Morte d&#8217;Arthur</title>. Southey was planning an
                        edition, about which he had written to Heber; see Southey to Richard Heber, 16 November 1807, Letter 1379.</note> when I
                    talked to him once about it, &amp; foolishly enough never thought how likely it is that he should have got one since. &#8211; I have not
                    asked the question.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is a nursery story for <ref target="people.html#WynnMary">Mrs Wynn</ref>. A little boy asked his nurse at
                    dinner for some potatoes. &#8216;Ask for them properly Master Wilson &amp; you shall have them. &#8211; Some potatoes if you please Nurse. &#8211;
                    Ask for them properly Sir, &#8211; Why I do ask for them properly, &#8211; some potatoes if you please. &#8211; It&#8217;s not potatoes Sir. &#8211; why yes
                    Nurse it is potatoes &#8211; No Sir &#8211; its peetatoes. &#8211; Why I am sure Nurse it is potatoes. &#8211; my mother has been teaching me this very
                    morning &amp; spell the word &#8211; p-o-po-t-a-ta-t-o-e-s-toes-p&#333;tatoes. Poo! Sir &#8211; its not p&#333;tatoes I tell you &#8211; theres nothing p&#333; but
                    p&#333;rkay &#8211; Literally true.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The minutiae in Esprella are impertinent to English readers at this time. If the book gets abroad they are not so
                    now, &#8211; &amp; if it be read at home half a century hence they will have ceased to be so. We forget how these things are continually
                    changing. &#8211; All this too is information in America. &#8211; I shall bring him to England again, &amp; endeavour to leave a compleat
                    picture of the present state of society <del>here</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am applied to to bear a part in the British Biography<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of
                        the <title>Biographia Britannica</title> was published from 1778&#8211;1793 but was left incomplete on the death of its compiler
                        Andrew Kippis (1725&#8211;1795; <title>DNB</title>). On 8 February 1808 a fire in a printer&#8217;s office destroyed the continuation to
                        which Southey had been asked to contribute.</note> &#8211; if I do anything it will not be till late in the work. &#8211; George Fox &#8211;
                        W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Penn<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1644&#8211;1718; <title>DNB</title>), Quaker leader and founder
                        of Pennsylvania.</note> &#8211; Wesley<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>): Southey
                        would publish a biography of him in 1820.</note> &amp; Whitefield<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Whitefield
                        (1714&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), Calvinistic Methodist leader.</note> are all that I feel solicitous to biographize. The two
                    former lives would include a history of Quakerism, the two latter that of Methodism Wesley is destined to hold as distinguished a
                    place in history as Loyola.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ignatius of Loyola (1491&#8211;1556), founder of the
                        Jesuits.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-12-03">Dec.3.1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>