<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1275</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2397</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1275" type="letter">
        <head>1275. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1807-02-13">13
                        February 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey &#8211;/ 11.
                        Craven Street/ Strand <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your news from the New Jerusalem,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Henry to
                        visit the Swedenborgian New Jerusalem church and report on what he witnessed for use in <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807); see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 17 January
                        1807, Letter 1260. The church was in York Street, St James Square, and was led by the Rev. Joseph Proud (1745&#8211;1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> which is all I wanted &#8211; except an account of the Preachers costume. This I have heard is very
                    splendid, but am inclined to think my information must be inaccurate as you do not mention it. Let me know, &amp; the sooner the
                    better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The letter which I wrote to <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> about the Hospital must surely
                    have miscarried.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter has not been traced. Southey had suggested that Carlisle
                        might have been able to assist Henry in finding a position at one of the London hospitals; see Southey to Henry Herbert
                        Southey, 17 January 1807, Letter 1260.</note> I thought it very strange &amp; very unlike him &#8211; that no answer should have
                    been returned; &#8211; but as he has not spoken about it to you am almost certain it can never have reached him. This is very awkward. &#8211;
                    However as things are you may perhaps as well make what use of Davids dispensary you can for a few weeks. Write to Lisbon &amp;
                    say you are ready to come over, <del>xxx</del> &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> in his answer will
                    I suppose supply you with means.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You should make haste with your reviewing &#8211; Johnes is just done &#8211; two evenings will finish Clarkson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) translated Sir John Froissart&#8217;s <title>Chronicles
                            of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry
                            IV</title> (1804) and the <title>Memoirs of John Lord de Joinville, Grand Seneschal of Champagne Written by
                            Himself</title> (1807). The book was reviewed in <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 215&#8211;219. Southey
                        reviewed Thomas Clarkson, <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar
                            Customs, Religious Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title> (1806), in
                    the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 594&#8211;607.</note> &amp; two after that, all that remains.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">As well as Clarkson's book, Southey reviewed the following in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to Cochin China, in the Years 1792, and 1793: Containing a General View of the
                            Productions, and Political Importance of this Kingdom; and also of such European Settlements as were Visited on the
                            Voyage, with Sketches of the Manners, Character, and Condition of their Inhabitants</title> (1806), 2&#8211;16; James Burney,
                        <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title>
                        (Vol. 2; 1806), 16&#8211;30; James Stanier Clarke (1765?&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of
                            Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 2; 1806), 71&#8211;72; <title>Report of the British and Foreign Bible Society</title> (1805), 155&#8211;160;
                        Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A New and Appropriate System of Education for the Labouring
                            People</title> (1806), 278&#8211;282; John Wooll (bap. 1767&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of the late
                                Revd. Joseph Warton, Master of St. Mary Winton College; Prebendary of Winchester Cathedral; and Rector of the Parishes of
                                Wickham and Upham, Hants: to which are added, a Selection from his Works; and a Literary Correspondence Between Eminent
                                Persons, Reserved by him for Publication</title> (1806), 298&#8211;305; Lucy Hutchinson (<title>n&#233;e</title> Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681;
                        <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title>
                        (1806), 361&#8211;378; James Grant Raymond (1771&#8211;1817), <title>The Life of Thomas Dermody</title> (1806), 383&#8211;397; Henry Richard
                        Fox, 3rd Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Life and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1806), 397&#8211;411;
                        Richard Duppa, <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806),
                        411&#8211;425; George Chalmers, (bap. 1742&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Sir David Lyndsay</title>
                        (1806), 482&#8211;494; Thomas Moore (1779&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epistles, Odes and Other Poems</title> (1806), 498&#8211;499;
                        [Society of Friends of Pennsylvania], <title>Accounts of Two Attempts Towards the Civilization of Some Indian Natives</title>
                        (1806), 589&#8211;593; Thomas Clarkson, <title>A Portraiture of Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline,
                            Peculiar Customs, Religious Principles, Political and Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title>
                        (1806), 594&#8211;607; Thomas Jarrold (1770&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dissertations on Man, Philosophical, Physiological and
                            Political; in Answer to Mr. Malthus&#8217;s &#8216;Essay on the Principle of Population&#8217;</title> (1806), 607&#8211;615.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Counts</ref> direction is 42. Princess Street &#8211; Leicester Square. As
                    for <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> there is <del>xxx</del> it seems a sort of Revolution in <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">that family</ref>, &#8211; &amp; in addition to this <del>Horace</del> they have &lt;just&gt;
                    found out what I knew three years ago &#8211; that <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> has lost his wits &#8211; So
                    under these circumstances you may as well keep away.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> On Horace, see Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 2 February 1807, Letter 1270.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It seems likely at present that I shall make up mind to remaining in <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">this
                        house</ref> &#8211; in which case it must be finished &amp; fitted up. In this case your Lordship may yet pass another summer here
                    before you begin your campaign. I must either decide upon quitting it in about a twelvemonth or upon keeping it &#8211; the reason of
                    this is a sort of secret history which I suppose it is not yet quite decorous for me to mention &#8211; so I shall keep puss in the bag
                    a little longer.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> was about to separate from <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his wife</ref> and so was quitting <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.
                        As a consequence, Southey was forced to decide whether to leave as well or remain in the house. He chose the latter, sending
                        for his books later in the year.</note> It suits my inclinations well to feel myself rooted here &#8211; tho it would have suited my
                    uncertain prospects better to have remained ready to remove at any time. If we fix upon remaining &#8211; &amp; <del>xxx xxx</del>
                    &lt;are for&gt; determining to remove at a given time I do not see how that is to be done for lack of means &#8211; huzza then for the
                    books! I asked <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughters</ref> opinion to day &#8211; whether she liked to go &amp; live in
                    another house or to stop here, &amp; she said she would <hi rend="ital">not</hi> live in another house &#8211; &amp; I think she was
                    right &#8211; Twas a sort of cat feeling of instinctive good sense.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Don M. will be finished as soon as your friend Richard Taylor pleases.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey was sending copy for <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807) to be printed by Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I am getting on with Brazil,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> appeared in three volumes from 1810 to 1819.</note> &amp; expect
                    (God willing) to do more this year than I have ever done in any preceding one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> are both
                    well. I call him the Ca&#245;zinho &amp; the little Mayortes &#8211; who you know was the great Ca&#245; (Khan) &#8211; he is entitled to these names
                    for his Tartar eyes &#8211; &amp; because I used to call him Doggy-bow-wow.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Palmerin
                            of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>, 4 vols (London,
                        1807), I, p. 54, Mayortes is identified as the first leader to call himself the Great Khan (Gran Can), because he had once
                        been enchanted into the form of a dog. &#8216;Ca&#245;zinho&#8217; is Portuguese for &#8216;doggy&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s humorous point is that his children&#8217;s
                        eyes resembled those of central Asians.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-02-13">Friday. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 13. 1807. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>