<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1713</idno><idno type="nines">rce2835</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), III, pp. 267–269 [in part and with omissions]. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1713" type="letter"><head>1713. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-11-25">25 November
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Lyra/ <del>Plymouth
                            Dock</del> Torbay [deletion and readdress in another hand]/ Single<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), III, pp. 267–269 [in part and with omissions]. </note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1809-11-25">Nov. 25. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I write to you for two reasons, thus shortly after my last.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dated 22
                        November; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 22 November 1809, Letter 1712.</note> The one is that I may direct to the Lyra,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Lyra</hi> was a Royal Navy Cherokee class 10-gun brig-sloop, launched
                        in August 1808.</note> because all my former ones being to the Dreadnought<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was a Royal Navy 98-gun second rate ship of the line, launched in 1801, which Tom had been
                        serving on since July 1808.</note> may miss you for some time, for I <del>xxx</del> perceive by the papers that that ship is
                    come in. The other, – a more interesting one, – is to tell you that I have this day finished Kehama,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> having written above 200 lines since
                    yesterday morning. Huzza – Aballiboozobanganorribo<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A word used in Southey’s <title>The
                            Doctor</title> (1834–1847), I, p. 165, in humorous imitation of ‘certain letters of unknown signification’ in the ‘Koran’
                        (Qur’an), whose ‘commentators say that the meaning of these initials ought not to be inquired’.</note> It is not often in this
                    life that a man finishes a long poem, &amp; as I have nobody to give me joy I must give myself joy. 24 sections, 4844 lines – 2 or
                    300 will probably be added in course of correction &amp; transcription, – all has been done before breakfast (since its
                    resumption) except about 170 lines of the conclusion. Huzza! better than lying-a-bed Tom, &amp; tho I am not quite ready to begin
                    another, I will rise as usual tomorrow &amp; work at the plans of Pelayo<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This would become
                        Southey’s poem <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &amp; Robin Hood.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had begun to plan a romance on this subject in 1804; it was not until 1823 that he began drafting the
                            verse, in collaboration with Caroline Bowles (1786–1854; <title>DNB</title>). The poem remained unfinished, and was published posthumously as a fragment in an
                        edition by Bowles: <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment by the Late Robert Southey and Caroline Southey, with other Fragments and
                            Poems</title> (1847).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Now am I a little impatient that you should see the whole; &amp; shall feel another job off my hands when your copy
                    is compleated. By beginning earlier with the next poem I shall be able to keep pace with it, &amp; send it to you as fast as it
                    proceeds. I do not think you can have it in a better shape than Kehama, – it folds up so conveniently as a frank, &amp; is not
                    liable to be crumpled by the postman as it would if larger.</p><p rend="indent1"> Very few persons will relish Kehama, – every body will wonder at it, it will increase my reputation without
                    increasing my popularity. – a general remark will be what a pity that I have wasted so much power. I care little about this, –
                    having in the main pleased myself, &amp; all along amused myself. Every generation will afford me some half dozen admirers of it,
                    – &amp; the everlasting column of Dantes fame does not stand upon a wider base. – There will be a good many minor ornaments to
                    insert, the metre will in many places be enriched, &amp; the story perhaps sometimes be rendered more perspicuous. Now that the
                    whole is before me I can see where to add &amp; alter. If it receives half the improvement which Thalaba<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1st edn, 1801; 2nd edn, 1809).</note> did I shall be
                    content.</p><p rend="indent1"> Pelayo is to be in blank verse, – where the whole interest is to be derived from human character, &amp; the
                    inherent dignity of the story, I will not run the hazard of enfeebling the finer parts for the sake of embellishing the weaker
                    ones. I shall pitch Robin Hood in a different key, – such as the name would lead one to expect, a wild pastoral movement, – in the
                    same sort of plastic metre &amp; language as Garci Ferrandez.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem ‘Garci
                        Ferrandez’, published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and
                        1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837–1838).</note> I shall aim it at about 2000 lines, &amp; endeavour not to exceed
                    three.</p><p rend="indent1"> Do not have the Yankee Madoc<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> An American edition of Southey’s poem was
                        published as <title>Madoc: A Poem</title>, in Boston, Massachusetts, in 1806.</note> bound, – as it will be to be looked at
                    &amp; not to be read, it will be more curious in numbers, just as published, &amp; I will have one of <del>those</del> &lt;the&gt;
                    book-shaped boxes made to hold it, so that it may take its place in order upon the shelf. What size is it &amp; what price were
                    the numbers?</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> has been exerting himself in your behalf, &amp; got a memorial presented
                    to Ryder<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tory politician Dudley Ryder, 1st Earl of Harrowby (1762–1847;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> one of our new ministers. What he is taught to expect is that your present appointment will be
                    set aside, &amp; that an early opportunity will be taken afterward to promote you. <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir
                        G Beaumont</ref> writes me that he has been prevented from applying as yet to Ld Mulgrave<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755–1831; <title>DNB</title>): diplomatist and politician who was
                        appointed First Lord of the Admiralty in 1807.</note> because Lady M. has ever since my letter to him<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 20 October 1809, Letter 1697.</note> been in such a state that
                    her death has been apprehended from day to day. This however cannot last much longer, &amp; he will take the first proper
                    opportunity to make the application. All things considered it seems to me that you are in a fair way, <del>&amp;</del> you will be
                    superseded in the Brig, &amp; in all likelihood pass your Xmas at <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> This Register<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed the ‘History of
                        Europe’ for 1808–1810 in James Ballantyne’s <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> has occasioned me to examine some
                    part of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesleys</ref> conduct in India, which I never did before, – &amp;
                    the result is a decided disapprobation, or rather detestation of him, as a man thoroughly unprincipled. I strongly suspect also
                    that he has acquired the reputation for talents very cheaply – Whenever a Governor possesses ample power for effecting his
                    purposes, makes no calculation of human lives, &amp; scruples at no means however oppressive, base or cruel, – very little credit
                    can be due to him for succeeding. <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> is something of the
                    same stamp, a brave man (which is saying little, – for not to be so would be infamous) but of no resources of mind, utterly
                    unequal to difficult <del>&amp;</del> circumstances, &amp; as was proved by the <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>
                        business<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A British inquiry into the circumstances surrounding, and the conduct of
                        those involved in agreeing, the Convention of Cintra (1808), under the terms of which the defeated French were allowed to
                        evacuate their forces from Portugal. See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 379–381.</note>
                    absolutely incapable of feeling the strength of the cause which he was sent out to support. In short a man blind deaf &amp; dead
                    to all generous sentiments, &amp; those feelings &amp; principles by which, &amp; by which only, Europe can be redeemed. The state
                    of home politics is perfectly hopeless, there is not a man on either side who is fit to carry guts to a Bear! – or rather,
                    according to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> story, they are &lt;all&gt; fit for it. Buonaparte
                    seems thoroughly to despise all we can do, – all that we have done, he is certainly entitled to despise, but if we had
                        Marlborough<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650–1722; <title>DNB</title>),
                        victor of the battle of Blenheim.</note> or Peterborough<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Mordaunt, 3rd Earl
                        of Peterborough and 1st Earl of Monmouth (1658?–1735; <title>DNB</title>), renowned for his daring tactics in an earlier war
                        in Spain.</note> alive again, six months would close his career for ever, even now. It remains to be seen whether he despises
                    the Spaniards enough to let things go on in their present course, or if he will enter Spain again &amp; <del>xxx the</del> overrun
                    the open country. In that case there is a line of large towns between Barcelona &amp; Cadiz, along the coast, <del>that may
                        be</del> some of which may be expected to hold out like Zaragoza &amp; Gerona,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Spanish city of Zaragoza had been besieged in 1808 and 1809, when it fell to the French after a heroic defence was broken by
                        an outbreak of disease. For Southey’s accounts of the sieges, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1
                        (1810), 306–321; and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508–527. The Spanish city of Gerona had
                        been under siege by the French since 6 May 1809. After nearly seven months it finally fell on 11 December 1809.</note> which
                    we could assist by sea, &amp; which would afford opportunities for such men as Cochrane<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775–1860; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and formerly Tom Southey’s captain.
                        Cochrane gained renown through a campaign of daring and brilliantly executed raids harassing and attacking settlements on the
                        Spanish and French coasts.</note> or Sir S. Smith<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer Sir William
                        Sidney Smith (1764–1840; <title>DNB</title>), who was promoted to the rank of Admiral and received several awards for his
                        actions in the war with France, achieving a high popular reputation by 1809.</note> grievously to annoy the besiegers, –
                    indeed to cut them off, if they had a good force. There ought to be four flying squadrons of 5000 men each, ready to land wherever
                    they were wanted, – under Cochrane they would keep five times their number of French in continual alarm. The only possible hope
                    from <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M Wellesley</ref> is that he may insist upon a vigorous effort – what we are doing
                    now is just worse than nothing. Our men drink themselves to death, our officers learn to despise the Spaniards &amp; Portugueze
                    because they do not dress, eat &amp; drink like themselves, &amp; their opinions pass current here in England &amp; the
                    consequence is that never were a people so cruelly &amp; basely calumniated, as this nation, which has done more against the force
                    of France, under every possible disadvantage than all the rest of Europe conjointly. What a different story Sir Robert Wilson
                    would tell who has kept the field with his legion of Portugueze thro all the perilous season!<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Robert Thomas Wilson (1777–1849; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and colonial governor, who in 1808 was
                        given command of the Loyal Lusitanian Legion, raised from Portuguese refugees in England under British officers. In August of
                        that year he went to Portugal as a Brigadier-General in the Portuguese army, where he was responsible for training Portuguese
                        recruits and organizing them into effective fighting units. He returned to England at the end of 1809.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> has left the Courier to itself for a long time past, &amp; you see what a
                    wretched hireling <del>xxx</del> journal it is become. I think when he returns to town he will revive the accursed Walcheren
                        business<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren expedition was an unsuccessful British attempt to open another
                        front in the Netherlands in support of the Austrian Empire’s struggle with France. Approximately 40,000 soldiers with
                        supporting horses and artillery landed at Walcheren on 30 July 1809. There was little fighting but the army sustained heavy
                        losses from sickness, and in December 1809 the rest withdrew.</note> &amp; call loudly for an inquiry. This wretched
                    administration will scarcely be able to stand their ground. Unless this affair of old Collingwood<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vice Admiral Cuthbert Collingwood, 1st Baron Collingwood (1748–1810; <title>DNB</title>), who assumed command
                        of the fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar (1805) upon Nelson’s death. In October 1809 three French warships escaped the British blockade of French ports. A squadron of Collingwood’s fleet chased and drove them shorewards; on 26 October two were destroyed, one escaped to harbour.</note> prove something brilliant (as probably it will) I
                    know not how they can meet Parliament, after having so deeply injured &amp; disgraced the country.</p><p rend="indent1"> My Brazil will not be out these two months,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> – so much has <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref><del>xxx</del> delayed it. I send off a large portion of notes tomorrow. the volume will exceed 700 pages, tho I shall print notes
                    in double columns &amp; in a type which will <del>xxx</del> make each column nearly equal to a page of the Cid-notes.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> They will contain a great deal
                    of curious matter. The Bibliography must be deferred till the end of the second volume.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1817.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>