<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1476</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2598</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1476" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1476" type="letter">
        <head>1476. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1808-07-09">9 July
                        1808</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ <del>L. B. Wxxxx Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            </del> [deletions and the remainder of the address in another hand]/ <del>Staunton upon Wye</del>/
                        Staunton upon Wye/ <del>Hereford</del>/ <del>Baxxxxx</del>/ Hereford; [second address/ endorsement in another hand] The/
                        Rev<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; [partial] BASING<lb />Postmarks: [twice] JY/ B/ 18/ 1808<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I copy the whole which Brito Freyre<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco de Brito Freyre (1625&#8211;1692),
                            <title>Nova Lusitania, Historia da Guerra Brasilica</title> (1675).</note> says of Tamandar&#233;.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Surtas estava&#333; as mais &amp; as melhores embarca&#231;o&#275;s na Costa do Recife; porque em Tamandar&#233;, ao entrar dos
                    primeiros, hum pataxo (salvo a gente &amp; a carga) se perdeo sem desculpa. pelo descudo do governo; que o porto pela capacidade
                    do fundo, a todos os de Parnambuco se aventaja. Ainda que por ficar muito distante das povoa&#231;o&#275;s, he pouco frequentado dos
                    navegantes. Felo ja conhecido, a perda que nelle recebera&#333; dos Olandeses, os navios governados de Jeronymo Serra&#333; de Payva. E
                    agora elegerem &#8211; no para as tres Frotas se incorporarem com <del>x</del> a Armada. &#8211; O que pudera&#333; facilitar menos, aquelles
                    Ministros &amp; Pilotos nomeados na carta que V. Magestada mandon escrever a Francisco de Brito. Que suposto a barra &amp;
                    surgidouro tenha&#333; agoa bastante para Galleo&#275;s de alto bordo, era preciso &amp; muito difficultoso, esperarmos depois que houvesse
                    terral, onde o h&#225; raras vezes. ou sahirem &#225;s toas larga distancia, huma por huma, tantas embarca&#231;o&#275;s juntas &amp; carregadas. Pelo
                    que entre as mais que ancorara&#333; na Costa: ancoron tambem o General. &#8211; Porem, quando ja podia ser menos a tardan&#231;a do Almirante,
                    para evitale depois &amp; nos incorporarmos em elle parecendo, se mandon tirar a Francisco Freyre, os navios de Tamandar&#233;.
                    Rapetiolhes perluxas toas; &amp; percedendo trabalho &amp; dila&#231;a&#333;, cada hum por sy, os poz de fora a todos, pela memoria do
                    passado, com mais receyo que perigo.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is the other passage &#8211; Recea&#333; muito os Pilotos apartaremse dos rumos costumados, porque quando erra&#333; com os
                    mais tem vulgar a desculpa; &amp; quando acerta&#333; por sy mesmos, na&#333; ganha&#333; mayor premio. A este resperto, se chega&#333; sempre a Costa
                    de Ethiopia, chamada de Guin&#232; geralmente. Segura&#333; a viage no vera&#333; daquella altura, porque correm os ventos de Leste para o Norte,
                    &amp; pelo contrario para a Sul no univerno. Como tinha achado Francisco de Brito, passando do Algarve a Bahia no anno de 1652.
                    Agora persuadido tambem do mais que lhe ensinon D Fr. de Faro, Conde de Odemira, dos Conselhos de Estado &amp; Guerra, &amp;
                    Presidente em o Ultramarino, procuron lhe mandasse, V. M. declarar no Regimento de suas Reaes Ord&#275;s que de Caboverde governasse ao
                        Sul.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The passages from <title>Viage da Armada da Companhia do Commercio, e Frotas do
                            Estado do Brasil</title> (pp. 33 and 11 respectively) translate as: &#8216;There are many ships anchored on the coast waiting to
                        enter the harbour and many others waiting to exit the harbor that are already loaded, waiting, concerned about departing
                        because the shallow canal is treacherous. One vessel, the Patax&#243;, tried to exit and sank. The government was ordered by the
                        king to deepen the canal, but no action was taken even after intervention of captains and ministers named by the king in a
                        letter to Franscico de Brito. In addition, the navigators also were aware of the loss of other Dutch vessels, governed by
                        Jeronymo Serr&#227;o de Payva, in the recent past. Therefore, navigators are avoiding the port./ The situation is made worse
                        because ships trapped in the harbour include three existing fleets that would not be incorporated with the armada./ The
                        situation is angering the people of the state of the Pernambuco, as the port of Tamandar&#233; is extremely important; other ports
                        are very far away and it represents their only means of transportation. All of the vessels, specially the bigger galleons, are
                        waiting for the &#8216;terral shift&#8217;. The crisis also resulted in the dismissal of Francisco Freyre, no longer responsible for the
                        vessels in Tamandar&#233;, which could make the waiting situation worse for the boats, anchored at the coast (including the
                        General&#8217;s) and also for the Almirante&#8217;s, loaded inside the harbour.// The captains were afraid to use the regular routes
                        because when they made a mistake, an excuse was considered vulgar among the other captains; and when they steered right for
                        themselves, they did not earn the higher premium. In this respect, they always reached the coast of Ethiopia, commonly called
                        Guinea. In the summer, the journey was made at a specific latitude, because the winds run from the East to the North. And, on
                        the contrary, the winds are to the south in the winter. In 1652 Francisco de Brito found these wind patterns during journeys
                        from Algarve to Bahia. He is now even more persuaded by what was taught by D. Francisco De Faro, Count of Odemira, of the
                        Councils of State and War. The president of the ultramarine provinces sought to inquire if your majesty would declare, in the
                        Regiment of Royal Orders, that Caboverde governs to the south; as explained the eighth chapter of the same
                    regiment.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This last extract is of little importance, as the course which he recommends has I suppose, long been followed. But
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, of whom I used to enquire about such matters, is no longer at my elbow. He has
                    been summoned away by an appointment to the Dreadnought, &amp; has by this time joined her off Brest. She is a 98. &amp; Admiral
                    Sotheby has her, &#8211; brother to that Sotheby on whom we called,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was a 98-gun second rate ship of the line launched in 1801. She had fought at Trafalgar (1805) and was
                        now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s acquaintance.</note> &#8211; &amp; who was complimented in the Anti-Jacobine Review as &#8211; &#8216;not
                    being the Jacobine Poet, but a very respectable Gentleman&#8217;.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> I am upon
                    very courteous terms with him, &amp; he once brought the Admiral to call on me; &#8211; so that for a chance appointment this happens to
                    be a <del>xxx</del> desirable one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had quite done with the Noticias,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey several times refers in his
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> to the <title>Noticias do Brazil</title> manuscript as a valuable source (e.g. I, p.
                        312). Borrowed from Hill, it was not listed in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> as you may perceive by the few marks
                    which are not <hi rend="ital">crost off</hi>. Vasconcellos &amp; Rocha Pitta<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de
                        Vasconcellos (1596&#8211;1671),<title> Vida do Vener. Padre Joseph de Anchieta, &#8230; Taumaturgo do Novo Mundo, na Provincia do
                            Brasil</title> (1672); Sebasti&#227;o da Rocha Pita (1660&#8211;1738), <title>Historia da America Portugeza, desde o anno 1500 ate o
                            de 1724</title> (1730).</note> both had this M.S. &amp; both overlooked some things of importance, which are not to be
                    found elsewhere. Some trifling errors in it are corrected by the Mem. of S Vincente.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fr.
                        Gaspar da Madre de Deos (1715&#8211;1800), <title>Mem&#243;rias para a Hist&#243;ria da Capitania de S&#227;o Vicente</title> (1797).</note> Fr
                    Gaspar is a pioneering Gentlemans-Magazine-sort of author, &amp; has committed some errors himself for want of reading my friend
                    Hans Stadt.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hans Staden (c. 1525-c. 1579) was a German adventurer shipwrecked off South
                        America and captured by the Tupinamb&#225; people of Brazil. In his <title>True History</title>, first published in German and
                        then, in Latin, in the collection of voyages edited by Johan Theodor and Johann Israel De Bry, <title>Peregrinationes</title>
                        (1598&#8211;1613) (where Southey found it), he claimed to have witnessed cannibal feasts.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The best account of the Almogavares is in Desclot &#8211; the Catalan.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernard
                        Desclot (13th century), <title>Historia de CatalunnaTraducida, de fu Antiqua lengua Catalana en Romance Castellana por Raphael
                            Cervera</title> (Barcelona, 1616).</note> I have added a supplementary note about them from him &amp; Moncada.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (London, 1808), Southey notes (p. 418),
                        of the people known as Almogavares that Francisco de Moncada (?-d. 1635) &#8216;in his <title>Expedition de los Catalanes y
                            Araguneses</title> (1623), f. 19, thinks the name refers rather to their origin than their customs, and that they were
                        descended from the Avars&#8217;.</note> The Partidas<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Siete Partidas</title>
                        (Seven-Part Code) or <title>Libro de las Leyes</title>, a comprehensive legal code, was complied during the reign of Alfonso X
                        (1221&#8211;1284), king of Castile, Le&#243;n and Galicia from 1252 until his death. No. 3610 of the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library
                        was <title>Las Siete Partidas del Sabio Rey Don Alonso el Nono</title> (1789).</note> have supplied me with many curious
                    notes, of which, as usual, I have made as many again as there was room to insert: but these works of supererogation turns to
                    account some time or other. The Comercio Antiguo de Barcelona is with you.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de
                        Capmany de Montpalau (1742&#8211;1813), <title>Memorias hist&#243;ricas sobre la marina, comercio y artes de la antigua ciudad de
                            Barcelona</title> (1779&#8211;1792).</note> The History of that country would throw great light upon the middle ages; &#8211; &amp; if
                    the book were here, it would perhaps tempt me to bestow more time upon it than can well be spared.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will be best perhaps to prefix to each volume an account of the materials from which it has been made: &#8211; &amp;
                    you may insert B. Freyres history in the portion when it reaches you. I shall send off the seven chapters next week, &#8211; a blinding
                    &amp; excoriating cold is now wearing off after a three weeks spell, &amp; leaves me once more able to do my daily work. &#8211; The
                    first vol. will hardly finish the Dutch War, &amp; yet will go hard upon it. Those Mem. of S Vincente mention one or two books
                    which I never before heard of, &#8211; but if Lisbon be recovered, as I suppose it must be, we might perhaps procure them thro John
                    Bell, &amp; also that life of Almeida by Vasconcellos,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos
                        (1596&#8211;1671), <title>Vida do Padre Joam d&#8217;Almeida da Companhia de Jesu, na Provincia do Brazil</title> (1658).</note> which is
                    likely to be the most curious of his works, because it is the first of them, in which he would naturally set down what was most
                    remarkable concerning the natives, &amp; to which he refers for many particulars about them. &#8211; I wish we had the works of
                        Ulloa<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio de Ulloa y de la Torre-Giralt (1716&#8211;1795) travelled to South America in
                        order to compile a confidential report for the Spanish government on the state of its colonies. After the voyage he published
                            <title>Relaci&#243;n Hist&#243;rica del Viaje &#225; la Am&#233;rica Meridional</title> (1784). Southey owned the English version,
                            <title>Voyage to South America</title> (1806), no. 2927 in the sale catalogue of his library. The report, however,
                        remained unpublished for many years; Southey owned a presentation copy of the 1826 edition <title>Noticias Secretas de
                            America, sobre el Estado Naval, Militar, &amp;c. de los Reynos del Peru y Provincias de Quito, &amp;c. por D.
                            Barry</title>. He also owned his <title>Noticias Americanas Entretenimientos Fisico-Historicos</title> (1792).</note>
                    &amp; Gumilla,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; Gumilla (1686&#8211;1750), <title>Historia Natural, Civil, &amp; Geografica
                            de las Naciones situadas en las Riveras del Rio Orinoco</title> (1791).</note> &amp; Dobrizhoffer de Abipponibus,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus</title> (1783&#8211;1784).
                        Dobrizhoffer, a German Jesuit, worked in the village colonies into which the Jesuits gathered the Indians in Paraguay. Southey
                        had <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> borrow a copy from the Advocates Library, Edinburgh in early
                        1809.</note> for which vain enquiry was made in London. I shall be glad to see what you can send me of Faulkener, when you
                    have an opportunity of sending it.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707&#8211;1784), an English Jesuit whose
                        papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note> It
                    is a curious point to ascertain how far certain customs extended, &amp; certain languages. Patagonia is also interesting because
                    of its giants, &#8211; who ought to be of different race from any other people in S. America. Do you find mention in him of an animal as
                    big as a horse with a neck like the cameleopard? Such an animal is represented in one of the prints to the voyage of Le Maire
                    &amp; Schowtens<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacob Le Maire (c. 1585&#8211;1616), a Dutch mariner who with Willem Cornelisz
                        Schouten (c. 1567&#8211;1625) circumnavigated the world, discovering a new route to the spice islands round what they named Cape
                        Horn. The voyage narratives were published in Dutch, German and, in Latin, as Joris van Spilbergen and Jacob Le Maire,
                            <title>Speculum orientalis occidentalisque Indiae navigationum, quarum una Georgii &#224; Spilbergen &#8211; altera Jacobi le Maire &#8211;
                            directa, Annis 1614 -18: exhibens Novi in mare Australe transitus, incognitarumque hactenus terrarum ac gentium
                            inventionem; praelia aliquot terra marique commissa, expugnationesque urbium, una cum duabus novis utriusque Indiae
                            historiis, Catalogo munitionum Hollandicarum, ducum et reliqui bellici apparatus, tretique quatuor, suis quaeque figuris
                            illustrata</title> (1619) and <title>Novi Freti, a parte meridionali freti Magellanici in Magnum Mare Australe Detectio.
                            Diarium vel descriptio laboriosissimi et molestissimi itineris, facti a Guilielmo Cornelii Schoutenio annis
                            1615&#8211;17</title> (1619) and in English as <title>The Relation of a Wonderfull Voiage made by Willem Cornelison Schouten of
                            Horne. Shewing how South from the Straights of Magelan in Terra Delfuego: he found and discovered a newe passage through
                            the great South Seaes, and that way sayled round about the world</title> (1619). The English translation lacked the
                        engravings of the other editions, which included a plate of what is either a llama or an alpaca.</note> &#8211; &amp; both <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Burney</ref> &amp; I, judging from every thing else in those prints
                    believe it to be the real representation of some nondescript beast. &#8211; What became of Faulkener?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> July 1767 the Jesuits were expelled from South America, and Falkner returned to England and became chaplain to
                        Robert Berkeley (1713&#8211;1804) at Spetchley Park, Worcester. He then became chaplain to the Beringtons at Winsley, Herefordshire,
                        and the Plowdens at Plowden Hall, Shropshire, where he died (<title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; for I shall like to tell all that
                    is known of him. A Catholick at Norwich told me that the Jesuits still exist as a body in England, &#8211; &amp; pointed out one to me
                    in the street. My informer is a leading &amp; very zealous man among them, &#8211; but they had not trusted him, &#8211; &amp; he knew nothing
                    more than this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> I suppose is to be addrest as the Rt. Honble. &#8211; but what is
                    his christian name? The papers say he is going to Spain, &#8211; if so I shall not get his translations, &#8211; &amp; you will lose a friend
                    at court, who might be of use if he would but exert himself.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Three of Frere&#8217;s
                        translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title>. Frere had been Britain&#8217;s ambassador to Portugal while Southey&#8217;s uncle had lived there; from 1808&#8211;1809 he was
                        ambassador to Spain.</note> &#8211; I have been a true prophet with regard to Spain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Joanna Baillie<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> (1762&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish dramatist,
                        friend of the <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Aikins</ref> and of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>.</note> has been here, &amp; drank tea with us, &#8211; a lively, good-humoured unaffected woman. I was very glad of
                    the opportunity of seeing her. &#8211; From some other chance lakers I hear that the eldest Miss Hammet<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> who was, &#8211; is dying of consumption at Falmouth, &#8211; or more probably dead, &#8211; there being no
                    hope.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The great Barl&#339;us<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caspar Barlaeus (1584&#8211;1648), <title>Rerum per octennium
                            in Brasilia et alibi nuper gestarum sub praefectura</title> (1647), a work containing many maps and charts. Southey&#8217;s
                        library, on his death, contained an edition of 1660.</note> may at any time be sent you, because I have a small edition. There
                    are parts of his prints which would add much to the value of a book if given as head &amp; tail-pieces. I cannot learn whether the
                    previous history of the Dutch in Brazil by Jan de Laet<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> After Southey&#8217;s death, the sale
                        catalogue of his library contained Johannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Novus Orbis seu Descriptionis Indi&#230;
                            Occidentalis</title> (1633) and <title>De Origine Gentium Americanarum</title> (1642). It did not contain the work about
                        which Southey enquires here: <title>Historia Naturalis Brasiliae</title> (1648).</note> &#8211; to which he alludes, was ever
                    published: from his words I should conclude that certainly it was, but my G. Biography does not mention any such work. &#8211; The
                    account of the coast I should think had better be comprest into as small a compass as possible, the state of the &lt;various&gt;
                    harbours will not be of importance to us for many many years. It is only there where there are considerable towns, which our ships
                    will frequent, &#8211; the rest will be supplied with our commodities by country vessels. It is well to indicate them all, but a
                    separate work concerning them would meet with very few purchasers. This subject will form <del>xx</del> a fit chapter in a volume
                    of statistic history. &#8211; I have got thro the dullest part of the Dutch War &amp; brought over Mauritz,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Johan Maurits of Nassau (1604&#8211;1679), colonial governor who, from 1637&#8211;1644, gradually extended the Dutch
                        possessions in Brazil.</note> &#8211; a great man, &amp; worthy to have been the founder of a great empire. Of what was the promised
                    second part of the Castriots Lusitens<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rafael de Jesus (1614&#8211;1693), <title>Castrioto
                            lusitano: ou, Historia da guerra entre o Brazil e a Hollanda, durante os annos de 1624 a 1654, terminada pela gloriosa
                            restaura&#231;&#227;o de Pernambuco e das capitanias confinantes</title> (1679).</note> to have treated? What more has Joam
                    Fernandez Vieyre<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jo&#227;o Fernandes Vieira (1613&#8211;1681), a wealthy Brazilian plantation owner,
                        led a successful rebellion against Dutch rule after Maurits had returned to Europe. He subsequently became Governor and
                        Captain-General of the Captaincy of Paraiba (1655&#8211;1657). Later he was appointed Governor and Captain-General of Angola
                        (1658&#8211;1661) and Superintendent of Fortifications in northeastern Brazil, from 1661 to 1681.</note> done? or had he engaged Fr.
                    Rafael the Bombastick<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rafael de Jesus (1614&#8211;1693), the biographer of Vieira.</note> to
                    second his exploits, &#8211; before he atchieved them? &#8211; There is a <hi rend="ital">Valeroso Lucideno</hi>
          <note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> A work celebrating the Portuguese liberation from the Dutch of its colonies in Brazil by Frei Manuel Calado do
                        Salvador (1584&#8211;1654), <title>O Valeroso Lucideno e Triunfo da Liberdade na Restaura&#231;&#227;o de Pernambuco</title> (1648).</note>
                    upon this subject, &#8211; but I have materials enough for a history so devoid of every thing beautiful.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-07-09">July 9. 1808.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>