<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1529</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2651</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4859 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        225&#8211;229.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1529" type="letter">
        <head>1529. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1808-11-06">6 November
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 27
                        Dec<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4859 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        225&#8211;229.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-11-06">Nov. 6. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I guest that account of Jean de Lery&#8217;s book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613),
                            <title>Historia Navigationis in Brasiliam, quae et America Dicitur</title> (1578).</note> in the Magazine<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> An account of the colonising expedition to Brazil undertaken by French (mainly Protestants but
                        also including Catholics), in whose number was de Lery, is given in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (1808),
                        242.</note> to be yours, &#8211; &amp; sorry am I to say that what made me think so was the way in which the facts were
                    misrepresented. Villegagnon was a scoundrel,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Durand, Sieur de Villegagnon
                        (1510&#8211;1571) was a Commander of the Knights of Malta and later a French naval officer. Villegagnon directed the expedition but,
                        disgusted by disputes between the Protestant and Catholic colonists, condemned some of the Calvinists to death, withdrew his
                        support, and returned to France.</note> &#8211; as you should have seen by the whole of his conduct towards Lery, &amp; especially
                    by his attempts to get him burnt for heresy in France. But you are blinded by your hatred of the Reformers, &amp; even an Irish
                    Papist is not more bigoted than you are. &#8211; I shall be very much obliged for this book, &#8211; the Latin version I have, but have
                        <del>xxxx</del>wanted the French<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Histoire d&#8217;un voyage faict en la terre du Br&#233;sil</title> (1578).</note> to elucidate passages that are not perfectly
                    clear, &#8211; &amp; to compare it with it throughout. for Lery was his own translator &amp; the two books are not exactly the same. He
                    is a writer of unblemished character, &#8211; there is only one better book about Brazil which is the contemporary one of Hans
                        Stadt;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hans Staden (c. 1525-c. 1579) was a German adventurer shipwrecked off South
                        America and captured by the Tupinamb&#225; people of Brazil. In his <title>True History</title>, first published in German and
                        then, in Latin, in the collection of voyages edited by Johan Theodor and Johann Israel De Bry, <title>Peregrinationes</title>
                        (1598&#8211;1613) (where Southey found it), he claimed to have witnessed cannibal feasts.</note> &amp; that is only better because
                    poor Hans was a prisoner among the Tupinambas, &amp; his narrative has all the charm of personal adventure. &#8211; You have confounded
                        <hi rend="ital">Caraibes</hi> with Caribees. The Caraibes were their jugglers, homebred, &amp; not of foreign importation. And
                    they were not sheer atheists.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had declared that &#8216;The account of the manners of the
                        savages is copious and curious. They are described as wholly without religion, sheer atheists; but certain priests of the
                        Caribbees come occasionally among them and preach about bad spirits&#8217;: <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (1808), 242.</note>
                    &#8211; My history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in three volumes
                        from 1810 to 1819.</note> will show you all this in its true light. &#8211; If you can convey the book to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, it will reach me in his next parcel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I still want one book to satisfy my own <del>xxxx</del>conscience about the French expedition <del>of</del> to the
                    Rio <del>xxxx</del>Janeiro, &amp; that is a history of the Civil Wars in France which is attributed to Beza.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Th&#233;odore de B&#232;ze or de Besze (1519&#8211;1605), a French Protestant who played an important role in
                        Calvin&#8217;s Geneva and wrote the <title>Histoire ecclesiastique des Eglises reformes au Royaume de France</title> (1580).</note>
                    Every other account I have examined.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For my own sake I shall be glad to hear you are reannexed to the Critical Review, &#8211; one who has so many enemies
                    among the Journalists cannot afford to lose a good friend. &#8211; Fellowes<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Fellowes
                        (1770&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>) took orders but never held a position with the Anglican Church, though he published several
                        books on religious topics, such as <title>A Picture of Christian Philosophy</title> (1799) and <title>Religion without Cant</title> (1801). He was the
                        editor of the <title>Critical Review</title> from 1804 to 1811.</note> I suspect <hi rend="ital">is</hi> hampered with M. de
                        Brusasque<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> M. de Brusasque (dates unknown), either the former husband or a relative by
                        her first marriage of Elizabeth Annabella Fellowes, n&#233;e Mackenzie (?-1814), author and translator. Elizabeth Annabella was
                        praised, under her married name Mme. de Brusasque, in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 8 (1806), 493, as &#8216;a lady whom it
                        would be more easy to commend too little than too much for her talents and her virtues&#8217;. She married the
                            <title>Critical</title>&#8217;s editor, Robert Fellowes, in 1806.</note> whom I saw at Thetford, &amp; then apprehended that he
                    would hurt his own character, &#8211; a thing much to be regretted. He is a very interesting man, &amp; you &lt;would&gt; gain more by
                    having him in society than you would lose by missing Houghton from the pulpit.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pendlebury
                        Houghton (1758&#8211;1824), Presbyterian minister at Norwich from 1787 to November 1808, after which he moved to Westminster before
                        again becoming minister at Norwich from 1811&#8211;1812.</note> What is become of Stone the ejected Clergyman?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Revd. Francis Stone (1738?&#8211;1813), Anglican rector of Cold Norton from 1765, was deprived of
                        this living in 1808 owing to his Unitarian theological views. According to the <title>DNB</title>, &#8216;thrown into debt by the
                        loss of his living, worth &#163;300 a year, Stone, as a debtor, was confined within the rules of the king&#8217;s bench prison from
                        Michaelmas 1810. The Unitarian dissenters, who were just emerging as a denomination (on a largely Presbyterian base), had
                        followed his trial in the consistory court with great interest, but disagreed about the morality of his remaining within the
                        established church. Some noted that he had little choice, as he was by then over seventy years of age, had married for a
                        second time, and had eight children, one of whom had been born after 1809. The Unitarians raised a subscription, from which he
                        was paid &#163;100 a year. He died within the rules of the king&#8217;s bench at 30 Garden Row, London Road, Southwark, on 1 November
                        1813&#8217;.</note> &#8211; It would become the Unitarians to offer him such a Bishoprick as that of the Octagon.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Presbyterian chapel in Norwich.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would have vexed me if you had not rightly appreciated that Chronicle of the Cid,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was based on Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c.
                        1043&#8211;1099), <title>Chronica de la Famoso Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593).</note> &#8211; the Spaniards themselves
                    have not found out that it is one of the most curious &amp; finest books in existence. &#8211; The morality of the Koran is surely
                    beneath notice, &#8211; &lt;Mohammed&gt; enjoins <del>xxxx</del> mercantile honesty, &amp; recommends hospitality to the Arabs: &#8211; this
                    he could not help doing. &#8211; That introduction had it contained half of what I know upon its subject, or any thing like as much as I
                    would have been well pleased to say, would have filled a volume. But much of the same matter will appear with equal fitness in the
                    History of Portugal.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project was never completed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Walter Scott has abjured the Edinburgh Review. I believe my refusal to bear a part in it set the cock of his
                    conscience crowing, upon the score of their base &amp; cowardly peace-politicks, &amp; possibly Marmion finished his
                        conviction.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s poem <title>Marmion</title> (1808) was negatively reviewed by
                            <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 12 (April 1808), 1&#8211;13. For
                        Southey&#8217;s refusal, see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 December 1807, Letter 1393.</note> That refusal of mine he had communicated
                    in what phrase he pleased before the criticism upon his own poem appeared, &#8211; then &amp; not till then, my letter was produced. I
                    have seldom written a page so pointedly to the purpose, nor with such strength &#8211; &#8211; He too is longing to review the Cid, who had he
                    but been a Scotchman, would have been the very David after his heart: but he knows not where to find a channel for it. &#8211; X</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have retired in toto from the Annual had it continued in <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur
                        Aikins</ref> hands. Much <del>xxxx</del>want of respect I had put up with, &amp; much of what others had pointed out to me as
                    detraction, &#8211; such as that introductory chapter to the poetry of the year which contained Madoc,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 535, Aikin wrote of modern poets&#8217; excellence at &#8216;the
                        mechanical and musical part of poetical composition. This, as far as it goes, is, no doubt, a very material improvement; but
                        in numerous instances, that might be cited, it has been acquired at the expence of more valuable qualities; or, what is
                        equally bad, has cheated the public into the opinion that harmony will atone for the absence of all the other qualifications
                        for poetry, especially when seasoned with a little licentiousness, or conjoined with that nauseous whining sentimentality, the
                        bane of every vigorous exertion and every high attainment in literature or morals&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; that praise of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> as our best narrative poet, &#8211; when there was none with whom he could be compared
                    except myself. But then last year <del>xxxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> had gone beyond my limits
                    of endurance, by inserting <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Barbauld</ref> reviewal of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> instead of mine.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had
                        written a review of Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> (1807); that which replaced it and which Southey
                        attributed to Barbauld (<title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 521&#8211;529), was less complimentary.</note> For if mine
                    had been no better than hers, or as bad as she might be pleased to think it, still the part I had borne in the Review entitled me
                    to the privilege of reviewing a friends book, to the exclusion of any hostile article. In like manner he supprest a reviewal of
                        <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> Poland by <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, to
                    make room for one which certainly has nothing but its gratuitous ill nature to recommend it.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review of George Burnett, <title>A View of the Present State of Poland</title> (1807) appeared in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1807</title>, 6 (1808), 110&#8211;113.</note> I have done with <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> forever. No threshold of mine shall ever again be sullied by his <del>xxxx</del>entrance: &#8211; but this sort of
                    service I will always do him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We have been trying to get a County Meeting here about the cursed Convention,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot
                        (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley,
                        who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were
                        content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title>
                        DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> but in vain.
                        <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> who is Omnipotent here &#8216;sees it in a very different light,&#8217; &amp;
                    it is better not to stir at all than to be beaten. However as we cannot get our sentiments upon the subject embodied in the form
                    there yet remains another <del>xxxx</del> wh<del>at</del>ich to my mind is a better, &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is about to write a pamphlet<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Wordsworth&#8217;s pamphlet <title>Concerning the Relations of Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common
                            Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the Convention of Cintra</title> was published in 1809.</note>
          <del>upon the xxxx</del> in which he will take up the business in its true light.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say in a former &amp; unanswered letter respecting Kehama is very true, &#8211; I perfectly agree with you that
                    the poem is in its nature out of the reach of human sympathies, &amp; that its strangeness will prevent it from interesting nine
                    tenths of its readers.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor had said: &#8216;Your plan of singing Pelayo appears to me a
                        wiser enterprise than &#8220;Kehama&#8221;, of which the story cannot be made interesting however great the beauties of detail&#8217;; see
                        William Taylor to Robert Southey, 26 July 1808, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, p. 221.</note> And yet in spite of the conviction I am
                    proceeding &amp; shall proceed, God willing, to the end. This is not out of sheer pride &amp; obstinacy, &#8211; but because I have
                    learnt to take <del>it</del> an interest in it myself, &amp; because I perceive that the few persons who like it at all, will like
                    it with all their heart, &amp; especially because unless my preconceptions greatly deceive me, the conclusion will infinitely
                    exceed in grandeur any thing that I have ever yet produced, or conceived. It is now about half done. I have not begun upon
                        Pelayo<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early name for the poem which became <title>Roderick, Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> because I have not satisfied myself exactly how it should begin. Thalaba has at last reached
                    a second edition &amp; is now in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> hands &#8211; from whom this evening I have
                    received the first proof. There is a long piece cut off from the end of the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book, &#8211; &amp; some metrical
                    &amp; &lt;other&gt; minor improvements made: &#8211; the notes printed at the end of each book, &#8211; a great difference in appearance &amp;
                    no very material one in reality.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> was published in 1809. For the alterations that were made to this edition see volume three of
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>