<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1276</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2398</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS 4813D (undated
                        letters).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1276" type="letter">
        <head>1276. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-02-15">[mid-February 1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales MS 4813D (undated
                        letters)<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since the restoration of the Imperial Abbot to the throne of the Franks,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>, Speaker of the House of Commons and thereby a possessor of
                        franking privileges; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> was his secretary.</note> &amp; of my worthy tho
                    unknown friend Mr Ley to his official powers &#8211; I have instructed D Manuel not to call upon you on his way up to the
                        mountains.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was arranging a way of mailing without charge the manuscript of
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> I still
                    however send him to you on his way to the Printers, for two reasons, &#8211; because it is one thing to ask a frank of the Abbot, &amp;
                    another to direct under cover to him, &#8211; &amp; because it is a fit thing that his Majestys Under Secretary of State should see all
                    the <del>manuscript</del> treason which may be going on in manuscript, but that honourable Gentleman is requested to bear in mind
                    &#8211; that all the treason by implication which can be suspected herein is said in Spain of England, &amp; in England of Spain, &amp;
                    so it cannot be treason at all &#8211; at all &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a very miscellaneous cargo, &amp; the dullest part it &#8211; <del>that is</del> the account of Animal
                        Magnetism<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> included an account of Mesmerism in England.</note> &#8211; is the most extraordinary. That
                    &amp; the accounts of Swedenborgianism &amp; of <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> included accounts of the English followers of the religious mystic Emanuel Swedenborg
                        (1688&#8211;1772) and the self-proclaimed prophet Joanna Southcott.</note> which are yet to come will show you that nothing is too
                    monstrous to find believers in this enlightened age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written one letter upon occasion of Despards conspiracy<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward
                        Marcus Despard (1751&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>) an Irish-born British colonel whose involvement in radical politics led to his
                        imprisonment without trial, in the late 1790s, and, in late 1802, to his being named by informers as a member of a conspiracy
                        to seize the Tower of London and Bank of England and to assassinate the king. He was executed for treason.</note> &#8211; with which
                    &#8211; if you liked the spirit of that upon the Manufacturing System &#8211; you will be well pleased. One other with a political
                    complection, is to be written upon the breaking out of war &#8211; which will I am quite sure please you &#8211; whatever the others may
                    do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The recapture of B. Ayres<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In June 1806, with Spain, the colonial master of
                        South America, under French sway and Britain&#8217;s enemy, a force under Admiral Sir Home Riggs Popham (1762&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and William Carr Beresford (1768&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), occupied Buenos Aires. The British forces
                        were pushed back by the creoles in December 1806.</note> may teach both the people &amp; the Government something which it is
                    well they should know. The people &#8211; that it is ill done to set about rewarding Officers for acting without orders &#8211; the government
                    if they do not already know it, that the way for England to profit by S America, is not by attempting to conquer it, but by making
                    it independent, &#8211; in which case we derive every possible advantage which can be derived from it, without risque, without expence,
                        <del>&amp;</del> without bloodshed, &amp; without the certainty of ultimate expulsion, &#8211; for certain that might be
                    demonstrated to be.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will not express any joy for Bonapartes defeat till it is beyond a doubt.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        On 7&#8211;8 February 1807, in eastern Prussia, Napoleon&#8217;s Grande Arm&#233;e failed conclusively to destroy a Russian army at the Battle
                        of Eylau. Although neither side was defeated, the French nevertheless lost somewhere between 10000 and 15000 men.</note> That
                    his career must have an end I firmly believe. We shall yet have to say of the defeat of the French what I well remember applying
                    to their first victories, &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ille justitiam confirmavere triumphe,</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Praesentes docuere deos<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lines 98 and 99 from Claudian&#8217;s (c. 370&#8211;404 AD),
                        panegyric for the emperor Honorius Augustus (384&#8211;423 AD) (Claudian, <title>Carmina Maiora</title> 8): &#8216;they have confirmed
                        justice with their triumph and have shown that the gods are present&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent2"> ________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received yours with the inclosure in time before this packet was made up &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> indeed &#8211; he wrote to me the other day
                    rejoicing in the prospect of <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horaces</ref> recovery &#8211; which seems to me a thing not
                    to be rejoiced in. <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> has not been sane for some years &#8211; as <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> knows, &amp; I know<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> On Horace, see
                        Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 2 February 1807 (Letter 1270) and Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 February
                        [1807] (Letter 1277).</note> &#8211;. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenors</ref> own health seems to me in
                    an alarming state &#8211; for liver complaints are rarely eradicated. The <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">old mans</ref>
                    imprudence is as mysterious as it is ruinous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You seem to enjoy your Pappaship as you ought to do,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn&#8217;s wife, <ref target="people.html#WynnMary">Mary</ref>, had given birth to their first child, Charlotte Williams-Wynn (1807&#8211;1869;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in January.</note> &#8211; I could write a volume about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my
                        son</ref> already, if it were &lt;only&gt; to explain the titles which I have given him in their serious relations &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>