<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1720</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2842</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 118&#8211;119.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1720" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1720" type="letter">
        <head>1720. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1809-12-06">6 December 1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ DEC 9/ 1809; 10o&#8217;Clock/ DE.9/ 1809F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 146 1809/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1810<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 118&#8211;119.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will wonder that I have not sooner replied to your last. the truth is that I have been waiting not so much to
                    make up my own mind, as to see if any chance might occur to break off my present engagement with the Ballantynes, <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref>.</note> &#8211; not that there <del>xxx</del> &lt;is&gt; any probability of it, still however the thing
                    is possible, &#8211; my way of speaking plain truth may not square with their immediate interest, &amp; they might expect concessions
                    which it is not possible for me to make.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was contributing the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217;
                        for 1808&#8211;1810 in James Ballantyne&#8217;s <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>, which was published between 1810&#8211;1812.</note>
                    Had this been the case it would not have suited me to pay the yearly insurance, &#8211; I trust it will not happen, &amp; thankfully
                    accept your offer of paying the premium for me, &#8211; which shall be repaid from my first Register receipts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for my profession, as neither poet nor historian, nor even reviewer are terms known in law I suppose I must be
                    designated gentleman. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The parish of Christ-Church, Bristol is my birthplace, &#8211; the date of my birth August 12. 1774. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My present residence <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, Keswick, Cumberland.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My age 35&#8211;6. the sum for which to insure 1000 &#163;. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had the small pox, I have not got the Gout, nor is it in my family on either side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The point of reference as to a medical man is easily answered. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref> of this town will vouch for my being in as good health as I have been these six years, &#8211;
                    that is to say as long as he has known me &#8211; I would refer to plenty of persons in London, who will take my word for my state of
                    health at present, &#8211; if they will not be satisfied with your affirmation, here is the nearest justice of the Peace, my neighbour
                        W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Calvert<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert (1771&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), was at
                        school with Wordsworth at Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death of his father, Calvert became a man
                        of independent means, inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east shore of Bassenthwaite , near Keswick
                            (<title>DNB</title>).</note> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Greta Bank, Keswick.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know that I must neither be hanged, nor die out of Great Britain. Have I a right to be drownd, or to break my
                    neck? This last I think, in a land of stage coaches is a privilege of which a free born Englishman ought not to be deprived.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have estimated that were I now dead, &amp; 1000 subscribers obtained for a collected edition of my works, it
                    would produce upon the least favorable calculation a net residuary profit of 3200 &#163;. &#8211; Full directions upon this head will be
                    found among my papers. &#8211; I had drawn them up in the form of a letter to you &#8211; immediately after my last, &#8211; but it &lt;is&gt;
                    sufficient to let you know that such directions are in existence. Every thing in this estimate is under-rated. With the sum
                    insured I should therefore have no doubt of leaving to my family 4000&#163; &amp; upwards,&#8211; nor is it by any means improbable that my
                    friends &amp; acquaintances by doubling the number of subscribers at which I have made <del>xxx</del> &lt;the&gt; estimate, should
                    double that sum. No part of my historical labours (except the Cid)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> is taken into this account; &#8211; nor any of those rags &amp; relicks for
                    which public curiosity is so eager when any person dies in the odour of literature.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask me respecting that horrid story in the Friend.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s
                        periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, which was published in 26 instalments from 1 June 1809 to 15 March 1810.The thirteenth
                        number, dated 16 November 1809, included the story of Maria Eleonora Schoning, which Coleridge claimed to have read on his
                        visit to Germany in 1798. See Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly
                            Paper</title> (London, 1809), pp. 194&#8211;208. See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols
                        (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp. 172&#8211;183.</note> I hope it is not true, &amp; have convinced myself that it cannot be.
                    I remember to have read, but it is so very many years ago that I cannot say where (probably in an old Annual Register)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The story of this sect is given in the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; in the <title>Annual Register for the
                            Year 1767</title> (1768), 164.</note> that there were a set of fanatics some forty or fifty years ago in Denmark who used
                    to commit murder for the sake of being put to death that they might be sure to die in a state of repentance, &#8211; &amp; children were
                    always their victims, on account of their innocence &#8211; The madness was speedily put <del>to</del> a stop to by the obvious method
                    of confining these poor frantic wretches for life instead of executing them. I strongly suspect that on this foundation some
                    German horrorist made the story &amp; published it as a fact, &#8211; &amp; that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has been taken in by it. &#8211; It is however rather singular that I should never have heard him mention it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I say in my last<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to John May, 16 November 1809,
                        Letter 1710.</note> that if your brother William<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), John
                        May&#8217;s youngest brother and business partner in Brazil.</note> could get me Grammar &amp; Dictionary, one or both, of the
                    Brazilian &#8211; <del>xx</del> i.e the Tupi<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tupi people were the main inhabitants of
                        coastal Brazil when the Portuguese arrived there in the early sixteenth century.</note> language, or the Guarani,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Guarani tribe of Paraguay.</note> it would be of very great service?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Kehama is finished,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                        (1810).</note> &amp; I am correcting &amp; transcribing it during those odds &amp; ends of time, &#8211; which like M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Windhams<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Windham (1750&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>): Secretary for War
                        and the Colonies, 1806&#8211;1807, &#8216;whose major contribution was a controversial overhaul of Pitt&#8217;s defence measures with the aim of gradually reducing the militia and volunteers, by improving the
                        remuneration and terms of service for regular enlistment&#8217; (<title>DNB</title>).</note> cheese-parings amount to a good round
                    sum by the close of the year. I have begun Pelayo in blank verse,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem was
                        published as <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> in 1814.</note> &#8211; <del>xxxxxxx</del> &amp; hope to do great things
                    with so noble a subject</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me very kindly to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>. I have no
                    thoughts of setting my face southward next year</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref>
            <date when="1809-12-06">Dec. 6. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>