<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1523</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2645</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Professor R.D. Havens (according to Curry).  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 175&#8211;177 [in part]; R. D. Havens, RES 5 (1929), 320&#8211;322; Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 483&#8211;485.Dating note: The year (1808)
                        added to Southey&#8217;s date in pencil, and internal evidence (i.e. refs to Cintra Convention would confirm that
                    date.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1523" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1523" type="letter">
        <head>1523. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1808-10-19">19 October
                        [1808]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Professor R.D. Havens (according to Curry)<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 175&#8211;177 [in part]; R. D. Havens, <title>RES</title> 5 (1929), 320&#8211;322; Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 483&#8211;485.<lb />Dating note: The year (1808)
                        added to Southey&#8217;s date in pencil, and internal evidence (i.e. refs to Cintra Convention would confirm that
                    date.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-10-19">Wednesday night. Oct 19.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a visit this morning from <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp;
                        Spedding<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Spedding (1770&#8211;1851) of Mirehouse, the house and estate near
                        Bassenthwaite lake, north of Keswick. Spedding was a school friend of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> at Hawkshead.</note> upon the subject of this accursed convention in Portugal.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot
                        (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellesley,
                        who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, who were
                        content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple (1750&#8211;1830;<title>
                        DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which Burrard and Dalrymple never again took command.</note> They &amp;
                    some of their friends are very desirous of bringing before the country in some regular form, the main iniquity of the business,
                    which has been lost sight of in all the addresses, &#8211; &amp; of rectifying public opinion by showing it in its true light. A
                    military enquiry may, or may not, convict Sir Hew Dalrymple of military misconduct. This is the least part of his offence; &amp;
                    no legal proceedings can attach to the heinous crime which he has committed, the high treason against all moral feeling, in
                    recognizing Junot by his usurped title,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon had made Junot 1st Duke of
                        Abrant&#232;s.</note> &amp; in deadening that noble spirit from which &amp; which only the redemption of Europe can possibly
                    proceed, by presuming to grant stipulations for the Portugueze which no government ever yet pretended to have power to make for an
                    independant ally. covenanting for the impunity of their traitors, &amp; guaranteeing the safety of an army of ruffians, all of
                    whom, without his interposition, must soon have received their righteous reward from the hands of those whom they had oppressed.
                    He has stept in to save these wretches from the holy vengeance of an injured people, he has been dealing with them as fair &amp;
                    honourable enemies, exchanging compliments &amp; visits, dining with them in the Palaces from which they had driven the rightful
                    Law, &amp; upon the plate which they had stolen; &#8211; he therefore has <del>disclaimed</del> abandoned our vantage ground, betrayed
                    the cause of Spain &amp; Portugal, &amp; disclaimed, as far as his authority extends, the feeling<del>s</del> which the Spaniards
                    are inculcating, &amp; in which is their strength &amp; their salvation, by degrading into a common &amp; petty war between
                    soldier &amp; soldier, that which is the struggle of a nation against a foreign usurper. a business of national life or death, a
                    war of virtue against vice, Light against Darkness, the Good Principle against the Evil One.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is of importance to make the country feel this. &amp; these sentiments would appear with most effect if they
                    were embodied in a County Address, of which the ostensible purport might be to thank his Majesty for having instituted an Enquiry,
                    &amp; <del>perhaps</del> to request that he would be pleased to appoint a day of national humiliation for this grievous national
                    disgrace. This will not be liable to the reproof with which he thought proper to receive the City address, because it prejudges
                    nothing, &#8211; military proceedings are out of the question; &#8211; what is complained of is <del>the</del> &lt;a&gt; breach of the law of
                    nations, &amp; an abandonment of the moral principle, which the words of the Convention prove, &amp; which cannot be explained
                    away by any Enquiry whatsoever.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now the reason why I have been called upon is this. Such an address might easily be carried by delivering it over
                    to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Curwen,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Whig MP for Carlisle, Workington landowner.</note> but it is no party matter, &amp; it is desirable that it should not be
                    &lt;so&gt; regarded <del>as such</del>. They wish me therefore to apply to you to sign the requisition, your <del>sign</del> name
                    being of <del>the</del> main importance, &#8211; &amp; they wish me also to ask <del>you</del> whether you would object to write to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> upon the subject. To make him consider it in a moral point of view is
                    probably not to be expected, &amp; we know well enough how little Government are desirous of having any thing so considered. But
                    if he could be convinced that this business is aloof from all party questions, he might be contented to let it take its course,
                    without using any direct or indirect means of impeding it, if he did not chuse to give it his open sanction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Spedding &amp; Calvert<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert (1771&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), who
                        was at school with Wordsworth at Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death of his father, Calvert became
                        a man of independent means, inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east shore of Bassenthwaite, near
                        Keswick, where he lived with his family.</note> know many persons who will come forward at such a meeting. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> or <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>
                    will be ready to speak, &amp; will draw up resolutions to be previously approved, &amp; brought forward by some proper person. We
                    will prepare the way by writing in the county papers. Here ends my part of the business, &amp; not a little surprized am I to find
                    myself even this much concerned in any county affairs, &#8211; when the sole freehold I [MS torn] ever likely to possess is a tenement
                    six feet by three in [MS torn] churchyard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The carriers have disappointed me, or I had hoped to have sent your Father,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Humphrey Senhouse (1731&#8211;1814).</note> before this, the Chronicle of the Cid,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> &#8211; in which he will find I believe something more about
                    Compostella &amp; Santiago than was contained in that little note. Every carriers day I look for the parcel, &#8211; &amp; if he will do
                    me the favour to place this volume in his library, I know few places <del>in</del> where it will be in such good company.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember us to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Senhouse &amp; at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>