<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1377</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2499</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    111&#8211;112.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1377" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1377" type="letter">
        <head>1377. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, <date when="1807-11-13">13 November 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    111&#8211;112.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-11-13">Nov. 13. 1807.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sirs,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have certainly some reason to complain of <ref target="people.html#CadellThomas">Cadell</ref> and Davies; poor
                    Cervantes, however, has more. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey was
                        abandoning his plans to edit <title>Don Quixote</title> upon learning that an edition was to be published by the firm of <ref target="people.html#CadellThomas">Cadell</ref> and Davies. This appeared as <title>Don Quixote de la Mancha. Translated
                            from the Spanish by Mary Smirke, Embellished with Engravings</title>, 4 vols (London: Cadell and Davies, 1818). Longman
                        had proposed Southey edit it earlier that year; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [end of August 1807], Letter
                        1356; for a fuller account, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 15 November 1807, Letter 1378.</note> Their splendid
                    edition will be sure to sell for its splendour. I would have made such a work as should have been reprinted after the plates were
                    worn out. I thank you for offering to engage in it, but my nature is as little disposed to this kind of warfare as yours; and I
                    have as many plans to execute as I shall ever find life to perform. Let it pass. Morte d&#8217;Arthur is a book which I shall edit with
                    peculiar pleasure, because it has been my delight since I was a school-boy.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur ... With an introduction and notes by Robert Southey. (Printed from Caxton&#8217;s
                            edition, 1485)</title> was published in two volumes by Longmans in 1817.</note> There is nothing to be done in it but to
                    introduce it with a preface, and accompany it with notes. No time need be lost. As soon as you can meet with a copy, it may be put
                    into <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople&#8217;s</ref> hands: and by the time he has got through it, the introduction and
                    annotations will be ready. I will send back <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber&#8217;s</ref> books (which I have detained,
                    expecting to use them for the D. Quixote). For the Athen&#230;um, it will be sufficient to say that I am preparing an edition of Morte
                    d&#8217;Arthur, with an introduction and notes.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>. Southey's <title>Morte d'Arthur</title> was
                        not announced in <title>The Athenaeum</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have materials for a volume of Travels in Portugal, which the expulsion of the English from that country, and the
                    consequent impossibility of my returning there to visit the northern provinces, as was my intention, induces me to think of
                    preparing for the press. In what form are such works most profitable? If in quarto with engravings, I can procure some sketches
                    and some finished drawings. If you judge it expedient to reprint my former volume, it must undergo some corrections; for though it
                    has pleased the public to receive my first publications far more favourably than my later ones, I am fully sensible of their
                    faults, and look upon them with efficient humiliation.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The expanded third edition of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797; 2nd edn 1798) was published in
                        two volumes by Longman in 1808 as <title>Letters Written During a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in
                        Portugal</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">.&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160; The D. Quixote shall be returned in my first parcel. The only reason I have for regretting that Mr. Balfour<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Balfour (dates unknown), author of <title>Fables on Subjects connected with
                            Literature; imitated from the Spanish of Don Tomas Yriarte</title> (1804).</note> has elbowed me out of an office to which
                    he certainly has no pretensions whatever is, that I wished to do something, the emolument of which should be certain, for I cannot
                    be anticipating uncertain profits without feeling some anxiety. I have translations enough almost to make a little volume like
                    Lord Strangford&#8217;s,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Percy Clinton Sydney Smythe, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems from the Portuguese of Luis de Camoens: with Remarks on his Life and Writings</title>
                        (1803). Southey reviewed this book in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 569&#8211;577.</note> but then I am not a
                    lord. I have ballads enough for half a volume, but people are more ready to ask copies of them now, than they would be to buy
                    them; and were I to write as many more, according to all likelihood I should not get more by publishing them than any London
                    newspaper would give me for any number of verses, good, bad, or indifferent, sold by the yard, and without the maker&#8217;s name to
                    warrant them. What I feel most desirous to do is to send Espriella again on his travels, and so complete my design; but this must
                    not be unless he hits the fancy of the public.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A follow-up to <title>Letters from England
                            by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) did not appear.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours truly,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>