<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1649</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2771</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 147&#8211;150.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1649" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1649" type="letter">
        <head>1649. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-07-06">6 July
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Keswick July Six 1809/ Lieut Southey/
                        H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth Dock/ [MS illegible] R Sharp<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30927<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 147&#8211;150.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-07-06">July 6. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> arrived on Monday night, not till ten o clock when we had given him up. He
                    has brought with him <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David Jardine</ref> &amp; his cousin Lewis,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> who tho nearly a year older, is shorter by the head &amp; shoulders. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Job</ref> is, as you may suppose, in great glory, having two such companions. They
                    return on Monday, leaving <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> here. <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Betham</ref> I expect will arrive immediately after they are gone, &amp; about the same time <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> will be here &#8216;to spend one day &amp; a half.&#8217; He brings me the Susoo
                    grammar from one of the Missionar<del>ies</del>y Societies,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Brunton (c. 1770&#8211;1813) a
                        member of the Edinburgh Missionary Society in Guinea, West Africa, wrote <title>A Grammar and Vocabulary of the Susoo
                            Language: to which are added, the names of some of the Susoo towns, near the banks of the Rio Pongas; a small catalogue of
                            Arabic books, and a list of the names of some of the learned men of the Mandinga and Foulah countries, with whom an useful
                            correspondence could be opened up in the Arabic language</title> (1802).</note> &#8211; the language is spoken far &amp; wide
                    among the negroes, &amp; will be a curious addition to my Library, &amp; useful in my Quarterly pursuits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Curwens bill<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>),
                        agriculturist and politician responsible for Curwen&#8217;s Act, passed in 1809. The act was a significant attempt at parliamentary
                        reform that intended to reduce the sale of seats and the number of government placemen in the House of Commons. The
                        government&#8217;s opposition took the form of suggesting modifications that watered down the bill so much that those who had
                        supported it voted against it because it was feared it would stand in the way of proper reform.</note> except in its preamble
                    which establishes the principle that seats in parliament ought not to be purchased, will do nothing but mischief, for it leaves
                    the power in the Treasury, &#8211; &amp; destroys it every where. A man can not now buy an opposition borough as he was wont to do, &#8211;
                    but government can still manage theirs, &amp; pay for them in half a thousand ways, so as effectually to elude the spirit of the
                    act themselves, while they enforce the very letter of it upon their opponents. In like manner that Bill to prevent the sale of
                    places was a mere juggle, &amp; an excellently clever one, &#8211; for by making it criminal <del>either</del> to buy, sell or assist in
                    the sale of any place under government, all persons who offended are provided with means of escaping discovery. It is no longer of
                    any avail to appoint Committees of the House &amp; examine them, &#8211; to every question (which before this rascally bill they were
                    obliged to answer) they have now only to reply &#8216;I must not criminate myself&#8217; &#8211; It is a legal answer, &#8211; the question cannot be
                    prest. &#8211; from this time forward therefore the trade is secured from all possibility of discovery, &amp; this was what <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> brought the bill in for. As for Curwen he neither meant harm nor good. He
                    is a hunter after popularity, &amp; merely thought to curry a little by doing something which should be talked about. The more I
                    have seen of him the less have I liked him. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> is here, &amp; I have a design upon him for the benefit of your letter.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Judging by the address sheet of this letter, and several others at this time, Sharp agreed
                        to frank Southey&#8217;s letters. The privilege Southey had previously enjoyed through his friend John Rickman, as secrretary to the
                        Speaker of the House of Commons, had been suspended while it was not in session.</note> I dined on Monday at Jansons<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John I&#8217;Anson (dates unknown), innkeeper of the Royal Oak at Keswick.</note> with Dickenson
                    &#8211; the Member for Somersetshire, whom I had <del>see</del> not seen since I stopt at his rooms at Oxford in 1792, seventeen years
                    &amp; a half ago.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dickinson (1771&#8211;1837), a pupil at Westminster School, who later
                        went on to Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795). He was Civil Lord of the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The second Quarterly contains only one article of mine,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of
                            <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez; com as Palavras Portuguezas Propriamente Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo
                            d&#8217;Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May 1809), 268&#8211;292.</note> as well as the
                        first.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication
                            of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in
                            his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the
                            Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity&#8230; By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the
                            Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to
                            India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> In the third will be
                    Holmes&#8217;s American Annals,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763&#8211;1837), <title>American
                            Annals; or, a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> in the<title> Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319&#8211;337.</note> &#8211; &amp; perhaps the Mission in the South Sea Islands.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea
                            Islands</title>, appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61.</note> Danvers&#8217;s arrival will
                    prevent me from getting Lord Valentias Travels ready in time for it.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of
                        George Annesley, Viscount Valentia (1770&#8211;1844), <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and
                            Egypt in the Years 1802, 1803, 1804, 1805, and 1806</title> (1809) appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2
                        (August 1809), 88&#8211;126.</note> These Travels are very interesting. he sent his draftsman &amp; secretary, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Salt<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Salt (1780&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), secretary and draughtsman to
                        Viscount Valentia, whose <title>Voyages and Travels to India, Ceylon, and the Red Sea, Abyssinia and Egypt</title> he had
                        illustrated and partly written, was sent by the government in March 1809 on a diplomatic mission to the Abyssinian
                        court.</note> into Abyssinia, &amp; Bruce has been convicted of many falsehoods, &#8211; gross exaggeration &amp; wilful lies to
                    extol himself, &#8211; &amp; the worse crime of inventing a survey of the African coast of the Red Sea, which is altogether
                        fictitious.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Bruce&#8217;s (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>)<title>, Travels to Discover
                            the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title>, which Southey knew well as he reviewed the second edition of
                        1804&#8211;1805, in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 2&#8211;16.</note> &#8211; I have offered to justify <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> against the friends of Sir John Moore,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diplomatist John Hookham Frere was sent to Spain as minister-plenipotentiary to the Central Junta on 4
                            October 1808 and when the French marched on Madrid he urged Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), the Commander of the British forces in northern
                        Spain also to advance upon Madrid, despite his inclination to retreat through Portugal. After the disastrous retreat to
                        Corunna, Frere was blamed for this advice and recalled by the British government. Southey did not write an article on this
                        topic.</note> if it be thought advisable so to do, &#8211; &amp; I have offered also to have another rush at the Methodists,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of [James Sedgwick (1775&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Hints to the
                            Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514.</note> &#8211; in which I should set to work seriously to
                    investigate the cause of their rapid progress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Austrians have disappointed my fears, &amp; things seem fairly on the balance, with this advantage on their
                    side that they have a good cause, &amp; must therefore necessarily get the better in the long run, if they hold out.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain and Austria were in alliance against France in 1809, and Napoleon advanced into Austria
                        where he suffered a significant defeat at the battle of Aspern-Essling (22 May 1809). The Austrians failed to follow up this
                        victory, which allowed Napoleon to seize the capital, Vienna, in early July. The Austrians were then defeated by the French at
                        the battle of Wagram on 5&#8211;6 July 1809.</note> Their policy is to avoid fighting as long as they can, &amp; harrass him by
                    cutting off his supplies. If this can be done till our army arrives in the Elbe, a powerful division will then be made in North
                    Germany, joined as I have no doubt we instantly shall be by the Prussian army. One great defeat destroys Bonaparte root &amp;
                    branch. If he falls, it will be once &amp; for ever. His power out of France has no other support than brute force, &#8211; in France it
                    rests wholly upon the opinion of his good fortune &amp; the splendour of his success. Beat him, &amp; the French will desert him
                    take him prisoner, &#8211; &amp; he falls so low that <del>he cannot</del> the common laws of war would hardly be granted to him, &#8211; but
                    he might be hung as he would hang Chastillas. I open the Courier<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London newspaper, the <title>Courier</title>,
                        edited by <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>.</note> daily with great doubts &amp; much anxiety, &#8211; but
                    it does appear to me that at present the advantage is on the side of the Austrians, &amp; the longer they can delay their power in
                    the nature of things strengthens &amp; his must be weakened.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That article upon the Austrians in the second Quarterly is written by <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George
                        Ellis</ref>, &amp; has been revised by Canning.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, George Canning, and <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref> (possibly with the German statesman Friedrich von Gentz (1764&#8211;1832)) reviewed <title>Proclamation
                            of the Archduke Charles to his Army; Declaration of War by the Emperor of Austria; Address of the Archduke to the German
                            Nation</title> (1809) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May 1809), 437&#8211;455.</note> The Review succeeds
                    excellently well, &amp; will probably soon put to death many of the inferior ones. It will be powerfully supported, &#8211; every number
                    for some time to come better than the last. I suppose <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> will bear a part when
                    he returns. If <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> is beaten in this struggle in the cabinet, then it becomes an
                    opposition review.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Canning had held the office of Foreign Secretary in the
                        government since 1807, but he offered to resign several times in 1809 over the progress of the war with France, his plans to
                        expel Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh and 2nd Marquess of Londonderry (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) from the War Office
                        (with a duel being fought between them on 21 September 1809), and his own ambitions to become Prime Minister. Canning lost his
                        position when <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref> became Prime Minister in October 1809.</note> &#8211;
                    this I hope will not be the case. At any rate the tune will be &#8216;fight on my merry men all&#8217;<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> A line which occurs in both the broadside ballad &#8216;John Armstrong&#8217;s Last farewel&#8217; (c. 1701) and &#8216;The Ballad of Chevy Chase&#8217;
                        (first recorded in the 15th century).</note> as long as the power of France remains unbroken. &#8211; &amp; I shall waive all
                        <del>xx</del> difference of opinions upon less important subjects for the sake of joining in in that chorus.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> is going very fast indeed. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Your nephew</ref> is as happy as the day is long, &amp; is as good as he is happy. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your niece</ref> goes on well &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is I think the sweetest infant of all our children, &#8211; at least I never loved so young a one so much before.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>