<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1712</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2834</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1712" type="letter">
        <head>1712. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1809-11-22">22 November
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You should have told me when you shifted your quarters into the Lyra<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS
                            <hi rend="ital">Lyra</hi> was a Royal Navy Cherokee class 10-gun brig-sloop, launched in August 1808.</note> whether I
                    were to direct to that ship or to the Dreadnought.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi>
                        was a Royal Navy 98-gun second rate ship of the line, launched in 1801, which Thomas Southey had been serving on since July
                        1808.</note> I am very doubtful which, but on the supposition that you must either return to your old ship, or find her in
                    dock at Plymouth, will continue the former direction. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There should be two numbers of Kehama<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Drafts of Southey&#8217;s poem <title>The
                            Curse of Kehama</title>, published in 1810, were being sent to his brother.</note> come to hand before this time, another
                    is on the stocks. I have finished the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> section to day, &amp; there remains but one more. We are in the very
                    middle of Hell, Yamens<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The god of the underworld in Southey&#8217;s poem.</note> three-legged
                    throne is ready, &amp; tomorrow the Rajah<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Kehama, the villain of Southey&#8217;s poem.</note> is
                    to come thundering in in a very unusual manner, &#8211; for you must know that Padalon (which is the underground floor of the world) is
                    of an octopus shape, &#8211; it has eight gates &amp; eight straight causways leading &lt;from there&gt; to the centre where the city of
                    Yamen stands, &amp; <del>xx</del> Kehama enters by all the gates at once. I leave you to guess how. O Tom you have stranger things
                    to learn than are ever to be met with at sea. I have made a new coach which goes upon one wheel, &amp; then my Hell is such an
                    invention that by the Lord I desire a patent for it. <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title>, Book 22 for the car, and 23 for Padalon, the adamantine hell.</note> You may well suppose that I now long
                    to be at the end of my long journey. The poem thus far contains 4558 lines, &#8211; the concluding section will bring it to about 4800,
                    &#8211; &amp; I fancy there will be insertions enough in the course of transcription to make up 5000. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> recommends the Thalaba form<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) was published in the cheaper format of octavo. The second edition was
                        published in 1809.</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> advises quarto,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was published in quarto.</note> &#8211; but he counts a good deal upon the effect
                    which the Register<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for
                        1808&#8211;1810 in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne&#8217;s</ref>
            <title> Edinburgh Annual
                        Register</title>.</note> is to produce, in exciting an increasing demand for my productions. Without calculating upon this, it
                    is most likely that I shall follow his opinion, because no man understands the humour of the public so well, &amp; because it
                    becomes me to keep <del>xx</del> &lt;up that&gt; sort of consequence which is attached to a guinea &amp; half quarto, rather than
                        <del>a xx</del> to smaller volumes of less price &amp; more convenience. You may be sure I am longing for the first proof
                    sheet, especially as in addition to all the other originalities of the book I think of a new mode of printing. Do you know what is
                    called <hi rend="ital">indenting</hi>? In printing poetry lines which do not begin upon a perpendicular line <del>up</del> with
                    each other are called indented. Now I have a notion that the page will have a much more beautiful appearance if the indenting be
                    so managed as to make every line bear the same proportion at the end as at the beginning to its regular <del>xx</del> above, &#8211; a
                    thing never yet attended to &#8211; in short to print the irregular poetry in this respect just as monumental inscriptions are
                        printed.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> was indented in this way for
                        publication.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was a good deal alarmed by reading some days ago in the Times that Lieutenant Smith of the Lyra Frigate had been
                    lost in a boat with 14 men,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant Smith is untraced.</note> &#8211; being pretty sure
                    there was no Frigate of that name, &#8211; &amp; not a little apprehensive that in <del>xx</del> a bad hand writing Southey might be
                    mistaken for Smith. Your letter which has just arrived put me out of suspense, &#8211; &amp; to tell you the truth I should not have had
                    heart to finish this &amp; send it off, <del>xx unless</del> till I had known the truth. I wish you were safely out of the Brig, &#8211;
                    that I must say, &#8211; but you are so well aware of the objections to the boating system, that I am confident you will do nothing
                    which you cannot afterwards upon your pillow approve, &#8211; &amp; this was my comfort when I read the paragraph.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ought to have received sundry letters written since my visit to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>, in one there is mention of having applied to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">G Beaumont</ref> to
                    use his interest with Ld Mulgrave<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>): diplomatist and politician who was appointed First Lord of the Admiralty in 1807.</note> for
                        you.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Thomas Southey, 18 October 1809, Letter 1696.</note> I
                    asked to have you made Post.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, promoted to captain, although not necessarily given
                        command of a ship.</note> This he told me was impossible. I then wrote again, for the intermediate step,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 20 October 1809, Letter 1697.</note> &amp; am very
                    certain he will make the attempt, &#8211; with what success remains to be seen, &#8211; be so good as not to get knocked on the head, &amp;
                    you will have your lapells at last; &#8211; for if the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenvilles</ref> come in <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will <del>xx</del> save us, &#8211; &amp; if ever Lord Melville comes in I will ask
                        <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, in full confidence of obtaining it. Be so good also as to
                        <del>xx</del> steer clear of Verdun, for in this Register I have made war upon Bonaparte upon the old ground of Capt Wright
                    &amp; Palm,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 25,
                        Southey wrote &#8216;the murder of Palm was an offence committed against all states and people, against all principles of law and
                        justice and social order; it was an act by which he outlawed himself in human society, and, from the hour in which it was
                        committed, he was under the ban of human nature. There is also one crime committed peculiarly against England, which should
                        for ever preclude the possibility of treating with its perpetrator; the murder of Captain Wright, an English officer, put to
                        death in prison&#8217;. Johann Philipp Palm (1768&#8211;1806) was a bookseller from Nuremberg, Germany, who was executed by a French
                        firing squad on 26 August 1806 for publishing and distributing libellous pamphlets about France and Napoleon. John Wesley
                        Wright (1769&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), was a British naval officer. In May 1804 his ship, the <hi rend="ital">Vincejo</hi>,
                        was captured off the coast of France by the French navy. Accused of having landed royalist agents, he was imprisoned in Paris,
                        where he died in solitary confinement. He was thought by the British to have been murdered. Hence Tom had better keep clear of
                        the fortified town of Verdun, used by the French to imprison British prisoners of war.</note> chargd him with direct murder,
                    insisted that upon this ground we ought never to treat with him, &amp; written a sentence <del>upon</del> &lt;concerning&gt;
                    tyrannicide which will make <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roscoes</ref>
          <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roscoe had advocated making peace with Napoleon; Southey attacked him for this in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 22&#8211;26, although his advocacy of killing Napoleon was toned down to a recommendation
                        that Britain should never enter a treaty with him.</note> hair stand on end.
                    <del>xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The American Madoc is a prize.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc: A Poem</title> was published
                        in Boston, Massachusetts, in 1806.</note> I had heard of it from poor Charles Fox (who is dead at last poor fellow)<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Fox (c. 1740&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), a Bristol-based acquaintance of Southey&#8217;s
                        whose <title>Poems, Containing the Plaints, Consolations, and Delights of Achmed Ardebeili, a Persian Exile</title> was
                        published by Joseph Cottle in 1797.</note> &#8211; but never saw it. Is it worth while to have a quarto copy sent you when you have
                    the more convenient edition? I should think you had better have it sent here to the dry shelf in the passage. This however is as
                    you please, &amp; perhaps you may like sometime to show me off in my grandeur.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Capt Bouverie<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain (later Admiral) the Honourable Duncombe
                        Pleydell-Bouverie (1780&#8211;1850), was a British naval commander and Whig politician.</note> whose invitation you did not accept
                    is married to a sister of <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, &#8211; &amp; this was probably the reason why he invited
                    you. Another reason which might have made you like to see him if you had recollected it, is that <hi rend="ital">I believe</hi> he
                    is brother to Lord <del>Folkestone</del> Folkestone.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician William
                        Pleydell-Bouverie, Viscount Folkestone, 3rd Earl of Radnor from 1828 (1779&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Salisbury
                        1802&#8211;1828. Folkestone was a Radical critic of the administration.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lloyd</ref> was here this time fortnight for two
                    nights, with her youngest child but without <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">her husband</ref>. You have probably heard from
                    him how narrowly she escaped from a vicious horse by throwing herself off; &#8211; she is quite recovered from the effects of the fall,
                    which were very alarming at first &amp; might very easily have been fatal. Lloyd has probably told you that he is printing a
                        novel,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lloyd&#8217;s novel <title>Isabel</title>, privately printed at Ulveston (a town to
                        the southwest of the Lake District). It was published in 1820.</note> &#8211; I <hi rend="ital">dis</hi>advised it when he asked my
                    opinion, &#8211; tho he has rewritten the book since he sent it to me ten years ago. he asked me to review it; &amp; this I shall
                    request <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to let me do, provided it is to be reviewed in the Quarterly at
                    all. If it is to be done I will endeavour that it shall pass thro my hands, but I shall be better pleased if it <hi rend="ital">slips</hi> thro them. He makes a feint of this business, &amp; yet prints it at Ulverstone, so that it will be apparent that
                    the author lives in that neighbourhood, &#8211; &amp; then his name ought as well be in the title page. The Dapp<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s dog, Dapper.</note> has had a paralytic stroke, from which he is much recovered, but
                    nevertheless every body thinks he is going apace, &amp; he is said to think so himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Slack of Liswick has built a house for himself near Portinscale, upon the hill above the river, between the bridge
                    &amp; the Lake; a good plain house, so situated as to be a very fine object from hence, &amp; much to improve our <del>pros</del>
                    view. <note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Slack (1774&#8211;1830) of Derwent Hill, Portinscale, a village south of Keswick
                        on the shore of Derwentwater. Lissick, Slack&#8217;s former residence, is near Bassenthwaite lake, just to the north of
                        Keswick.</note> We see it with Grisedale<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grisedale Pike, a fell to the west of the
                        Newlands valley, visible from <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> directly behind. It will be well if
                    he does not improve its appearance by whitewashing, otherwise it is really a greater improvement than you could suppose. &amp;
                    Miss Christian, Curwens sister,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>),
                        agriculturist and politician who was the Whig MP for Carlisle. His sister, who became a friend of the Southeys after her move
                        to Keswick, was Mary Christian (1759&#8211;1831).</note> has taken a new house in Keswick. I had a letter a few nights since from
                        <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel Peachey</ref> on his return to England, he proposes to send <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> some little memorial of <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">his wife</ref>. The
                        Island<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Derwent Isle in Derwentwater.</note> he does not talk of parting with, but
                    desires me to replace any trees which may be blown down. I think however that as he anticipates little pleasure in returning to
                    it, a good purchaser will tempt it him to sell it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> is provokingly slow. I scarcely get a sheet a week from him. we
                    have got on 552 pages, &amp; I think shall fill 650 before we come to the notes, &#8211; which I must print in double columns &amp; a
                    smaller type to reduce as much as possible the size of the book.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to
                        the first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> published in 1810.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> has only printed two sheets of the Register, he has four more in his hands, &amp; I have between three &amp;
                    four in my desk. What I am doing will be <del>xx</del> in great part very dull from its including all the parliamentary
                    proceedings for instance. &#8211; when I speak for myself it will be plain pointed &amp; to the purpose. The Scotchmen<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey means <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref>, the publishers of the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title>.</note> are greatly astonished, &#8211; &amp; so I dare say many other persons will be. &#8211; my politicks are to
                    the tune of Tantara-rara<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s parlance for the noise and hot air produced by party
                        spirit on the benches of the House of Commons. <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by John
                        O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Dramatic Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1798),
                        III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All Fools All&#8217; was a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>)
                        play <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> &#8211; or rogues all. I am quite heartless &amp; hopeless about the ins &amp; the
                    outs, &#8211; yet full of heart &amp; hope for the country, for if invasion ever takes place, John Bull<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> A common personification of Britain, or more particularly England.</note> will do his work let who will be at
                    the head of affairs, &amp; shall make a glorious finish of it. Peace would certainly bring it to this, &#8211; but my cry is war against
                    Bonaparte, against him personally &amp; as long as he lives: no terms, no truce, with him; &#8211; call him a tyrant, a villain, a lyar
                    &amp; a murderer, &amp; hang him for one if ever you catch him. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> says
                    Oh for a single hour of Dundee, in one of his sonnets,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> Line 11 of Wordsworth&#8217;s sonnet &#8216;In
                        the Pass of Killiecranky&#8217; (1803), referring to John Graham, 1st Viscount of Dundee (known as Bonnie Dundee; 1648?&#8211;1689;<title>
                            DNB</title>), Jacobite army officer.</note> &#8211; Oh for a year of Marlborough<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650&#8211;1722; <title>DNB</title>), victor of the battle of Blenheim.</note> or of the Black
                        Prince<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Mordaunt, 3rd Earl of Peterborough and 1st Earl of Monmouth
                        (1658?&#8211;1735; <title>DNB</title>), renowned for his daring tactics in an earlier war in Spain.</note> say I! &#8211; At present we do
                    nothing but injure our allies &amp; disgrace ourselves. Nevertheless the issue must be good.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-11-22">Nov. 22. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>