<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1654</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2776</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3878.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 246&#8211;248 [in part]; H. J. C. Grierson
                        (ed.), The Letters of Sir Walter Scott, 12 vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), II, p. 206 [in part]</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1654" type="letter">
        <head>1654. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1809-07-13">13 July
                        1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Edinburgh
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: JY/ 1809/ 15<lb />Watermark: shield/ 1807/ T BOTFIELD<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ 13
                        July 1809<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3878<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 246&#8211;248 [in part]; H. J. C. Grierson
                        (ed.), <title>The Letters of Sir Walter Scott</title>, 12 vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), II, p. 206 [in part]</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-07-13">July 13. 1809</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are two channels thro which I could perhaps make application for <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdales</ref> countenance, &#8211; thro <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G. Beaumont</ref> who knows him
                    well, &amp; would try to serve me with more zeal for the sake of the woods, &#8211; &amp; thro the <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouses</ref>, a family in the Lonsdale interest, with whom I am more intimate than
                    with any other in the county.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In July 1809, Southey was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the stewardship of the Derwentwater Estates (which were owned
                        by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the incumbent; see Southey to Walter Scott, 6 July 1809,
                        Letter 1648. In his reply, Scott had enquired if Southey had &#8216;any interest with the present Lord Lonsdale&#8217;, who &#8216;is likely to
                        be listened to in the appointment upon the Derwentwater estate&#8217;, and promised to assist him; see Walter Scott to Robert
                        Southey, 8 July 1809, <title>The Letters of Walter Scott</title>, ed. H. J. C. Grierson, 12 vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), VIII, p.
                        204. Southey asked several friends to intercede on his behalf, including Senhouse and George Beaumont, but in the end the
                        position was considered unsuitable for him; see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 August 1809 (Letter 1666) and Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter 1669).</note> If your enquiries should show that there is any likelihood of success in
                    this quest, I will make application thro both these quarters; &#8211; till this be ascertained it will be better to abstain. I could
                    also obtain the good word of Lord Bute,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 4th Earl of Bute (1744&#8211;1814;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> if he be upon good terms at <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>. Let this
                    matter end as it may, it is I trust needless for me to say how greatly I feel beholden to you for your friendly solicitude.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> pamphlet will fail of producing any general effect, because the
                    sentences are long &amp; involved, &amp; his friend <ref target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref> who corrects the
                    press has rendered them more obscure by an unusual system of punctuation.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A defeated
                        French army was allowed by the British to evacuate Portugal under the terms of the Convention of Cintra (30 August 1808). On
                        27 December 1808 and 13 January 1809 Wordsworth published, in <title>The Courier</title>, an article condemning the
                        Convention. In May 1809 Longmans published the article as a pamphlet: <title>Concerning the Relations of Great Britain, Spain,
                            and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected by the Convention of
                            Cintra</title>.</note> This fault will outweigh all its merits. The public never can like any thing which they feel it
                    difficult to understand, &#8211; they will affect to like it, as in the case of Burke,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund
                        Burke (1729/30&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), politician and author who was renowned for his eloquent but involved style.</note>
                    if the reputation of the writer be such that not to admire him is a confession of ignorance, &#8211; but even in Burkes case the public
                    admiration was merely affected, his finer beauties were not remarked, &amp; it was only his party politics that were generally
                    understood, while the philosophy which he brought to their aid was heathen Greek to the multitude of his readers. I impute
                    Wordsworths want of perspicuity to two causes, &#8211; his admiration of Miltons prose, &#8211; &amp; his habit of dictating instead of
                    writing: if he were his own scribe his eye would tell him where to stop, &#8211; but in dictating, his own thoughts are to himself
                        <del>xx</del> familiarly intelligible, &amp; he goes on unconscious either of the length of the sentence, or the difficulty a
                    common reader must necessarily find of following its meaning to the end, &amp; unravelling all its involutions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A villainous cold which makes me sleep as late as I possibly can in the morning because the moment I wake it wakes
                    with me, has prevented me from finishing Kehama.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> It would else ere this have been compleated. I think of publishing it on my
                    own account in a pocket volume of about 350 pages, &#8211; but this is not yet determined.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This
                        scheme was not adopted.</note> One of the pleasures which I had promised myself in seeing you was that of showing you this
                    wildest of all wild poems, &#8211; believing that you will be one of the few persons who will relish it. The rhymes are as irregular as
                    your own, but in a different key, &amp; I expect to be abused for having given the language the freedom &amp; strength of blank
                    verse, tho I pride myself upon the manner in which this is combined with rhyme.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Eclogue which I have sent <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> has suffered a little by
                    having all its local allusions cut out.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem &#8216;The Alderman&#8217;s Funeral, an English
                        Eclogue&#8217;. It was not included in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English
                            Authors; with some Original Pieces Hitherto Unpublished</title> (1810), but Southey included it in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810) along with &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; and &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; (i-xiii). Both these works were
                        published by the firm of Ballantyne.</note> This was done lest what was intended as a generic character should have been
                    interpreted into individual satire. The thing was suggested by my accidentally crossing such a funeral some years ago at Bristol,
                    &#8211; &amp; had I been disposed to personal satire the hero of the procession would have afforded any scope for it. As soon as he knew
                    his case was desperate he called together all the persons to whom he was indebted in <del>the</del> his mercantile concerns.
                    Gentlemen, said he, I am going to die, &#8211; &amp; my death will be an inconvenience to you, because it will be some time before you
                    can get your accounts settled with my Executors &#8211; Now if you will allow me a handsome discount, I&#8217;ll settle them myself at once.
                        <del>By this xxxxxx xxxxxxxxery xxxxxbly xxxxxx.</del> They came into the proposal &amp; the old Alderman turned his death
                    into nine hundred pounds profit. &#8211; If Queen Orraca is not too long for the English Minstrelsy I will with great pleasure send off
                    a corrected copy for it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem was first published as &#8216;Queen Urraia and the Five
                        Martyrs of Morocco&#8217; in the <title>Morning Post</title> in early September 1803, and in the <title>Iris</title>, 3 November
                        1804. It was published as &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best
                            English Authors; with some Original Pieces Hitherto Unpublished</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), I, pp. 269&#8211;280. It was also
                        published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I feel so perfectly confident <del>that</del> of making a triumphant answer to Sir J Moores friends, that it will
                    greatly disappoint me if <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> does not entrust James Moores history, &amp; the
                    other books upon the subject to my hands.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British commander, Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), who was
                        killed in battle at Corunna on 16 January 1809 after a disastrous retreat. Southey was highly critical of Moore&#8217;s conduct,
                        accusing him, for example, of forming &#8216;unjust and self-paralysing prejudices against the Spanish people&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 479. James Moore (1762&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), surgeon and biographer,
                        defended his elder brother in <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British Army in Spain</title> (1809). The &#8216;other
                        books&#8217; were perhaps Adam Neale (1778?-1832), <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain: Comprising an Account of the Operations
                            of the Armies under their Excellencies Sir Arthur Wellesley and Sir John Moore</title> (1809). Possibly Robert Ker Porter
                        (1777&#8211;1842), <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain: Written During the March of the British Troops under Sir John Moore. By
                            an Officer</title> (1809).</note> The whole line of the retreat I have in strong recollection having walked from Coru&#241;a to
                    Benevente, &#8211; no country can be stronger by nature than that part of it which is called the Bierzo. But as you say the battle
                    should have been fought at Somosierra, &#8211; if our troops could not have joined Blake,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Lieutenant General Joaqu&#237;n Blake y Joyes (1759&#8211;1827), a Spanish army officer who served with distinction in the war against
                        France.</note> there they should have been, &amp; under the walls of Madrid, which would then have been saved from Morlas<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> General Tom&#225;s de Morla y Pacheco (1748&#8211;1812), agent of the Junta that governed unoccupied
                        Spain, misled Moore as to the whereabouts of the French and the support to be given the British by Spanish troops. Arriving at
                        Madrid, Morla negotiated its surrender to Napoleon, and was subsequently branded a traitor.</note> treason, &amp; would have
                    vied with Zaragoza.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two sieges of Zaragoza took place in 1808&#8211;1809. For Southey&#8217;s
                        accounts: <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 306&#8211;321; and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508&#8211;527.</note> The next news will be that Madrid is evacuated, &amp; the French falling back to
                    the Ebro. There I trust <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellesley</ref> will follow them, &amp; all must go on
                    well.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>