<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1486</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2608</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 477&#8211;480.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1486" type="letter">
        <head>1486. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-08-03">3 August
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought./ Plymouth
                        Dock<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 477&#8211;480.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1808-08-03">August 3. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was, as you may well suppose, right glad to learn that you had joined your ship at last, &amp; now God speed the
                    Dread nought!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was a 98-gun second rate ship of the
                        line launched in 1801. She had fought at Trafalgar (1805) and was now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby
                        (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s
                    acquaintance.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How provoking that you should not be here! The Floating Island came up ten days ago, &amp; there it is now. &#8211; &amp;
                        <del>xx</del> if you had been here, we would have put our wits to work, &amp; tried all sorts of experiments upon it. It is
                    about half an acre of the bottom of the Lake forced up to the top, &amp; kept there by what cause Heaven knows, &#8211; but probably the
                    same <del>as that</del> which produces the bottom winds. A M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wolseley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Reverend Robert Wolseley (d. 1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740&#8211;1817). The family seat was at Wolseley Park, Rugeley in Staffordshire.</note> who is laking here for the summer, &amp; brought letters from <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref>, ventured on it, &amp; had some difficulty to get off again, &#8211; he says there
                    is a frightful hole in the middle, &#8211; which it would be certain death to approach. The first time I saw it was about 20 hours after
                    its appearance. the waters were quite still &amp; I could see the rough sides of its banks, &#8211; there were near it holes in the
                    bottom like peat-bogs, &#8211; &amp; at a little distance a thin steam might plainly be seen rising from the water. This was not there a
                    few days ago, &amp; the edges of the island, instead of being just on a level with the lake, &#8211; or rather just above it, had bent
                    downwards, like the flaps of a table which is heavy laden &amp; supported by insufficient brackets. A very very odd thing it is,
                    &amp; I heartily wish you had been here, &#8211; we would have sounded in all directions, got at the hole in the middle by means of
                    planks, &amp; tried whether the island was moveable or not, for the thing desirable it is to tow it away, &amp; examine the place
                    from whence it came.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Lakers have flowed in upon us like a spring tide. Stafford of Liverpool was the first; &#8211; he came with a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Duckworth of Manchester,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> a man whose appearance
                    was very prepossessing &amp; who brought a large family of daughters with him. <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharpe</ref>
                    made his appearance next &amp; remained a week at the Queens Head.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> An inn in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</note> Lord Darnley<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bligh, 4th
                        Earl of Darnley (1767&#8211;1831).</note> called upon him here one morning which I suppose was meant as the least formal way of
                    being introduced to me, &#8211; a very good natured man. I dined with him at the R Oak,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Another
                            <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> inn.</note> &amp; he begged leave to renew his acquaintance when he came
                    again, He &amp; his Countess have fallen in love with the Island, &#8211; but tho I like them well, I should be very sorry to change the
                    Lady of the Lake for any other Lady, &amp; the Imperial for any thing less than Imperial.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Derwent Isle, the usual summer residence of the the Lady of the Lake &#8211; <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachey</ref>
                        &#8211; and her husband the Imperial, <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Lt. Col. Peachey</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Wolesley<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 2.</note> was at Westminster with me, &#8211;
                    at the head of the school when I went there. he is botanizing, &amp; learning Welsh out of my books. His wife is a goodnatured
                    woman, <del>&amp; xx</del> but she makes unmerciful morning visits.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Wolseley married a Miss Hand; her first name and dates are not known.</note> You may remember the name of an Admiral who was his
                        Uncle.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wolseley (1756&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer, who was
                        promoted to Rear Admiral in 1804.</note> &#8211; Beside them a <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Browne</ref> &amp; his daughter are lodging here, they are young &amp; not handsome, but to be much liked when they are known
                    &#8211; &amp; the father a fine respectable man, with a good solid understanding. He also wants the island, &#8211; &amp; would buy
                    Pocklingtons house<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The house on Derwent Isle, where the Peacheys spent their summers, had
                        been built for Joseph Pocklington (1736&#8211;1817), who had bought the island in 1778. Pocklington also had there a Druids&#8217; circle
                        and a fort and battery, from which he fired cannon during the annual Derwentwater regattas.</note> I believe if it be to be
                    sold. <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barkers</ref> Uncle from Llandaff called on Monday &#8211; post haste in the way to
                    Glasgow, &#8211; he would not stay to sup here press him whatever I could, &#8211; &amp; he sent <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> a brace of excellent pines,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Jeremiah Homfray (1759&#8211;1833), was Mary
                        Barker&#8217;s maternal uncle; his gift was of pineapples.</note> &#8211; which you should have been here to have criticised, &amp;
                    compared with those which grow in the open air in their native climate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">Tom Smiths</ref> present of a N Wiltshire cheese came last week, &amp; the rug which had
                    travelled in company as far as Kendal was left there for another carriers-day. <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> For
                        Southey&#8217;s letter acknowledging these, see Southey to Thomas Smith, 15 August 1808, Letter 1492.</note> Tomorrow we expect it.
                        <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> Hist. of the Slave Trade is arrived &#8211; as a presentation copy.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Clarkson (1760&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the Rise, Progress, and
                            Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808).</note> The title page
                    of the Cid<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note>
                    was returned yesterday to the Printer. <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Freres</ref> translations are by this time in
                    his hands; they are to be printed in an Appendix, with the original below, in a smaller type &amp; this &amp; the Table of
                    Contents will fill about three sheets more. A fortnight will compleat the whole &amp; by that time it will probably be published.
                    My last<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Thomas Southey, 11 July 1808, Letter 1478.</note> told
                    you I was just finishing the 9 section of Kehama,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is now just drawing to its end: it is a long
                    one 270 lines written, &#8211; &amp; about thirty or forty more to compleat it. When compleated the new part of the poem will be rather
                    longer than what was written before. Your transcript stands still &#8211; because as all the new part is written in rhyme, it becomes
                    necessary to rhyme all before it, except what is in some very strongly marked metre, &#8211; or has some very strong passion to bear it
                    up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Miss Wood<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isabella Wood (dates unknown), cousin of <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>.</note> has been prevented from coming by a most unpleasant
                    circumstance. Some friends of <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> were on a visit at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Nether hall</ref>, &#8211; &amp; the Lady owing it is said to travelling in the hot weather fell
                    ill, &amp; was in danger when we last heard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My cold is fairly gone &#8211; I was up <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> last week with Wolseley, &#8211; a
                    magnificent cloud rose under our feet when we were on the top, &#8211; it rose from the Dod, &#8211; filled it compleatly, &amp; cut off our
                    view of Basenthwaite, &#8211; but repaid us with something far finer. It was truly a grand sight to behold it rising below like bright
                    smoke in the sunshine. The boat wants you. We took <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharpe</ref> out to tea in it, &amp; I
                    have rowed the women up to the floating island, which is near the shore, by the birch grove between Pocklingtons<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Derwent Isle.</note> &amp; <ref target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref>. The Lake has been so
                    low that one day when I went out to bathe &amp; took <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Job</ref> with me, in going
                    across the oars touched the bottom &lt;at&gt; every stroke, &#8211; &amp; it was not possible to get into the river. Our weather has
                    been &lt;as&gt; fine since you left us as it had been for six weeks before, &#8211; &amp; yet there has been rain enough in the night,
                    &amp; in day showers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pelayo<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s original name for the poem which became <title>Roderick,
                            Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is not yet begun, nor will it be till I flag with Kehama which will not be yet
                    for one or two cantos, for I see my road clear before me. In the next Arvalan is to be smashed against the great adamant at the
                    Pole, &#8211; &amp; then he will lie &#8216;cased in polar ice&#8217; &amp; howling to his father, till Kehama accomplishes that sacrifice which
                    Ladurlad spoilt by killing the horse, &#8211; &amp; ousts Indra from the Swerga.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events in
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book 11.</note> Then there is to be &#8216;boderation&#8217; in that Heaven, &#8211; the Curse takes
                    effect again &amp; Kalyal is sent to the famous temple of Juggernaut &#8211; where all sorts of strange things <del>will</del> are to
                        happen.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book 14.</note> There will be bustle &amp; business enough, &amp; the farther it gets on,
                    the finer it is likely to be.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> is in Bettys<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> A servant of the
                        Southeys.</note> phrase &#8216;a grand talker grown&#8217; he tries to say every thing, &amp; seldom fails to make himself understood.
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> continues as quiet &amp; as good a sleeper as ever &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> is the worthiest of children.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>