<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.912</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2034</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.912" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="912" type="letter">
        <head>912. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-03-12">12 March
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Rather than let <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> go empty handed I will gallop thro a
                    letter. We are expecting somewhat eagerly the contents of <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">old Lovells</ref> will; that if
                    he has not made provision for <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref>, <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph</ref> may do it, or see that it is done; on this you may be sure I shall be very explicit with them &amp; very
                    plain-spoken. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref> is very <del>xxxx</del> &lt;ill&gt; &#8211; she has fairly fretted
                    herself out, &amp; is in my opinion in decline, induced wholly by <del>xxx</del> perpetual discontent. All else are well &#8211; &amp;
                    if I can as much about a month hence you may give me joy as a happy man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is going certainly to Malta,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge travelled abroad to Malta for his health, taking up a temporary post as private secretary to Sir
                        Alexander Ball (1757&#8211;1809), the naval officer governing Malta.</note> certainly as far <del>any</del> as any thing that
                    respects him can be said to be certain before it has taken place. this was the account of his letter, &amp; that he expected to be
                    on his voyage in a fortnights time, but I suppose <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> has heard a more full account from
                        <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> than I give you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a box of books to my great joy arrived at Liverpool &#8211; &amp; the merchant to whom they are consigned (a
                        <del>Portugueze</del> &lt;Lisbon&gt; friend) designs to do his best to cheat his Majesty, quoting a Portugueze proverb &#8211; &#8216;who
                    robs a thief shall be forgiven a hundred years Purgatory.&#8217; To be sure it is a truly abominable tax, &amp; disgraceful to a
                    civilized nation. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith</ref> has written to me &#8211; as you may
                    suppose &#8211; very civilly. they still hold their intention of visiting the Lakes this coming summer, &amp; I hope you can arrange
                    your journey so as to be there at the same time. I expect to live in one continual round of company during the summer. the Lakers
                    come by swarms &#8211; &amp; begin to look upon the Poets among the curiosities of the country, &amp; get letters of introduction &#8211; as
                    people do tickets to the grotto at Clifton.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The grotto at Goldeney Hall, Clifton, Bristol,
                        was made in the early eighteenth century and is still in existence.</note> We ought to charge five shillings admittance.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent5"> King <del>Alf</del> Alfred is sent<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Cottle, <title>Alfred; an
                                Epic Poem, in Twenty-four Books</title>, the second edition (1803) of which Southey had just received from its
                            author.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent5"> To me, a pres&#275;n&#772;t </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> That I may behold his new birth.</l>
          <l rend="indent5"> But his coming down</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Cost me half-a-crown, &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Which is thirty pence more than his worth.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle</ref> in his preface observes &#8216;that <hi rend="ital">interest</hi> can only be attained by <hi rend="ital">moving the breast</hi>,&#8217; &#8211; an apothecary attains it by moving the
                    bowels. <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> should read the second edition &amp; compare it with the first &#8211; which I
                    suppose he will rather decline upon the plea of business, however let him look in the Preface &amp; see a passage from the noble
                    Alfred translated by the author into the florid style of poetry, for the sake of <del>comparing</del> contrast. If he be at all
                    hypochondriac at the time, its effect may lead him to introduce a class of remedies called gelasticks.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey presumably means to laugh, from the Greek word &#8216;Gelos&#8217; which means &#8216;laughter&#8217;. A gelastic seizure is a rare fit of crying or laughing that breaks out in a person with no apparent cause.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must tell you a good story of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyds</ref> youngest brother. he
                    had served his apprenticeship at Ipswich to a brewer, &amp; being now in business himself was passing thro that town, when he saw
                    a girl at a window whom he knew well by sight, tho they had never spoken to each other. However now an inclination of the head
                    past between them &#8211; as persons who had not seen each other for some time, <del>xxx</del> he asked her to let him in &#8211; &amp; never
                    having said a word to her before in his life &#8211; he actually made her an offer, &#8211; she only asked time to consider &#8211; &amp; so they
                    are to be married &#8211; or are so by this time. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Ll.</ref> &amp; his wife both aver this
                    to be literally &amp; strictly true.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This weather makes me quite long to be lazy &#8211; to go upon the hillside &amp; lie down in the sun, &amp; without even
                    the trouble of thinking, breathe the warm spring air, &amp; feel the comfort of existence. the birds are all alive, &amp; the very
                    flies have crept out of their winter hiding places &amp; are buzzing about the window. And yet I seldom get out for want of
                    company, &amp; of an object. if I do not live within reach of a booksellers, &amp; of a few stalls my legs will be of little use
                    to me. this morning I have only been down the orchard to fling a few stones in the river &amp; now am I yawning for pure laziness.
                    if I had been born a Prince I should have beat the Stadtholder hollow in sleeping.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly a reference to William V (1748&#8211;1806), Prince of Orange-Nassau, who was the last Stadtholder of the Dutch Republic.
                        Between 1795 and 1806 he led the Government of the Dutch Republic in Exile in London, and was caricatured asleep by James
                        Gillray (1757&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) in his satirical print <title>The Orangerie</title> (1796).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am getting on with all my occupations &#8211; &amp; as soon as Edith is safely in bed<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s daughter, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, was born on 30 April
                        1804.</note> &#8211; as I hope she will be early in April shall think of travelling Londonward to deal with the Devils.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The printers.</note> Now if you have any business in town this spring let us contrive to
                    meet.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours in haste</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1804-03-12">Monday. March 12. 1804.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>