<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1341</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2463</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4856 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        198&#8211;203.Dating note: dating inferred by endorsement.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1341" type="letter">
        <head>1341. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1807-07">[July
                        1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 31
                        July<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4856 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                        198&#8211;203.<lb />Dating note: dating inferred by endorsement.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> How much better a Decameron might you make yourself, than you can translate from Tressan!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis-&#201;lisabeth de la Vergne, Comte de Tressan (1705&#8211;1783), translator of the <title>Decameron</title> of
                        Giovanni Boccaccio (1313&#8211;1375) into French.</note> Tressan frenchifies &amp; modernizes &amp; Parisianizes every thing which
                    he touches, &amp; tho I like French cookery, yet their literary cookery absolutely nauseates me whenever there be one serious
                    ingredient in the mixture. It would cost you little more trouble to draw from your own well, than to rebottle water which he had
                    distilled till it has lost all its life &amp; freshness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you remember the story of Thorkill in Saxo Grammaticus? L.8.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Saxo
                        Grammaticus (c. 1150&#8211;1220), author of the <title>Gesta Danorum</title>, a sixteen book Latin history of Scandanavia. In Book 8
                        appears the story of Thorkill, who piloted King Gorm up river to a magical land where the women, the food, the drink and the
                        treasures are all charmed, and destroy those who partake of them.</note> &#8211; I transcribed it ten years ago with the view of
                    making something out of it. You might easily dress it up into a <del>xxxx</del> fine tale: &#8211; I wish I could see you versify some
                    wild legends as you versified Ellenore;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor&#8217;s translation of the supernatural ballad
                        &#8216;Lenore&#8217; by Gottfried August B&#252;rger (1747&#8211;1794) was published in March 1796, in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> &#8211;
                    were you to make a volume of such things I would gladly repay some old Anthology<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor
                        had given Southey the idea for the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800).</note> debts to you, &amp; thank you for
                    giving me a motive to write verse, &#8211; which without strong motive I am in danger of neglecting till the habit perhaps may be lost.
                    St Athendio &amp; the Devil &#8211; the five martyrs &#8211; King Ramiro, Garci Ferrandez &#8211; &amp; <del>xxxx</del> the Inchcape Bell are at
                    your service,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published these poems as follows: &#8216;A True Ballad of St Antidius, the
                        Pope, and the Devil&#8217; in the <title>Morning Post</title> in early February 1803 and revised for <title>Minor Poems</title>
                        (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838); &#8216;Queen Urraia and the Five Martyrs of Morocco&#8217; in the
                            <title>Morning Post</title> in early September 1803, in the <title>Iris</title>, 3 November 1804, in <title>English
                            Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with some Original Pieces hitherto
                            unpublished</title> (2 vols, Edinburgh, 1810), in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (Edinburgh, 1810),
                        in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838); &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; in September 1803
                        in the <title>Morning Post</title> and on 12 May 1804 in the <title>Iris</title> (edited by Taylor) and then, revised, in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and with revisions in
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838); &#8216;Garci Ferrandez&#8217;, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>
                        (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838); &#8216;The Inchcape Rock&#8217;, in
                        mid October 1803 in the <title>Morning Post</title>, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, in <title>Minor
                            Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838).</note> &amp; I would do my best to produce
                    something better for you, &#8211; for I have stories enow to spare.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Are you sure that <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref> is not really &amp; rightly quoting Leyden, who
                    may have given your matter in his own words? I have not the book to refer to, but you are aware I suppose that there is a D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Leyden,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Leyden (1775&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), son of a
                        shepherd, miscellaneous writer, ballad collector, friend of Heber and of Scott. Leyden&#8217;s facility for languages earned him a
                        career in Britain&#8217;s Indian colonies.</note> a very odd fish, but a man of great antiquarian knowledge, &amp; great genius, if
                    he did but know what to do with it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">Owen</ref> lent me when I was last in town a tale of King Arthurs Court from the
                        Mabinogion,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was reading a translation by Owen Pughe of the Welsh romances
                        dating from the eleventh to the thirteenth centuries, collected in fourteenth-century Welsh manuscripts and known as the
                        Mabinogi. Some of these were published in the journal edited by Pughe, <title>The Cambrian Register</title> (1796, 1799),
                        where they are entitled <title>The Mabinogion, or Juvenile Amusements, being Ancient Welsh Romances</title>. The tales
                        preserving Arthurian lore are <title>Culhwch ac Olwen</title> (Culhwch and Olwen), <title>Peredur son of Efrawg</title> and
                            <title>Breuddwyd Rhonabwy</title> (The Dream of Rhonabwy).</note> truly Welsh &amp; savage. If it be possible to make him
                    get thro this work <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> will do it, but poor Owen is one of <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcotts</ref> four &amp; twenty Elders, &#8211; to whom Espriella will soon introduce
                        you,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) included a section on
                            Southcott. For this section see <ref type="l" target="/editions/southey_prophecy/">
              <title>Robert Southey and
                                Millenarianism: Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic Era</title>
            </ref>.</note> if you <del>x</del> are yet ignorant of this mystery
                    of fatuity rather than iniquity. You will find too an account of the Swedenborgian mythology there,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A religious movement that developed from the teachings of Emanuel Swedenborg (1688&#8211;1772), a Swedish scientist
                        and theologian, who claimed to have received a new revelation from Jesus Christ. In 1788 his followers styled themselves &#8216;The
                        New Church&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s account of Swedenborgianism is given in Letter 62 of <title>Letters from England</title> (1807).</note>
                    &#8211; if you make a Decameron take some of these wild heresies for the creed of a tale, &amp; let us see a Swedenborgian romance, a
                    Manich&#230;an one &amp;c &#8211;. But to return to <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">Owen</ref> &#8211; this tale of Peridur<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Peredur Son of Efrawg</title>, in which the hero visits Arthur&#8217;s court.</note> bore no resemblance to any of the other
                    Round Table stories, &amp;, like both the other Mabinogion which I have seen, was of genuine Welsh growth.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had read translations by <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen
                            Pughe</ref> of the Welsh romances dating from the eleventh to the thirteenth centuries, collected in fourteenth-century
                        Welsh manuscripts and known as the Mabinogi; see Southey to William Taylor, 1 July 1804 (Letter 958) and 27 May 1806 (Letter
                        1189). Some of these were published in the journal edited by Pughe, <title>The Cambrian Register</title> (1796, 1799), where
                        they are entitled <title>The Mabinogion, or Juvenile Amusements, being Ancient Welsh Romances</title>. The tales preserving
                        Arthurian lore are <title>Culhwch ac Olwen</title> (Culhwch and Olwen), <title>Peredur son of Efrawg</title> and
                            <title>Breuddwyd Rhonabwy</title> (The Dream of Rhonabwy).</note> When the customs of chivalry became prevelent the
                    popular stories of all Xtendom became of one character, &#8211; before that time &lt;the fictions of&gt; each had probably a national
                    character of their own, &amp; these Welsh tales are of that earlier stamp, &#8211; Celtic <hi rend="ital">Sagas</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frank Sayers (1763&#8211;1817;
                            <title>DNB</title>); whose 1792 collection <title>Poems</title> had influenced Southey&#8217;s early work.</note> for me. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is always sending parcels to me, &amp; <del>his book</del> the expectation of
                    his book<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A new edition of Sayers&#8217;s <title>Poems, Containing Sketches of Northern
                            Mythology</title> was published in 1807.</note> will give me a new cause for pleasurable impatience, which I always feel
                    when one is on the way. By that means it may easily be conveyed. &#8211; Tell me what of my books you have not got, that when Espriella
                    is ready I may direct Longman to make amends for <del>my</del> former neglect. Remember this is a question, &amp; requires an
                    answer, at no very remote time, &#8211; for Richard Taylor<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was printing <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez. Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807).</note> has but a few sheets more to print.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry White</ref> I have all the information that his own family,
                    &amp; his own letters could supply.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had written to Taylor regarding his edition
                        of <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title> (1807); see Southey to William Taylor, 13 April 1807, Letter
                        1307.</note> You will smile to find me editing Evangelical letters, &#8211; but you will be struck by the promise of excellence
                    which many of his <del>later</del> pieces, especially of the fragments, display. Coldham &amp; Enfield<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The firm of lawyers of Middle Pavement, Nottingham, to which Kirke White was apprentice, gave him a month&#8217;s
                        leave of absence for the benefit of his health as he prepared himself for university. George Coldham (1766&#8211;1815), was <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor&#8217;s</ref> cousin.</note> were remarkably kind to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Palmerin<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> will appear nearly at the same time with Espriella &#8211; I am about the Preface. It is not so fine a book as
                        Amadis,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of the Spanish romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1803).</note> which I deem one of the great books of the world; &#8211; but it is so unlike it that it cannot be called the
                    second-best. Had I known how much it was necessary to translate I should never have undertaken it, &#8211; about a third I guess of the
                    first volume, &#8211; &amp; not less than four fifths of the last, nor than half of the second &amp; third. My next work will be the
                    Cid, which you will find <hi rend="ital">very very</hi> curious. The age of this Chronicle is not known, &#8211; the whole of it, with
                    few alterations is to be found in the General Chronicle compiled by order of Alfonso X (El Sabio)<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It
                        comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica Particular del Cid</title>, with additions from the <title>Cro&#769;nica de
                            Espan&#771;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise and the <title>Poema del Cid</title>. Here Southey also refers to the <title>Chronica
                            de Espana (las Quarto Partes Enteras de la) que Mand&#243; Componer el Rey D. Anonso el Sabio. Donde se Contienen los Acont
                            Cimientos y Haza&#241;as Mayorca y mas Se&#241;aladas que Sucedieron en Espana; des de su Primera Pobolacion Hasta Casi los Tiempos
                            del Dicho Senor Rey. Vista y Enmendada Mucha Parte de su Impression por el Florian Docampo</title> (1541).</note> &#8211; about
                    the year 1250. which is the transcript is uncertain. What is fiction must have been at least a century old before it would thus be
                    incorporated into history. There is a metrical history of the Cid of which the date also is unascertained, but it is the oldest
                    poem in the language, &amp; certainly one century anterior to the <del>Romance</del> &lt;Chronicle&gt;. Whatever of picture &amp;
                    of costume this contains &amp; the Chronicle does not I weave in, &amp; also whatever is to be found upon the subject in other
                    works of equal antiquity, &#8211; &amp; at the end of every section give full references. The Introduction will give a summary of the
                    history of Spain from the Gothick conquest, &amp; the whole will form a compleat picture of its heroic age, &amp; the most curious
                        <del>picture</del> specimen of chivalrous history in existence, as well as the oldest. It will supply the place of much
                    introductory matter to my history of Portugal, as showing the state of the peninsula at the time when that history commences, the
                    Cid having been a contemporary with Count Henrique<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry of Burgundy, Count of Portugal
                        (1066&#8211;1112).</note> &#8211; the father of the Kings of Portugal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I abhor the cry of Popery with you, but I dissent from relaxing the laws against it with Erskine<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Erskine, 1st Baron Erskine (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor between 1806
                        and 1807 in the Ministry of All the Talents.</note> &amp; with Ellenborough.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward
                        Law, 1st Baron Ellenborough (1750&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chief Justice and member of the cabinet in the Minstry of
                        all the Talents. Together, Erskine and Ellenborough were the chief law officers of a government that attempted to change the
                        law that imposed civil penalties on Catholics.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis Burdetts</ref> success is symptomatic of a healthy state of public opinion; &#8211; he is
                    very honest &#8211; I wish his ability were equal to his honesty, &#8211; &amp; wish he had a better set of about &lt;him&gt; than
                        Clifford<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Clifford (1768&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer, acted for Burdett in
                        a case arising from the Westminster election of 1807.</note> &amp; Yorke<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Redhead Yorke (1772&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), former radical writer, turned defender of the establishment, nearly fought a
                        duel with Burdett in 1806.</note> &amp; others, who <del>have</del> want that sound morality which should be the <hi rend="ital">salt</hi> of patriotism &#8211; in scriptural phrase.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The salt of the earth&#8217;:
                            <title>Matthew</title> 5: 13.</note> Sheridan daily continues to sink lower &amp; lower in baseness, flattering the mob
                    without novelty &amp; without wit, &amp; even flattering Sir Francis &#8211; after the last Middlesex election, when all these ousted
                    curs who are now looking up to the people with their tails between their legs, were yelping in one cry against him! <note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), the Whig politician who had lost his
                        seat in the Westminster election of November 1806 because of the attacks made on him in the press by radicals &#8211; principally
                        William Cobbett (1763&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>). Returned for a different constituency in the 1807 election, and hoping to
                        lead the radical Whigs in the House of Commons, Sheridan now sought the support of those who had criticised him a few months
                        previously.</note> &#8211; I am very sorry for Paul,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Paull (1770&#8211;1808;
                            <title>DNB</title>), an MP and ally of radicals &#8211; Burdett&#8217;s fellow radical candidate for Westminster in the 1807 election.
                        After disagreements, Burdett and Paull fought a duel; radicals withdrew their support of Paull; he lost the election. Plagued
                        by his duelling wound, and having suffered a gambling loss, Paull cut his throat on 15 April 1808.</note> very sorry for him,
                    he is wanted to bait M. Wellesley to death, &#8211; <del>for</del> who, I suppose, will prove to be the efficient minister.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paull attempted to hold Richard Colley Wellesley, 1st Marquess Wellesley (1760&#8211;1842;
                            <title>DNB</title>), former Governor General of Britain&#8217;s colonies in India, to account for misgovernment in India. Faced
                        by proceedings against him, Wellesley declined a ministerial position in the new government.</note> If I had resolution enough
                    to set about it I feel inklings <del>&amp; inclination</del> to address an ode to the people of Liverpool, in what may be called
                    the style documentary.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain&#8217;s largest slave trading port. The Abolition of the Slave
                        Trade passed into law on 25 March 1807; the last British slave trading ship left from Liverpool in July 1807. Southey did not
                        write such an ode.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> we may soon look for news. I miss him much at this
                    season when he has been wont, for the last three years, to come with the warm weather, bear a hand at the oar in our evening
                    parties, &amp; give me lessons in swimming. &#8211; I am angry with you for your No Popery in the Monthly:<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> In &#8216;Concerning a War Whoop&#8217;, in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 23 (1807), 327&#8211;328, Taylor argued that
                        &#8216;No Popery&#8217; campaigns had historically been repressive witch hunts.</note> &amp; <del>xxxxxxxxxxxx</del> I justify the penal
                    laws of Elizabeth &amp; James against the Priests,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> During the reigns of Elizabeth I and
                        James I a series of penal laws placed restrictions upon Catholics: they were to be prevented from holding civil office, fined
                        or imprisoned if they did not attend Anglican service, forbidden to celebrate Mass, and executed if they harboured or assisted
                        Catholic priests.</note> acknowledging at the same time the high merit of those who suffered. There was nothing else to be
                    done &#8211; the Papists burnt every heretic; &#8211; we said be Papists if you like &#8211; but you shall have no priests; it was self defence.
                    they began burning &#8211; which you have kept out of sight, &#8211; &amp; they continued it till within &lt;about&gt; thirty years, &#8211; &amp;
                    they would begin again if they dared. I am glad to find <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> agree with me in my intolerance of Popery. the measure of Ld Grenville<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bill to relieve Catholics from the remaining restrictions on them &#8211; including becoming
                        officers in the army and navy &#8211; introduced by the ministry of William Wyndham Grenville, 1st Baron Grenville (1759&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister from 1806 to 1807. The King&#8217;s refusal to accede to legislation of this kind brought
                        the ministry down.</note> was a foolish one, which would not have satisfied the Catholicks &#8211; &amp; would have introduced a
                    Popish Chaplain with every regiment &amp; every ship in the service. I would rather have had the ministry turned out, than that
                    they should have succeeded but that is not the question &lt;now&gt; at issue between the King &amp; the Constitution, in which of
                    course I go with the Constitution. But when ever such a measure is likely to be carried then I shall cry no popery as loud as I
                    can.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>