<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1551</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2673</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4860 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 229&#8211;232.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1551" type="letter">
        <head>1551. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1808-12-06">6 December
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 27 Dec<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4860 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 229&#8211;232.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>My dear friend</opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> I understand has ordered some of his
                        Prospectuses<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prospectus for Coleridge&#8217;s self-published journal <title>The
                            Friend</title>, which he produced in 1809 and 1810. For the text see <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2
                        vols (London and Princeton, 1969).</note> to be sent to you, relying upon me to write to you on the subject. He manages things
                    badly &#8211; a letter from me on the blank side of one prospectus would have done without packing off to you a bundle of papers too
                    stiff for any ordinary purpose, &#8211; &amp; a few advertisements in newspapers &amp; magazines would have done better than any
                    prospectus at all. &#8211; The thing however is done, &amp; that with so little deliberation, tho not till after much delay, &#8211; that some
                    of it requires undoing: for should he have many subscribers in the country there will be no mode of regular delivery other than by
                    post, &#8211; in that case the numbers must be stamped, &amp; stamps cover only a single sheet. Smaller type &amp; Larger paper will
                    bring it to the same quantity of contents, &amp; the same market value.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will he go on with this undertaking, &#8211; will be your first question. He can do it with little more trouble than that
                    of arranging &amp; putting together fragments already in existence, &amp; yet I will own <hi rend="ital">to you</hi> that I have
                    great doubts &amp; misgivings. &#8211; I do not like the Prospectus. It is too much like what it pretends to be, too fit for a letter,
                    to be proper for the public. There is an injudicious adulation, as it may almost be called, of his friends, &amp; an overdone
                        <del>xxxx</del>abasement of himself, &#8211; on the whole a want of manliness which I cannot away with. But assuredly if he carries
                    it into effect great things will be done; &#8211; sounder criticism &amp; sounder philosophy established as well as addressed, than
                    modern ages have seen; great truths upholden, &amp; the axe laid at the root of those great errors which have been for the last
                    century held <del>xxxxxxxx</del>to be the very name &amp; thirty articles of philosophical faith.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you collect your synonimes you would do well to mark what is the existing use of words, as well as to hunt out
                    their primary meaning. I am almost pleased that you persevere so steadily in this collection, which will form a very valuable book
                    in itself, &amp; be of signal utility to the compilers of a national dictionary, whenever that work shall be undertaken.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Taylor&#8217;s <title>English Synonyms Discriminated</title> was published in
                        1813.</note> I believe I shall withdraw from the Athen&#230;um altogether. <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> among other rejections has thought proper to suppress an article in the Omniana, for no other
                    imaginable reason than that it called Pitt a babbler<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> &amp; Buonaparte a barbarian. I do not blame him for
                    rejecting any thing which he thinks dull, because God knows any magazine <del>xxxx</del>which he conducts will always have its
                    full complement of dull matter, &#8211; but this was a curious collection of facts about the change of climate in the last fifty years,
                    put together <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;as is my custom&#8217;.</note> &amp; his
                    only objection can have been <del>to the</del> that the politicks are not in accord with his own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a precious article is that in defence of Polygamy!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;An Obstacle to the
                        Conversion of the Hindoos Considered&#8217;, <title>The Athen&#230;um, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>
                        (November, 1808), 407&#8211;412.</note> the writer did not recollect that the Polyandrian system in Malabar utterly overthrows the
                    physical assertion on which he rests, &amp; that Xtianity originated in a hot climate. The Moravian Missionaries make no
                    difficulty about the matter, &#8211; they let a convert keep his wives, following S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls authority, that it is
                    unjust to put a heathen wife away against her consent, &amp; perceiving the cruelty of giving <del>x</del> our institutions a
                    retroactive effect, in this case. The only difference they make is that a man under such circumstances is not appointed to any
                    office in the church. Thus <del>xx</del> the obstacle to conversion is effectually removed, &amp; <del>they</del> the children
                    being educated Xtians, naturally obey the Xtian ordinances. I am writing a View &amp; Vindication of the existing Protestant
                    missions for an unborn review which has never yet been heard of, &amp; has <del>as yet</del> neither name nor existence, but will
                    &lt;hoist the bloody flag&gt; run along side the Edinburgh &amp; engage her yard arm &amp; yard arm.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> What wretched work ha<del>d</del>s Sidney Smith made
                    of this subject of the Missions!<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Indian
                        Missions&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 12:23 (April 1808), 151&#8211;181.</note> It were better be a fanatic than such a
                    buffoon as this, for fanaticism implies some feeling, some sincerity, some heart of flesh &amp; blood.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is writing a pamphlet upon the cursed
                        Cintra-Convention,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Concerning the Concerning the Relations of
                            Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically as Affected
                            by the Convention of Cintra</title> (1809) was triggered by the agreement, made on 30 August 1808, of the British generals
                        to allow a defeated Napoleonic army to withdraw from Portugal to France unmolested and with its weapons &#8211; a decision he and
                        Southey thought pusillanimous.</note> &#8211; it will be in that strain of political morality to which Hutchinson, &amp; Milton,
                    &amp; Sidney<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Three republican writers: Algernon Sidney (1623&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>),
                        executed for involvement in the Rye House plot to assassinate the monarch. John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>),
                        republican polemicist as well as poet; Colonel John Hutchinson (1615&#8211;1664; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan commander in the
                        English civil war and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I, as revealed in a posthumously published memoir by
                        his widow, Lucy Hutchinson (1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>): <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806).
                        In the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 361&#8211;378, Southey extolled the conduct and morality of
                        Hutchinson.</note> could have set their hands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Brazil goes off to press in a few days,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> having travelled into Herefordshire<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, to his uncle Herbert Hill, resident at Staunton-on-Wye.</note> &amp; back for revision
                    &amp; correction. Do not expect a splendid book, &#8211; there is no splendour in the materials of which it is composed, &#8211; look for an
                    honest one, with that pervading life &amp; soul <del>of free opinion</del> which nothing but free opinion &amp; the love of God
                    &amp; man can give, &amp; you will not be disappointed.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1808-12-06"> Dec 6. 1808.</date>
          </p>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>