<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1130</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2252</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 357&#8211;60 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1130" type="letter">
        <head>1130. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-12-07">7 December
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey./ H. M. S. Amelia/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kitts/ or elsewhere./ Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ DEC10<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 357&#8211;60 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-12-07">December 7. 1805.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Dear Tom I was preparing last night to write to you, but the newspaper came, &amp; seeing therein that a mail was
                    arrived I waited till this evening for a letter &amp; have not been disappointed. Thank you for the turtle, &amp; thank Heaven it
                    has never reached me; &#8211; in bodily fear lest it should I wrote off immediately to give it to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams
                        Wynn, 24 November 1805, Letter 1125.</note> &amp; if he had not been in town should have given it to any body who would have
                    been kind enough to have eased me of so inconvenient a visitor. How the Devil Tom could you think of sending me a turtle! When
                    indeed I come to be Lord Mayor it may be a suitable present<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Turtle was served annually to the Lord Mayor of London and assembled dignitaries on the day of the Lord Mayor&#8217;s show.</note> &#8211; but now! &#8211; Its carriage down would have been not less than forty
                    shillings &#8211; &amp; we should have been quite as much puzzled with it as the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">Old
                        Gentleman</ref> was. Nobody would have known how to kill it, how to cut it up, or how to dress it &#8211; there would have been
                    nobody here to help us to eat it nobody to whom we could have given it. &#8211; Whether <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has got it I cannot tell, but most likely <del>xxx</del> it has been eaten upon the way.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The turtle did not reach <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, but died in quarantine; see Southey
                        to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806, Letter 1140.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You mention the contents of poor Ld Probys<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby
                        (1779&#8211;1804), eldest son of John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), who was the previous
                        captain of Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> and had recently died of yellow fever.</note> common place
                    books. If you can procure them for his father Ld Carysfort,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of
                        Carysfort: judge, diplomat, Whig politician and poet, who was the author of <title>Dramatic and Narrative Poems</title>
                        (1810). He was a fellow pupil of Southey&#8217;s at Westminster School.</note> both he &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will be exceedingly obliged to you.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had recently described these
                        in a letter to Wynn; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 24 November 1805, Letter 1125.</note> I am desired by <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to say this, &#8211; or indeed if you can send any thing that belongs to him which
                    would be likely to be valued by his friends. If you can get the papers direct them to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211; 5. Stone Buildings, Lincolns Inn &#8211; London &#8211; by the by you asked his direction, &amp; this is it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Extracts are very interesting, but several have miscarried &#8211; the Devil seems to be Post-Master General on that
                    station. Go on as you have begun, &amp; you will soon collect more &amp; more valuable materials than you are aware of. Describe a
                    W. Indian tavern &#8211; its difference from ours. Go to church one Sunday, to describe church &amp; congregation. Inquire at every town
                    if there be any schools there &#8211; any dissenters &#8211; how the Methodists get on. collect some Jamaica newspapers, &#8211; &amp; if you can
                    the magazine which is printed there. Your Tortola<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The largest island in the Caribbean
                        group, the British Virgin Islands.</note>-letter is a very delightful one. Put down all the stories you hear. When you go
                    ashore take notice of the insects that you see &#8211; the birds <del>xxx</del> all make parts of the picture. <del>xxx</del> Lose
                    nothing that a Creole, or any man acquainted with the Islands, tells you concerning them. Send me all the stories about
                        Pompey<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Pompey&#8217; was a popular name for African slaves, after Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus,
                        also known as &#8216;Pompey the Great&#8217; (106&#8211;48 BC), a military and political leader of the late Roman republic.</note> &#8211; he must be
                    a curious character. ask him his history. What sort of churchyards, have they? any epitaphs? where do they bury the Negroes? is
                    there any funeral service for them?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom eventually published his &#8216;extracts&#8217; as <title>A
                            Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1828).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My last was directed to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Kitts,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of the Leeward
                        Islands in the West Indies.</note> where it seems I must direct always! &#8211; in all my last letters I have advised you to get to
                    Europe if you can. Sir Samuel is made Admiral in the last promotions.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vice-Admiral Sir
                        Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), had been in command of the fleet in which Tom Southey served, and
                        was replaced by Admiral Sir Alexander Forrester Inglis Cochrane (1758&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I have heard nothing
                    of his having <del>a</del> command &#8211; but certainly he is a man to look to, &amp; one who will not be laid aside upon the shelf. I
                    go to Lisbon next year, most likely not till the Autumn. Whether <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> goes will
                    depend upon the state of politics, for <del>xxx</del> it would be foolish to take her if there should be much danger of being
                    turned out. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is still there &amp; will stay as long as he can. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> has left the service a third time &#8211; is with <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref>, &amp; struts about in regimentals &#8211; tho he has no commission. he told <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> three months ago he was to be gazetted the next week as Lieutenant in the
                    Caermarthenshire &#8211; now he says it is to be in the regulars at once. Nothing that he says is to be believed. He never tells truth &#8211;
                    unless there is any thing to be got by it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am happy to hear you have got rid of the Amsterdammers.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amsterdammers
                        was a Southey family name for haemorrhoids; see Southey to John Rickman, 26 June 1807, Letter 1336.</note> the complaint seems
                    to be so common that I think myself fortunate to have lived at this age without ever having experienced it. &#8211; You talk of
                    invasion. depend upon it, it never will &amp; never can be attempted while our fleet is what it is, &#8211; &amp; poor Nelson<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horatio, 1st Viscount Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233; (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), who had
                        recently been killed at the Battle of Trafalgar in October 1805.</note> has left its name higher than ever. Good God what a
                    blaze of glory as he departed in! &#8211; the Spaniards you will see behaved most honourably to the men who were wrecked &amp; who fell
                    into their hands &#8211; &amp; about our wounded, &#8211; &amp; the French very ill. Continental Politics are too much in the dark for me to
                    say any thing. it is by no means clear that Prussia will take part against France &#8211; tho highly probable, &amp; now highly politic.
                    if she should I think Bonapartes victories may prove his destruction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Still busy reviewing &#8211; the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &amp; 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Annuals should be at Barbadoes by
                    this time. You have somewhere an account of my articles in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. In the third look at these articles as mine
                    &#8211; Chap.1. Numbers. 5. 6. 9. 11. Chap 3 &#8211; N<hi rend="sup">os</hi> 8. 9. 17. Ch. 5 &#8211; N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 11. Ch. 8. &#8211; 9. 10. 11.
                    16. 17. Ch. 10 &#8211; 1. 3. 5. 6. 7. 9. 10. 11. 13. 14. 17. 18. 19. 21. 22. 23. 27. 30. 31. Ch. 12. &#8211; 2. 3. 4. 7. 8. Ch. 21. &#8211; 8. &#8211; All
                    these good bad &amp; indifferent are mine.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review
                            for 1804</title>, 3 (1805): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of Travels into the Interior of
                            Southern Africa, in the years 1797 and 1798, including Observations on the Geology &amp; Geography, the Natural History
                            ... and Sketches of the Various Tribes Surrounding the Cape of Good Hope</title>, Vol. II (1804), 22&#8211;33; Robert Percival
                        (1765&#8211;1826), <title>An Account of the Cape of Good Hope</title> (1804), 34&#8211;41; Daniel Mackinnen (1767&#8211;1830), <title>A Tour
                            Through the British West Indies, in the years 1802 and 1803 giving a Particular Account of the Bahama Islands</title>
                        (1804), 50&#8211;56; John Barrow, <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and Comparisons Made and Collected
                            in the Course of a Short Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a Subsequent Journey from Pekin to
                            Canton</title> (1804), 69&#8211;83; <title>Sir John Froissart&#8217;s Chronicles of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from
                            the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans. Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816;
                            <title>DNB</title>) (1804), 189&#8211;194; George Heriot (1766&#8211;1844), <title>The History of Canada, From its First Discovery:
                            Comprehending an Account of the Original Establishment of the Colony of Louisiana,</title> 194&#8211;197; <title>Part the First
                            of An Address to the Public from the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with
                            a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803),
                        225&#8211;231; Edward Ledwich (1738&#8211;1823), <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398&#8211;413; <title>Original Correspondence
                            of Jean Jacques Rousseau, with Mad. La Tour de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title> (1804), 485&#8211;488; Anna Seward,
                            <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on his Writings</title> (1804),
                        488&#8211;93; David Irving (1778&#8211;1850),<title> The Lives of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary Dissertations on the Literary
                            History of Scotland and the Early Scotish Drama</title> (1804), 493&#8211;499; Walter Scott, <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical
                            Romance by Thomas of Ercildoune</title> (1804), 555&#8211;563; Charles Abraham Elton (1778&#8211;1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804),
                        564&#8211;565; William Day (dates unknown), <title>The Shepherd&#8217;s Boy: being Pastoral Tales</title> (1804), 567&#8211;568; E. Warren
                        (dates unknown), <title>The Poet&#8217;s Day, or, Imagination&#8217;s Ramble</title> (1804), 568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a
                            Series of Prints, Designed by her Royal Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with
                            Poetical Illustrations by T. P</title> [Thomas Park (1758/9&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>)] (1804), 568&#8211;580; Thomas Green
                        Fessenden (1771&#8211;1837), <title>Original Poems</title> (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777&#8211;1805), <title>The Powers of
                            Genius</title> (1801), 571; Thomas Clio Rickman (1761&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in Celebration of the
                            Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint Domingo, November 29, 1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield, <title>Good
                            Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert Spencer (1770&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of Sorrow</title>
                        (1804), 574&#8211;575; <title>British Purity: or, the World we Live in. A Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries&#8230;By Lory Lucian and Jerry
                            Juvenal, &#8230; Assisted by S. Scriblerus, etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804), 575; William Falconer (1732&#8211;1769), <title>The
                            Shipwreck,</title> (1804), ed., James Stanier Clarke (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), 577&#8211;580; William Tooke (1777&#8211;1863),
                        ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles Churchill: with Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his Life</title>
                        (1804), 580&#8211;585; J. Amphlett (dates unknown), <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title> (1804), 585; Joseph
                        Jefferson (1766&#8211;1824), <title>Horae Poetic&#230;. Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586&#8211;587; Alexander Campbell
                        (1764&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804), 587&#8211;591; William Crowe
                        (bap. 1745, d. 1829; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593&#8211;594; John Finlay (1782&#8211;1810),
                            <title>Wallace, or, The Vale of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594&#8211;596; Jessie Stewart (dates unknown),
                            <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768&#8211;1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected with
                            Literature. Imitated from the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597&#8211;598; <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> (1804), 621&#8211;634; Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Celtic Researches, on
                            the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language, of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive
                            Society</title> (1804), 634&#8211;644; [Anon.] <title>No Slaves - No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour
                            of the African Trade by a Liverpool Merchant</title> (1804), 644&#8211;648; William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813), <title>Indian
                            Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title>
                        (1803), 658&#8211;670; John Gardiner (fl. 1758&#8211;1792), <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670&#8211;674;
                        Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the Fresco Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918&#8211;923.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref> you can always discover, &amp; &#8211; except in the
                    scientific part, there is little or nothing good in the work but what comes from him or from me. His chief department is in the
                    historical &amp; political part, &#8211; &amp; whatever he touches he fertilizes. In the next volume he reviews Madoc,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Taylor reviewed <title>Madoc</title> (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4
                        (1806), 604&#8211;613.</note> who has been abused beyond all bounds in the Monthly<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) reviewed <title>Madoc</title> in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, n. s. 48 (October
                        1805), 113&#8211;122.</note>
          <del>xxx</del> such clumsy malice as fairly to defeat itself. the passages quoted to be abused there &amp; in the Edinburgh<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis Jeffrey</ref> reviewed <title>Madoc</title> in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> struck Windham,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">William Windham
                                (1750&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary for War and the Colonies, 1806&#8211;1807.</note> so much that
                    he expressed great admiration to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211; &amp; sent for the book. Surely you have it
                    from Barbadoes by this time. &#8211; The Spaniard<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> goes on well &#8211; about half done. I give to it
                    all the intervals of reviewing &amp; shall have it published in the spring, when I must go to London, to get the Specimens<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly edited anthology, <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (1807).</note> concluded over which <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &lt;will
                    then&gt; have been dawdling <del>eigh</del> two compleat years!! &#8211; I mean to publish the history of the Cid in a little
                        volume<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> &#8211;
                    with learned notes, full of Spanish erudition. All this will fill up my winter &amp; spring After this year I review no more. &#8211; It
                    will be very hard if better employments should not pay me better. I do not regret the time thus far bestowed upon it, &#8211; by no
                    other means could I have acquired such facility of stile &#8211; it has been a useful apprenticeship, &amp; has had also the advantage
                    of making me acquire much information, &amp; looking into my own opinions upon many subjects on which I should not else have
                    thought. &#8211; No farther news of the sale of Madoc. the reviews will probably hurt it for a time &#8211; that is in their power &amp; that
                    is all they can do. Unquestionably the Poem will stand &amp; flourish. I am perfectly satisfied with the execution, &#8211; now eight
                    months after its publication, in my cool <del>&amp; self-distxxxting</del> judgement. <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> has said it is the best English poem that has left the Press since the Paradise Lost.
                    indeed this is not exaggerated praise &#8211; for unfortunately there is no competition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want you grievously to tell Espriella stories about the navy, &amp; give him a good idea of the present
                        state,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The navy is discussed in Letter 76 of <title>Letters from
                        England</title>.</note> which of course I cannot venture to do except very slightly &amp; very cautiously, fully aware of my
                    own incompetence. Some of your own stories you will recognize. the book will be very amusing, &amp; promises more profit than any
                    of my former works. Most praise I have had for Amadis,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> for the obvious reason that it excited no envy, &#8211; they who were aiming at
                    distinction as poets &amp;c without success had no objection to allow that I could translate from the Spanish. But praise &amp;
                    fame are two very distinct things. Nobody thinks the higher of me for that translation, or feels a wish to see me <del>xxx
                        xxx</del> for it, as they do for Joan of Arc &amp; Thalaba.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poems
                            <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1st edn 1796, 2nd edn 1798, 3rd edn 1806), <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note>
                    Poor Thalaba got abused in every review except the Critical<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reviews of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> were: <title>British Critic</title>, 18 (September 1801), 309&#8211;310; <title>Monthly Mirror</title>, 12
                        (October 1801), 243&#8211;247; Francis Jeffrey, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1 (October 1802), 63&#8211;83; <title>Monthly
                            Review</title>, 39 (November 1802), 240&#8211;251; Anna Seward, <title>The Poetical Register, and Repository for Fugitive
                            Poetry, for 1801</title> (London, 1802), pp. 475&#8211;486; William Taylor, <title>Critical Review</title>, 2nd series, 39
                        (December 1803), 369&#8211;379.</note> &#8211; &amp; yet there has not any poem of the age excited half the attention, or won half the
                    admiration that that has. I am fairly up the hill.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Little Edith</ref> looks at the picture of the Ships in the Cyclop&#230;dia<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ephraim Chambers&#8217; (1680?&#8211;1740; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Cyclopedia, or, An Universal Dictionary
                            of Arts and Sciences</title>, which was first published in 1728 and reprinted many times in the eighteenth century. An
                        expanded edition, updated by Abraham Rees (1743&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), was published from 1778&#8211;1788.</note> &amp; listens
                    to the story how she has a poor Uncle who lives in a ship, &amp; loves her dearly &amp; sends her a kiss in a letter. She is a
                    plain child &#8211; but you would love her very dearly &#8211; I never saw a more promising intellect. &#8211; the profile came safe &amp; highly do
                    I value it. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has taken himself a <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Rickwoman</ref>. I have not yet seen her, but expect to be her guest in March or April. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> at Edinburgh, fagging Law for his degree in July. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> daily expected in England, &amp; his return notwithstanding as
                    uncertain as ever.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was acting as Public Secretary to the British Civil
                        Commissioner in Malta and though due to return, he did not arrive back in England until August 1806.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles of Antwerp</ref> well &#8211; do you write to him? he has sent you a set of Couriers
                    with the Annual Review. Poor Cupid<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> A dog, formerly belonging to Southey and entrusted to
                        Danvers.</note> has been hung at last for robbing a hen roost! Your three half-crown sticks you see were bestowed upon him in
                    vain. He is the first of all my friends who ever came to the gallows &#8211; &amp; Heaven send that one of our relations may not one day
                    or other follow him! &#8211; I am very sorry for him, &#8211; poor fellow &#8211; I was his godfather. &#8211; Of Joe<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s dog, who was being looked after by Danvers.</note> the last accounts were good. Thus have I
                    turned my memory inside out to rummage out all the news for you &amp; little enough it is. We live here in the winter as much out
                    of the way of all society as if we were cruising at sea. From November till June not a soul do we see &#8211; except perhaps <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> once or twice during the time. Of course it is my working season,
                    &amp; I get thro a great deal. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &#8211; God bless you Tom &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>