<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1727</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2849</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    182&#8211;185.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1727" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1727" type="letter">
        <head>1727. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1809-12-31">31 December
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    182&#8211;185.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-12-31">Dec. 31. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should be more sorry at having unintentionally occasioned a quarrel between you and _______,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Capel Lofft (1751&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), Whig landed gentleman, lawyer and poet, notoriously
                        testy of disposition. Lofft was the patron and editor of <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Robert Bloomfield</ref>
                            ,<ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke"> Kirke White</ref> and a number of other writers from poor backgrounds. He was
                        a regular contributor to the <title>Monthly Mirror</title>. Lofft was offended by a paragraph in which Southey praised
                        himself, rather than Lofft, for bringing White&#8217;s poetry to notice after the setback of a cruel review. For further details,
                        see Southey to Neville White, 28 November 1808, Letter 1545.</note> if there were anything in his correspondence which either
                    you or any person could possibly regret. That poor unlucky man is strangely wrong-headed; &#8211; with the best disposition in the world
                    he is always getting into hot water. He has sent <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> a communication
                    for the &#8216;Friend,&#8217; and quarrelled with him because he could not read it; if it could have been read there would have been another
                    ground of quarrel, I will venture to say, in consequence of its non-insertion.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s
                        periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, was published in 26 instalments from 1 June 1809 to 15 March 1810. Lofft&#8217;s hand was
                        notoriously illegible.</note> As for the passage which has given him offence (God knows how innocently on my part!), do you
                    alter the words &#8216;would probably&#8217; into &#8216;might possibly,&#8217; in the next edition, and then I think neither he nor any one else can
                    object to them.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his &#8216;Account of the Life of H. K. White&#8217; in the third edition of the
                            <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, Southey states, &#8216;It is not unworthy of remark, that this very reviewal, which
                        was designed to crush the hopes of Henry, and suppress his struggling genius, has been in its consequences, the main occasion
                        of bringing his Remains to light, and obtaining for him that fame which assuredly will be his portion. Had it not been for the
                        indignation which I felt at perusing a criticism at once so cruel and so stupid, the little intercourse between Henry and
                        myself would not have taken place; his papers would probably have remained in oblivion, and his name, in a few years, have
                        been forgotten&#8217;, <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White &#8230; with an Account of his Life</title>, 2 vols (London, 1808), I, p. 27.
                        In later editions of the <title>Remains</title> &#8216;would probably&#8217; was not changed to &#8216;might possibly&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our difference of opinion respecting that part of Dr. Collyer&#8217;s &#8216;Lectures&#8217;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Bengo Collyer (1782&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), congregational minister and religious writer, who published
                            <title>Lectures on Scripture Prophecy</title> (1809). For Southey&#8217;s thoughts on these, see Southey to Neville White, 10
                        October 1809, Letter 1691.</note> has nothing to do whatever with any difference of faith, our faith being the same respecting
                    the Crucifixion; and the simple question is, whether it be not a very forced, unlikely, and unnatural interpretation to allegorise
                    a high-wrought fiction of temporal prosperity into a prophecy of that event. If the same latitude be allowed, any conclusion may
                    be drawn from any premises. It has nothing to do with Calvinism nor Arminianism,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wesleyan
                        Methodists and some Anglicans espoused beliefs set out by Jacobus Arminius (1560&#8211;1609) in the significance of faith, and of
                        the acceptance of grace, in salvation. Evangelicals, both Anglican and Methodist, tended to accept the Calvinist doctrine of a
                        predestined elect.</note> nor any of the other <hi rend="ital">isms</hi>; being wholly a matter of opinion &#8211; of critical
                    judgment &#8211; not a <hi rend="ital">joint</hi> of faith. That he might have more talents for poetry than for prose, was a mere
                    supposition founded on no other ground than this &#8211; that he seemed at all times to trust more to the exertions of fancy than of any
                    other faculty; and this ground I readily admit to have been insufficient.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">the printer&#8217;s</ref> fault that my first volume has not already made
                    its appearance.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was
                        published in 1810.</note> He goes on so slowly that I dare not say when it will be completed. My poem is gone to the
                        press.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> The first proof has not reached me yet; and the interval between the first
                    and last is so completely at the printer&#8217;s mercy, that there is no guessing at its length. Young authors are apt to be very
                    impatient upon these occasions. For my part, I wait with as much tranquillity as the public themselves, and no work of mine can
                    possibly occasion less sensation in its appearance than it does on me. I have the satisfaction of composing it, of correcting it,
                    sheet by sheet, from the press, and finally of seeing the finished volume: then my solicitude ends &#8211; the brood is fledged, and has
                    left the nest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably seen &#8216;The Friend,&#8217; and, after Miss Smith&#8217;s book,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Elizabeth Smith (1776&#8211;1806), <title>Memoirs of Frederick and Margaret Klopstock. Translated from the German by the Author of
                            &#8216;Fragments in Prose and Verse&#8217;</title> (1808).</note> would be interested by the account of Klopstock,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the eighteenth number of <title>The Friend</title>, dated 21 December 1809, an account is
                        included by &#8216;Satyrane&#8217; of Coleridge&#8217;s and Wordsworth&#8217;s visit to the German poet, Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803) in
                        1798. See Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London, 1809), pp. 276&#8211;288. See
                        S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp.
                        239&#8211;247.</note> and the heads of his conversation with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>. If <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> should fulfil his intent of criticising the &#8216;Messiah,&#8217;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Klopstock, <title>Der Messias</title> (1748&#8211;1773).</note> you will be convinced that Klopstock&#8217;s
                    merits as a poet have been ridiculously exaggerated. I, who am no German, have heard enough read, and seen enough translated by
                    his admirers, to be convinced that he is full of buckram and bombast. Not that this, in the slightest degree, lessens the interest
                    one feels in his admirable wife. His reputation has long been on the wane in Germany. <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry&#8217;s</ref> &#8216;Christiad&#8217;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Kirke White&#8217;s poem, &#8216;The Christiad, A Divine Poem&#8217;,
                        remained unfinished on his death and was included in Southey&#8217;s <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White &#8230; with an Account of his
                            Life</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 171&#8211;191.</note> would have been worth fifty &#8216;Messiahs.&#8217; Sacred epics seem
                    likely to be the fashion. Some gentleman gives his plan for &#8216;The Deluge&#8217; in the last &#8216;Monthly Magazine.&#8217;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter titled &#8216;Outline of a Poem on the Deluge&#8217; and signed &#8216;J. B.&#8217; was published in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title> (1 December 1809), 409&#8211;411.</note> In 1801 I formed a plan upon the same subject while on my voyage home
                    from Lisbon. It will never be executed;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey never did write this epic poem.</note>
                    but it was not ill conceived, and had many grand situations. This in the &#8216;Magazine&#8217; is thoroughly common-place, and nothing good
                    can come of it. In fact, there exists, against all stories connected with the great facts of Scripture history, the objections
                    which I have stated before the &#8216;Christiad.&#8217; You cannot blend fiction with truths which are so universally and definitely
                        known.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s prefatory comments to Kirke White&#8217;s &#8216;Christiad&#8217;, included the
                        observation that &#8216;the mixture of mythology makes truth itself appear fabulous&#8217;, in the <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White &#8230;
                            with an Account of his Life</title> (London, 1807), I, p. 172.</note> Every person instantly feels when the truth ends and
                    the fiction begins. &#8216;The Deluge&#8217; and &#8216;The Last Day&#8217; are also subjects too vast; no canvas can hold &#8211; no imagination conceive
                    them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen the two last &#8216;Quarterlies.&#8217; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">The publisher</ref> has been out
                    of town, and they have not been sent me. There ought to be an article of mine upon Holmes&#8217; &#8216;American Annals&#8217; in this fourth, but I
                    do not see it advertised.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763&#8211;1837), <title>American
                            Annals; or, a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> in the<title> Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319&#8211;337.</note> The great &#8216;Life of Nelson&#8217; is come down to me for this review. It is a
                    book which never can be read, from its bulk.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to James Stanier Clarke
                        (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur (1755&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson,
                            K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title> (1809). He reviewed this work, as well as several other books about Nelson in
                        his article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262. These included John Charnock (1756&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord Viscount Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.; with Observations,
                            Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d. 1847), <title>The Life of Lord Nelson</title> (1806); T. O.
                        Churchill (fl. 1800&#8211;1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount Nelson, Duke of Bront&#233;, &amp;c</title> (1808). Southey&#8217;s article
                        was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> His life and his letters are so intermixed,
                    that the work is neither the one nor the other; and what is worse, the time is not yet come when either the one or the other
                    could, with propriety, be fully laid before the public. Both, therefore, are not only mingled injudiciously together, but both are
                    unavoidably incomplete.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you saw <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge&#8217;s</ref> letters in the &#8216;Courier,&#8217;
                    especially that in which he justifies himself for speaking of Buonaparte in terms of abhorrence.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stuart had authored several letters on the Peninsular war in the <title>Courier</title> in 1808. These took
                        issue with the negotiations and peace arguments of the Whigs and radicals. See the <title>Courier</title>, 8, 9, 26, 29
                        November (&#8216;The Campaign in Spain&#8217;); 14, 15, 16 November (&#8216;The Court of Inquiry&#8217;); 1 December (&#8216;The Apstoacy of Don Cevallos&#8217;),
                        2 December (&#8216;Apostacy of the <title>Edinburgh</title>&#8217;), and 22 December (&#8216;Spain and Revolutions&#8217;). <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> also praised these articles and responded to them with his own
                        &#8216;Letters on the Spaniards&#8217; in the <title>Courier</title> of 7, 8, 9, 15, 20, 21, 22 December 1809 and 20 January 1810. See S.
                        T. Coleridge, <title>Essays on his Times</title>, ed. David V. Erdman, 3 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1978), II, 41 and
                        44&#8211;100.</note> This man is continually giving the surest proof of intellectual weakness in altering his plans. He builds up
                    kingdoms and pulls them down, just as children serve their card houses: aiming at nothing permanent, and incapable of producing
                    anything that can be so. Many happy new years to you and yours.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>