<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1467</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2589</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1467" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1467" type="letter">
        <head>1467. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1808-06-14">14 June 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        277&#8211;281.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> You probably know Senhora that I thanked <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward</ref> for the
                    books, eight or nine days ago, soon after their arrival; &#8211; not immediately, &#8211; because <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> was at that time very ill. He has had a severe attack of bilious fever, which has sadly reduced him, &amp; left
                    him in a state of great debility. For about a week I was too uneasy about him to do anything, except reading, &amp; this has
                    brought upon me an accumulation of letters to be written, &#8211; for seldom as I write to anybody, &amp; little as I love
                    letter-writing, it is still an occupation which takes up more time than I can either conveniently or willingly spare. &#8211; This
                    however is the reason why I have not sooner told you of the arrival of the books, thanked you, &amp; abused the Stafford
                    bookbinder, for his vile lines, &amp; the yet viler way in which he has inserted the prints, so as to render it impossible to see
                    them fairly open.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books of gold leaf came seasonably, after Lieutenant Juniper<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Underlined
                        by Mary Barker in red ink with asterisk and note in the left margin: &#8216;See Saint <hi rend="ital">Juniper</hi> and Disciple of
                        St [two words illegible]&#8217;. Juniperize meant to add a gold border and lettering to the bindings of Southey&#8217;s books. The
                        allusion was to Friar Juniper, disciple of St Francis, who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to give to
                        a poor woman begging alms.</note> had been about ten days at a stand for want of it. I anticipate with a good deal of pleasure
                    your entrance into the room, &amp; the discussions we are to have. Whether piles of one colour look better than merry-andrewers of
                    all colours, &#8211; whether the illuminated first letter looks best in red &amp; gold, in blue &amp; gold &#8211; or with both colours,
                    together with sundry other points of the same nature, which the Lieutenant &amp; I debate with all due solemnity. Uncle Toby &amp;
                    the Corporal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The obsessive &#8216;hobby horses&#8217; of characters in Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759&#8211;1767).</note> were not more
                    in earnest about their fortifications than we are about these piles &amp; pyramids of parchmentarians &amp; vellumarians,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, Southey&#8217;s valuable manuscripts, stored on shelves bracketed to the wall.</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; thus I will venture to say that nobody in Europe has anything like them. &#8211; Talk of Lord Spensers Library!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George John Spencer, 2nd Earl Spencer (1758&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) was noted for his library
                        at Althorp.</note> &#8211; The worst is Senhora that I shall assuredly set the fashion &amp; then be eclipsed in it, &#8211; for here will
                    come <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> some day, &amp; the device will win his heart, &amp; he will go to his
                    bookbinder, &#8211; substitute real morocco for our poor old Spanish sheep-skins, plaistered with vermillion, &#8211; &amp; pay one two &amp;
                    three guineas per volume for what costs <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> an hours work with the [MS obscured] &amp;
                    the gold leaf.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am seriously at work before breakfast every morning (unless my rest has been too much broken by the children to
                    allow me to rise) &#8211; upon Kehama,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &amp; am seriously advancing with it, very much to my own satisfaction. But
                    this Senhora is not enough for me. I am persuaded that I can write two poems better at a time than in sequence, &amp; that time
                    will be saved by so doing; because I can be going on with one when at a stand with the others. for tho the whole story be made
                    out, the immediate way of getting forwards is not always obvious, nor to be found by beating about for it. There is nothing to be
                    done in such cases but to lie still &amp; wait for a revelation. Now I believe that by having two at once upon the stocks, I may
                    be working one field while the other lies fallow, &amp; so I am planning a long poem in blank verse upon Pelayo, the Restorer of
                        Spain,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project was eventually published as <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; whom I suppose you will find called Pelagius<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Pelagius/Pelayo (c. 685&#8211;737), founder of the Kingdom of Asturias. Through his victory at the Battle of Covadonga, he is
                        credited with beginning the Christian reconquest of the Iberian peninsula from the Moors.</note> in common histories. A fine
                    story I hope to make of it, &amp; it will not be very long before the plan is made out sufficiently for me to set at work. Huzza
                    Senhora &#8211; another nine thousand lines for five &amp; twenty pounds, &#8211; is it to be so think you? I shall make a quiet trial whether
                    it be possible to get five hundred subscribers &amp; so secure the whole profits of an edition to myself, instead of letting the
                    booksellers take the Lions share, &#8211; it is not very likely, &#8211; it is not at all likely that I shall succeed, &#8211; I do not believe that
                    I shall get half the number. &#8211; but perhaps if I were to succeed so far, a bargain might be made to let the book-seller print as
                    many as they please, &amp; give me my subscription copies, &amp; thus my end would be answered. At any rate as I write no poetry
                    after breakfast, whatever the profit be, it will be so much gained as the price of morning-sleep, &amp; if it be not sufficient to
                    enable me to afford other times of the same pursuit &#8211; paciencia<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Portuguese for
                        &#8216;patience&#8217;.</note> &#8211; I shall have done enough.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have one or two friends among those whom I love best in the world, &amp; who love me best, who do not dissuade me
                    from writing poetry, but who are better pleased at seeing me otherwise employed, because they think truth more valuable than
                    fiction; &#8211; &amp; if it were impossible to pursue both, I should be of their opinion. But there is one man in the world who thinks
                    poetry exclusively the only worthy pursuit of any one who can succeed in it, &#8211; &amp; yet has never once expressed to me the
                    slightest wish that I should not utterly abandon it, as I seemed to have done, &amp; did in fact for three full years.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> After publishing <title>Madoc</title> in 1805 Southey did not publish another long poem until
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), because, as he often remarked, he could not afford it.</note> This was [two
                    word deletion]<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The blotted words were undoubtedly &#8216;<ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William Wordsworth</ref>&#8217;.</note> He may be said to think justly upon the average
                    of all the world, &#8211; for he thinks so much more than he ought of himself, &amp; so [MS obscured] less of every body else, &#8211; that
                    upon averaging the account you make it tolerably fair.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the Portugueze paying the losses of the English<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, of the
                        British merchants who had lost their businesses in Portugal when the French took over the country.</note> &#8211; it will be done
                    about the same time that we shall pay off the national debt. &#8211; My blood swells when I think of Spain &#8211; Often have I said that if
                    Europe is to be delivered in our days, it is Spain that her deliverance will begin. Love &amp; remembrance from a whole household,
                    &amp;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> from RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-06-14">Tuesday. June 14. 1808</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>