<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1612</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2734</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1612" type="letter">
        <head>1612. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-04-01">[early April
                        1809]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/
                        Hereford <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished. <lb />Dating note: On top of the
                        letter in a different hand: &#8216;Probably March 1809 April In answer to a letter dated March 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi>&#8217;.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not a little surpized &amp; vexed at what your letter tells me. The MSS set off with the books which were
                    mentioned, directed to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>
          <hi rend="ital">for you</hi>. They wrote to tell me it contained some books &amp; no directions what to do with them, &#8211; from which
                    I understand that they had stupidly opened the parcel, &#8211; but concluded that they had sent the papers by themselves, &#8211; &amp; in the
                    persuasion that you had read them, have I corrected the whole eighth chapter, which contains every thing relating to the manner of
                    the Tupinambas.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was
                        published in 1810. The Tupinamba, one of the main ethnic groups of Brazilian indigenous people, are described in chapters 7
                        and 8. Southey had intended that Hill should comment on the accounts; see Southey to the Herbert Hill, 8 March 1809, Letter
                        1596.</note> &#8211; &amp; the beginning of the next. The 10 &amp; 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> I have now ordered <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">the printer</ref> to send off to you without delay, &amp; you will have looked
                        <del>over</del> them over by the time he is ready for them. The 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is the most episodical of the whole
                    work, yet half the story belongs strictly to my subject, &amp; being obliged to tell half, I could not leave it imperfect because
                    it led me out of my limits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Arrowsmith<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), cartographer
                        of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map
                            of America</title> (1804), which depicted North and South America. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1817) contained Arrowsmith&#8217;s <title>Map of Brazil and Paraguay with the Adjoining
                        Countries</title>.</note> found Dobrizhoffer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791),
                            <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquari&#230;</title> (1784). Southey eventually owned a copy of this
                        work, no. 843 in the sale catalogue of his library. It was translated by <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> (with Southey&#8217;s encouragement), as <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of
                            Paraguay</title> (1822).</note> at Sir Joseph Banks&#8217;s,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Banks, Baronet
                        (1743&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), naturalist and patron of science, whose house in Soho Square, London held the best collection
                        of natural history and travel narratives.</note> I having sent him hunting for his maps. The copy of which I made use came
                    from the Advocates Library, procured for me in breach of law by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, &#8211; but I
                    am very desirous of obtaining one for myself, as it is incomparably the best book that has ever appeared concerning any part of S
                    America. I have now from the Red cross Street Library,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Williams&#8217;s Library, established
                        in Red Cross Street, Cripplegate, in 1729, through the bequest of the Presbyterian minister and benefactor, Daniel Williams
                        (c. 1643&#8211;1716; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; the only one in England which is liberal enough to let its books travel to a man
                    who can make use of them; Acosta,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; de Acosta (1539&#8211;1600), a Spanish Jesuit missionary
                        and naturalist who published several works, but Southey is probably referring to his <title>Historia Natural y Moral de las
                            Indias: Vida Religiosa y Civil de los Indios</title> (1590), no. 3220 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; in
                    whom I <del>do not</del> find <del>much</del> &lt;little&gt; which I did not know before, for his book relates almost exclusively
                    to Mexico &amp; Peru &#8211; a Latin translation of Benzo or Benzone<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giralomo Benzoni&#8217;s (b.
                        1519), <title>Historia del Mondo Nuovo</title> (1572) was translated into Latin as <title>Recentes Novi Orbis Histori&#230;</title>
                        (1612) by Urbanus Calveto (dates unknown).</note> (I know not which is his true name) &#8211; &amp; the Imago primi Saeculi
                        Soc-Jesu.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Johannes Bolland (1596&#8211;1665), <title>Imago Primi S&#230;culi Societatis Jesu a
                            Provincia Flandro-Belgica eiusdem Societatis Repraesentata</title> (1640). This was no. 1435 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> A Secular volume instead of a Carmen Sec.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A secular hymn, or
                        song of the ages; a title used by the Roman poet Horace (Quintus Horatius Flaccus: 65 BC&#8211;8 BC).</note> in honour of the
                    Company, but to which no second was produced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I almost fear that a parcel from <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> must have been lost on its
                    way to you, &#8211; for Pimentel is advertised,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manoel Pimentel (1650&#8211;1719), <title>The Brazil
                            Pilot; or, a Description of the Coast of Brazil, Translated from the Portuguese of Manoel Pimentel &#8230; to which are added,
                            Charts, of some of its most Considerable Ports</title> (1809). This was no. 2331 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> &#8211; &amp; both the Annual<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the following in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809): <title>Tour Through Spain and Part of Portugal</title>, Volume 3 of
                        Richard Phillips, <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages and Travels</title> (1805&#8211;1810), 56&#8211;57;
                        Christian Augustus Fischer (1771&#8211;1829), <title>A Picture of Madrid: Taken on the Spot. Translated from the German</title>
                        (1808), 57&#8211;60; Thomas Clarkson, <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African
                            Slave-Trade by the British Parliament</title> (1808), 127&#8211;148; <title>Report of the Committee of the African Institution,
                            Read to the General Meeting on the 15th July, 1807, Together with the Rules and Regulations which were then Adopted for
                            the Government of the Society</title> (1807); Thomas Zouch (1737&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and
                            Writings of Sir Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224&#8211;235; Robert Drury (1687&#8211;1734?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Adventures of Robert Drury, During Fifteen Years Captivity on the Island of Madagascar; Containing a Description of that
                            Island; an Account of its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; With an Account of the Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion,
                            and Civil Policy of the Inhabitants: to Which is Added, a Vocabulary of the Madagascar Language. Written by Himself, and
                            now Carefully Revised and Corrected from the Original</title> (1807), 253&#8211;263; John Finlay (1782&#8211;1810), <title>Scottish
                            Historical and Romantic Ballads: Chiefly Ancient with Explanatory Notes and a Glossary</title> (1808), 457&#8211;462; Charles
                        Kirkpatrick Sharpe (1781?-1851), <title>Metrical Legends</title> (1807), 473&#8211;473; Francis Douce (1757&#8211;1834),
                            <title>Illustrations of Shakespeare, and of Ancient Manners: with Dissertations on the Clown and Fool of Shakespeare; on
                            the Collection of Popular Tales entitled Gesta Romanorum; and on the English Morris Dance</title> (1807), 554&#8211;562; Charles
                        Lamb, <title>Specimens of English Dramatic Poets, who Lived about the Time of Shakespeare</title> (1808), 562&#8211;570; [Howard
                        Luke (1772&#8211;1864)], <title>A Brief Apology for Quakerism, Inscribed to the Edinburgh Reviewers</title> (1808), 354&#8211;356.</note>
                    &amp; Quarterly<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title> (published from 1794); [John Scott-Waring (1747&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Vindication
                            of the Hindoos from the Aspersions of the Reverend Claudius Buchanan, M.A. With a Refutation of the Arguments Exhibited in
                            his Memoir, on the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India, and the Ultimate Civilization of the
                            Natives, by their Conversion to Christianity&#8230; By a Bengal Officer</title> (1808); Thomas Twining (1776&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to the Chairman of the East India Company, on the Danger of Interfering in the
                            Religious Opinions of the Natives of India; and on the Views of the British and Foreign Bible Society, as Directed to
                            India</title> (1807), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> published &lt;more
                    than&gt; a month ago: &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> four volumes were I know ready for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">my Aunt</ref> long since.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had
                        arranged for Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Lyrical Ballads and other Poems</title>, 2 vols (1800) and <title>Poems in Two
                            Volumes</title> (1807) to be sent to Catherine Hill; see Southey to the Herbert Hill, 8 March 1809, Letter 1596.</note>
                    You had better write &amp; make enquiry.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly not only pays sooner but better, than any other mode of publication would do. I do these things with
                    good will &amp; good spirits, but you may be sure I should never do any such things were it not for the sake of that goodly
                    guerdon which there is no doing without. Half my time I write for subsistence, &#8211; the other half that I may leave something behind
                    me worthy of remembrance, &#8211; had I neither of these motives I should write just as much for my own pleasure, &amp; for intellectual
                    exercise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My idea of the map is precisely the same <del>xx xx</del> as yours. I have something about the settlements on the
                    Negro, in that Journal of Ribeiros,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joa&#771;o Pinto Ribeiro (d. 1649), <title>Observa&#231;&#245;es
                            Historicas e Criticas para Servirem de Memorias ao Systema da Diplomatica Portugueza Oferecidas ao Serenissimo Principe do
                            Brazil</title> (1798).</note> of which I have made great use as you will soon see, in the history of <del>Ac</del> Texeira
                    &amp; Acunhas voyage,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Teixeira (d. 1641) was a Portuguese explorer who became, in
                        1637, the first European to travel up the entire length of the Amazon, an expedition which helped extend Portuguese colonial
                        possessions there at the expense of Spain. Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;1676?), a member of Texeira&#8217;s expedition, published
                            <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title> (1641).</note> &#8211; giving there a compleat account of the
                        Orellana.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The initial name of the Amazon river.</note> &#8211; We have printed 264 pages
                    the volume will contain between six &amp; seven hundred, &amp; even then there will be no room for the critical catalogue of
                    documents, &#8211; that must be reserved for the end of the work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Could we not employ John Bell<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Sir John Bell (1782&#8211;1876;
                            <title>DNB</title>), army officer who served in Portugal throughout the Peninsular War.</note> to hunt out books at
                    Lisbon, it is a commission in which he could take an interest which no other person can do. &#8211; Have you any list of Governors after
                    Rocha Pitta<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebasti&#227;o da Rocha Pita (1660&#8211;1738), <title>Historia da America Portugeza,
                            desde o anno 1500 ate o de 1724</title> (1730).</note> stops? &#8211; <del>Xx</del> I know not where to look for them. I shall
                    get <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">J May</ref> to put some questions for me to his brother William<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> John&#8217;s younger brother, William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), was a Lisbon merchant who, after the French invaded Portugal, relocated his
                        business to Brazil.</note> concerning the state of the natives &#8211; if there be any, in the vicinity of Rio Jan. the proportion
                    of mixed breed, &#8211; &amp; in particular whether any such amalgamation of the Tupe<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        indigenous people of the Amazon.</note> &amp; Portugueze has taken place in the inland settlements as has <del>xxx xxxx</del>
                    between the Spanish &amp; Guarani<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> An indigenous people of Paraguay.</note> in Paraguay.
                    My history proves to be much more amusing in print than I had expected it to be, &amp; the second volume will be more so than the
                    first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You do not seem to look upon an increasing family in the light that I do. The more the merrier, is my philosophy, &#8211;
                    &amp; I reject the sequel of the proverb.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The proverb in full is: &#8216;the more the merrier;
                        the fewer, the better fare&#8217;.</note> Brothers &amp; sisters in general, help one another thro the world, &#8211; &amp; let me have as
                    many as may come I have no fear for their well doing. My copy right will one day become good property. There will be a law to
                    extend the term, even that will be sufficiently unjust, &amp; I do not despair of having literary property made perpetual, like
                    every other. But at any rate there is a way of renewing the lease to my family, by leaving corrected editions behind me &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> goes for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary Sealy</ref> in
                    May. I shall visit him towards the end of that month.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Queen Orraca spelt her own name with an O.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Afonso II (1185&#8211;1223), King of
                        Portugal 1211&#8211;1223, married Urraca (d. 1220), daughter of Alfonso VIII (1155&#8211;1214), King of Castile (1158&#8211;1214) in 1208.
                        Southey&#8217;s poem on &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; entitled &#8216;Queen Urraca and the Five Martyrs of Morocco&#8217; was published in the <title>Morning
                            Post</title> in early September 1803, in the <title>Iris</title>, 3 November 1804, in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a
                            Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with some Original Pieces hitherto unpublished</title>, 2 vols
                        (Edinburgh, 1810), in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), in <title>Minor Poems</title>
                        (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> who can repeat any thing which he has heard three times, learnt that
                    ballad by making me recite it, &amp; then gave it a fashion in London. He made me copy it for the Princess of Wales.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caroline of Brunswick-Wolfenb&#252;ttel (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>) the wife of the Prince
                        Regent, who was Princess of Wales between 1795 and 1820.</note> It is good in its way &#8211; but nos haec novimus esse nihil<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Martial&#8217;s (Marcus Valerius Martialis; AD 38&#8211;41 to AD 102&#8211;104)<title> Epigrams</title>
                        (AD 86&#8211;103), Book 13, Epigram 2, line 8: &#8216;we know these to be nothing&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p>I will make up a packet for <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> H</ref> in the same form as the last,
                    from time to time, till there be enough <del>for</del> &lt;to&gt; form a volume. I believe you have never seen my ballad of Bishop
                    Athendio, the Devil &amp; the Pope<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;A True Ballad of St Antidius, the Pope, and the
                        Devil&#8217;, published in the <title>Morning Post</title> in early February 1803 and revised for <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815
                        and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838).</note> &#8211; nor some strange stanzas which made a great buzz in the
                    world about ten years ago, called the Devils Thoughts,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The Devil&#8217;s Thoughts&#8217;, a
                        political ballad jointly authored by Southey and Coleridge, and first published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, on 6
                        September 1799. For the complex later publication history of the poem, see <title>The Poetical Works of Samuel Taylor
                            Coleridge</title>, ed. J. C. C. Mays, 3 vols (London and Princeton, 2001), I.ii, pp. 726&#8211;750 and <title>Robert Southey:
                            Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, <title>Selected Shorter Poems</title>,
                        pp. 451&#8211;474.</note> for most of which Satan was indebted to me.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> The postscript is
                        written upside down across the top of the first page.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>