<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1113</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2235</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    341&#8211;344.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1113" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1113" type="letter">
        <head>1113. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1805-10-20">20
                        October 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.
                        P./ Wynnot/ Wrexham<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                    341&#8211;344.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-10-20">Sunday Oct 20</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I reached home yesterday &#8211; just as your letter with the draft had arrived.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We found a week at Edinburgh quite enough, &amp; both I &amp; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>
                    were willing to get home again. It is certainly a magnificent city. The new town resembles Bath in the regularity, the cleanliness
                    &amp; the silence of its streets, &amp; in the colour of the buildings; but the houses being only of ordinary height are dwarfed
                    by the old city. There they are commonly six seven or eight stories on the one side &#8211; ten &#8211; twelve or thirteen on the other &#8211;
                    &amp; this height increased by the chimneys which rise like a sort of turret from the front of the house instead of the gable end.
                    The famous view of Leith<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A district in the north of Edinburgh, on the south shore of the
                        Firth of Forth, which provides a port for the city.</note> &amp; the river which the Scotch boast of so loudly &#8211; is nothing to
                    one who has seen Lisbon. I did not even think it of the second best order. But that from Princes Street<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of the main thoroughfares of central Edinburgh.</note> is truly surprizing. You cross a valley (once a
                    Loch) by a high bridge &amp; the back of the old city appears on the edge of this depth so vast &#8211; so irregular &#8211; with such an
                    outline of roofs &amp; chimneys that it looks like the ruins of a Giants palace. I never saw any thing so impressive as the first
                    sight of this. &#8211; there was a wild red sunset slanting along it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of Edinburgh society I think very little. <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> very justly observed
                    that of the three faculties of the mind judgement is the only one which they cultivate or value. <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> is amusing from his wit &#8211; in taste he is a mere child, &amp; he affects to
                    despise learning &#8211; because he has none. Perhaps I am not a fair judge, having been accustomed to live with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>,
                    &#8211; but the plain truth is that <del>x</del> compared with such men as these the Scotch <hi rend="ital">literatuli</hi>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A diminished form of literati, or men of letters, intended to be derogatory.</note> are very low
                    indeed. <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> was not in good health, &amp; did not open much. I had however
                    conversation enough with him to see that he never regarded anything in the broad moral point of view. As for <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> I really cannot feel angry with any thing so diminutive.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey consoled himself for Jeffrey&#8217;s printed criticisms of his work in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, by reflecting on his diminutive stature.</note> He is a mere homunculus<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning a little or diminutive man; a mannikin.</note> &amp; would do for a Major in Gog &amp; Magogs<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The church of St Dunstans in the West, on Fleet Street, London, bears a clock, with two
                        small figures, known as Gog and Magog, who strike the hours and quarters with clubs.</note> army were they twice as little.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We were three days at <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> &#8211; a much superior man, whom it is
                    impossible not to like. He was delighted with the M. S. &amp; has commissioned me to offer 15 guineas for it for the Advocates
                        Library.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his letter to Wynn of 3 October 1805 (Letter 1109), Southey mentions being
                        alerted to &#8216;an old MSS volume of poems&#8217; by Robert Hurrell Froude (1770/71&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), a Church of England
                        clergyman, who was later Archdeacon of Totnes. The volume contained the text of three rare medieval metrical romances:
                            <title>Sir Isumbras, Sir Gowther</title>, and <title>Amadas</title> (or <title>Sir Amadace</title>). It had been owned by
                        the Sherbrooke family of Oxton, Nottinghamshire since the sixteenth century. Southey arranged for its purchase, through the
                        good offices of Scott, by Scott&#8217;s friend Thomas Thomson (1768&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), the Edinburgh advocate, record keeper
                        and editor of medieval manuscripts. See letter 1147 of this edition. From Thomson the manuscript went to the Advocates
                        Library, Edinburgh. It remains in their collection today (National Library of Scotland, Advocates MS 19.3.1).</note> Were
                    there any sale for such things I would willingly add three more volumes to Ritsons<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        antiquary, Joseph Ritson (1752&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), published in 1802 two works that were intended to revive interest in
                        medieval literature. One was his edition <title>Ancient English Metrical Romance&#235;s</title>; the other was <title>Bibliographia
                            Poetica, a Catalogue of Engleish poets, of the Twelfth, Thirteenth, Fourteenth, Fifteenth, and Sixteenth, Centurys, with a
                            Short Account of their Works</title>.</note> &#8211; but these must be left to be done by future Academies &#8211; perhaps the London
                        Institution<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The idea of establishing a London Institution to promote the diffusion of
                        science, literature and the arts was first mooted in March 1805, with a formal meeting taking place on 23 May 1805 to discuss
                        the practical details of setting it up. The Institution was established on 18 January 1806.</note> may bestow some of its
                    funds upon our national literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> sent me the Censura Literaria.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Censura Literaria: Containing Titles, Abstracts, and Opinions of Old English Books, with Original Disquisitions,
                            Articles of Biography, and other Literary Antiquities</title> (1805&#8211;1809), ed. Samuel Egerton Brydges (1762&#8211;1837;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> You seem to appreciate it accurately yet execrable as it is, it is like <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> story of the bad weather &#8211; better than none.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Fr Aikin</ref> has written to me for the article Lobeira for his Biographical Dict.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin&#8217;s <title>General Biography or, Lives, Critical and Historical, of the Most
                            Eminent Persons of all Ages, Countries, Conditions, and Professions, Arranged According to Alphabetical Order</title> was
                        published in 10 volumes between 1799&#8211;1815. Southey contributed a biographical notice on Vasco Lobeira (d. 1403), the
                        Portuguese author of <title>Amadis de Gaul</title> for volume 6 (1807), 314&#8211;317. Southey was
                        familiar with Lobeira&#8217;s work after publishing a translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul, by Vasco Lobeira</title> in 1803.</note>
                    Requesting me to contribute all that relates to Sp. &amp; Port. Literature. I have promised to &lt;do&gt; this &#8211; it is only
                    printing what I should else be accumulating in manuscripts &#8211; &amp; I may as well get paid for my first drafts.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> According to Kenneth Curry (<title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, p. 403) the other entries that Southey contributed to the <title>General Biography</title> were to volumes VI
                        (1807), VII (1808) and VIII (1813): Volume VI: &#8216;Francisco Rodrigues Lobo&#8217;, 318; &#8216;Fernam Lopez&#8217;, 340; &#8216;Gregorio Lopez&#8217;, 340;
                        &#8216;Francisco de Losa&#8217;, 344&#8211;345; &#8216;Joam de Lucena&#8217;, 371&#8211;372; &#8216;Miguel de Luna&#8217;, 388; &#8216;Fr. Francisco de Santo Agostinho Macedo&#8217;,
                        434&#8211;435, &#8216;El Enamorado Macias&#8217;, 437&#8211;438; &#8216;P. Fr. Pedro Malon de Chaide&#8217;, 506; &#8216;D. Jorge Manrique&#8217;, 523&#8211;524; &#8216;Don Juan Manuel&#8217;,
                        529&#8211;530; &#8216;Ausias March&#8217;, 542&#8211;543; &#8216;Juan de Mariana&#8217;, 555&#8211;557; &#8216;Vicente Mariner&#8217;, 558; &#8216;Luis de Marmol Carvajal&#8217;, 569; &#8216;P. M.
                        Fr. Juan Marquez&#8217;, 574&#8211;575. Volume VII: &#8216;Juan de Mena&#8217;, 28&#8211;30; &#8216;Don Inigo Lopez de Mendoza&#8217;, 37&#8211;38; &#8216;D. Diego Hurtado de
                        Mendoza&#8217;, 38&#8211;39; &#8216;Menezes&#8217;, 41&#8211;42; &#8216;Christoval de Mesa&#8217;, 59&#8211;60; &#8216;George de Montemayor&#8217;, 174&#8211;175; &#8216;Ambrosio de Morales&#8217;,
                        194&#8211;198; &#8216;Alonso de Castro Nunez&#8217;, 466; &#8216;Antonio de Naxara&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Abraham Nehemias&#8217;, 469; &#8216;Florian de Ocampo&#8217;, 471&#8211;472; &#8216;Fr.
                        Diego de Olarte&#8217;, 487; &#8216;Fr. Andres de Olmos&#8217;, 497; &#8216;Jerome Osorio&#8217; [with Thomas Morgan (1752&#8211;1821)], 530&#8211;533; &#8216;Alonso de
                        Ovalle&#8217;, 548; &#8216;Andres de Oviedo&#8217;, 555&#8211;556; &#8216;Gonzalo Fernandez de Oviedo&#8217;, 556&#8211;557; &#8216;Lorenzo de Padilla&#8217;, 578; &#8216;Pedro Paez&#8217;,
                        578&#8211;580; &#8216;D. Juan de Palafox y Mendoza&#8217;, 585. Volume VIII: &#8216;Josef de Ossau, Salas y Pellicer&#8217;, 25&#8211;26; Bartholom&#233; Pereira&#8217;, 46;
                        &#8216;Luys Pereyra&#8217;, 46; &#8216;Antonio Perez&#8217;, 46&#8211;47; &#8216;Ruy de Pina&#8217;, 173; &#8216;Juan de Pineda&#8217;, 175; &#8216;Fernam Mendes Pinto&#8217;, 178&#8211;179; &#8216;Thome
                        Pires&#8217;, 182&#8211;184; &#8216;Fernando de Pulgar&#8217;, 385.</note> My busy season is setting in &#8211; &amp; there is a world of work before me,
                    which might appal an indolent man. This engagement for one thing &#8211; the proofs to the Specimens<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s</ref>
                        jointly-compiled anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; to supply the gap made in the
                    2 Vol. of Poems by the omission of the Vision, &#8211; which must be done by tinkering the Retrospect &#8211; Rosamund &amp;c.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published in 1806, with the &#8216;Vision of the
                        Maid of Orleans&#8217; &#8211; originally published in the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799) &#8211; printed at the end of the poem.
                        Southey now wished to fill the gap made by the removal of the &#8216;Vision&#8217; in the new 1806 edition of <title>Poems</title> that he
                        was preparing for the press. He filled it with &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217;, originally published in <title>Poems</title> (1795) but did
                        not include &#8216;Rosamund to Henry, Written after She Had Taken the Veil&#8217;, also originally published in <title>Poems</title>
                        (1795). Other poems brought into the 1806 edition to make up for the removal of the &#8216;Vision&#8217; were, &#8216;Translation of a Greek Ode on Astronomy, written for the prize at Cambridge, 1793&#8217; (pp.  3&#8211;9); &#8216;Remembrance&#8217; (pp. 40&#8211;43); &#8216;To Recovery&#8217; (pp. 49&#8211;51); &#8216;Youth and Age&#8217; (pp. 52&#8211;53); &#8216;The Traveller&#8217;s Return&#8217; (pp. 54&#8211;55); &#8216;Autumn&#8217; (pp. 56&#8211;58); &#8216;The Destruction of Jerusalem&#8217; (pp. 59&#8211;62); &#8216;The Spanish Armada&#8217; (pp. 63&#8211;66); &#8216;St Bartholomew&#8217;s Day&#8217; (pp. 67&#8211;69); &#8216;To a Bee&#8217; (pp. 74&#8211;75); &#8216;Metrical Letter&#8217;, pp. 76&#8211;79. For the alterations, see <title>Robert Southey. Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols
                        (London, 2004), I.</note> a full sixth of the Annual,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806): James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB</title>), <title>Travels to Discover
                            the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768&#8211;73</title> (2nd edn, 1804&#8211;1805), 2&#8211;16; Thomas Lindley (dates unknown),
                            <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ... with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and
                            Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto Seguro</title> (1805), 27&#8211;32; Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The Present
                            State of Peru, Comprising its Geography, Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and Manners of its
                            Inhabitants; Embellished by ... Engravings of Costumes</title> (1805), 49&#8211;60; John Griffiths (dates unknown),
                            <title>Travels in Europe, Asia Minor and Arabia</title> (1805), 67&#8211;77; James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 1; 1805), 99&#8211;100; Charles
                        Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title>
                        (1805), trans. B Lambert (dates unknown), 177&#8211;187; William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de
                            Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467; Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848), <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805), 477&#8211;483;
                        Dieudonn&#233; Thi&#233;bault (1733&#8211;1807), <title>Original Anecdotes of Frederic the Second, King of Prussia, and of his Family, his
                            Court, his Ministers, his Academies, and his Literary Friends: Collected During a Familiar Intercourse of Twenty Years
                            with that Prince</title> (1805), 488&#8211;495; William Parr Greswell (bap. 1765&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of
                            Angelus Politianus, Joannes Picus of Mirandula, Actius Sincerus Sannazarius, Petrus Bembus, Hieronymus Fracastorius,
                            Marcus Antonius Flaminius, and the Amalthei: Translations from their Poetical Works: and Notes and Observations Concerning
                            Other Literary Characters of the Fifteenth and Sixteenth Centuries</title> (1805), 509&#8211;515; George Ellis, Sp<title>ecimens
                            of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805), 536&#8211;544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Works of Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544&#8211;555; William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Spirit of Discovery</title>
                        (1804), 568&#8211;573; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals,
                            with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title> (1805), 575&#8211;576; John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810), <title>Oriental
                            Tales: Translated into English Verse</title> (1805), 576&#8211;578; Francis Burroughs (dates unknown), <title>A Poetical Epistle
                            to James Barry Esq.</title> (1805), 578&#8211;579; Vincenzo Monti (1754&#8211;1828), <title>Penance of Hugo: A Vision</title> (1805),
                        trans. Henry Boyd (1748/9&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), 581&#8211;588; James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Sabbath</title> (1805), 588&#8211;591; Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rhymes on Art, or, The
                            Remonstrance of a Painter</title> (1805), 592&#8211;596; Samuel Whitchurch, (dates unknown), <title>Hispaniola, a Poem</title>
                        (1804), 596&#8211;597; Matthew Rolleston (dates unknown), <title>The Anti-Corsican, A Poem</title> (1805), 597&#8211;598; Charles Grant,
                        Baron Glenelg (1778&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poem on the Restoration of Learning in the East</title> (1805), 598;
                        Edward Coxe (dates unknown), <title>Miscellaneous Poetry</title> (1805), 598&#8211;600; Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818; DNB), <title>The
                            Poems of Ossian, Containing the Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with Notes and
                            Illustrations</title> (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald Macdonald (1739&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>),<title> Some of Ossian&#8217;s Lesser
                            Poems Rendered into Verse [from Macpherson]; with a Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s Critical and
                            Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity of Ossian&#8217;s Poems</title> (1805), 620; Philip Massinger (1583&#8211;1640;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Plays</title> (1805), ed. William Gifford, 625&#8211;634; Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781),
                            <title>Nathan the Wise; a Dramatic Poem in Five Acts</title> (1805), trans. William Taylor, 634&#8211;639; John Collett (dates
                        unknown), <title>Sacred Dramas: Intended Chiefly for Young Persons</title> (1805), 639; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the
                            Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805), 679&#8211;699; Hannah More, <title>Hints Towards Forming the
                            Character of a Young Princess</title> (1805), 708&#8211;713; Joseph Lancaster (1778&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Improvements in Education as it Respects the Industrious Classes of the Community</title> (3rd edn, 1805), 732&#8211;736;
                        Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of
                            Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary Friends and Select Re-publications</title>
                        (1805), 736&#8211;738; William Henry Ireland (1775&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Confessions of William Henry Ireland
                            Containing the Particulars of his Fabrication of the Shakespeare Manuscripts</title> (1805), 743&#8211;745.</note> which shall
                    be my last work of the kind &#8211; &amp; Espriellas letters<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from
                            England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> to compleat &amp; transcribe.
                    Of the play I shall think to do more than think will be impossible till this mass is cleared off.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was contemplating writing a play, stimulated by an offer, sent via Wynn, from Matthew Gregory Lewis
                        (1775&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>) to smooth its passage to the stage. He contemplated various plans, including a Greek drama, a
                        dramatisation of Madoc, and a play set in the reign of Mary I (1516&#8211;1558, Queen of England 1553&#8211;1558; <title>DNB</title>); see
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4th series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 190&#8211;192, Southey to Peter
                        Elmsley, 10 July 1805, Letter 1081 and Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 12 July 1805, Letter 1083.</note> By April I
                    expect &#8211; if no sickness or sorrow interrupt &#8211; to have got thro the campaign; &amp; then I hope to sail for Lisbon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have heard at second hand that Thalaba is selling with increased rapidity.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801). A second edition was not called for until
                        1809.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> told&#160;<ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref>. It is very likely
                    Madoc, in spite of all attacks &amp; all prejudices, will push <del>xxxx</del> &lt;himself&gt; &amp; his brethren. Success in
                    these cases is slow but sure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &amp; I parted yesterday morning at Carlisle. When we shall see so much of
                    each other again heaven knows. This I know that it will be long before I shall have so pleasant a companion <del>xxxxx</del>. I
                    know few men who approach to his learning, not one who judges so sanely upon all subjects. We have been very serious together
                    &amp; very merry, &amp; I believe no two travellers were more disposed to take things quietly, &amp; laugh at inconveniences.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Home is very comfortable after even a short absence. I am glad work is come &#8211; that I may be once more fairly at
                    work &#8211; &amp; yet wish it were over that the work were done.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-10-20">Sunday Oct 20. 1805. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>