<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.947</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2069</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.947" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="947" type="letter">
        <head>947. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-06-01">1 June
                        1804</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Galatea/ Barbadoes/ or
                        elsewhere./ Single <lb />Postmark: [partial] JU/ C/ 1/ 804<lb />Endorsement: Received in Antigua Hospital Sep<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 28. 1804<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-06-01">June 1. 1804</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am this day leaving London, &amp; such has been the perpetual hurry &amp; fatigue in which I have been bustling
                    from the hour of my departure from <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> that the post day is come before I am ready to
                    write a letter! &#8211; My last was written at the end of April &#8211; in order to go by the May packet. a few days after it was gone <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> was safe in bed, &amp; she &amp; her daughter <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> were well as could be when last <del>I heard</del> a letter came from home.
                    thank God I am on the point of setting out to see them. you can have no conception of the tremendous fatigue it is to be in London
                    on business, <del>with</del> having the numerous acquaintances I have. never was I so thoroughly worn out &#8211; every day costs me
                    more exertion of legs &amp; lungs than &lt;would&gt; serve for three months consumption in the country. &amp; much as you know I
                    hate a journey, to get in the <hi rend="ital">Brummejam</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Slang, based on the locals&#8217;
                        unique accent, for the city of Birmingham.</note> coach this evening will seem like rest. mind the spelling of that word,
                    &amp; always remember to pronounce it so, lest you be mistaken for a Birmingham-man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will meet me at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> has been unluckily deprived of a birth by the ousting Capt Markham<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Markham (1761&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and member of the Board of Admiralty
                        (1801&#8211;1804 and 1806&#8211;1807) and M.P. for Portsmouth (1801&#8211;1818 and 1820&#8211;1826).</note> in these late changes. however there is
                    another Lord of the Admiralty to whom I have some means of applying, &amp; the business will soon be done. Every body rejoices
                    that Lord S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincent has been turnd out, it being universally acknowledged that he was the very worst first
                    Lord of the Admiralty ever remembered.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was First Lord of the Admiralty from 1801&#8211;1804.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must forgive a very worthless &amp; disordered letter. I have just finished my packing up. at two o clock have
                    to travel to the very farthest part of Marybone in the hope &#8211; &amp; barely a hope &#8211; of seeing <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> &#8211; at four dinner &#8211; at five the coach. &amp; it is now nearly one &#8211; &amp; I am in
                    expectation of some disturbing visitor or other, &amp; my wits are wool gathering &#8211; in fear lest I should have forgotten any thing
                    &#8211; which probably will prove the case.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc goes to press immediately, it will be printed in Scotland.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was printed in Edinburgh by the firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James
                        Ballantyne</ref>.</note> &amp; the proofs sent by post to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. a pleasant
                    circumstance &#8211; you know how I enjoy a proof sheet &#8211; in the country it will be as good as a newspaper. The Specimens of the Later
                    English Poets are also to go to press without delay.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, which Southey jointly edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, was not published until 1807.</note>
                     I have worked at them as hard as a Negro &#8211; &amp; in fact till I made myself as black as a negro. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> takes the remainder of the trouble &amp; will have to correct the proofs, &amp; also to collect such
                    specimens as I have not been able to meet with. It will be very hard if the profits of these two works do not enable me to take a
                    house. I have been a hard worker &#8211; &amp; yet it goes as it comes &#8211; I live comfortably perhaps one year more so than another &#8211; but
                    tho not behind hand; some damnd thing or other always comes in to prevent me from getting forward. &#8211; there are above 180 pages of
                    mine in the last Annual,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2
                        (1804): James Burney, <title>A Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with
                            Charts</title> (Vol. 1; 1803), 3&#8211;12; James Stanier Clarke (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Progress of Maritime
                            Discovery, from the Earliest Period to the Close of the Eighteenth Century, Forming an Extensive System of
                            Hydrography</title> (1803), 12&#8211;20; James Curtis (dates unknown), <title>A Journal of Travels in Barbary in 1801 ... With
                            Observations on the Gum Trade of Senegal</title> (1803), 20&#8211;23; Louis Maria Joseph, Count O&#8217;Hier de Grandpr&#233; (1761&#8211;1846),
                            <title>A Voyage in the Indian Ocean, and to Bengal ... To Which is Added a Voyage in the Red Sea, Including a Description
                            of Mocha, and of the Trade of the Arabs of Yemen</title> (1803), 48&#8211;54; John Davis (1774&#8211;1854), <title>Travels of Four
                            Years and a Half in the United States of America, During 1798, 1799, 1800, 1801, and 1802</title> (1803), 54&#8211;59; Lockhart
                        Muirhead (dates unknown), <title>Journals of Travels in Parts of the Late Austrian Low Countries, France, the Pays de Vaud and
                            Tuscany in 1787 and 1789</title> (1803), 59&#8211;63; Charles William Doyle (1770&#8211;1842), <title>A Non-Military Journal; Or,
                            Observations Made in Egypt, by an Officer upon the Staff of the British Army: Describing the Country, its Inhabitants,
                            their Manners and Customs</title> (1803), 63&#8211;66; William Wittman (fl. 1799&#8211;1804), <title>Travels in Turkey, Asia Minor,
                            Syria, and Across the Desert into Egypt During the Years 1799, 1800, and 1801, in Company with the Turkish Army and the
                            British Military Mission</title> (1803), 66&#8211;71; [Ann Blund (dates unknown)], <title>Journal of a Short Excursion among the
                            Swiss Landscapes</title> (1803), 79&#8211;80; Isaac King (dates unknown), <title>Letters from France</title> (1803), 88&#8211;90;
                            <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London,
                            1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public
                            Support</title> (1803), 187;<title> Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (Vol. 1, 1803), 189&#8211;201; William Myles
                        (1756&#8211;1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People called Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists of the
                            Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803), 201&#8211;213; Thomas Malthus
                        (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future Improvement of
                            Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), 292&#8211;301; William
                        Godwin, <title>Life of Geoffrey Chaucer ... Including Memoirs of ... John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster; with Sketches of the
                            Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in the Fourteenth Century</title> (1803), 462&#8211;473; George Mason
                        (1735&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Richard Earl Howe</title> (1803), 499&#8211;501; Joseph Ritson (1752&#8211;1803;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ancient Engleish Metrical Romancee&#776;s</title> (1802), 515&#8211;533; George Ellis, <title>Specimens
                            of the Early English Poets</title> (3rd edn 1803), 538&#8211;542; Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Poetical Works of the Late Thomas Warton</title> (1802), 543&#8211;546; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper, Esq.</title> (1803), 457&#8211;462; Peter Bayley (bap. 1778&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems</title> (1803), 546&#8211;552; Henry Kirke White, <title>Clifton Grove, a Sketch in Verse,
                            with other Poems</title> (1803), 552&#8211;554; Josiah Walker (d. 1831), <title>The Defence of Order, a Poem</title> (1803),
                        557; <title>The Inquiry. Part 1</title>, 557&#8211;558; William Barnes Rhodes (1772&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Epigrams</title> (1803), 558; James Woodhouse (bap. 1735&#8211;1820), <title>Norbury Park, a Poem with Several Others
                            Written on Various Occasions</title> (1803), 558; Henry William Tytler (1752/3&#8211;1808), <title>The Voyage Home from the Cape
                            of Good Hope</title> (1803), 559; Luke Booker (1762&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Calista, or a Picture of Modern
                            Life, a Poem</title> (1803), 564; D. A. G. B. Cassano (dates unknown), <title>Il Fiore della Poesia Italiana</title>
                        (1802), 562&#8211;563; Percy Clinton Sydney, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems from the
                            Portuguese of Luis de Camoens</title> (1803), 569&#8211;577; William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Picture, Verses Suggested by a
                            Magnificent Landscape of Rubens</title> (1803), 582; John Peter Roberdeau (bap. 1754&#8211;1815), <title>Fugitive Verse and
                            Prose</title> (1803), 582&#8211;583; George Owen Cambridge (d. 1841), <title>Works of Richard Owen Cambridge, Esq. with an
                            Account of his Life and Character</title> (1803), 583&#8211;585; Anne-Louise-Germaine Necker, Baroness de Sta&#235;l-Holstein
                        (1766&#8211;1817), <title>A Treatise of Ancient and Modern Literature</title> (tr. 1803), 643&#8211;650; <title>Asiatic Researches; or
                            Transactions of the Society Instituted in Bengal for Enquiring into the History and Antiquities, the Arts, Science and
                            Literature of Asia</title> (vol. VII, 1803), 898&#8211;908.</note> which you will probably discover without a key. or by the
                    help of this general one, if the article be <hi rend="ital">quaint</hi>, &amp; is not <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref>, for whom you never can mistake me &#8211; it is mine. for I love quaintness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you Tom! I hope to find a letter from you on my return. &amp; I will make amends for this by the next
                    packet. once more God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>. <address>
              <placeName>Palace Yard.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1804-06-01">Friday.</date>
          </p>
          <p>Tomorrow Brummejam, thence on to <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Penkeridge</ref> for <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> &#8211; &amp; on to Manchester, &amp; Kendal &amp; <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &#8211; about
                        340 miles!</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>