<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1011</idno><idno type="nines">rce2133</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 66.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1011" type="letter"><head>1011. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1804-12-31">31 December
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esqr/ at Mr Postlethwaites/ Harting/
                        near/ Petersfield/ Hampshire/ Single <lb/>Stamped [partial]: KESWICK<lb/>Postmark: E/ JAN 3/ 1805<lb/>Endorsement: RS./ Decr.
                        21./ 1804<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 66<lb/>Unpublished.<lb/>Note: Joseph Postlethwaite (dates unknown) was the father of
                        Susannah Postlethwaite, who Rickman married in October 1805.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1804-12-31">Dec 31. 1804. </date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></dateline><salute>Dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I thank you heartily for your invitation, but if you will look at the map &amp; then at the thermometer, you will
                    allow that weather &amp; distance should be sufficient motives for keeping me at home, were there no others. the book is going to
                    press, or gone, &amp; when once begun it will keep moving for I left more than three fourths or four fifths ready in <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">his hands</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s poem
                            <title>Madoc</title>, published in 1805.</note> Besides that the journey <del>xxxx</del> is not necessary therefore,
                    travelling is of the nature of a luxury inasmuch as it is expensive. one nights starvation in a stage coach would cost more than
                    would keep my great room warm for three months even in this dear coal country. – If there be war with Portugal I should probably
                    visit London for the sake of meeting <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &amp; this is so probable that it
                    would be another reason for not going there at present. General Moore, say the papers, is gone to see if we can enable the
                    Portugueze to defend their country.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784–1790. After the controversial
                        Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally
                        wounded at the Battle of Corunna. The <title>Morning Chronicle</title> reported on 20 December 1804: ‘Government, it is said,
                        aware that the Emperor of FRANCE will endeavour to <hi rend="ital">force</hi> Portugal into the War against this Country, has sent General MOORE, in a fast-sailing cutter, to enable them to judge how far any disposable force which we could send to the aid of our ally, might be adequate, with that of the country, to repel such attacks’.</note> the country is very defensible – provided there were Englishmen to defend it, or if all the
                    Portugueze officers were hung. It would be very easy to prevent the French from winning it, if it were possible to prevent the
                    nation from losing it. His answer will be no. that is a hopeless business. If however contrary to my belief he take hope &amp; we
                    send off an army I will try for a civil appointment in it.</p><p rend="indent1"> About <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Fricker</ref>. I have no particular intentions, &amp; only
                    wish him settled in any office or any counter where he could earn a decent maintenance. his city friends are two people whom <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> fell in with – a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Salt<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> who talked largely &amp; will I suppose from that very circumstance do
                    nothing &amp; Mawman the bookseller.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Mawman (1763–1827): publisher (1804–1813) and
                        joint-editor (1805–1807) of the <title>Critical Review</title>. Mawman wrote and published, in 1805, <title>An Excursion to
                            the Highlands of Scotland and the English Lakes</title>. Mrs Coleridge may have talked with him while he was in
                        Keswick.</note> I design to ask <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peche</ref> if he can get him into the India
                    House – expecting a <del>xxxx</del> denial – but what is to be done without asking? To any kind of mill-horse work he is fully
                    competent, &amp; has this in his favour that is he thoroughly trust-worthy. We are trying every quarter to get him a situation,
                    but with little chance of success. If <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> were returned there would be
                    more hope, for his friends &amp; mine are quite distinct. he talked of many things when he sent for him up to London &amp; may
                    perhaps do them when he comes back. but meantime I know not how poor <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> is to
                    shift. What you can do for him I do not see, unless you invent a third office, &amp; so reclerkify him.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> was vaccinated because I believe the vaccine to be
                    the mildest variety of the small pox, &amp; think it will ultimately answer.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May had
                        been inoculated against smallpox, using cowpox serum; a method popularised by Edward Jenner (1749–1823; <title>DNB</title>) in
                            <title>An Inquiry Into the Causes and Effects of the Variolæ Vaccinæ</title> (1798).</note> you are a little prejudiced by
                        <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> – who is very apt to be prejudiced himself. Of the children
                    vaccinated here some have been inoculated, other exposed to the disease without effect. At any rate if it only secure the
                    constitution for a given time that given time would make it very possible &amp; very practicable to annihilate the small pox. I
                    would rely more upon the belief which Jenner found in the country than upon his own authority in fact the thing was known in many
                    other parts.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The fact that dairymaids did not contract smallpox had long been known in the
                        West Country rural population.</note><ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Pooles</ref> brother<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Poole (1770–1798), the
                        only brother of Thomas Poole to reach maturity, was educated for the medical profession.</note> was busied upon it &amp; would
                    have very likely had the start of Jenner, if he had not died. There is a great deal of vulgar knowledge in the world if
                    philosophers would but look for it.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> will necessarily reside in Hereford city or shire if he comes to
                    England, which he will not do if he can help it. If the army go over I shall thro him apply for a civil appointment to Lord
                        Bute<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 4th Earl of Bute (1744–1814; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; to
                    the Duke of Bedford.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766–1839; <title>DNB</title>):
                        known as Lord John Russell until 1802, he was Lord Lieutenant of Ireland from 1806–1807.</note> to both of whom he could well
                    address himself, <del>xxx</del> knowing them well. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> also would do something for
                    me. there are plenty of suitable offices such as inspector store keeper &amp;c &amp;c – &amp; I have no objection to give his
                    Majestys forces my services for the morning, for a <del>xxx xxx</del> &lt;reasonable allotment&gt; of pay, baugh &amp; forage
                    money &amp; rations, &amp; for the privilege of breathing Lisbon air &amp; reading Portugueze in the evening. The probabilities
                    against this are – that we shall send no troops to Portugal – &amp; still more likely that some foolish &amp; disgraceful peace
                    will be patched up – for you must know I am very much in the humour for carrying on a war against the Bonapartes ad infinitum. but
                    he wants to be acknowledged Imperator &amp; our ministers want to get out of a scrape, &amp; it must be confessed that we all want
                    to get rid of a few taxes.</p><p rend="indent1"> A week will finish my reviewing &amp; send me back to history like a giant refreshed. Madoc, if the last notes do
                    not miscarry on the road is off my hands. my mornings will therefore be given to Portugal or Portugueze Asia<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘History of Portugal’ which he never completed.</note> – &amp; my evenings to the very
                    important consideration of – additional ways &amp; means for the year. I expect to do much before the fine weather comes round,
                    &amp; draws me &amp; the dormice out together. My eyes are in tolerable order &amp; have continued so unusually long so as to give
                    me a hope that I shall get rid of the disease, &amp; I am in as sound health of body &amp; mind as <del>x</del> you could wish me
                    to be.</p><p rend="indent1"> Amadis has been eulogized by the British Critic<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s 1803 translation
                        of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> was reviewed in the <title>British Critic</title>, 24 (1804), 471–481.</note> – as the work
                    is not original I am not ashamed of their praise, &amp; its not being original accounts for it. translation excites nobodys
                    envy.</p><p rend="indent1"> There is in one class of diseases something very analogous to vegetation. they strike root, grow, ripen &amp; seed
                    – the variolous sorts blossom <del>xxx</del> the yellow fever is cryptogamic. I suppose this illustration cannot be new to any
                    body else <del>xxx xxx xxx</del>, it is so very striking, but it came into my head as I was looking at the cow pock on the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithlings</ref> arm which <del>xxx</del> is now overblown &amp; has dropt off.</p><p rend="indent1"> Has <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George I</ref><del>xxx</del> had a legacy or not? how goes on the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> with his opus? – did I
                    ever tell you that John Thelwall in a printed poem addresses the head of the office for overseeing returns of the poor – in blank
                    verse – by the name of Arcadian <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref>. which would no little annoy the &lt;said
                    Arcadian&gt; in conversation.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thelwall’s phrase for Tom Poole, implying that his rural
                        location in Somerset was Arcadian, or idyllic, rather than a place of poverty, appears in ‘Lines written at Bridgewater, in
                        Somersetshire’, in John Thelwall (1764–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems Chiefly Written in Retirement</title>
                        (Hereford, 1801), p. 131.</note> – Somebody has christened the young Roscius – Master Helisabad<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Betty (1791–1874; <title>DNB</title>), the boy actor, termed ‘young Roscius’ after the Roman actor
                        Quintus Roscius (c.126–62 BC), who caused a sensation when he made his Drury Lane debut in 1804. ‘Helisabad’ is a Latinate pun
                        on ‘Elizabeth’, the full form of the colloquial name ‘Betty’, as well as the name of the hero’s companion in <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title>, translated by Southey in 1803.</note> – presuming that the name has been vulgarized into Betty in process of
                    time.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. many happy returns!</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>