<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1087</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2209</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        99&#8211;101.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1087" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1087" type="letter">
        <head>1087. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1805-07-26">26 July 1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: [partial] E/ [MS torn]Y29/ [MS torn]805; 10o&#8217;Clock/ JY.29/ 1805 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 111 1805/ Robert Southey/ No place 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        July/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> August<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published:
                        Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        99&#8211;101.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your long silence makes me uneasy, especially as I know your eyes have been severely affected, &#8211; &amp; therefore am
                    apprehensive that the disorder still continues. My own, since last I wrote,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to
                        John May, 22 May 1805, Letter 1069.</note> have had a wearying attack, from which they are hardly yet recovered. a sad &amp;
                    sore evil it is, &#8211; one which it is impossible ever to forget while it continues, <del>equally</del> &amp; which cuts off one of
                    our best resources. Do let me hear of you, if not from you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last number of the Edinburgh Review has been by mere accident dropt here, &#8211; else I never see a new book except
                    such as come to me to be tried.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring to his employment for the
                            <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> I looked with some curiosity to the account of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpole&#8217;s
                        poems.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horace Walpole (1717&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Isabel, from the Spanish
                            of Garcilasso de la Vega, with other Poems and Translations from the Greek, Italian &amp;c. &amp;c.</title> (1805) was
                        reviewed in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 8 (July 1805), 290&#8211;300.</note> You must know that when I saw this book
                    advertised I had thoughts of sending to <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">A. Aikin</ref> to say I would review it, &#8211; for the
                    sake of doing it civilly; &#8211; the main evil which ill-natured reviews do is that they give pain to the friends of an author &#8211; (I
                    mean those who are really his friends) &#8211; &amp; I know just enough of the Walpoles to be willing to do any silent &amp; secret
                    civility of this kind. &#8211; The Scotch account wants a little courtesy at its set-out, else it is in a proper spirit. I have been
                    somewhat sorry that I did not enlarge upon the vicious colouring &amp; character of Lord Strangfords mock translations,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Percy Clinton Sydney, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Poems from the Portuguese of Luis de Camoens</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        569&#8211;577.</note> as nothing can be so mischievous as that kind of writing which is just not indecent, &#8211; which exhibits a
                    profligacy of morals, thro a transparent veil of good manners. If your friend has been fairly accused of trespassing in this way,
                    I am glad I did not send for his book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is long since I had any tidings of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &amp; his last
                    letter complained of ill health. The last news of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> were from Jamaica
                    whither he has gone with Admiral Cochrane<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral Sir Alexander Forrester Inglis Cochrane
                        (1758&#8211;1832), appointed commander of the Leeward Island station in 1805.</note> in pursuit of the Rochefort squadron;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The squadron of French ships commanded by Contre-Admiral Zacharie Allemand (1762&#8211;1828) and
                        based at Rochefort, which slipped past the British blockade and harassed British ships in the Atlantic and West Indies.</note>
                    &amp; from whence he was about to return to Barbadoes. His prizes had escaped, but he feared that the general distress occasioned
                    in the Leeward Islands by the contributions raised by the French &amp; the havoc they made among the shipping, would materially
                    lessen their value.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804 HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas
                        Southey was a lieutenant, captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with cotton. It was
                        customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict.</note> &#8211; Home
                    news I have none, &#8211; &amp; in these cases no news is good news. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the little one</ref>
                    grows &amp; does well. she runs about &amp; daily enlarges her vocabulary of half-articulated words. My friend <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> is with me, &amp; he &amp; I &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> are about to explore the whole of the Lake country on foot, after which I
                    shall accompany him on his return as far as the Yorkshire caves.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Ingleborough Cave and
                        White Scar Cave, near Ingleton in Yorkshire.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Among the few books which have yet arrived for the next years review are Lindleys voyage to Brazil,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Lindley (dates unknown), <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ... with
                            General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto Seguro</title>
                        (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 27&#8211;32.</note> which you will probably have seen, &amp;
                    Villars&#8217;s Essay on the Reformation,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Charles Franc&#807;ois Dominique de
                        Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title>, trans. B Lambert (dates
                        unknown) (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 177&#8211;187.</note> which gained the prize of the National
                    Institute, &#8211; a book surprisingly good, considering it is the work of a Frenchman. The Author has evidently learnt his religion in
                    Germany &#8211; it is a good symptom <del>xx</del> that such a subject should have been proposed by the Institute, &amp; still better
                    that the premium should have been awarded to a work written upon decidedly protestant principles.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Froude<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Hurrell Froude (1770/71&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), Church of
                        England clergyman of Dartington, South Devon, and later Archdeacon of Totnes.</note> is in this country, visiting his wifes
                        brother,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Froude was married to Margaret (1774/5&#8211;1821), daughter of John and Margaret
                        Spedding of Armathwaite Hall, Keswick (<title>DNB</title>). Her brother was John Spedding (1770&#8211;1851) of Mirehouse, the house
                        and estate near Bassenthwaite lake. Spedding was a schoolmate of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>
                        at Hawkshead.</note> perhaps I spell his name wrong. I met him at dinner at your house in Bedford Square once, of which he
                    reminded me. &#8211; We are still in daily expectation of letters from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    to announce his arrival in England, which however still depends upon contingencies so out of his power, that daily disappointment
                    neither surprises nor alarms us. He holds the situation of public Secretary (the second person in the Island)<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> was in Malta at this time.</note>
                    till the person to whom the reversion of the Office was given by government arrive to relieve him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is, as you may suppose, my idle season. I am peripateticating among the mountains, laying in appetite for my
                    books &amp; fireside when the solitary season comes on. Some idle time too has been occasioned by indisposition. I had not been
                    well when my last was written, &amp; have since been alike incapacitated for pleasure or for business by an obstinate cold which I
                    have not yet wholly shaken off.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The reception of Madoc,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Madoc</title> was published
                        in March 1805.</note> as far as I can learn at this distance, is very satisfactory. Some persons indeed are disappointed by
                    it, whose good opinion would have weighed with me. It seems to have disappointed all those who much admired Thalaba,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> &amp; to have much delighted
                    all who had no taste for Thalaba. It is easier to form a true judgement of my own poem in print, than when it lay in manuscript
                    &amp; was exclusively my own. I am satisfied with the execution, but cannot help feeling that I could have executed equally well a
                    plan which should have required a higher key. &#8211; If you have not read the Lay of the Last Minstrel<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott, <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805).</note> let me recommend it as a very
                    delightful poem.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-07-26">July 26. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>