<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1155</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2277</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 85.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 23&#8211;25 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1155" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1155" type="letter">
        <head>1155. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1806-02-11">11 February
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />
                        Endorsement: RS./ 11 Feb. 1806<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 85<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 23&#8211;25 [in
                    part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If it had pleased God to send William Pitt to the Devil in the year 1790 &#8211; but better late than never.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806. He died on 23
                        January 1806.</note> And so the wise people of England are going to record their own infatuation upon marble &#8211; as if paper
                    &amp; printers-ink would not sufficiently preserve the memory of it to posterity!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It seems to <del>x</del> me that the Grenvilles get into power just as they could wish, but that it is otherwise
                    with <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> &amp; Grey.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Ministry of all
                        the Talents&#8217;, established in February 1806, included <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville, Baron
                            Grenville</ref> as Prime Minister 1806&#8211;1807, Charles James Fox and Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764&#8211;1845;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1830&#8211;1834 and leading Whig; he became First Lord of the Admiralty in 1806&#8217;.</note>
                    They are pledged to parliamentary reform, &amp; in this their colleagues will not support them. It will be put off at first with
                    sufficient plausibility under the plea of existing circumstances &#8211; but my good old friend Major Cartwright<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Cartwright (1740&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), political reformer.</note> (who is as noble an old Englishman
                    as ever was made of extra-best superfine flesh &amp; blood) will find that existing circumstances have no end. &#8211; <del>the xxx xxxx
                        xxx</del> so there must come a time when it will appear that if the question be not honestly brought forward it has been given
                    up as the price of their admission to power. &amp; in that case <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> had better for
                    himself have died instead of the other ministers who had nothing to lose in the opinion of wise men. &#8211; So that I am not sure that
                        <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Foxs</ref> friends ought to rejoice at his success.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But quoad<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;with respect to&#8217;.</note> Robert Southey things are
                    different. I have a chance of getting an appointment at Lisbon (this course is said to yourself only) either the Secretaryship of
                    Legation &#8211; or the Consulship.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey expected to benefit from the change in office as his
                        friend and patron <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref> was appointed Under Secretary of
                        State in the Home Office of the new ministry under his uncle, Lord Grenville.</note> whichever falls vacant first has been
                    asked for me, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> has promised to back the application. Blessed
                    however is he that putteth not his trust in man! I shall follow my own plans, relying upon nobody but myself, &amp; still go to
                    Lisbon in the autumn, if fortune finds me there so much the better, but she shall never catch me on the wild goose chace after
                    her. &#8211; I have some hope for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, if Sir S. Hood<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Vice-Admiral Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), was in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey
                        served, but had retired from the Admiralty in 1800.</note> be in the Admiralty, &#8211; &amp; indeed it is possible that I have
                    means of interest with Grey &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to be an Admiral, that when he is fourscore he may be killed
                    in a great victory &amp; get a monument in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls &#8211; for this reason. I have some sort of notion that one day
                    or other I may have one there myself, &amp; it would be rather awkward to get among so many sea captains unless one had a friend
                    among them to introduce me to the mess-room. &#8211; It is ridiculous giving the Captains this honour &#8211; a Colonel in the army has the
                    same claim. better build a pyramid at once <del>of marble</del>, &amp; insert their names as they fall, in this marble
                    gazette.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On Monday the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> (barring accidents) my reviewing will be finished now &amp; for evermore,
                    Amen. This will be a great emancipation, &amp; is on my part rather a bold one, as I proceed upon the assumption that I can raise
                    the <del>xxx</del> deficit by worthier labour in the same time. I am old enough to calculate upon the chances of life, &amp;
                    knowing myself to have consumption in contingency &#8211; even if it should not prove to be in strict entail &#8211; will not leave till
                    tomorrow what should be done today. As soon as I come back from Lisbon I begin to publish &#8211; if I stay there I get the copy ready
                    &amp; care not how long it remain in manuscript, &#8211; in either case the work will be done.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s plans to return to Portugal to finish his &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; did not materialise and his work remained
                        unfinished.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tuesday 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; I return to Espriella,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> to work
                    uninterruptedly at it for one month &amp; then I shall emerge from my den, come to London, &amp; get myself a new outside. Our
                    fathers which are in the Row<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A jokey reference to Southey&#8217;s publisher <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Thomas Norton Longman</ref>, who had premises in <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref> (&#8216;Paternoster&#8217; meaning &#8216;Our father&#8217;) in
                        London.</note>
          <del>x</del> will be glad enough to see me make my appearance &amp; put an end to all future intercourse between
                    them &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey and Gosvenor Charles Bedford were jointly editing an anthology for Longman entitled <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, published in 1807.</note> &#8211; I shall be <del>gloryfied</del> glorified shortly in the <hi rend="ital">weekly-annual</hi>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Taylor reviewed Madoc in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 604&#8211;613.</note> &#8211; would there were any way of discovering who the gentleman is who
                    menstruates upon me in the Monthly<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), had
                        written a hostile review of Southey&#8217;s poem, <title>Madoc</title> (1805), in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 48 (October
                        1805), 113&#8211;122.</note> &#8211; by the blessing of God I would not be long in his debt &#8211; a little revenge is very amusing, &amp; good
                    for the bile.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will trouble you to ship off for me per waggon an old trunk in your possession &#8211; full of all sort of womaniana.
                    it is a round-topt trunk, which I believe once was a hair one, &amp; will <del>keep</del> need a strong cord having no lock.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If Don Manuel be not sent to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> it may as well not be
                        sent,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman used the powers he had as secretary for the Speaker of the House of
                        Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>, to frank mail on Southey&#8217;s behalf.</note> &#8211; for my route
                    to London must be a different one. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> also is an Emperor now.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman had recently been appointed Under Secretary of State in the Home Office and so had the
                        power to frank mail; see Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 8 February 1806, Letter 1153.</note> &#8211; I had almost forgotten to say
                    that two proof sheets will be sent to you for the sign manual &#8211; which is to save me thirteen pence upon each. It cost me precisely
                    a penny postage to correct Madoc &#8211; &amp; a penny more to the booksellers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-02-11">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 11. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>