<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1702</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2824</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: S. T. Coleridge, The
                            Friend, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, 495&#8211;497.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1702" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1702" type="letter">
        <head>1702. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1809-10-26">26 [October 1809]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ S. T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.<lb />MS:
                        MS untraced. Formerly in the possession of Rev. N.F.D. Coleridge, the MS was sold at Sotheby&#8217;s, 15 July 2010, present location
                        unknown. Text is taken from copy at British Library, RP9236.<lb />Previously published: S. T. Coleridge, <title>The
                            Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, 495&#8211;497.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Coleridge</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Porter kept your letter, manuring it in his Pocket till Tuesday, &amp; it then found its way to me at such an
                    hour that as soon as I could get pen in hand to answer it news came that the carriers were going. &#8211; I will endeavour to do what
                    you desire so as to send it on Saturday.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had asked Southey on 20 October 1809
                        to &#8216;look over the eight numbers&#8217; of <title>The Friend</title> &#8216;and to write a letter ... in a lively style, chiefly urging, in
                        a humorous manner, my Don Quixotism in expecting that the public will ever pretend to understand my lucubrations, or feel any
                        interest in subjects of such sad and unkempt antiquity&#8217;, meaning to answer Southey&#8217;s letter in a future number of <title>The
                            Friend</title>. See <title>The Collected Letters of S. T. Coleridge</title>, ed. E. L. Griggs, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956&#8211;1971),
                        III, p., 254. As well as this letter, Southey also wrote a reply intended for publication, which however arrived too late for
                        Coleridge to use it in <title>The Friend</title>. For that letter, see Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, [28 October 1809],
                        Letter 1704.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Friend is faulty in nothing but its mode of publication, which certes is the most unsuitable that <del>xxxx
                        has</del> could possibly be <del>xxxxx</del> chosen for matter of close reasoning &amp; high philosophy. The mischief however
                    is only temporary, &#8211; <del>&amp;</del> the objection applying only to these Essays while they are appearing in weekly sheets,
                        <del>not</del> &amp; ceasing as soon as they are in a collected form. It would be better to intersperse numbers of amusement,
                    &#8211; indeed <del>t</del> give three four or five in succession &#8211; so as to put the great children who read it in good
                        <del>humour</del> &lt;humour&gt;; give them sugar plumbs so that they may be ready with open mouth to swallow a tonic bolus &#8211;
                    every now &amp; then before they are aware of what is coming. At present they expect physic &amp; make up their mouths
                    accordingly, &amp; what is worse, their stomachs too. Any dislocation of the logical order of the Essays is an inferior
                    consideration, that can be remedied in reprinting them. At present the one thing needful is to amuse the readers for a while &amp;
                    give them something that they can <hi rend="ital">talk about</hi>, &#8211; Heaven help us &#8211; it is for this end only that the precious
                    &#8216;Public&#8217; condescend to read.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You told me you had proved those mad<del>x</del> scenes in Jeronymo to be Shakesperes. I have no doubt they are so.
                        <del>xxx</del> make this the subject of an early number<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his <title>Specimens of
                            English Dramatic Poets</title> (1808), pp. 6&#8211;12, <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> suggested that these
                        scenes in Thomas Kyd&#8217;s (1558&#8211;1594; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Spanish Tragedy: or, Hieronimo is mad again</title> (1580s) may
                        have been written by John Webster (c.1580 &#8211; c.1634; <title>DNB</title>). Coleridge would lecture in London on Shakespeare and
                        Elizabethan drama in 1811 and 1812, but did not discuss the issue in <title>The Friend</title>.</note> &#8211; there will be
                    something for the talkers, &amp; for the mudlarks &amp; gold-finders of literature, &amp; for the magazine-men to discuss, &#8211;
                    besides its own value.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you have an Essay upon the Spanish Ballads &#8211; showing how much worse they are than the English, &amp;
                    introducing three or four specimens of the different kinds which happen to be lying by me? I do not propose this as any thing
                    striking, tho it may turn out better than the subject promises, &#8211; but merely because I know not what else to offer. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> An essay on this subject did not appear in <title>The Friend</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">G. Coleridges</ref> conduct exemplifies the precious consequences of substituting faith
                    for good works, &amp; talking about religion till you cease to feel it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s
                        elder brother George had rejected his appeal to help finance <title>The Friend</title>. See Coleridge&#8217;s letter of 18 October
                        1809 in <title>The Collected Letters of S. T. Coleridge</title>, III, pp. 249&#8211;251.</note>
          <del>When xxxx xx should xxxxxx</del> In general men degrade their intellects by corrupting their hearts: he has gone thro the
                    opposite process which is rather the worst of the two. &#8211; What do you mean about <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>, &#8211; that was the most unpleasant part of your letter, &#8211; the rest related to light vexations &amp; evils all
                        removable.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stuart had criticized Coleridge&#8217;s method of publishing and distributing
                            <title>The Friend</title> in a letter to him of 5 October 1809. The text is given in S. T. Coleridge, <title>The
                            Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, p. 493.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have undertaken the whole historical part of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> New
                    Register, at unreasonable notice &amp; ill prepared for the task, &#8211; but he was in distress, having been disappointed in the sample
                    he received from the person originally engaged &#8211; (&#8211; whom I suspect to have been W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Rose, old Georges son) &#8211;
                    &amp; he made me an offer which it <del>would</del> became me to accept.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ballantyne had
                        offered Southey &#163;400 a year to edit the historical sections of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. The suspected
                        predecessor was the poet and translator William Steward Rose (1775&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>); his father was the Pittite
                        loyalist MP George Rose (1744&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I am working at this, &amp; greatly pressed for time. The
                    first Chapter is printed, &#8211; it will displease the Foxites<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A faction within the Whig
                        party who were followers of the policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James Fox</ref>.</note> as much
                    as your Letters did, &amp; it will offend all parties in turn, being tolerably strong &amp; stinging. &#8211; Will you give me as
                    briefly as you please the history of that Maltese Regiment which behaved so ill at Scylla last year?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a slip on Southey&#8217;s part for Capri. The Maltese regiment was not involved in fighting at Scylla,
                        Calabria, in 1809, but in 1808 became notorious when on 4 October it fled back to barracks and allowed itself to be taken
                        prisoner, rather than face flanking fire from the French. Coleridge supplied Southey with information on the Maltese regiment
                        in a letter of 24 December 1809 (see <title>The Collected Letters of S. T. Coleridge</title>, III, 265). Southey used this
                        information as the basis of his account of the affair&#8211;blaming British officers for removing the Maltese from the defence of
                        their own island&#8211;in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 213.</note> I will tell any truths
                    about Sicily that you may think fit to be told.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have asked <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> to use his influence with Lord
                        Mulgrave<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>):
                        diplomatist and politician, appointed First Lord of the Admiralty in 1807.</note> on behalf of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Sir George
                        Beaumont, 12 October 1809, Letter 1692.</note> This was done with no little reluctance &amp; gizzard-grumbling on my part, &#8211;
                    but knowing how intimate Sir G. is in that quarter, I thought it was not justifiable to let my own dislike to asking favours stand
                    in the way here. What may come of it God knows. Sir G. wrote me an answer sufficiently kind recommending me rather to apply to Ld
                        <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lonsdale</ref>, &#8211; that however was out of the question. He has county &amp; borough
                    applications of that nature out of number.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. was very interesting. I did not venture being no German to
                    alter the name of <hi rend="ital">Munster</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A
                            Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London, 1809), p. 116. The text is given in S. T. Coleridge,
                            <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, p. 497.</note> tho I believe
                    it should be <hi rend="ital">Muncer</hi>, &#8211; &amp; I was in hopes you would have said more of him, he being one of my Worthies of
                    the World.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>The Friend</title>, 5 October 1809, Coleridge had cited
                        &#8216;Munster&#8217;, alongside Luther and Erasmus. He may have meant Sebastian M&#252;nster (1489&#8211;1552), editor of the Hebrew Bible, or
                        Thomas M&#252;nzer (c. 1490&#8211;1525), the German leader of the Anabaptists. Southey means the latter. The text is given in S. T.
                        Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, p. 497.</note> At
                    present the little mention you have made of him leaves him under his usual load of obloquy. Would the lives of Loyola &amp; Wesley
                    be fit for the Friend? The one you know I have by me, &amp; materials at hand for amplifying or amending it; &#8211; there is none that
                    I know of in our language except <del>such</del> slight second-hand notices, &#8211; nor is there any account of Wesley except those
                        <del>we</del> &lt;which&gt; have been written by his disciples.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not
                        write the lives of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) and Ignatius Loyola (1491&#8211;1556) for <title>The Friend</title>
                        but did publish <title>The Life of Wesley: and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> &#8211; Tell me any thing
                    that I can do, &amp; I will purloin time to do it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Fricker is released at last, &#8211; a great blessing for herself &amp; for poor <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref>  &#8211;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Martha Fricker (n&#233;e Rowles), the mother-in-law of both Southey and Coleridge, was nursed in her final illness by her daughter
                        Martha.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1809-10-26">Thursday 26.<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            </date>
          </p>
          <p>
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref>  expected to hear that the
                        Applethwaite was received, which was sent in a letter by young Benson.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps
                            Coleridge&#8217;s manuscript of &#8216;At Applethwaite&#8217; (1804), <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> sonnet
                            on the property given him in 1803 by <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>, forwarded from
                            Keswick to Coleridge in Grasmere by his wife Sara. &#8216;Young Benson&#8217; may have been the son of Ann Benson who worked as a maid
                            for the Wordsworths.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>