<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1387</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2509</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 120.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 28&#8211;30.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1387" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1387" type="letter">
        <head>1387. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-12-01">1 December
                    1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 1
                            Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1807<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 120<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 28&#8211;30.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is arrived after a six weeks passage. Provokingly enough he has sent the
                    letter which he wrote for me to Falmouth, &amp; directed one to me which ought to have gone there, so that I neither know any
                    thing of his <del>xxx</del> movements, nor whether <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>  be with
                    him. I have written to know how long he stays in town,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Herbert
                        Hill, 30 November 1807, Letter 1384.</note> &#8211; &amp; my business in now writing is to ask whether, in case his answer should
                    wish me to set forward without loss of time &#8211; it be convenient for you to receive me in the course of the next fortnight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My plans for the coming year are tolerably extensive. the first volume of Brazil certainly goes to press in the
                        spring.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was not
                        published until 1810.</note> I think also of setting forward a volume of Travels in Portugal, for which I possess matter in
                        abundance.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not produce this projected book; but his 1797 <title>Letters
                            Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> were reprinted in an expanded form in 1808 as
                            <title>Letters Written During a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note> Espriella sells &#8211;
                    about 300 are left of the thousand, &amp; the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> think it likely that in
                    another month it will be expedient to send it again to press; &#8211; when the humour takes me therefore I may prudently proceed with
                    the projected completion.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). A second edition was published in 1808; a sequel was not
                    forthcoming.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Overtures have been made me to bear a part in the Edinburgh Review, choosing my own books, &amp; expressing my own
                    opinions: &#8211; they come through <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> but unquestionably from Constable.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), the Edinburgh publisher of the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title> and Scott&#8217;s <title>Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (1805) and <title>Marmion</title>
                        (1807). For Southey&#8217;s answer, see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 December 1807, Letter 1392.</note> I have returned no answer as
                    yet, having written one in refusal, &amp; detained it for farther consideration. To the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> however I communicated this offer<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter has not been
                        traced.</note> &#8211; that they may see the unfitness of my reviewing at seven pounds the Annual sheet,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, for the <title>Annual Review</title>, for which Southey had been reviewing for four years.</note>
                    when I am offered ten guineas <del>xx</del> Scotch-measure <del>xxxx</del> &amp; told that the price is soon to be considerably
                    increased. I differ from all the opinions of the Edinburgh Review &#8211; both in taste, morals, politics &amp; religion. The question
                    is whether it be worth while in this rascally <del>xxx</del> age of party-feeling to secure good treatment for myself in that
                    quarter, &amp; take care of my friends; &#8211; as for the employment in a financial point of view it is likely that my time may be as
                    profitably given to better work. My greatest inclining is to lay every thing else aside &amp; get the Brazilian book forward. The
                    sale of 500 cannot be doubtful. &#8211; enough to pay the expense of publication quite certain to be immediate. I mean therefore to
                    print it on my own account, &#8211; for which I can, without difficulty, borrow the necessary sum. &#8211; there is no reason why the
                    booksellers should share my profits <del>xx</del> as interest for an advance of money, which is merely nominal, &#8211; <del>xx</del>
                    they paying nothing before they receive.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had extraordinary weather here &#8211; a deeper snow than has been remembered since 1767. Three days we were
                    without a post, &#8211; on one day only one person came into the town. In some places the ro[MS torn] is cut thro drifts seven or eight
                    feet deep [MS torn] went out to see this pass thro <del>banks of snow</del> walls of snow, &amp; very singular it is. Even today
                    after four days gentle thaw, a hundred men are employed in opening the road to Penrith, where the stage has been stuck since
                    Friday week last: &#8211; there the drifts are in some places twenty feet deep. The mountain scenery has been fine beyond all powers of
                    pen or pencil to express &#8211; at morning when the valley was in mist. the heights in sunshine &#8211; &amp; blue sky above them, &#8211; &amp;
                    &lt;at noon&gt; when clouds lay upon their summits, &amp; the sun shone upon the clouds, &amp; the clouds &amp; the snow &amp; the
                    sunshine made up one glory.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is little &lt;doubt&gt; that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> will wish me to
                    meet him in town speedily. His letter I shall get on Saturday or Sunday next, &amp; start within three or four days after I
                    receive yours. But I shall halt three or four ways on the way.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1807-12-01"> Tuesday. Dec 1. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>