<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.949</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2071</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.949" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="949" type="letter">
        <head>949. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1804-06-07">7 June 1804</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 7 June 1804<lb />Postmark: E/
						JUN11/ 1804<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Safe &amp; sound, &amp; if you had ever accomplished a journey of three hundred &amp; fifty miles you would
					understand with what a full sincerity comes the aspiration, thank God!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will inclose to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> by tomorrows post &#8211; or rather by the next
					post, there being none tomorrow, a letter introductory for you to <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>. the process
					advisable is this &#8211; first to carry the list of desiderata to <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Hill</ref>, &amp; let him hunt
					them out by his catalogue. to seek what are still wanting in Hookhams Catalogue,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas
						Hookham (dates unknown) was a bookseller, stationer and book binder and owner of a famous circulating library, who produced
							<title>A New Catalogue of Hookham&#8217;s Circulating Library, on a New and More Extensive Plan ... Consisting of Near Forty
							Thousand Volumes in English, French, and Italian, in History, Antiquities, Voyages, Travels, Lives, Memoirs</title>
						(1785).</note> which <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> as a subscriber, has, &#8211; or at the
						Museum,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British Museum.</note> which last has the inconvenience of imposing upon
					yourself the trouble of transcription<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is advising Bedford here on the collection
						and transcription of texts for inclusion in the jointly edited volume that he and Southey were compiling, which was published
						as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; but so few will remain that this is no serious matter
					if after all any be still wanting &#8211; send the list in a note to <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, after by the
					help of <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> or <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> you have seen
					him, if you will digest an alphabetical list of the whole, marking those you want, he will very likely supply several which have
					escaped my memory or research. Of those whose works are still on sale <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> can
					probably provide you with &#8211; that is those who occur in the last ten years. I will send you from hence several of these, &amp; one
					or two of an earlier date &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cockburne &#8211; Relph a Cumberland poet &#8211; Isaac Ritson &#8211; <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref> &#8211; [illegible word] &#8211;
						<ref target="people.html#HucksJoseph">Hucks</ref> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Robinson.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Extracts from the poetry of Catherine Cockburne (1679&#8211;1749) appear in Southey&#8217;s <title>Specimens of the Later
							English poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), II, pp. 119&#8211;123. Josiah Relph (1712&#8211;1743; <title>DNB</title>), a Cumberland
						poet who published <title>A Miscellany of Poems</title> (1747) also features in Southey&#8217;s <title>Specimens</title>, I, pp.
						369&#8211;375. Isaac Ritson (1761&#8211;1789; <title>DNB</title>), schoolmaster and classical scholar, does not feature in the
							<title>Specimens</title>, and nor do <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Robert Lovell</ref> or <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref>. <ref target="people.html#HucksJoseph">Joseph Hucks</ref> was the
						Cambridge undergraduate companion of Coleridge on their walking tour of 1794, who published a collection of
							<title>Poems</title> in 1798. He does not appear in the <title>Specimens</title>, though Southey had included verse by him
						in the <title>Annual Anthology</title>, 2 (1800), p. 50. Mary Robinson (1757&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>): poet, novelist, woman
						of fashion, courtesan, who contributed poetry to the <title>Morning Post</title>, is not included in the
							<title>Specimens</title>.</note> if you examine the index to the Monthly Review few names, or none, will have eluded us.
					The sooner it goes to press the better, for it of material advantage to a book to appear shortly after Xmas. Winter <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Winter (dates unknown), a printer who frequently worked on books published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> may be directed to copy the earlier extracts first by marking
					them on his instructions. to use his own joke he must not let his namesake out-run him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>xxxxx xxx xxxx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> should let me know something of his movements &#8211; when he
					starts &#8211; when he calculates to arrive that I may engage a lodging for him as there may be else some difficulty. his trunk should
					be directed here (to me <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> Cumberland &#8211;) &amp; do not let him forget fishing tackle
					of all kinds, for this is the land of fishing. Books he will find here, but if he will take the surest way to certain celebrity by
					useful labour &amp; in the fittest way possible, he should bring with him his Persian &amp; Arabic Grammars. A version of
						Ferdusi<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hak&#299; m Abu&#8217;l-Q&#257;sim Firdaws&#299; T&#363;s&#299; (Farsi: &#1581;&#1705;&#1740;&#1605; &#1575;&#1576;&#1608;&#1575;&#1604;&#1602;&#1575;&#1587;&#1605; &#1601;&#1585;&#1583;&#1608;&#1587;&#1740; &#1578;&#1608;&#1587;&#1740; )
							(940&#8211;1020): an Iranian poet renowned for his epic, the <title>Sh&#257;hn&#257;meh</title>. This was one of Southey&#8217;s many book-making schemes designed to bring his friends and relatives renown and money. Horace Bedford did not publish a translation of Firdaws&#299;.</note>
					would make him such a fame as would make a fortune. Other men can do what he could do with European languages, but Oriental
					scholars are very few, &amp; there is a world of work to be done. I will write to him upon this subject which is to me a very
					interesting &amp; important one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Farewell. I have yet to recover &lt;from&gt; some fatigue, &amp; to interpose some little flesh between the
						periosteon<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A membrane that lines the outer surface of bones.</note> &amp; cellular
					membrane &#8211; for I was worn to the very bone in London. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> remembrance. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Thursday June 7. 1804.</p>
          <p>Zounds I have mistaken the day! no post to London.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>