<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1700</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2822</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert
                        Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        326&#8211;331..  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 171&#8211;175.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1700" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1700" type="letter">
        <head>1700. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1809-10-24">24 October
                    1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert
                        Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        326&#8211;331.<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 171&#8211;175.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Senhora<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s mode of address for Barker after first meeting her in
                            Portugal.</note>
          </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is saying little &#8211; that I would pay some deference to your opinion when Mr. Pratts<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Jackson Pratt (1749&#8211;1814), miscellaneous writer under the pseudonym of &#8216;Courtney Melmoth&#8217;.</note>
                    would not weigh more with me than the sound of the wind. You have exactly said of this poor Blacket<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Blacket (1786&#8211;1810), shoemaker&#8217;s apprentice and poet. Pratt published <title>Specimens of the
                            Poetry of Joseph Blacket</title> (1809) and <title>The Remains of Joseph Blacket</title> (1811).</note> what I should
                    judge from these extracts, &#8211; there is force &amp; rapidity in them, &amp; he is in earnest. &#8211; As for my knowing him, the time when
                    that could have been of any service is past, as he has, by your account found friends &amp; richer ones than I could have found
                    for him. If his book were to be bought I would send for it, &amp; then were you here to bid me do it, would perhaps write him a
                    letter &#8211; for the sake of giving him half a days happiness. Poor fellow I have little hope of his recovery, that phrase of &#8216;very
                    fearful health&#8217; hath so consumptive a complection, &amp; consumption is the disease which doth so easily beset us poets, that I
                    generally account the first symptom of it to be fatal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When a young Poet is cut off, Senhora, it appears to me like the death of a young Hero, &#8211; a new &amp; permanent
                    interest is thrown over all that he has done, &amp; he escapes the chance of disappointing the expectations built upon the
                    promises which he had given. There is plenty of genius in the world, &#8211; I am sure you will not suspect me of undervaluing it, in
                    any particular instance, for saying so. &#8211; there is plenty of it, &#8211; but God knows it is a melancholy consideration to think how
                    very little comes to maturity. &#8211; What would have been <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry</ref>  Whites fate if
                    Heaven had not mercifully taken him? &#8211; he would either have let his fanaticism extinguish the light that was in him, &amp; have
                    become a mere Evangelical, &#8211; or that light would have occasioned a struggle which must have overset either his worldly fortunes,
                    if he had followed it; &#8211; or his moral principles if he had shut it up within the dark Lanthorn of expediency, &amp; gone on
                    praying &amp; preaching when it would have been only lip-worship. &#8211; And death is no evil to the Dead; &#8211; they are at their
                    journey&#8217;s end, &#8211; rather to be envied than lamented for having got there. Of all other disagreeable things we say &#8216;I wish it was
                    over&#8217; &#8211; When you have heard me say Senhora that I wished the year 1900 were come &#8211; the same feeling was implied. &#8211; Yet that I am a
                    very happy man you know. That good Lady who as you remember, physiognomised me so luckily for &#8216;a man of sorrow &amp; acquainted
                    with woe,&#8217;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> From Isaiah 53:3. In an 1807 letter to Charles Danvers, Southey writes of
                        what &#8216;M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Fletcher in Edinburgh &#8211; (Miss Smiths friend) said of me? &#8211; that <del>xxx</del> I was &#8220;all that
                        was intellectual, but that it was plain from every feature in his face that he was a man acquainted with woe.&#8221; This tickled me
                        not a little&#8217;; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 25 May 1807, Letter 1326.</note> &#8211; did not happen to know that my acquaintance
                    with Woe has been broken off long since. We certainly did keep company once, &amp; I have been in as many situations of real
                    suffering as falls to any mans lot between the years of 17 &amp; 22. &#8211; But since that time no mans life can have passed more
                    smoothly. &#8211; Sorrows I have had &#8211; but only such as came in the ordinary course of nature, &amp; which resulting from the laws of
                    Nature bring with them their own cure in a sense of the necessity as well as duty of resignation. Suffering arising out of the
                    evils of Society are of a different character, &#8211; they call up resentment indignation &amp; a whole host of turbulent feelings.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This has led me from the matter. What I should have said is that Henry White excites more love &amp; admiration now
                    than he could have done under any other circumstances. You feel more from his fragments than you would have done had they been
                    finished, &#8211; his heart &amp; his hopes have all been laid open to the world, &#8211; which had he lived never would have been the case, &#8211;
                    &amp; every body is ready to praise &amp; regret him, because he is no longer an object of envy. His history poor fellow shows
                    what death will do for a poet! He published a little volume while he lived, &amp; it was neglected or abused.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Clifton Grove, a Sketch in Verse, with other Poems</title> (1803). The book was
                        violently attacked in the <title>Monthly Review</title> (February 1804), after which Southey wrote to White offering
                        encouragement.</note> Nobody noticed it for praise except a few young Poets of kindred aspirations, &#8211; &amp; a certain poor man
                    who having written poetry till he could afford it no longer, was engaged in humble prose among the Cumberland mountains. He died,
                    &#8211; two volumes were published,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition of <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke
                            White, of Nottingham with an Account of his Life</title> (1807).</note> nine tenths of which consisted of pieces which he
                    himself rejected from his own publication &#8211; &amp; now it is who can admire him the most.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I incline to think that if poor Blacket dies, as I suppose he will ere long, more laurels will grow about his
                    grave, than he could ever have earned for his brow. For look you Senhora, Genius is not all that is required to make a man a poet.
                    The best poets have been always the most learned &amp; the wisest men of their time. Shakespeare alone excepted as to learning, &#8211;
                    but intuition in him, &amp; in his peculiar walk, supplied its place, &#8211; as there has been but one Shakespeare since the Creation
                    it is not altogether absurd to suppose that there may not be another till the day of Judgment. All that Blacket hitherto has done
                    I conceive to be imitation, produced indeed by genuine feeling, &#8211; but still such close imitation, as to render it doubtful whether
                    he be capable of anything original. He can have no learning, no store of knowledge of his own, &#8211; &amp; I am afraid with more
                    powers than <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Robert Bloomfield</ref>, &amp; an intellect of higher pitch, he will yet
                    rank below him, because Bloomfield is after all a writer of a distinct character, formed by himself. As for the drama which Pratt
                    talks of,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Blacket&#8217;s play <title>The Earl of Devon; or The Patriots</title>,
                        which was not published until after his death in 1811.</note> Pratt, who hath written tragedy himself, little knows what is
                    required in dramatic composition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me talk of something else. I would <hi rend="ital">lend</hi> one of my ears to any person who wants such a
                    quick little moveable for the rest of the evening, &#8211; if I could have you here, &amp; read Kehama to you. It is all but
                        finished<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem, <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, was published in
                        1810.</note> &#8211; I have heroically adhered to my resolution of never writing it except before breakfast, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">the child</ref> often disturbs me &amp; prevents me from rising. Soon it will go to
                    press, &amp; you will see that I shall be paid for it with plenty of abuse, &amp; less money than will be got by others for
                    abusing it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref>  is gone. In my own mind I always look on to
                    having you for our next door inhabitant hereafter.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barker lived at Greta Lodge in
                        Keswick, next to Greta Hall, between 1812 and 1817.</note> &amp; have a good many dreams upon the improvements which are there
                    to be made.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You wrote to me about the Scudamore Pedigree:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Scudamore family (c.
                        1500&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>): gentry descended from a Norman ancestor who settled at Upton Scudamore in Wiltshire, the
                        family became established in Herefordshire and the southern marches of Wales. The most prominent member of the family at this
                        time was Frances Fitzroy-Scudamore (1750&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), who in 1771 married Charles Howard, later 11th Duke of
                        Norfolk (1746&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) and immediately succumbed to mental illness.</note> of which I know as much as the Man
                    in the Moon, &amp; care as little as I know. The butcher of Norfolk<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note
                        10.</note> is alive &amp; well, the question therefore appertains more to <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir
                        E.&#8217;s</ref>  heir<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Edward&#8217;s heir was the politician Edward
                        John Littleton (1791&#8211;1863; <title>DNB</title>). The son of Moreton Walhouse, Edward changed his name to Littleton in 1812 in
                        order to comply with the terms of the will of his great uncle Sir Edward Littleton, the bulk of whose estates he inherited. He
                        was elected MP for Staffordshire in 1812, and supported <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> and Catholic
                        emancipation. In 1835 he was created Baron Hatherton of Hatherton.</note> than to himself. &#8211; &amp; you will not be very
                    anxious about it for him. You tell me of pictures &amp; drawings. N.B. my chimney piece will speedily have five of <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Miss Bethams</ref> pictures.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Matilda Betham
                        painted miniatures for Southey of himself, <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>. See
                        letter 1680 of this edition.</note> Whereof one is to be the portrait of &#8211; <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George
                        Dyer</ref>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> Are not you a vile Senhora that there should be
                    nothing of yours there? &#8211; Send me the crayons-portrait<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to
                        Barker&#8217;s portrait of him, which has not been traced; see Southey to Mary Barker, 8 September 1809, Letter 1679.</note> &#8211; as
                    you hope to be forgiven for having <hi rend="ital">assassinated</hi> me.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>