<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1170</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2292</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 417&#8211;419.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1170" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1170" type="letter">
        <head>1170. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1806-03-22">22 March [1806]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MAR25/ 1806 <lb />Endorsement: 22 March
                        1806<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 417&#8211;419.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had an Oxford Sausage once<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Warton (1728&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>),
                        (ed.) <title>The Oxford Sausage, or, Select Poetical Pieces Written by the Most Celebrated Wits of the University of
                            Oxford</title> (1764).</note> &#8211; but where the Devil it is now is more than I can tell. tis a book easily found. has not
                        <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> one? As for Mary Latter<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is
                        discussing entries for the anthology, jointly edited by himself and Bedford, which was published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, as a
                        companion to George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803). Mary Latter
                        (bap. 1722&#8211;1777; <title>DNB</title>), author of poetic satires and burlesques, was not included in <title>Specimens of the
                            Later English Poets</title>.</note> I do not remember even her name &#8211; there is a Mary Leapor I think of whom I marked out
                    specimens at <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Hills</ref>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Extracts from Mary
                        Leapor&#8217;s (1722&#8211;1746; <title>DNB</title>) poetry appear in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London,
                        1807), II, 91&#8211;95.</note> &#8211; but these things may now wait for my appearance. I am surprized at the patience of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Our Fathers</ref>. you have been requiring <del>xxxx</del> exertions from them as much out
                    of their way &#8211; as it would be out of mine to open a ball at court. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>xxx</del> To a pleasanter subject. It is you who are mistaken about the Butler. Whoever knows you well Grosvenor knows that
                    your talent is for humour, &amp; of this extravagant character. You were trained up at Westminster in the way which you should go.
                    Other things you may learn to do well &#8211; but not excellently; this you can do inimitably well by merely following your own genius,
                    &#8211; I think you can do it better than any person before you, &amp; that you may take the first place, without danger of ever being
                    superseded. Put the book together<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey often prompted Bedford to publish their comic
                        inventions, which originated in schoolboy stories at Westminster. They were never published by Bedford, but provided the hint
                        for Southey&#8217;s comic novel/miscellany <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> &#8211; this will be amusement not labour &#8211; show
                    it when it is done to <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &#8211; (<ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my
                        daughter</ref> calls him Emily) &#8211; to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211; to W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Nicol<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nicol (d. c. 1855), publisher, and friend of Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s. He was the son of
                        George Nicol (1740?-1828), in whose publishing firm he became a partner in 1800.</note> &#8211; to <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>. take their opinion upon it &#8211; I am sure it will coincide with mine. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not how the second cargo of Espriella<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from
                            England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> was published in 1807.</note> past you by &#8211;
                    but it is no matter as you will soon see the whole of what is done. It is my purpose to work hard in London &amp; go abroad as
                    little as possible. Shall you have leisure sometimes to go sight-seeing with me, with a pair of foreign spectacles on?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning in the persona of Southey&#8217;s pseudonymous traveller, Don Manuel Espriella.</note> &#8211; This
                    last week has been a sort of holyday with me &#8211; I have done nothing but read Beausobre<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Isaac de Beausobre (1659&#8211;1738), a French Protestant clergyman, who published a history of Manichaeism, entitled
                            <title>Histoire Critique de Manich&#233;e et du Manich&#233;isme</title> (1734&#8211;1739). Southey&#8217;s copy of this work was no. 185 in the
                        sale catalogue of his library.</note> &amp; sketch out a strange piece of biography which went off last night to one of his
                    Majesties Under Secretaries of State.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, who was under-secretary of state
                        for the Home department in the new ministry.</note> &#8211; You know that I have done with reviewing for ever &#8211; Heaven be praised.
                    This is the boldest thing I ever yet ventured to do for it has been my sheet anchor. Rats &amp; mice &amp; such small deer have
                    been my food for seven long year. But if I stay in Portugal the resource will not be needed, &amp; if I do not, the materials
                    collected there will be better ways &amp; means on my return.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey anticipated his
                        work as a reviewer for the <title>Annual Review</title> would end with his projected visit to Portugal; after the cancellation
                        of the visit he remained in this employment until 1809.</note> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will go with me &amp; be my fellow traveller there. I wish you could see him, &#8211; you never saw a young man of
                    manners &amp; person more prepossessing or of finer promise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the quotation about <hi rend="ital">Deicide</hi>&#8211; the word of course signifies both crime &amp;
                    criminal like <hi rend="ital">Parricide</hi>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Book VII, line 233,
                        Southey refers to a person as the &#8216;mighty Deicide&#8217;. See volume 2 of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004).</note> &#8211; This leads me to think of the Reviewers &amp; that to ask you whether by
                    the Horatian way you can get <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> taken care of in that review which to the disgrace
                    of Britain is called the British Critic?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa&#8217;s book was <title>The Life and Literary
                            Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with his Poetry and Letters</title> (1806). The <title>British Critic</title> reviewed
                        the book in volume 29 (1807), 480&#8211;488.</note> &#8211; I am intriguing in all directions to get him fairly used &#8211; in the Edinburgh &#8211;
                    in the Critical &amp; Annual I think he is safe.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Duppa&#8217;s work in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 411&#8211;425.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> marriage gives me very great pleasure.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn married Mary Cunliffe (d. 1838), daughter of Foster Cunliffe, 3rd Baronet (1755&#8211;1834) on 9 April 1806.</note> it is
                    about one o clock with him, &amp; he has a long afternoon to look on to. I think it too not unfavourable to happiness to have been
                    once disappointed.</p>
        <p rend="center"> _________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you &amp; I dispute about poetry we argue from different premises. I wish you would buy the Lyrical
                        Ballads<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title> Lyrical Ballads, with Other Poems</title>, first published in 1798,
                        with further editions in 1800, 1802 and 1805.</note> &#8211; if you have them not already. You will see in the Preface &amp;
                    Postscript my critical creed. Since the days of Pope our poetical language has been systematically barbarized. &#8211; I shall weed
                        Thalaba<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poem, <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, published in
                        1801.</note> &#8211; it was my intention to have woven in many more mythological ornaments &#8211; but there are enough already, &amp; it
                    will perhaps be little more trouble to write another Mohammedan poem hereafter. Your remark upon the proposed alteration in Madoc
                    is a very judicious one &amp; has great weight with me. I shall make the alteration &#8211; &amp; perhaps let the fault remain till a
                    convenient season.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published in
                        1807 with little alteration.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will not see me in London so early as you expect. I hope to drink <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> health <del>on</del> upon the bridal day &#8211; which is not long!<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        quotes part of the refrain from Edmund Spenser&#8217;s (1552?&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Prothalamion</title> (1596).</note> &#8211;
                    but it will be silently &#8211; among people who do not know him. The case is that I am obliged to alter my plan of operations, &amp;
                    for the sake of returning by way of Herefordshire upon some troublesome &amp; unpleasant business for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Hill owned a living at
                        Staunton-on-Wye, Herefordshire, which, while he was in Lisbon, he had left in the care of <ref target="people.html#ThomasDr">Dr Thomas</ref>, father of his business agent <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">William Bowyer Thomas</ref>,
                        who had died in 1802. Southey was visiting his uncle&#8217;s estate to investigate the payment of tithes on his behalf; see Southey
                        to Charles Danvers, 17 March 1806, Letter 1166.</note> must elbow eastwards to Norwich on the road up. It is four years since
                    I have seen <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, &amp; as God knows when there may be another opportunity
                    I am going to pass a week with him. He is one of the men in the world for whose talents &amp; knowledge I have the highest
                    respect, &amp; for whose individual virtues the greatest affection. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had forgotten my friend D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dodd. You are right enough about the joke, which perhaps is none
                    even to you yourself. say what you will about him or leave it &lt;for&gt; me on my arrival at your own pleasure &#8211; something should
                    be said to this purport, that he was a rascal &#8211; but that it is to be hoped the country will not long be disgraced by so many
                    executions for <del>xxxxxx</del> forgery.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dodd (1729&#8211;1777; <title>DNB</title>),
                        clergyman and writer, who was hanged for forgery.</note> I can send you no specimens &#8211; but you may buy on my score the Doctors
                    poems &#8211; in Cookes<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Cooke (d.1810), publisher at Shakespeare&#8217;s Head, Paternoster Row,
                        London.</note> edition. I will have them for two reasons &#8211; &lt;first&gt; <del>the one</del> &#8211; because a long poem written by a
                    man who is going to be hanged is a curiosity &#8211; &amp; secondly &#8211; because there is <del>portrait</del> &lt;print&gt; of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dodd in a full-bottomed wig receiving a visit from an Angel in Newgate. <note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Dodd, <title>Thoughts in Prison, and other miscellaneous pieces ... With the life of the author.
                            Cooke&#8217;s edition ... With engravings</title> (1796).</note> So if you walk near Paternoster Row call at Cookes &amp; lay
                    out three or four shillings in the purchase of this book &#8211; NB the best edition &#8211; ie &#8211; the fine paper, in decent binding</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall write our Preface<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> For <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (1807).</note> in London &#8211; we have a hundred things to talk about &#8211; &amp; now &#8211; farewell till we meet.</p>
        <closer rend="indent1"> RS.</closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1806-03-22">Saturday 22 March</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>