<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1323</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2445</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Duke
                        University Library, Southey papers.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 8&#8211;12.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1323" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1323" type="letter">
        <head>1323. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1807-05-17">17 May 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ MAY 20/180; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MY 20/ 1807 FNn<lb />Endorsement: N.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 127
                        1807/ Robert Southey/ No place 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>; Portugal<lb />MS: Duke
                        University Library, Southey papers<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 8&#8211;12.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1807-05-17">May 17. 1807</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My last was written in great haste,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John May, 30 March 1807,
                        Letter 1301.</note> as soon indeed as I myself knew the intelligence which it communicated, &#8211; &amp; in that haste, if my
                    memory do not now deceive me, I neglected to inform you that I had decided upon making this place my permanent abode. This however
                    you would have learnt from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>. The motives for this are so cogent that in
                    fact it can hardly be called a choice; &#8211; if I had not determined upon remaining I must have removed, neither knowing where to go,
                    nor being by any means prepared for the heavy &amp; inevitable expence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now one trouble to request of you in consequence of this determination; &#8211; you have some pictures &#8211; &amp;
                    some few books of mine &#8211; with the set of Picart<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernard Picart (1673&#8211;1733),
                            <title>C&#233;r&#233;monies et coutumes religieuses de tous les peuples du monde</title> (1723&#8211;1743).</note> they will fill a large
                    package, &#8211; too heavy indeed for land carriage; &#8211; will you at your leisure send them round by sea, either to Whitehaven or
                    Workington, no matter which, &#8211; by which means they will reach me at easy <del>expence</del> &lt;cost&gt;. My <del>library is
                        advan</del> &lt;study&gt; is hardly if at all less than yours; it is one of the most delightful rooms you have ever seen,
                    &amp; it will be well filled when my books are all gathered together, as they are now likely to be, &#8211; a source of no little joy to
                    me. &amp; when they are collected, the only inconvenience of this situation will be in great reason removed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The expence of getting my scattered things together, &#8211; of book-shelves &#8211; &amp; of a few decencies, for the want of
                    which the prospect of removal has hitherto been an excuse &#8211; I shall be well able to meet by the end of the year; &#8211; if till then,
                    you will supply me with fifty pounds it will be a great convenience, &#8211; the state of my affairs with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is this. When last in London I had 100 &#163; of him, &#8211; in fore payment for the
                    first edition of Espriella,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; or rather in
                    part of fore payment, &#8211; for <del>it was</del> my share of its profits will <del>pro</del> in all probability be more. He has on
                    sale or our joint account The Specimens &#8211; the Metrical Tales &amp; Madoc.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805),
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> A small edition of Madoc is just compleated.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The second duodecimo edition of 1807.</note> And Espriella &amp; Palmerin<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> are both nearly compleated also. Slow as the Printers are I fully expect both to be published within six weeks
                    at farthest. Of the old books &#8211; (the 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> edition of Madoc &amp; the Met Tales) the sale cannot have been much,
                    or I should have been made acquainted with it; &#8211; but every copy which sells is clear profit. By the Specimens <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> mismanagement will I suspect make me lose credit &amp; prevent me
                    from getting money &#8211; I shall try to remedy both evils by a supplementary volume.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        supplementary volume was planned, but did not appear.</note> Espriella must beyond a doubt sell off an edition in little time
                    &amp; I think there &lt;is good&gt; chance of its having a great sale. Palmerin will net not less than 50 &#163; by Xmas, not more than
                    100 &#163;. I shall draw on Longman for 50 &#163; at present, &#8211; which my last years reviewing with the half of the Athen&#230;um<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Athen&#230;um, a Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, a new magazine launched in 1807, edited by
                            <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> and published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, to which Southey had contributed &#8216;Ominiana&#8217;.</note> entitles me I suppose to do: &#8211; &amp; as soon as I
                    have the like sum in his hands again will appropriate it to the repayment of what I now request of you. I am in great hopes &#8211;
                    indeed in expectation &#8211; that the produce of all these books will enable me at the end of the year to make you a more considerable
                    payment. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My reviewing used to exceed 80 &#163; for the last three years. I did little this year because I would not, much as I
                    needed the money, sell the time. so Harry had half the books which came to me. And &lt;as&gt; now I have nothing to impede me from
                    prosecuting the Brazilian history<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published
                        in three volumes from 1810&#8211;1819.</note> straight forward &#8211; for which I am certain of more considerable profits than have ever
                    yet fallen to my share; &#8211; the Chronicle of the Cid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid,
                            from the Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Cro&#769;nica particular
                                del Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the <title>Cr&#243;ica de Espa&#241;a</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and
                            <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632).</note> is the only other occupation in hand, &#8211; this, as I believe I
                    have informed you, will comprize in its preliminaries great part of what would else have been the introduction to my European
                    history of Portugal. I find it oeconomy of time to carry on two works at once, &#8211; I find it also essential to the preservation of
                    my health; for by long experience I know that whenever my attention is devoted to one object, that object <del>can</del> affects
                    my brain too strongly, &amp; my sleep is disturbed by perplexing dreams concerning it: <del>in</del> the remedy is easy &#8211; I do one
                    thing in the morning, another in the evening, &#8211; &amp; never dream of either: &amp; thus it is that I am enabled to do so much. The
                    Cid &#8211; comprizing a history of the heroic age of Spain &#8211; will go to press as soon as some books from Madrid arrive, which <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has sent for. I know not whether they will reach him in time for the next
                    convoy &#8211; but I expect Rocha Pitta&#8217;s America Port.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebasti&#227;o da Rocha Pita (1660&#8211;1738),
                            <title>Historia da America Portugeza, desde o anno 1500 ate o de 1724</title> (1730). Southey did acquire this
                        work.</note> by that convoy &amp; some other books &#8211; to come by way of <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref>, who is very conveniently situated for me. I have nearly advanced as far <del>I</del> as I can without this book
                    of Rocha Pitta, &#8211; &amp; must in the course of a few days begin with another part in consequence. My first volume will be
                    compleated early in the winter, &#8211; &amp; the Cid I hope published early in the Spring</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I shall do no reviewing except of a friends book, or of new travels which I want to read &amp; cannot obtain by
                    any other means.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Has Ld Roslyn (I think this is his title &#8211; the one who was upon the strange embassy to Lisbon)<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> General James St Clair-Erskine, 2nd Earl of Rosslyn (1762&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), a soldier
                        and politician who was, in 1806, a member of the special mission to Lisbon which resulted in Sir Arthur Wellesley (later Duke
                        of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) being sent to the peninsula.</note> delivered certain maps of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> to Mr Burn?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burns
                        (dates unknown), a member of the English Factory, Lisbon.</note> they are what I must get engraved for my Brazil &amp;
                    Paraguay &#8211; &amp; he desires me to make this inquiry for them &#8211; Ld R. borrowed them to get them copied. I have another thing to
                    trouble you about &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> will not apply to you, <del>on account</del>
                    &lt;because&gt; of the state of his account &#8211; but he applies to me to send him a Master of Arts Gown, &#8211; &amp; some black silk
                    stockings &#8211; being in want of both. Now I must apply to you &#8211; having nobody else to apply to &#8211; Send them to him as a parcel from
                    me, &amp; I will settle for them in the first draft which I shall be able to remit &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The country is becoming very beautiful &#8211; I wish there were hopes of seeing you here, &amp; showing you our lakes
                    &amp; mountains &#8211; your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god daughter</ref>, &amp; little <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>. Early in the winter you will probably see me &#8211; I purpose travelling to
                    London to examine a few books necessary for compleating the notes &amp; preliminaries to the Cid, &#8211; &amp; perhaps <del>to</del>
                    may put the first volume of Brazil to press at the same time.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was not published until 1810.</note> Another part of my business will be to
                    transcribe a MSS of Jeronymo Lobo<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jer&#243;nimo Lobo (1593&#8211;1678) travelled to Ethiopia and to
                        Goa; papers concerning his journey were found, in the twentieth century, in the library of the Duke of Palmela, and in the
                        Ajuda library at Lisbon.</note> which is in the Museum, &amp; which <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    wishes me to restore to its own country &#8211; as I shall very gladly do &#8211; if I can get it transcribed I shall save myself the
                    trouble.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> writes me that his ship has at last got a weeks cruise &#8211; &amp; they have taken a
                    privateer in that time of 14 guns. I know not what his share will amount to, it cannot be much, but it has put him in good
                    spirits, &amp; the weather has put him in good health. &#8211; Whether Lord Cochrane<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral
                        Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), a daring ship&#8217;s captain in the Napoleonic war.
                        Cochrane, angry because he felt corruption in the administration of the navy had denied him prize money and promotion, became
                        a radical MP and critic of John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), former First Lord of the
                        Admiralty (until 1804) and, from 1806 to 1807, Commander of the Channel fleet.</note> speaks truth about the navy remains to
                    be seen, &lt;I believe he does &#8211; indeed I can believe any thing ill of Ld S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> V.&gt; but the Pallas<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom&#8217;s ship, launched in 1804, was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was Cochrane,
                        under whom she was involved in the capture of many French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command passed to Captain George
                        Miller. According to a letter to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, the ship was &#8216;so miserably manned&#8217;
                        that Thomas was &#8216;almost worn out with duty&#8217;; see Southey to Mary Barker, 4 February 1807, Letter 1273.</note> was certainly
                    sent to sea without a sufficient complement of men. there was scarcely a man on board when my brother joined who knew one rope
                    from another ; &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> stated to me that the men were so few as well as so little used to
                    their work that the ship was not safe in bad weather. They were so exhausted for want of hands in bad weather, that he said it
                    made his heart ache to drive them on to fresh exertions. The ship had no master, &amp; to compleat &lt;the matter&gt; one of the
                    Lieutenants knocked himself up at Plymouth, so that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; the other were watch
                    &amp; watch (ie every other <del>three</del> four hours on deck) till they were both so ill that the Captain &#8211; which he ought to
                    have done sooner &#8211; allowd an old Midshipman to take charge of the deck. The men have now learnt their duty.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>