<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1301</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2423</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 414&#8211;417 [in part].Dating note: Warter dates the letter 2 March 1807; it was written over several
                        days.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1301" type="letter">
        <head>1301. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1807-03-30">[started before
                        and continued on] 30 March 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ APR 2/ 1807<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 414&#8211;417 [in part].<lb />Dating note: Warter dates the letter 2 March 1807; it was written over several
                        days.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have desired Our Fathers which are in the Row<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The firm of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> of <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster
                        Row</ref>.</note> to send you <hi rend="ital">a</hi> book which you <hi rend="ital">will</hi> not like much, <del>&amp;
                        whi</del> but which, were it even less interesting to you, it is fitting that you should have as being mine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> It is abominably incorrect, &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> has played the very Devil with his absurd omissions &amp;
                    more absurd insertions. He has taken more liberties with what I had actually done, than I should have thought it decent to have
                    taken with him. There is no help for this &#8211; only that I have ordered some cancels for the sake of public decency, &#8211; &amp; that it
                    is very likely there must be a supplementary volume.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although planned, a supplementary
                        volume never appeared.</note> You need not however tell people that it is a bad book &#8211; they will find out soon enough
                    themselves. The printing is beyond any thing execrable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have something to tell you with which you will not be pleased. In consequence of some arrangements of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> it became necessary that I should either resolve upon quitting the
                    place at a given time, or of remaining with it. The latter suited me best &#8211; it was in fact the only choice to be made &#8211; &amp; here
                    then we have resolved to remain indefinitely &#8211; to fit up the house more decently &amp; to gather together the books. As soon as
                    the weather permits the plastering is to be done, &#8211; &amp; as soon as that is done I shall <del>give xxx</del> give you your last
                    trouble with the books which will be to <hi rend="ital">ship</hi> them off for Whitehaven or Workington, &#8211; taking out one tea
                    chest full of the most valuable for fear of accidents. We are just beginning to inclose the garden where we shall plant shrubs
                    &amp;c &#8211; &amp; heartily do I wish that you were here to be chief Gardener out of doors &amp; headman in the improvements
                    within.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> is on her way to Bristol with the two younger
                        children<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> &#8211; she will bring the pattern of a certain marble paper, of which I will thank you to get me four
                    quire at Barry&#8217;s,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown), of 21 High Street, was Southey&#8217;s
                        favourite Bristol bookseller and stationer; he frequently sent Danvers orders for books to be supplied by Barry.</note> &#8211; if
                    he have not so much he can get it. You will wonder at so large an order, &#8211; but the truth is we conceive that it will make a very
                    good bordering for a room, &amp; be much cheaper as well as much prettier than any to be obtained here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is my full intent to see you in the latter end of the year, God willing, &#8211; &amp; you must make up your mind the
                    first summer you can, to revisit <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; see all the things which you left unseen &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Dominie</ref> is gone for Lisbon. I shall miss him when we launch the boat,
                    &amp; very often envy him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaven knows when the intolerable delays of the printer will let Espriella<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). It was being printed
                        by Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>).</note> appear! I have not three days work to do &lt;to&gt; it, &#8211; &amp; am
                    hurrying him thro every possible channel, &#8211; for fear you know lest another translation should appear first. I am hastening towards
                    the end of Palmerin, &amp; shall feel a great weight off my shoulders when it is done.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> Another book that for you, which you will not like &#8211; but I pray you remember that I do not expect you to read
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> goes on well, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>
                    is growing a very fine boy. He is plagued with an eruption on his head, which is very ugly, &amp; teazes him much with itching,
                    but I know not whether we ought to be sorry that it is there. At least <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmundson</ref>
                    advises us to repel it &#8211; wherein he agrees with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Underwood,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Michael
                        Underwood (1737&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Treatise on the Diseases of Children</title> (1784; with many further
                        editions).</note> whose book I have bought, &amp; with my own opinion, &#8211; we keep it clean by washing it twice a day with
                    butter &amp; beer, &amp; that is all we do. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">little Tartar</ref> has eyes as fit for
                    the Grand Khan as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref> would be for his favourite Sultana, but they are of the
                    finest colour that can be conceived, &amp; he begins to get very kissable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> is right. I am he that is greater than Miller in the Athen&#230;um &#8211; which he of course
                    knew by the Rats.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> King had recognised as Southey&#8217;s a piece in the &#8216;Omniana&#8217; section of the
                            <title>Athen&#230;um; A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title> (February 1807), p. 138, which suggested
                        novel ways of diminishing the rat population: eating them as a delicacy; using their fur in clothing; inoculating them with
                        smallpox. Southey was &#8216;greater than Miller&#8217; in the sense that his jokes were cornier than those of Joe Miller, putative author
                        of a famous joke book: Joseph Miller (1684&#8211;1738), was a popular comic actor on the London stage from 1709 until his death,
                        after which the publisher T. Read issued <title>Joe Miller&#8217;s Jestbook</title>, compiled by the hack writer John Mottley (1692&#8211;1750). Many
                        further editions appeared, and &#8216;a Joe Miller&#8217; became shorthand for a bad joke.</note> I dare say my quaintness annoys no one
                    so much as <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Dr Aikin</ref>, &#8211; that family has a dread of any thing out of their own way &#8211; they
                    are as much afraid of it as a cat is of wetting her feet. I will lay my life that I do not feel half so much satisfaction in
                    putting one of my odd things into a reviewal, as <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> does in drawing his
                    expurgatorical pen thro it. It would move any Christians heart to confession &#8211; yea it would <del>set free</del> set a very Jobs
                    gall bladder in fermentation<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning that even the biblical character, Job, who remained
                        steadfast to God despite the extreme tests sent to try his patience, would be galled by such treatment.</note> could it be
                    told how &lt;unrelentingly&gt; that said <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> has caponized the Cocks of my
                        conceit.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> By &#8216;caponized&#8217; Southey means castrated.</note> I look at my own articles
                    when the volume comes down, &amp; feel upon the perusal &#8211; just as I should do if when calling for a glass of soda water I found
                    the footman had drawn all the corks half an hour before dinner &#8211; for fears the bottle should burst. Oh he is a cruel <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> &#8211; &amp; he serves <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref> just as he serves me &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your information concerning Miss Scott<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> is the first
                    which I have heard since her return to England. What is her complaint supposed to be? It could not surely be consumption &#8211; or she
                    could not have lasted so long?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count Burnetski</ref> flourishes as an author. his Polish letters are to extended to a
                    little volume which Longman prints, &amp; his Specimens are very likely to form a very respectable book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>View of the Present State of Poland</title> (1807); from essays originally published in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>. <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers</title> (1807); a companion to George Ellis&#8217;s <title>Specimens
                            of the Early English Poets</title>.</note> &#8211; Thank God for the Abolition! but Lord Percys motion ought to have been
                    supported &#8211; I have addresst a sonnet to him upon it which you will <del>first</del>soon see in the Courier.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 17 March Hugh Percy, Earl Percy (1785&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>) had launched a motion in
                        parliament proposing the gradual abolition of slavery in Britain&#8217;s Caribbean colonies. The poem was published in <title>The
                            Courier</title> on 22 April 1807 and is included in <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, vol. V, <title>Selected Shorter Poems</title>, ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), pp. 426&#8211;427.</note> About the
                    Catholick question I compleatly agree with the King.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of All the
                        Talents, of which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was a member, fell in March 1807 because the King would
                        not accede to its plan to introduce an act emancipating Catholics from the civil penalties and restrictions placed upon
                        them.</note> Upon this subject I suppose <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; I differ from
                    the other friends of freedom, but I have been deeply concerned that that accursed religion cannot be in the slightest degree
                    fostered without great danger; &#8211; &amp; that Europe is about to be as strikingly divided into two great religious-political parties
                    as it was in the days of the Palatine is very probable.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Monday March 30. &#8211; This evenings post enables me to give you some information concerning myself. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> did his best to snatch something for me out of the fire &#8211; as he says. He could
                    get only the offer of a place in the West Indies worth about 600&#163; a year,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The post of
                        Register of the Vice-Admiralty Court of St. Lucia.</note> &#8211; or a pension of 200&#163; (as a man of letters) at home <del>x</del> &#8211;
                    the latter he chose &#8211; before my answer<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [25
                        March 1807], Letter 1298.</note> could reach him, which answer he rightly divined. Fees &amp; <del>xxx</del> Taxes take away
                    one fifth of this &#8211; I remain therefore with a net income of 160, &#8211; the precise sum which I have hitherto received from him &#8211; &amp;
                    that of course I receive no longer, now that it is no longer needful, &#8211; Are you not amused at my getting a pension from his
                    Majesty? &#8211;&#8211; I am therefore neither richer nor poorer than before &#8211; but better satisfied, &#8211; &amp; peace will give me an additional
                    20 pounds &#8211; which is a reason for wishing for it. Will you procure some Jerusalem &#8211; or underground &#8211; artichokes &amp; give <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Miss Fricker</ref> to send with the things to her sister &#8211; I want to set them in the
                    garden, &amp; there are none to be had here &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>