<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1242</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2364</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1242" type="letter">
        <head>1242. Robert Southey and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref> to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-12-12">[12 December 1806]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: from internal evidence; Thomas says he has &#8216;just returned from
                        Old Brathay&#8217; and this was on Friday 12 December 1806 according to letter 1247 to Thomas Southey, dated 21 December
                        1806.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be glad of Whitfields Memoirs<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Whitefield (1714&#8211;1770;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Calvinistic Methodist leader, whose <title>Journals</title> were published in an unauthorised version
                        in 1738. The authorised version, <title>The Two First Parts of Whitefield&#8217;s Life, with his Journals Revised, Corrected and
                            Abridged</title>, appeared in 1756. Whitefield is discussed in <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                            Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807), Letter 53.</note> &#8211; &amp; also of his Letters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library after his death, no. 3010 is George Whitefield&#8217;s
                            <title>Select Collection of Letters</title> (1772).</note> if the copy you speak of be in good &amp; cleanly condition,
                    there being I think some danger of its displaying the unction of female fingers. Have you any friend at Bath who can buy me a book
                    there? &#8211; for I remember years ago in Hazards Catalogue,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Samuel Hazard (dates
                        unknown), printer and bookseller of Cheap Street, Bath.</note> where it is likely to remain still &#8211; the Pilgrims Progress from
                    Quakerism to Christianity by a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bugg,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Bugg (1640&#8211;1727;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress from Quakerism to Christianity &#8230; Together with a Remedy Proposed for
                            the Cure of Quakerism</title> (1698).</note> &#8211; a name of such remarkable beauty as not easily to be forgotten. Now a few
                    shillings may well be ventured upon this Essence of Bugg, &#8211; for I have to review <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> book,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Thomas Clarkson, <title>A Portraiture of
                            Quakerism, as Taken From a View of the Moral Education, Discipline, Peculiar Customs, Religious Principles, Political and
                            Civil &#338;conomy, and Character, of the Society of Friends</title> (1806), in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5
                        (1807), 594&#8211;607.</note> &amp; also to write one of Espriellas letters upon the Quakers,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (London, 1807), Letter
                        57.</note> &amp; if this book be any way correspondent to its title it would repay its own cost.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As it seems you have to look out the books again (&#8211; indeed I am sorry to give you so troublesome a job &#8211;) add to
                    them a small 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> &#8211; Juniperized<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> To &#8216;Juniperize&#8217; meant to add a gold
                        border and lettering to the bindings of Southey&#8217;s books, with a possible allusion to Friar Juniper, disciple of St Francis,
                        who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to give to a poor woman begging alms.</note> in [MS obscured]
                    &amp; lettered Romances Sueltos.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> This is probably no. 3720 of the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Romances Sueltos en Verso Espanola</title>. Published in Alicante, Seville and Valladolid, the date
                        of publication is unknown.</note> &amp; Wesleys Journal &#8211; 5 Vols in boards.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        journals of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) were first published in twenty parts (London, 1740&#8211;1789).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Almost I may say that the only uncomfortable thoughts or feelings I have are when I think about my poor books,
                    &amp; certainly it does fret my very heart strings to think how much I want them &amp; how much they want me, &#8211; &amp; that instead
                    of being the pride of my eyes &amp; joy of my life as they would be, they are a source of inconvenience &amp; vexation. I will try
                    my very utmost to raise money next year, &amp; settle them &amp; my family before I go abroad &#8211; if abroad it should be possible to
                    go. My Cid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s edition, <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> was
                        published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1808.</note> will &#8211; with its historical introduction,
                    its notes, &amp; its appendix of bibliography &amp; criticism, well fill a quarto volume, &#8211; so do my plans usually extend before
                    me! When this is ready I will offer the copy right for sale, &amp; ask three hundred <del>xxx</del> for it, resolving to take 250.
                    It is doubtful whether I can get this, yet I think not unlikely. It is not pleasant to do it, because it is parting with the
                    principle, &#8211; &amp; if it pays the bookseller for this price, it would have paid me better not to have sold it, &#8211; but &#8211; where there
                    is no remedy patience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Oh how busy I am! &#8211; half thro Palmerin<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published an English
                        translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> &#8211; about 70 pages of
                    Espriella yet to write &#8211; which is more than half a volume. A cargo to ship off tomorrow for <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> &#8211; &amp; then to fall to upon more reviewing than I expected or calculated upon. &amp;
                    yet with all this have spent this morning in walking with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> around the Lake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">[in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey&#8217;s</ref> hand]</p>
        <p>Dear Charles</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Robert has of course answered that part of your letter which concerns him about the books &#8211; &amp;c &#8211; for myself I
                    have little to tell you &#8211; except that I am exceedingly glad I made a point of seeing Sir Saml<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), in command of the
                        fleet in which Tom had served in the West Indies.</note> and am perfectly satisfied with the result &#8211; my hopes of promotion
                    are raised since I saw you &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> writes from Lisbon that he &lt;has&gt;
                    written to his friend the Duke of Bedford<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839;
                            <title>DNB</title>): known as Lord John Russell until 1802, and Lord Lieutenant of Ireland from 1806&#8211;1807.</note> &#8211; whose
                    brother is one of the Admiralty lords about me<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Russell (1767&#8211;1840), brother of
                        John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), was a Civil Lord of the Admiralty.</note> &#8211; this with what
                        <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">the first lord</ref> said to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211;
                    leads me to hope when next I go to sea twill be as <hi rend="ital">Captain</hi> &#8211; if so my time is certainly better employed here
                    than it could be on board.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall write to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> shortly &#8211; and will mention the cause of
                    the Taunton letter &#8211; he is dashing about at Norwich and will be for three weeks longer &#8211; then he goes to walk the hospitals in
                    London &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am just returned from <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Old Brathay</ref> &#8211; when I either see or write to them
                    again your remembrances shall not be forgotten &#8211; writing from Bath you ought to have told me how Miss Phillot<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Phillott (first name and dates unknown) was an acquaintance of Bristol days and a member of
                        a prominent family of professionals and tradesmen centred on Bath.</note> did &#8211; I hope if you saw her my compliments were not
                    neglected &#8211; as you expected in London my time was so completely taken up and I was so tired that I could not see M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickards I hope however the letters I was entrusted
                    with reached her safe inquire of Rebecca Reed<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rebecca Ann Reid (1785&#8211;1834), younger
                        sister of Southey&#8217;s old friend from Bristol, <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref>, would marry Benjamin Rickards (dates unknown), of London. Here the Mrs. Rickards with whom Danvers was to check was presumably her prospective mother-in-law or sister-in-law.</note> when next you see her &#8211; &amp; make my remembrances at the same time &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Madox&#8217;s particularly M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charles<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers lived in Park Street, Bristol, with his old business partner, Charles Madox (or Maddox) and his
                        brother, John (dates unknown).</note> I beg my best respects &#8211; when does your brot<hi rend="sup">hr</hi> go to Plym<hi rend="sup">t</hi>? I am very glad he has got the appointment he wished &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Roberts health is tolerable &#8211; we seldom let an opportunity of walking escape &#8211; but the weather is damnable &#8211; I wish
                    to God he was fixed &amp; his books round him three hundred miles further South &#8211; the want of them and the idea of how much they
                    want him &#8211; is the only thing I know of that vexes him &#8211;&#8211; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is here
                    his stay uncertain &#8211; I understand he goes to the <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> in Leicestershire
                    from hence &#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Sincerely Yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Ths. Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>