<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1033</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2155</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales MS 4812D.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 321&#8211;322.Dating note: Southey&#8217;s dating of &#8216;Saturday&#8217; suggests 9 February, as this was the first
                        Saturday before the postmark date of 13 February 1805. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1033" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1033" type="letter">
        <head>1033. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1805-02-09">[9
                        February 1805]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ Lincolns
                        Inn/London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: FREE/ FEB13/ 1805<lb />MS: National Library of Wales MS 4812D<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 321&#8211;322.<lb />Dating note: Southey&#8217;s dating of &#8216;Saturday&#8217; suggests 9 February, as this was the first
                        Saturday before the postmark date of 13 February 1805. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-02-09">Saturday night</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been grievously shocked this evening by the loss of the Abergavenny &#8211; of which <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> brother was Captain.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Wordsworth (1772&#8211;1805), captain of the East Indiaman, the <hi rend="ital">Earl of Abergavenny</hi>, went down with his ship on
                        the Shambles rocks off Portland Bill, on 5 February 1805.</note> Of course the news came flying up to us from all quarters &#8211;
                    it has disordered me from head to foot: &#8211; <del>At</del>In such <del>occasions</del> &lt;circumstances&gt; I believe we feel as
                    much for others as for ourselves &#8211; just as a violent blow occasions the same pain as a wound, &amp; he who broke his shin feels as
                    acutely at the moment as the man whose leg is shot off. &#8211; In fact I am writing to you merely because this dreadful shipwreck has
                    left me utterly unable to do anything else. It is the heaviest calamity <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> has ever experienced &#8211; &amp; in all probability I shall have to communicate it to him as he will very likely
                    be here before the tidings can reach him. &#8211; What renders any near loss of this kind so peculiarly distressing is that the
                    recollection is perpetually freshened when any like <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;<del>xx</del> event&gt; occurs &#8211; by the mere mention
                    of shipwreck, or the sound of the wind. Of all deaths it is the most dreadful from the circumstances of terror which accompany
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have to write the history of two shipwrecks &#8211; that of Sepulveda &amp; his wife &#8211; which is mentioned by
                        Camoens,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Manuel de Sousa Sep&#250;lveda (1500?&#8211;1552) was shipwrecked on the South
                        African coast in 1552. He, his wife, Dona Lianor de Sa (dates unknown), and their young children died. Lu&#237;s Vaz de Cam&#245;es
                        (1524&#8211;1580) lamented the death in <title>Lusiads</title> (1572), Canto 10, verses 46&#8211;47.</note> &amp; that of D. Paulo de
                    Lima, one of the last Portuguese who distinguished himself honourably in India.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dom Paulo
                        de Lima Pereira (1538&#8211;1589) was wrecked in the S&#257;o Thom&#233; in 1589. The events are narrated by Diogo do Couto (1542&#8211;1616) in
                            <title>Vida de D. Paulo de Lima Pereira, Capitam mor de Armadas do Estado da India, Onde por seu Valor, e Esfor&#231;o Nas
                            Batalhas de Mar, e Terra, de que Sempre Conseguio Gloriosas Vitorias, foy Chamado o Hercules Portuguez</title> (1765),
                        collected in the compendium of shipwreck narratives by Bernardo Gomes de Brito (1688&#8211;1759), <title>Historia
                            Tragico-Maritima</title>, 3 vols (Lisbon, 1735&#8211;1736), II, pp. 153&#8211;213.</note> Both these, but especially the first, were
                    so dreadfully distressful &#8211; that I look on the task of dwelling upon all the circumstances &amp; calling them up before my own
                    sight &amp; fixing them in my own memory as I needs must do, with very great reluctance. Fifteen years ago the more melancholy a
                    tale was the better it pleased me &#8211; just as we all like tragedy better than comedy when we are young. But now I as unwillingly
                    encounter that sort of mental pain as I would any bodily suffering.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Once more I am historifying &#8211; <hi rend="ital">totis viribus</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning
                        &#8216;with all one&#8217;s might&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; that with much such a feeling as we used to have when the bible exercise was done &#8211;
                    &amp; there was a clear week before us without any other such nuisance. Whether the expedition to Portugal takes place or not I
                    neither know, nor think about, nor that I have done all which befitted me to do. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has spoken to General Moores brother,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>),
                            Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790. After the
                            controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He
                            was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna. In December 1804 he was sent to review the practicability of defending
                            Portugal from a French invasion. His favourable report was widely leaked to the press, e.g. <title>Aberdeen Journal</title>, 9 January 1805. Moore was part of a large and well-known family that included his younger brothers, Dr James Moore (1763&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>) and the Royal Navy officer Graham Moore (1764&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; my name has been mentioned &#8211; or is on the road to the General &#8211; by two other roads. The
                    army will most likely be wasted if it goes there: &amp; for my own private convenience I should rather <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> were driven to England than that Mahomet should go to the mountain, &#8211; for
                    by the help of Lord Butes<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute (1744&#8211;1814;
                        <title>DNB</title>), son of the 3rd Earl of Bute (1713&#8211;1792, Prime Minister 1762&#8211;1763; <title>DNB</title>) a literary patron,
                        whose library the Marquess inherited.</note> Library, &amp; the Museum<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British
                        Museum.</note> I could do quite well enough to satisfy every body except myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will get Madoc early in March. It was finished the beginning of this week &#8211; the plates are quite ready, &#8211; &amp;
                    as the publishers are always interested in making speed there will be no delay in that quarter. They tell me the title page is
                    very beautiful &#8211; I have not seen it. Tomkins<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Tomkins (1743&#8211;1816;
                        <title>DNB</title>): writing-master and calligrapher, who took commissions for decorative book titles of luxury
                        publications.</note> who wrote the Gothic letters for me by <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> desire, is an
                    amateur in the art as well as an antiquarian &amp; they are perfect in their kind. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was directed to send you the Metrical Tales &#8211; which have the merit of a good motto.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805) was published with the Latin motto &#8216;nos haec novimus esse nihil&#8217; meaning
                        &#8216;we know these things are nothing&#8217;. It comes from Martial&#8217;s (Marcus Valerius Martialis AD 38/41&#8211;102/104)
                            <title>Epigrams</title> (AD 86&#8211;103), XIII. 2.</note> &#8211; I have a ballad hatching for you &#8211; which if it be ready by next
                    Xmas will be in time &#8211; for thus saith the first stanza which is all that is written &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> A Xmas tale this Xmas time</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Dear friend you ask of me &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> I will begin, dear Williams Wynn</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> A Xmas tale for thee.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem was not published.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">The subject is one of the quaintest that ever man devised, &amp; was begotten one morning by a dream. I will say no
                    more of it than that it is designed to illustrate three things, first the Platonic doctrine of Ideas, secondly the omnipotence of
                    Law, in Hookers sense of the word,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Hooker (1554&#8211;1600; <title>DNB</title>), wrote
                            <title>Of the Lawes of Ecclesiastical Politie</title> (1593&#8211;1662), in which he argued that &#8216;The laws which have been
                        hitherto mentioned, i.e. the laws of nature, do bind men absolutely, even as they are men, although they have never any
                        settled fellowship, never any solemn agreement amongst themselves what to do, or not to do: but forasmuch as we are not by
                        ourselves sufficient to furnish ourselves with competent store of things, needful for such a life as our nature doth desire, a
                        life fit for the dignity of man; therefore to supply those defects and imperfections which are in us, as living single and
                        solely by ourselves, we are naturally induced to seek communion and fellowship with others: this was the cause of men&#8217;s
                        uniting themselves at first in politic societies. But I moreover affirm, that all men are naturally in that state, and remain
                        so, till by their own consents they make themselves members of some politic society&#8217; (Book I, section 10).</note> &amp; lastly
                    the sin of cheating at cards. But I have been so amused with the conception that in all likelihood the execution will disappoint
                    me, &#8211; &amp; so it stands still till the humour comes on.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>