<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1532</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2654</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 490&#8211;492.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1532" type="letter">
        <head>1532. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1808-11-11">11 November 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single.<lb />Endorsement: 11 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1808<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: E/ NOV 14/ 1808<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 490&#8211;492.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I replied to you in haste, &amp; upon chewing the cud of the business, perceive that all which should have been
                    said has not been said, &amp; that what was said has not been exactly what it should.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey had been invited to contribute to the newly established <title>Quarterly Review</title>. For his first reply, see
                        Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 9 November 1808, Letter 1530.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A more valid objection to my writing about Spain than the probable want of length in the article is to be found in
                    the way in which I contemplate this war with Bonaparte. Peace while he lives &amp; reigns would be suicide, &#8211; &amp; the struggle
                    between us is on our side, a business of national life &amp; death. Yet however the men in power may feel the first of these
                    propositions, they would probably fear to sanction it, &amp; still less would they suffer me to speak of the Convention &amp; Sir
                        Hew,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August, whereby the French army
                        commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the 1st
                        Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons,
                        from Portugal. Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by two veteran generals, just
                        arrived in Iberia, who were content to make peace: Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Hew Dalrymple
                            (1750&#8211;1830;<title> DNB</title>). Public outcry led to an inquiry, after which Burrard and Dalrymple never again took
                        command.</note> on whom it would be impossible not to imprecate one deep &amp; deadly curse.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I wrote upon the Hindoo question, the various pamphletts &amp; books upon the subject should be sent me, &amp;
                    form the heading or text of the chapter.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts of
                            the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not infer that I am unwilling to write about Spain, or that I refuse to do it. I have only stated my own feeling
                    of unfitness. On the other hand no man better understands the Spanish character. something I know of the country, much of their
                    history, every thing of their literature. &#8211; &amp; the heart of man is not capable of a stronger interest than what mine feels in
                    their present cause. If it be thought proper that I should write I will do my best &amp; <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> may expunge what is too strongly marked with the stamp of Robert Southey, &#8211; <del>xxx</del> or knead such parts
                    as he thinks with any body elses article, &#8211; or reject the whole. On such occasions I have no mutinous feelings about me state this
                    to him, &#8211; tell me his determination with the least possible delay &#8211; &amp; let me know the names of some of your Respectables &#8211;
                    that I may see into what company I am likely to get.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A good thing would be an article upon Spanish literature if a text could be found. There is a collection of their
                    poets not yet compleated, but I am afraid at a stand &amp; of too old a date: otherwise it would supply three or four striking
                    articles, with translated specimens. With the fine literatures of France &amp; Italy I am well acquainted, &#8211; our own I have no
                    desire to meddle with. not being disposed to knock calves on the head.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Uncle, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hill</ref>, is just married. This is to
                    me a circumstance of great joy, for the only thing that lay with any weight upon my mind, was the thought of his solitary
                    situation at a time of life when solitariness is not desirable. My Uncles age I believe is <del>xxx</del> 57. This is somewhat
                    late for marriage, but having been plucked up by the roots from that country &amp; society wherein all his habits had grown, he
                    had new ones necessarily to acquire, &amp; the main objection to so late a change of life is therefore not applicable. You are to
                    understand that neither immediately nor remotely does this match in any way affect my fortunes. <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">My new relation</ref> is the daughter of Lovelace Bigg Wither a Hampshire
                    gentleman of the very ancient family of good old George Wither the Poet<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Wither
                        (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, a favourite of Southey&#8217;s.</note> whom I love so well.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lovelace Bigg (1741&#8211;1813) inherited the estate of Manydown, Hampshire, in 1789. He then took the name
                        Bigg-Withers and brought up his children there.</note> At my age this seems to me more like the marriage of a brother than an
                    Uncle. I was surprized with the news of this <del>xxx</del> family connection on the evening which brought your letter, &amp;
                    possibly my reply might have been fuller &amp; better if my thought had not sometimes been wandering in consequence of
                    intelligence so unexpected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scotts</ref> first scruples of conscience against the Edinburgh Review were probably
                    brought out by my refusing to bear a part in it, for its base politics, among other reasons. <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s letter to Scott, see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 December 1807, Letter 1392.</note> He
                    admitted the objection to be valid &amp; confessed that he felt it himself more &amp; more strongly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Curse the land tax. &#8211; This pension might as easily have been made nominal three hundred as two, &#8211; one consolation
                    however is that whenever it is taken from me for speaking like an Englishman (as likely enough it one day may be) I have the less
                    to lose. At present I am swimming with the stream, but it is the stream that has turned, not I.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-11">Nov. 11. 1808. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>