<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1012</idno><idno type="nines">rce2134</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4849 .  Previously  published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 62–69.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1012" type="letter"><head>1012. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1805-01-06">6 January
                        1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 7 Mar<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4849<lb/> Previously published: John Warden Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 62–69.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1805-01-06">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 6. 1805.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> What you tell me of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> surprizes me &amp; somewhat provokes
                    me. he has said nothing to me about his intentions, knowing that whenever he talks of Cambridge I always spoke of it in reply as a
                    thing altogether out of the question. I shall write &amp; ask him what he has done <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 8 January 1805, Letter 1013.</note> &amp; simply point out the impossibility of his going on
                    if he has begun. he knows that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">his Uncle</ref> cannot supply him, &amp; if that
                    expression fails to convince him it must be changed to will not. I have no tolerance for that vile vanity which would sacrifice
                    every thing.</p><p rend="indent1"> We shall miss the Iris, tho we have long missed you in it, &amp; had if my guess be right the M. Chronicles
                    paragraphs in your stead.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly
                            Advertiser</title> was the Norwich newspaper edited, from 1803 by Taylor, which he was now giving up. With Taylor’s
                        withdrawal approaching, the columns were filled by reports borrowed from the London paper the <title>Morning
                        Chronicle</title>, such borrowing being a common practice in provincial papers.</note> – I also am a loser by Hamilton – some
                    thing from 10 to 30 £, which for two years I have looked for in vain.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Hamilton
                        (dates unknown), owner of the <title>Critical Review</title> 1799–1804. Hamilton’s departure from the <title>Critical</title>
                        left Southey unpaid for reviews he had written.</note> my friend <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> is a
                    heavier loser by Robinsons. the whole profits upon two editions of his account of the French at Rome.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The booksellers George Robinson (d. 1811; <title>DNB</title>) and John Robinson (1753–1813;
                        <title>DNB</title>), Paternoster Row, London, went bankrupt on 8 December 1804 after a fire in a printing house in which they
                        had invested. Duppa was owed royalties by Robinsons for the sale of his <title>A Brief Account of the Subversion of the Papal
                            Government in 1798</title> (2 edns, 1799). The firm was relaunched and repaid creditors in full.</note> I thought it
                    possible that the Review would be sold with all its debts but since <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Philips</ref> has
                    bought it there is no hope for creditors who are no longer contributors.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The
                            Critical Review</title> was in fact bought by Joseph Mawman (1763–1827).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The delay of Madoc is not mine.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s poem <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805).</note> It rests chiefly with the carriers between this place &amp; Edinburgh, who keep my parcels <del>xxxx</del>
                    weeks upon the road <del>than</del> instead of days. my work has long been over. – there are about six sheets of notes to print, a
                    fortnights work – another fortnight to carry the sheets to London – allow as much more for the obstetrical work of folding
                    stitching &amp;c – so that I fear you will not receive your copy till February be far advanced.</p><p rend="indent1"> You <hi rend="ital">are</hi> strong upon European politics – &amp; with all my heart &amp; soul do I wish that you
                    would put forth your strength in some efficient way. Such a pamphlet as you could with a weeks work <del>produce</del> &lt;bring
                    forth&gt; would produce more immediate effect than all those articles in the Review, which will <del>produce</del> &lt;do&gt;
                    little till some thirty or forty years after you &amp; I are both gone to visit Moses &amp; the Prophets &amp; the Druids &amp;
                    our friends of the days before us. then some political Peter Bayley<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Peter Bayley (bap.
                        1778–1823; <title>DNB</title>), imitator of <title>Lyrical Ballads</title>, regarded by Southey as a plagiarist. Southey
                        damned Bayley’s <title>Poems</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 546–552.</note> will pick
                    out all <del>our</del> the golden threads with which you have embroidered such worthless canvass – to lace his own waistcoat. You
                    will be a <del>xxxxx</del> mine to any literary poacher who has just sense enough to feel what is good &amp; put it together. –
                    You see what notice this Berlin politician has excited.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Correspondence in a Series
                            of Letters between a Gentleman in Berlin and a Person of Distinction in London, from August 1803, to June 1804</title>
                        (1804), reviewed in <title>Anti-Jacobin Review</title>, 19 (December 1804 ), 376–86.</note> are you not sure &amp; certain
                    that both in knowledge &amp; in imagination he is very much your inferior? – The Anti Jacobine<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine, or, Monthly Political and Literary Censor</title>.</note>
                    crepitations never reach me. I see no review but the Monthly,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Monthly
                            Review</title>.</note> which is not worth seeing. no newspaper but the Whitehaven,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware’s Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note> – no new books but the <hi rend="ital">Annuals</hi>,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Books Southey was reviewing for the <title>Annual
                        Review</title>.</note> a good name for such deciduous productions – no society but an old East Indian General<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Peche (dates unknown), who had served in the East India Company’s army, gazetted as Colonel
                        in 1796 and Major-General in 1798.</note> with whom I once in a month or so play a rubber at whist. Am I the better or worse
                    for growing alone like a single oak? – <hi rend="ital">growing</hi> be sure I <hi rend="ital">am</hi>, striking my roots deeper
                    &amp; spreading out under branches.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have had some unpleasant intelligence of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. he has been
                    brought to a Court Martial for neglect of duty, disobedience of orders, &amp; contempt of his Captain.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain (later Admiral) Henry Heathcote (1777–1851), in command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>
                        1803–1805.</note> the two first charges were not proved – the last was &amp; he has been by sentence dismissed the ship. the
                    fact proved was that when the Captain accused him of the faults, which could not be proved on trial, he replied I beg your pardon
                    Sir, I must contradict you. – So much for martial justice! – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is waiting at
                    Barbadoes in expectation of another appointment which it is probable Commodore Hood<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>), in command of the fleet in which
                        Thomas Southey served.</note> will give him, as he told him to wait, if he thought proper, till the minutes of the Court
                    Martial had been sent him, he having only seen the sentence as yet. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> breakfasted
                    with him the day on which he wrote which looks well. &amp; it is [not] unlikely the Commodore may be disposed to befriend
                    &lt;him&gt; remembering that if his brother<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Alexander Hood (1758–1798), who died
                        of a wound to the thigh on 2 April 1798, sustained when his ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> engaged the French ship <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi> off the coast of Brittany. Nearly 400 men, and both captains, died in the fight; Tom Southey, on
                        board the Mars, was wounded.</note> had not fallen he would not have wanted a friend. – I am vexed of course, but as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has been sinned against rather than sinning it is that sort of vexation which is
                    most bearable. &amp; I<del>t</del> should not forget to state that this affair prevented him from going to cut out the Lilly, for
                    he was under arrest, &amp; the Lieutenant who went in his place was killed, – a fearful escape!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas Southey’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> made an unsuccessful
                        attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or wounded. Southey
                        had suspected that his brother was among the dead, having read in the newspapers that the first lieutenant had been killed.
                        Thomas had been placed under arrest and Lieutenant Charles Hayman (d. 1804), his replacement on the raid, died.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If Madoc sell well I shall move – &amp; to help on the operation mean to set about raising extraordinary supplies
                    as soon as the Annual work<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, reviewing books for the <title>Annual
                        Review</title>.</note> is over. the want of libraries here is very prejudicial to all my pursuits.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>