<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.903</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2025</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="903" type="letter">
        <head>903. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1804-03-01">[c. 1 March 1804]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address:
                        To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ Portland Square/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ MAR 1/ 1804<lb />Watermark: C HALE<lb />Endorsement:
                            <del>170 </del>
            <hi rend="ital"> 68<lb />
            </hi>MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb />Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was glad at seeing your hand writing this evening &#8211; &amp; in truth you would have seen mine before &#8211; if I had had heart to write to you &#8211; that could not be done
                    without adverting to our removal from Bristol, a subject which still brings with it too much pain to be ever voluntarily admitted into my mind. You will, I am sure, rejoice to hear
                        <del>x</del> that it is probable I shall soon again become a father, but indeed the recollection of what has past makes it to me a thing more of anxiety than of hope.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You seem in M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Newtons business<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Newton (1749&#8211;1804), sister of Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770;
                            <title>DNB</title>), was the principal beneficiary of the sales of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>, which Southey and Cottle edited to relieve Chatterton&#8217;s
                        family from financial distress. In 1803 Southey reckoned that the publication would clear over &#163;400 for her.</note> to have done every thing that could be done. in a woman of
                    her line of life, &amp; still more one who had been cheated, suspicion was to be expected, &amp; both you &amp; I did foresee it &amp; wisely provide against it. But if any farther
                    symptoms should appear, it will then be proper to wash our hands clean &amp; let her negociate immediately with the publishers. It will be well to publish the statement in the
                    Monthly Magazine, &amp; perhaps in the Gentlemans also when the booksellers whom you mention have settled their accounts. She has good reason to be thankful &#8211; for we have done
                    better for her in publishing than ever we did <del>by</del> for ourselves. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have long looked among the advertisements for Alfred<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of Cottle&#8217;s<title> Alfred; an Epic Poem, in
                            Twenty-four Books</title> was published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">Rees</ref> in 1804.</note> without
                    success, thank you! <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> had a parcel to send me this week, &amp; it is probable therefore that the Kings of the West Saxons &#8211; or
                    rather of England &#8211; may be at this moment travelling in the Flying Waggon. I hope in the course of the next winter to pay you in kind &#8211; for Madoc is about to be printed.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797&#8211;1799 and was revising for publication. It was published in 1805.</note> my
                    bargain is the same as yours, &#8211; to share the eventual profits. they however are to expend more upon the work, for it is to have vignettes &amp; tail-pieces, some in copper, some in
                    wood according as the subjects suit. I made this stipulation. not from any ambition of what is merely ornamental, nor solely from the wiser motive of setting eye-traps in the
                    booksellers windows, but because I wish to have the costume, the antiquities, &amp; the natural history of the poem elucidated. Thus there will first come Madocs vessel &#8211; such as
                    ships of burthen were at that period. Queen Emma in her Saxon dress.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emma of Anjou (b. c. 1138) was the illegitimate half-sister of Henry
                        II, (1133&#8211;1189; King of England 1154&#8211;1189; <title>DNB</title>) who married Dafydd (in English, David), King of Gwynedd, son of Owain Gwynedd (1100&#8211;1170, Prince of Gwynedd
                        1137&#8211;1170; <title>DNB</title>). She is described in <title>Madoc</title>, Part 1, Book 2.</note> The armour of that day &#8211; the Welsh dress, the various Indian dresses &amp;c &#8722;
                    &amp;c &#8722; &amp;c. all this if designed with taste will be very beautiful as well as very useful.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the event <title>Madoc</title> was
                        published with only two engravings. For further details of Southey&#8217;s plan for illustrations; see Southey to Mary Barker, 17 February 1804, Letter 896.</note> I divide the poem
                    into parts &#8211; of which the first ending with his return to America, &amp; comprising the old six books, is finished. The subdivisions are now eighteen in number, called by no
                    &lt;common&gt; name, but each having its title from its subject &#8211; as thus &#8211; 1. The Return. 2. The Banquet. 3. Cadwallon. 4 The Voyage &amp;c &#8722; &amp; the length perfectly at
                    pleasure. some exceeding 300 lines, some short of 100. the whole 18 containing about 3700. from 8 to 9000 will be the content of the whole. These minutenesses would interest you as
                    mere literary gossip if I were not assured that you will take a nearer interest in a poem which is among your old recollections &amp; belongs to an old friend. You will find great
                    additions &#8211; of the alterations you will hardly be sensible, as they are of that nature which occur almost in every line, affecting the sentences not the story, the story remaining
                    nearly the same, except that much is ingrafted into it. It has cost me much labour, &amp; will yet cost much. What is added in the second part will relate chiefly to the
                    extirpation of idolatry &#8722; &amp; in fact the philosophy of the poem will be showing how to civilize &amp; convert by force &#8722; for the last tail piece &#8722; or else for the title-page
                    there shall be this emblem, the Cross planted upon a rock, a Palm Tree beside it, &amp; a spring of living waters gushing forth.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        engraving of the palm tree and cross appears above the exordial lines of <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you may suppose it is some pleasure &amp; some pride to look forward to the termination of this labour. In 1789 I conceived the design of writing upon Madoc &amp;
                    in the course of that &amp; the two ensuing years more than once began &#8211; In the winter of 1794 the first book &amp; half were written in the state which you may remember. In the
                    spring of 1797 <del>rewritt</del> corrected &amp; carried on to the [MS torn] of the fourth book, in 1798 resumed &amp; finished in 1799. It then remained till October 1801 when
                    the rewriting was commenced at Dublin &#8722; &amp; this is the history. Yet so much of my thought &amp; so many of my solitary feelings have been fixed upon this object, that the
                    getting rid of it at once &#8211; the turning it adrift, &amp; making my main private delight public property &#8211; seems the most serious thing I have ever done in my life. Not from any
                    anxiety for its fate &#8211; for I know the acorn will come up, tho I shall never see its growth, nor sit under the shade of my own Oak: but having considered it as my own great work,
                    the publication will bring with it a feeling that my great work is done &#8211; &amp; that I may go to rest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> However there is the History<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> to succeed, &amp; in that I make a daily
                    progress. the reviewing has impeded every thing. but that is over for the year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You tell me nothing of your own pursuits &#8211; do not however forget that I shall always take an interest in hearing of them. Of your sister <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Sarahs</ref>  marriage I am glad, looking at it with a calm &amp; uninfluenced mind &#8211; were she my own sister I should like you
                    have some regret mingled. God bless her in her change! you will remember me &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>  to her, &amp; to your sister
                        <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Mary</ref>  &#8722; &amp; <del>Mary</del>
          <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Anne</ref>  &amp; your good Mother. We did not see them before our departure for obvious reasons &#8211; in fact we were both nearly
                    heart-broken &#8722; &amp; both feel the blow still. howbeit sorrow is like unripe fruit &#8211; sour &amp; bitter only because unripe, &amp; afflictions always mature into blessings. &#8211; I am
                    in good health &#8211; indeed never better, only that my eyes are still at times a vexation. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is to send down for my perusal a Life
                    of Chatterton by John Davis,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Davis (1774&#8211;1854), <title>The Life of Thomas Chatterton</title> was published in London in 1806 by
                        Thomas Tegg (1776&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), rather than <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> a man who printed Travels in America<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Davis&#8217;s <title>Travels of Four Years and a Half in the United States of America; during 1798, 1799, 1800, 1801 and
                            1802</title> (1803), in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 54&#8211;59.</note> at Bristol last year &#8211; a book which if you have not seen, is, with great defects,
                    well worth seeing, for he <del>is a</del> has genius. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>