<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1472</idno><idno type="nines">rce2594</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1472" type="letter"><head>1472. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-06-23">23–24 June
                        1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ Post-Office/ Plymouth Dock/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK / 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1808-06-23">Thursday 23. June 1808.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As I expected Mondays carrier brought the stockings, – &amp; with them the works of Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                    Jones with his life by Ld Teignmouth,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Listed in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library
                        thus: Sir William Jones (1746–1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Works, with his Life by Lord Teignmouth, portrait, 13 vol.
                            Presentation Copy, calf extra, marbled leaves, from J. Neville White, with an extract from Landor in the autograph of the
                            Poet Laureate</title> (1799–1806). For Southey’s letter thanking Neville White for this gift, see Southey to Neville
                        White, 20 June 1808, Letter 1470.</note> – thirteen volumes in all better bound than any others in my whole library. I wanted
                    you here to have been present when the first paper (for they were seperately papered) was opened; – to have joined in the chorus
                    of admiration, – to have presided at a <del>xx</del> cabinet council held to determine where they should be placed, – &amp; then
                    to have picked out the <del>xxxx</del> ricolings from the rico shelf, which were to be degraded for the purpose of making room.
                    They are, in brown calf, almost the colour of Russia, – or rather as dark as Russia, the lettering on the leather, – bands on the
                    back, &amp; a very rich tool. The leaves marbled to the pattern of the inside paper. A less costly binding than that of <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady Hollands</ref> present,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Father
                        Stanislaus Canovai (1740–1811), <title>Elogio d’Amerigo Vespucci che ha riportato il premio della nobile Accademia Etrusca di
                            Cortona nel dì 15. Ottobre dell’anno 1788. Con una dissertazione giustificativa di questo celebre navigator</title>
                        (1788).</note> but more showy, &amp; equally well executed.</p><p rend="indent1"> A proof arrived on Sunday – the day you left us, – &amp; at the same time a letter from <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> inclosing a Bill ‘for the encouragement of literature’ – which proposes to
                    extend our term of copyright.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Bill for the further encouragement of Learning in the
                            United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, by securing to the Libraries of the Universities, and other public libraries,
                            copies of all newly-printed books, and books reprinted with additions, and by further securing the copies and copyright of
                            printed Books to the authors of such books, or their assigns, for a time to be limited</title>. For Southey’s reply to
                        Wynn, see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 19 June 1808, Letter 1469.</note> The Bill is a bad one, &amp; would only
                    benefit the booksellers. he will therefore oppose it altogether, on the ground that it is too late in the session to consider it
                    sufficiently, – &amp; by &amp; by a better one will be brought in. I have pressed upon him the justice of making literary property
                    as inheritable as any thing else, – &amp; of securing to my children as exclusive a right to the works of my head, as they would
                    have to the works of my hands. <del>xx xx xx</del> Sooner or later this justice will be done to men of letters, &amp; then my
                    childrens children will be well provided for. – A second proof is come this evening.</p><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> &amp; his family arrived, on their way
                    to Maryport: – how unlucky that that Admiral Ty should have turned you away. He reminded me of our engagement to travel over the
                    mountains, &amp; said he should return here in a few days to meet some friends, – so that I shall be likely to see much of him
                    this summer.</p><p rend="indent1"> Friday –</p><p rend="indent1"> I was interrupted last evening by the arrival of the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonels</ref> party
                    of Lakers, whom <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachey</ref> had previously announced. The
                        Calverts<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Calvert (1771–1829; <title>DNB</title>), who was at school with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> at Hawkshead, where he later became the schoolmaster. On the death
                        of his father, Calvert became a man of independent means, inheriting, with other property, the estate of Bowness on the east
                        shore of Bassenthwaite, near Keswick, where he lived with his family.</note> who knew them well brought them here, &amp; we
                    asked them to dine tomorrow, – which they accepted, – &amp; then wrote a note to excuse themselves, having given up their plan of
                    ascending <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, for the sake of exploring Borrowdale. They come to tea instead, – so we
                    have shown our civility &amp; saved some trouble – for they were a large party – four themselves – &amp; the Calverts. And the new
                    plates &amp; knives &amp; forks must wait for another opportunity before they make their first appearance.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your little <del>xx</del> copy of Kehama<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A manuscript of <title>The Curse
                            of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> is in hand. <del>xx xx</del> four numbers were made as soon as I got home after leaving
                    you, &amp; I began the first – but my progress in this &amp; in every thing else is stopt by one of my violent colds, – which was
                    beginning when you went away, &amp; as bad as it well can be. It affects my eyes so much that I can scarcely read or write, for
                    any length of time, – &amp; am condemned to idleness. In consequence of this <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    began yesterday to make preparations for a batch of juniperizing,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Juniperize’ meant to add
                        a gold border and lettering to the bindings of Southey’s books. This is an allusion to Friar Juniper, disciple of St
                        Francis, who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to give to a poor woman begging alms.</note> – as I
                    could <del>xx</del> superintend that, tho I could nothing else. But it has so happened that she saw something at Miss
                        Crosthwaites<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Crosthwaite (b. 1771), the daughter of Peter Crosthwaite
                        (1735–1808), a <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> inventor, mapmaker and showman, who established a museum there
                        in 1780, at which his daughter assisted. She also kept a shop selling paper and material.</note> which was thought excellently
                    suitable for a sopha case, &amp; for cushions for my window seat, – a fancy has taken them to have the former ready for our Lakers
                    tomorrow, &amp; my poor books are laid by for this more conspicuous piece of new grandeur.</p><p rend="indent1"> And now having told you this I must hunt about for something more to tell you. – Oh – by great good fortune we have
                    got rid of our worthless Cook. she walks off on Tuesday, – we have a prospect of another, – but even if no other could be got, it
                    is agreed upon by all hands, mistresses &amp; maids that we are better without her <del>&amp; rather</del> than with her. </p><p rend="indent1"> At any time I should have mist you such, – but particularly at this time, – when from inability to do any thing I
                    want a companion to walk with, &amp; boat with, &amp; bathe with. I have past the greater part of the day, in my bedroom, to avoid
                    light. It is to be hoped that a few days will remove this – so my eyes be but spared, I <del>xx</del> shall resign my nose to the
                    pocket handkerchief with great composure, &amp; blow away upon my own trumpet as long as the cold lasts. But it is vexatious to
                    have the old affection of the eyes return in this manner, when I believed myself rid of it for ever –</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> has given me a kiss regularly every night to be sent to you in
                    a letter. they are all well – God bless you – my next I hope will tell you better news of Kehama<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Thomas Southey, 11 July 1808, Letter 1478.</note> –</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>