<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1144</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2266</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Houghton Library, Harvard University, Ms Hyde 10
                        (652).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1144" type="letter">
        <head>1144. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Thomas Norton Longman</ref>], <date when="1806-01-10">[10
                    January 1806]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Houghton Library, Harvard University, Ms Hyde 10
                        (652)<lb />Unpublished<lb />Dating note: listed in the Houghton information as &#8216;Autograph letter draft, signed, [no place] to
                        [Thomas Norton Longman] [1806?] 1s. Describing his plan for a literary magazine. A later note by Southey, signed and dated
                        1807 Sept., notes that this plan was used by Longman as a blueprint for the magazine <title>The Athenaeum</title>, launched in
                        1807 Jan&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s note reads: &#8216;This plan was sent to Longman in a more detailed form &#8211; &amp; out of it <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> produced the Athen&#1237;um: &#8211; a plan which originated
                        avowedly from the dullness with which <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> A.</ref> had palsied the M
                        Magazine, ended in making a new one to be paralysed by &lt;the&gt; same torpedo touch! RS. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1807.&#8217; See
                        also Southey to Charles Danvers, 13 May 1806, Letter 1179.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have long thought that a Literary Magazine would be a good speculation,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The short-lived magazine was named <title>The Athenaeum, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>
                        (1807&#8211;1809). It was edited by <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> and published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> &amp; last night, after the receipt of your letter, being
                    prevented from sleeping the whole night by this &lt;a&gt; dreadful tempest, &#8211; I made some use of watchfulness by reducing what I
                    had before only thought of cursorily into some shape.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It should be exclusively Literary, &#8211; that is without any rigmarole controversies between Mr Wood &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Good, or <del>Doo</del> Noodle &amp; Doodle, without any metaphysical disputes. foolish questions &amp;
                        <del>que</del> foolish answers, general obituary, or magazine poetry. Materials enough are furnished by Literature, &#8211;
                    Biographies of eminent men, <del>xx</del> criticisms &amp; analyses of good or curious books in all languages, &#8211; illustrations of
                    good books topographical, historical or <del>xxx</del> glossarial, &#8211; &amp;c. In particular there should be from time to time
                    accounts of &amp; extracts from the MSS. in the Museum.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Good workmen in literature are not to be had so certainly for money as artificers of any other kind, yet the best
                    price gets the best, &amp; old Magazines become worthys by filling their pages with correspondence. You might I think engage some
                    Saxon scholar to work in his department at the Museum, <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">Owen</ref>  &amp;
                    Edward Williams,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Williams (Iolo Morganwg) (1747&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>),
                        scholar and forger of Welsh literature, reviver of bardism.</note> between them would supply you with the lives of the Welsh
                    bards &amp; translations, &amp;c &#8211; some Runic scholar might be found to give an account of the Sagas, &amp; thus every different
                    department of curious <del>xxx</del> literature might be explored. In every number there should be a portion of curious anecdotes,
                    really so &#8211; not such as <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Phillips</ref>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillips was a commercial publisher, who included a section of this kind in his <title>The Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> Man of Letters
                    produces from his Portfolio, which have been told regularly <del>xxxx</del> in all the Magazines <del>for</del> ever since
                    Magazines were invented. You probably know that <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">Sewards</ref> anecdotes<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Seward (1747&#8211;1799; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Anecdotes of Some Distinguished
                            Persons, Chiefly of the Present and Two Preceding Centuries</title> (1795).</note> were printed thus as scraps originally
                    in the European. An account of new plays would be proper, &amp; such gleanings only from the London &amp; provincial newspapers as
                    a man who cuts out curious things would select to paste in in his blue paper volume.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The European gives two Prints, sometimes very good ones. I conclude from this that they can be afforded. One should
                    always be a portrait from some scarce pictures or prints, or of some living man of eminence, if a foreigner the better. The other
                    should be <hi rend="ital">an illustration</hi>, as it is the fashion to call such things. for instance a view of the ruins of
                    Spensers dwelling in Ireland,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552?&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>) lived
                        from 1589&#8211;1598 at Kilcolman Castle, near Cork.</note> with other &lt;scenes&gt; in its neighbourhood &#8211; Penshurst where Sir
                    Philip Sydney<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586; <title>DNB</title>) was born at Penshurst
                        Place, Kent.</note> was born &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; Branksome &amp; Newark &amp;c for <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                        Scotts</ref> Lay.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (1805). Branksome
                        Hall therein is based on Branxholme Castle, near Hawick, Scotland, ancestral seat of the Scott clan. Newark is thirty miles to
                        the north east of Nottingham.</note> Or occasionally a facsimile of some illumination from MS manuscripts. Many persons will
                    purchase the book for the sake of the print. You might price it <del>xxxxxxxxxxxx</del>, &amp; have your printing handsomely open
                    like the Censura.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Samuel Egerton Brydges, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1837;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Censura Literaria. Containing Titles, Abstracts, and Opinions of Old English Books, with
                            Original Disquisitions, Articles of Biography, and Other Literary Antiquities</title> (1805&#8211;1809).</note> Six sheets would
                    make two yearly volumes, &#8211; &amp; the Editor should start with <del>six</del> materials for half a year in hand.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>