<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1154</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2276</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 105&#8211;107.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1154" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1154" type="letter">
        <head>1154. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1806-02-10">10 February 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ FEB13/ 1806; 10o&#8217;Clock/ FE.13/ 1806F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: shield/ 1803/ T
                        Botfield<lb />Endorsement : N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 116 1806/ Robert Southey/ No place 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb./ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        March<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 105&#8211;107.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1806-02-10">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 10 1806</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is so very long since I have heard from Lisbon that your letter has relieved me from some uneasy apprehensions.
                    it came opportunely also, as I was on the point of writing, having many things to say.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> First of the new changes as far as we are concerned in them. There is more reason to expect something from the
                        Duke<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey hoped to make interest via John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839;
                            <title>DNB</title>) whose brother William Russell (1767&#8211;1840) was appointed a Civil Lord of the Admiralty in the new
                        administration.</note> than you perhaps are aware of. About eighteen months ago he &lt;as he thought&gt; gave <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> a living &#8211; but the incumbent recovered. Do not mention this, which I now
                    tell you because you will be pleased to find that the Duke has given this pledge &amp; promise of his good will. I also have
                    reason to expect something. Whichever falls vacant first, the Secretaryship of Legation &lt;at Lisbon&gt;, or the Consulship, is
                    asked for me, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> seconds the application. This also is for your
                    own ear only. I may be disappointed, but this is quite certain that if <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> does not
                    get one of these situations for me, he will sooner or later, procure something else. No man can have a steadier friend than I have
                    had in him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has been given up by the young Lady in
                    obedience to her parents.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> While at the home of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> near Ambleside, Harry had met Emma Noel (d. 1873). She was the daughter of Gerard Noel Edwardes, of
                        Exton Park, Rutland (1759&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), who had adopted the surname Noel in 1798, and inherited a baronetcy in
                        1813 to become the 2nd Baronet Barham. When her family objected to the couple&#8217;s plans to marry, the relationship soon ended.
                        For more information; see Southey to John May, 1 November 1805, Letter 1116.</note> He has been very unwell, partly occasioned
                    by the stench of a dissecting room, &amp; over application. In April his examination takes place &amp; the next day the fees of
                    graduation are to be paid, tho the diploma is not given till summer. They are heavy &#8211; if I recollect rightly not less than fifty
                    pounds. But, I will procure a statement of the sum, &amp; learn the day on which he makes his trial. This will I trust be the last
                    occasion on which it will be necessary to apply to you on <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> account. When
                    he has his medical commission, he will be able to do something for himself, &#8211; in some way or other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I look daily for letters from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. This change of ministers will give
                    him some hopes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prime Minister, William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), had died on 23 January 1806 and was
                        replaced by <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Baron Grenville</ref>. Because his friend and patron <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref> was appointed Under Secretary of State in the Home
                        Office of the new ministry under his uncle, Grenville, Southey expected his family to benefit from the change of
                        office.</note> &#8211; for he begins to be out of heart &#8211; seeing men put over his head who were boys when he was Lieutenant. If we
                    live long enough we shall all three do well &amp; of that I have no fear, &#8211; but our path has been an up-hill one, &amp; without
                    the best friends, unexpectedly found, it would have been impossible to have emerged. I look back with wonder.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylors</ref> reviewal is to be in the Annual,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor was reviewing Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> (1805) in the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4
                        (1806), 604&#8211;613.</note> &#8211; at which said book I have been employed since my last, with no other interruption than what two
                    attacks of influenza occasioned: but these interruptions threw me behind hand. &amp; I have still a fortnights work to do.
                    Espriellas letters are not gone to press,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don
                            Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>, was published in 1807.</note> nor will they now till I go
                    to London, which will be late in March or early in April, <del>if</del> as far as one may calculate upon the future. Bernal Diaz
                    has been translated by a Mr Keating &amp; published when I was last abroad.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Maurice
                        Keating (d. 1835), army officer and writer, published a translation from the Spanish of Bernal D&#237;az del Castillo&#8217;s
                        (1492&#8211;1585), <title>The True History of the Conquest of Mexico</title>, in 1800.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When the Annual is published I shall remit you a draft for my last debt. The delay of the Specimens,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s jointly edited <title>Specimens of the Later English
                            Poets</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; wholly imputable to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, except
                    that I am to blame for relying upon him, &#8211; has been very vexatious to me &amp; <del>x</del> seriously inconvenient. Had they been
                    published when they ought &amp; as I expected, enough would by this time have been sold to have given me something at command &#8211;
                    instead of being behind-hand. Madoc cannot have sold well, or <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> would have
                    told me so; &#8211; it will sell in the long run, &amp; make its own fortune certainly, &amp; perhaps help to make mine, <hi rend="ital">patiens quia aeternus</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as &#8216;patient because he is
                        eternal&#8217;.</note> should be the motto of a man who writes for posterity, or who regulates his life <del>by</del> more with
                    regard to another world than to this. I am worth at present the half profits of Madoc &amp; the Metrical Tales both on sale, &#8211;
                    have fifty or sixty pounds (I forget which) to receive whenever the edition of Amadis is sold, &#8211; &amp; the reversionary copy right
                    of Thalaba.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> and <title>Metrical Tales and Other
                            Poems</title> were both published in 1805, his translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> in 1803 and <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> in 1801.</note> Espriellas Letters &amp; the Specimens both to be published if I live &amp; am not
                    disabled, in the spring, are more saleable books &amp; will be more productive. they will make my years income easy. I review no
                    more after this Annual; if it still be necessary by temporary expedients to raise ways &amp; means I can certainly write a play in
                    less time. or produce such a poem as Thalaba in little more, nor ought I so to employ myself, if it be possible to avoid it. But
                    better days are dawning, &amp; as you see I have good reason to hope ere long for a good situation which will lead to a permanent
                    establishment. Your <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughter</ref> is a delightful little playfellow, &#8211; of
                    intellects almost too quick. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be remembered to yourself &amp; <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> to whom I beg my remembrances. Of your late loss I have
                    only to say that when death comes in so gentle a form &amp; at so full an age &#8211; it brings with it its own consolation. What an
                    expression is that of <hi rend="ital">falling asleep</hi>! My own feelings have for some time been of an <del>even</del> afternoon
                    character, &#8211; when one looks forward to rest with satisfaction. I am as happy &lt;here&gt; as most people, but the next world is a
                    better one than this.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RSouthey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I have often thought of telling you that the portrait of Pratt prefixed to a despicable book called Harvest Home<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>),
                                <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary
                                Friends and Select Re-publications</title> (1805). Southey reviewed this work in the <title>Annual Review for
                                1805</title>, 4 (1806), 736&#8211;738.</note> is so like poor old Mr Grosett that it quite startled me. If young Walpole has
                        no likeness of his grandfather he may be glad to know this.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole
                            (1781&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), classical scholar, born in Lisbon, was the eldest son of Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810),
                            envoy to Portugal, and his first wife, Diana Grossett (d. 1784), daughter of Walter Grossett (dates unknown).</note>
            <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips</ref> is the publisher of the book, &amp; I shall apply to him for two or
                        three of the impressions.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>