<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1252</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2374</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1(25).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 401&#8211;403.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1252" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1252" type="letter">
        <head>1252. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1806-12-29">29 December 1806</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmarks: [partial, illegible] A.1/ N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; [partial, illegible] E/ 1807<lb />Endorsement: N. 12A.
                        1806/ Robert Southey/ Noplace 29th Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 1807/ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1(25)<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 401&#8211;403.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1806-12-29">Dec 29. 1806.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will, perhaps, wonder that I should not sooner have thanked you for the information in your last letter, and,
                    thro you, made my acknowledgment to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burn<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burns (dates unknown), a member of the English
                    Factory, Lisbon.</note> for his friendly offices.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked John May to help his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref> secure promotion, and William Burns had applied on his behalf to John Markham (1761&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), a
                    naval officer who was a member of the Board of Admiralty (1801&#8211;1804 and 1806&#8211;1807) and MP for Portsmouth (1801&#8211;1818 and
                    1820&#8211;1826); see Southey to Thomas Southey, 28&#8211;29 September 1806, Letter 1221.</note> The cause of delay has been this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref>, in two letters, one written the day after the other,
                    has urged me to lose no time in setting about and getting ready that part of my Magnum Opus<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s projected, but never
                    completed, &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> which relates to Brazil; &#8211; &amp; in consequence of the enquiries relative to that country which
                    were made at Lisbon by the mysterious embassy, instructed me to offer to Government such information as his papers, in my
                    possession, contained;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The prospective flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil
                        (occurred 29 November 1807) prompted Southey, at his uncle <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill&#8217;s</ref>
                        request, to begin a history of Brazil, using papers sent him by Hill and stored by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>; see Southey to John Rickman, 23 December 1806, Letter 1247.</note> &#8211; which he believes to be more than any
                    other person in Europe possesses, except the Abbe du Boys,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The identity of this French
                        cleric is unclear. It is likely that he was Abb&#233; Francois Garnier (1722&#8211;1804), the long-standing chaplain to the French
                        factory in Lisbon. A less likely possibility is Abb&#233; Jean-Antoine Dubois (1765&#8211;1848), was a French Catholic missionary in
                        India, whose long sojourn in the southern districts brought him into contact with the legacy of Portuguese Catholic
                        colonialism there. Dubois&#8217;s manuscript history of Indian religion was purchased by the East India Company and published in
                        English as <title>Description of the Character, Manners and Customs of the People of India, and of their Institutions,
                            Religious and Civil</title> (1816).</note> &#8211; much of whose information is derived from them. Accordingly, I wrote to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &#8211; who in return informs me of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
                        Grenville&#8217;s</ref>  reply &#8211; that my materials relate to the wrong side of S. America, for their present views,
                    but that he very much recommends me to postpone the rest of my history, &amp; set immediately to work upon this, in consequence of
                    the present bias or the public mind.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Charles Wynn to use his position
                        as Under Secretary of State in the Home Office, to ascertain whether the government might provide him support during the
                        preparation of a work likely to supply useful information in the new political situation; see Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, [15 December 1806], Letter 1243.</note> Government, he adds, has no wish to keep this sort of information
                    private, &amp; would rather encourage me in publishing it. &#8211; The papers in question came to me in sealed packets which I had never
                    opened, not knowing their contents; &#8211; they were in London, &#8211; &amp; if I had been called on to prepare an abstract from them, it
                    would perhaps have been advisable that I should travel up to them. Till this was determined I <del>xxx</del> delayed writing to
                    you. &#8211; I have now written for them, &amp; for all my books relating to this part of the history. A good many are here already,
                    &amp; if neither my health nor eyes fail me expect in no very long time to report good progress in this very interesting &amp;
                    important work. The whole copy of Espriella<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by
                            Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> will be finished &amp; sent off to the
                        Printer<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who
                        would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with his son William Francis (1817&#8211;1904;
                        <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> by the end of January, &amp; the whole of what reviewing I have. Then I shall instantly
                    begin. My mornings in February will compleat the rest of Palmerin,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published an
                        edition of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 4 volumes in 1807.</note> &amp; then I shall do nothing
                    else till this be compleated. The arrangement is mapped out in my own mind which is a great point done. I am in possession of
                    almost every printed book relating to the subject except such as may be in Dutch, &amp; have made arrangements for procuring
                        these.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to [Richard Duppa], fragment [December 1806], Letter
                        1248.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>  is with <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>, &amp; will I suppose, set off for London as soon as he hears from you. I shall
                    direct him where &amp; at what hour he may hope to see you in town, &#8211; his appearance and manners I trust will please you well.
                    Perhaps you will take him some day to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burns<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 1.</note>
                    &#8211; I never knew a young man who was so generally admired.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>  was here, working hard at Portugueze, when his appointment arrived.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had been appointed to the <title>Pallas</title>. Launched in 1804, she
                        was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first captain was Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860;
                            <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the capture of many French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command
                        passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown).</note> he set off instantly, &#8211; but there has been no time for me to hear that
                    he has joined. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your god-daughter</ref>  is as healthy &amp; as forward a child as
                    can be wished. the young <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>  sadly troubled with wind, but still very
                    thriving. &#8211; I was, as you may suppose, a good deal shocked at hearing of poor Isabel&#8217;s death.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> May&#8217;s infant daughter.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref>  would be greatly affected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>. I shall not now see
                    you so soon as I expected, &#8211; as it will hardly be advisable that I should stir from here till this work is fairly afloat. &#8211; Have
                    you seen the Memoirs of Colonel Hutchinson?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucy Hutchinson (<hi rend="ital">n&#233;e</hi>
                        Apsley; 1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>) and Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel
                            Hutchinson</title> (1806). Southey reviewed this work in the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807),
                        361&#8211;378.</note> Very, very rarely has any book so greatly delighted me. It is in unison with almost every feeling and every
                    principle I have at heart. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>