<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1207</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2329</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1207" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1207" type="letter">
        <head>1207. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1806-08-05">5
                        August 1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.
                        P./Whitehall/ London/ Private<lb />Postmark: FREE/ AUG 8/ 1806<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaven knows how long it is since I have seen your hand-writing. I will wish you speedily removed to some situation
                    where you may be paid better for doing less, if it be only that you <del>have</del> may &lt;have&gt; leisure for now &amp; then
                    writing an unofficial letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Barker I hope may have made way for his own release &#8211; he being the very man who jumped into the river &amp; saved
                    the boy &#8211; as you may have seen in the newspapers. The French have made so much of this in their way of telling it that they ought
                    to have set him free.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 8 May 1804, the brig, <hi rend="ital">Vincejo</hi>, under Captain
                        John Wesley Wright (1769&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), returning from a mission to transport French counter revolutionaries, ran
                        aground on the coast of Brittany. The crew, including Lieutenant Edward Barker (dates unknown), were taken prisoner by the
                        French. Wright died in prison (either by murder or suicide) in 1805; in 1806, according to the newspapers, &#8216;Mr. Barker, a
                        Lieutenant in the English Navy, and prisoner at Verdun, lodged in apartments overlooking the Meuse, where he had been for some
                        time ill of a tertian ague. While he was suffering under a violent fit a few days ago, he perceived a child of eight or ten
                        years old, who, carried by the current from the bathing place to the deep part of the river, was on the point of being
                        drowned. Mr. B. forgetting his own critical situation, rushed out, jumped into the river with his clothes on, and was lucky
                        enough to save the child, and restore him to his parents. After this affecting incident, the disorder of the stranger
                        increased, but the strength of his constitution and his youth enabled him to overcome it&#8217;. <title>The Bury and Norwich Post:
                            Or, Suffolk, Norfolk, Essex, and Cambridge Advertiser</title>, Wednesday, July 16, 1806. Barker was a relative
                        of <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, hence Southey&#8217;s efforts to mobilise assistance for him.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has been talking to me about poor Lord Proby.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Allen Proby, Lord Proby (1779&#8211;1804), eldest son of John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort
                        (1751&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), was the previous captain of Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> and died of
                        yellow fever in 1804. Wynn had previously asked Southey if his brother could recover any of Proby&#8217;s papers for his family and
                        friends. For the request, see Southey to Thomas Southey, 7 December 1805, Letter 1130.</note> It is very probable that if the
                    cold-water system had been in use on board the ship he might have been saved &#8211; this I hope his father will never know &#8211; but it
                    will show you the fitness of making any discovery of this kind as speedily known as possible.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> This contemporary treatment was publicised by Robert Jackson (bap. 1750&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), military
                        surgeon and medical writer, who published several works on cures for fever, including <title>An Exposition of the Practice of
                            Affusing Cold Water on the Surface of the Body, as a Remedy for the Cure of Fever</title> (1808).</note> Between one &amp;
                    two hundred men were carried off by the fever from the Amelia in that visitation. A Captain on the same station came on board
                    &amp; asked <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> if they had not used the cold water bath stating with what success he
                    had adopted it. Some time afterwards Tom had been dining on board another ship &amp; on his return was told that two men were
                    taken with the fever &#8211; &amp; the Doctors mate was on shore &#8211; (the Doctor had died before Lord P.) He filled <del>xx</del> a tub
                    &amp; dipt them both in &#8211; then by way of a sudorific gave a glass of very weak grog &#8211; which was about as bad a thing as he could
                    have given. However both men recovered; &#8211; &amp; the system was acted upon from that time, so that they lost only seven men. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> himself was desperately ill &#8211; &amp; they dipt him every half hour for twelve hours,
                    dosing at the same time with calomel.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The common name for mercury chloride, which was
                        taken for various ailments.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Lord P. was troubled about the Dan&#228;e<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Proby was captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Danae</hi> from 1798, until 1800, when a mutiny took place on board the ship and it was captured by the French
                        navy.</note> in his illness &#8211; he said he had behaved very ill there &amp; hoped God would forgive him. No man seems ever to
                    have more completely <del>changed him</del> perceived &amp; amended his own errors &#8211; he was almost become too mild a commander. To
                    his first lieutenant <del>whose</del> who had greatly misconducted himself, he behaved like a father &#8211; &amp; once when two of his
                    officers were taken prisoners &#8211; he sent them immediately a hundred pounds each. Every body on board his ship loved him &amp; God
                    knows this is not very often the case on board a ship.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am out of spirits at seeing <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> look so old: &#8211; <del>For</del>
                    &lt;In&gt; fourteen years he has been only nine months on shore. He &amp; I &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
          <del>xxx</del> have never been together till now in the whole of that time, &amp; till now he has never seen <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> but for one day these ten years.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>If you see <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> ask him <del>from</del> for the life of Dona Luisa
                            Carvajal<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza (1568&#8211;1614), was a Spanish missionary who devoted herself to the cause of the
                            Catholic faith in England during the reign of James VI and I (1566&#8211;1625, King of Scotland, England, and Ireland 1603&#8211;1625;
                                <title>DNB</title>). An account of her life was written by Luis Mun&#771;oz (d.1646) as <title>La Vida Y Virtues de la
                                Venerable Virgin Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title> in 1632, and was summarised by Southey in the third edition
                            of his <title>Letters from Spain and Portugal</title> (1808).</note> &#8211; &amp; send it me &#8211; I must fit it into a shape for
                        the Athen&#230;um.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Athenaeum, A Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous
                                Information</title> was edited by <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> and published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> between 1807&#8211;1809. Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;The Life of Dona Luisa de
                            Carvajal&#8217; was published in 1 (1807), 270&#8211;277, 391&#8211;399 and 495&#8211;500.</note>
          </p>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-08-05">Tuesday Aug. 5. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>