<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1628</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2750</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From
                        1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 312&#8211;316..  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 137&#8211;139 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1628" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1628" type="letter">
        <head>1628. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1809-05-13">13 May 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Penkridge/ Staffordshire.<lb />Postmark: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From
                        1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 312&#8211;316.<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 137&#8211;139 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be beginning Senhora to wonder that you hear no news from <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,
                    &amp; it is well that I have not bad news to communicate. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has had the
                    croup, &#8211; the particulars I shall not relate because I do not like to remember them. &#8211; thank God the disease was speedily subdued,
                    &amp; he is now recovering from the remedies. The marks of the blister are disappearing from the throat, &amp; his complection to
                    day has a healthier colour than it has had since he was waked out of his sleep to have six ounces of blood taken from the jugular
                    vein. We have as you may well suppose, gone thro much anxiety. I have but four of the fourteen, yet &amp; they bring with them a
                    good deal of uneasiness, &#8211; nevertheless I&#8217;se for the whole number. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Piggarel</ref> is not,
                    but you know her of old, &amp; I do not find that all her grumbling about them before they come makes her like them a jot the less
                    when they are here. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> thrives, &amp; Nurse says she is a beauty, which is more
                    than I can say. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> is grown a bonny wench, &#8211; &amp; as for your truly begotten <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughter</ref> she is taller than <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref>. I hope you will be pleased to hear that she takes after her father, &amp; professes a determination never to
                    learn to dance, &#8211; tho her cousin dances all morning at the dancing-masters &amp; all the evening at home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We go on increasing in grandeur, &#8211; &amp; the only thing I do not like in your Teddesleyfication<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley Hall</ref> was the home of <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward Lyttleton</ref> for whom Barker acted as a nurse and companion.</note>
                    is that it has prevented you from being a happy assistant in the great works of improvement, which are continually in hand. My
                    room is finished, &amp; the paper has not succeeded well &#8211; the seams have a bad appearance, &amp; in some places the wall has
                    changed its colour &#8211; by candle light these imperfections are not seen, &amp; many of them will be hidden at all times if your
                    Senhoraship will send me two drawings for the chimney-piece, &#8211; tho what I should like better would be a copy of a certain portrait
                    in crayons which I saw at <ref target="places.html#Congreve">Congreve</ref>, &amp; which I have coveted &amp; desired ever
                        since.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Since Congreve was the home of Mary Barker&#8217;s father, the portrait may have been
                        of her.</note> &#8211; I can hardly tell whether I wish you to come to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> with a party
                    or not, <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir E</ref> should see this country, that is certain, &#8211; but where he can be
                    lodged is the difficulty. As for the next house that is out of the question &#8211; Just when you would be coming poor <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> would be dying in the only decent bed-room there. He cannot live thro the
                    summer &#8211; I am still <hi rend="ital">getting</hi> my lease, in which that house is included, &#8211; of course for the only purpose of
                    securing myself against an unpleasant neighbor. But <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> has built another
                    adjoining the wood-house, &#8211; poor man, thinking all along that he was accommodating us, &#8211; calculating that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> would occupy his present tenement, &amp; he himself remove into the
                    new one. The shell is compleated, the only thing which makes me regard it with any complacency, is a sort of dream, that one of
                    these days you may perhaps take up your abode there,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Barker moved to Keswick in 1812,
                        she lived in <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> with the Southeys and then in the unoccupied house next door
                        that he describes here, called Greta Lodge.</note> &amp; that when anything is to be said from one house to the other, I may
                    vociferate the message from the Organ-room window.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mr. White wrote me an intimation of <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward&#8217;s</ref> death.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Seward&#8217;s cousin Rev. Henry White (dates unknown), sacristan of Lichfield cathedral, Seward&#8217;s
                        cousin and supporter. She died on 25 March 1809.</note> I was right enough in supposing her farewell letter to me was not
                    written in so desperate a state as it purported to be, for she recovered that attack, &amp; died of a different complaint. She had
                    however distinctly at other times expressed an apprehension of the particular disease which threatened her, &amp; a conviction
                    that her days were near their end. Her will, the Wolseleys<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Robert Wolseley (d.
                        1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740&#8211;1817). Wolseley married a Miss Hand (first name and dates unknown). The
                        family seat was at Wolseley Park, Rugeley, Staffordshire, near Seward&#8217;s home at Lichfield. He was a friend of Seward&#8217;s, and
                        also knew Southey as a fellow pupil at Westminster School. He and his wife visited Keswick several times in 1808 and
                        1809.</note> tell me filled fourteen folio sheets, &amp; Scott has a legacy of 100&#163;, &#8211; for which he is expected to write her
                        epitaph.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The following couplets written by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> are inscribed on Anna Seward&#8217;s monument in Lichfield Cathedral: <lg type="stanza">
              <l rend="indent3">Amid
                                these aisles, where once his precepts showed</l>
              <l rend="indent3">The heavenward pathway which in life he trode,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">This simple tablet marks a father&#8217;s bier,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">And those he loved in life in death are
                                near;</l>
              <l rend="indent3">For him, for them, a daughter bade it rise.</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Memorial of domestic
                                charities.</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Still wouldst thou know why, o&#8217;er the marble spread,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">In female
                                grace the willow droops her head;</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Why on her branches, silent and unstrung,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">The minstrel harp is emblematic hung;</l>
              <l rend="indent3">What poet&#8217;s voice is smothered here in dust</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Till waked to join the chorus of the just,&#8212;</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Lo! one brief line an answer sad
                                supplies,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Honoured, beloved, and mourned, here Seward lies!</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Her worth, her
                                warmth of heart, let friendship say,&#8212;</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Go seek her genius in her living
                    lay.</l>
            </lg>
          </note>&lt;/note&gt; A bequest of 500&#163;, &#8211; for her own monument is the only foolish part of her arrangements, &#8211; that
                    was a poor vanity, &#8211; the very verger when he shows the monument, will relate it to her discredit. I am glad I have seen her &#8211; glad
                    too that you were present at the first interview,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey visited <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Seward</ref> with Barker in March 1808.</note> &amp; not in [MS obscured] slightest degree
                    surprised that when it rains legacies none should fall upon me. Every body who has money to dispose of, knows persons who ought to
                    have it, &#8211; &amp; they are greatly to be censured who give any part of their property to those who have no claim to it, &#8211; of course
                    I include moral claims as well as those of kindred. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> legacy &amp; her
                    monument-money should have gone to Miss Fern.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elizabeth Fern (dates unknown), Seward&#8217;s
                        companion and housekeeper.</note> She might have left me a set of her works or some piece of her plate, &amp; I should have
                    shown such a token with pleasure. Her papers, which are in Constables hands are very numerous &#8211; the Letters alone would fill
                    fourteen quarto volumes, &#8211; of which two are to be published. <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Some, but not all of
                        Seward&#8217;s letters to Southey appeared in <title>The Letters of Anna Seward Written Between the Years 1784 and 1807</title>,
                        published by Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) in six volumes in 1811.</note> Then I suppose I shall come
                    in, &amp; be adored to my face. &#8211; She was a woman of great abilities, &#8211; &amp; if ever I pass thro Lichfield again I shall feel
                    with regret that she is gone.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> I hear is in a deep decline. God have mercy on him, never was
                    a good heart so wofully corrupted by a vain head. It grieves me to think how differently this intelligence affects me from what it
                    would once have done. He is better dead than living, &#8211; but it is shocking that I should think so. I think there was a time when
                    that mans heart was as pure &amp; innocent as the heart of man could be. That so beautiful a flower should have had its fruit so
                    cankered! The question whether it would have been otherwise if he had never known me will occur to many persons. On that score I
                    have nothing to repent. I set him no example but what was good. As long as he loved me he loved what was good. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I expect daily to hear of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry&#8217;s</ref> marriage with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary Sealy</ref>. &#8211; God bless you. I suppose <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir E</ref>. is in town &amp; therefore do not inclose the letter</p>
        <closer rend="indent1"> RS.</closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent2">
            <date when="1809-05-13">May 13. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>