<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1710</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2832</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 175&#8211;179.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1710" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1710" type="letter">
        <head>1710. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1809-11-16">16 November 1809</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 175&#8211;179.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <date when="1809-11-16">Nov. 16; 1809.</date>
          <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Parliamentary Report for which you wish is not to be obtained. When any report is considered curious, every
                    member takes care to claim his copy, and there are none to be disposed of among the profane. This is very seldom the case, and the
                    usual fate of Parliamentary Proceedings is to be condemned for waste paper. I myself used no other paper for packing up all my
                    books. This Historical Report, that upon a new London bridge<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A competition to design a new
                        London Bridge was held in 1799. Parliament chose a design by John Rennie (1761&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>).</note> (containing,
                    by a strange waste of public money, engravings of all the plans which were delivered in); the Population Returns,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1801, Rickman had organised the first census of the British population.</note> the Poor
                        Returns,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1804, Rickman took charge of a parliamentary report on the state of the
                        poor.</note> and the evidence upon the Duke of York&#8217;s affair,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke
                        of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was
                        forced to resign after a parliamentary enquiry into allegations that he had profited by allowing his mistress, Mary Anne
                        Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for which promotion was
                        arranged.</note> were all in request and unobtainable. Of the Population, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>
                    secured me a copy, as being his work; he wished to do so with the very book in question, but it was not in his power. In all
                    ordinary cases it is only to ask and to have.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you furnish me with any particulars of the conduct of the French at Lisbon, or in any other part of Portugal? I
                    should be glad to state specific instances of their rapacity and excesses.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s
                        work on the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> for which, from 1810 to 1812, he contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for
                        the years 1808&#8211;1810.</note> My hopes, or, to speak more accurately, my faith, respecting that peninsula. remains unshaken. The
                    people of both countries have much to go through, and may perhaps be for a time overpowered (though never, I think, wholly
                    suppressed), but the event will be their regeneration, &#8211; a new birth into freedom, a resurrection of glory. This, however, cannot
                    be under Fernando and Prince D. Joan.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833), twice King of Spain: in
                        1808 and from 1813 until his death, and in 1809 deprived of his throne by Napoleon and under effective house arrest in France.
                        Prince Regent, John VI (the Duke of Braganza) (1767&#8211;1826), the ruler of Portugal had fled to Brazil, as the French invaded his
                        country, in 1807.</note> The striking parallel between the situation of the former and of the Portuguese Infante D. Joao, the
                    son of Inez de Castro,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In&#234;s Peres de Castro (1325&#8211;1355), the lover of King Pedro I of
                        Portugal (1320&#8211;1367) died before he became king. She was supposedly exhumed and, as a corpse, legally married to Pedro so that
                        their son, John, Prince of Portugal (1349&#8211;1397), became legitimate and therefore the heir to the throne.</note> is very
                    remarkable. Like him, Fernando is a mere rallying word for the present; and as he cannot make his escape, his nominal authority
                    can do no harm. It is otherwise with the Prince of Brazil; he might return, and with him the old abominations.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John VI did return from Brazil and became King of Portugal in fact as well as in name in
                        1821.</note> I should wish therefore to see a revolution proclaimed and acted upon in Portugal, though the recall of our army
                    were to be the immediate consequence. I am afraid we do them, and have done them, more harm than good. The salvation of nations
                    (under God) must come from their own right hand. The appointment of the <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke
                        of Wellington</ref> to the chief authority would dispirit me more than any other circumstance (being a measure at once so
                    degrading and so disheartening to the Portuguese), if I did not recollect how, during many years of the Dutch war,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> After 1580 Portugal was in a dynastic union with Spain: over the next fifty years it was involved
                        in war with the Dutch, first in the Netherlands and, from 1602, in the East Indies and South America. The Portuguese allowed
                        Spanish and German officers to lead several campaigns.</note> they looked to other nations for help, and accepted leaders from
                    them. The history of that war furnishes much important matter of parallel and instruction. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In Paraguay the Spaniards are losing their own language. At Rio Janeiro this will not be the case; but will you
                    inquire of your brother,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> After the 1807 collapse of the May trading firm in Portugal,
                        William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), John May&#8217;s younger brother, had become a merchant trading in Brazil.</note> whether it be not so in other parts less
                    immediately connected with Europe, and especially in the interior; that is to say, whether the Tupi or Brazilian, as it may
                    perhaps be called, is much spoken by the Brazil-Portuguese,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The language of the native
                        Tupi people of Brazil. In the early colonial period Tupi was used as a lingua franca throughout Brazil by Europeans as well as
                        Amerindians.</note> or whether a mixed language, according to the usual process, is growing up. Are there <hi rend="ital">any</hi> natives about Rio? &#8211; <hi rend="ital">many</hi>? &#8211; of what tribes, and in what condition? Do the two races intermix
                    as they used to do, and is there in the mixed breed any of that <hi rend="ital">mulish</hi> obliquity of nature which has been
                    represented by the Jesuits as characterising the Mamalucos?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A term used in South America
                        for mixed race European-Indian people, and more specifically applied in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries to the
                        organized bands of Portuguese who roamed the interior of Brazil and Paraguay capturing and enslaving Indians. The Jesuits,
                        opposing them, brought the Indians into village colonies under their protection.</note> I think not, except from causes as
                    easily to be removed as explained. The vicious disposition of mules results from the physical imperfection of their nature. I
                    think I can explain why. All animals are vicious when under the influence of lust: materialists, who look no further, may triumph
                    in the fact. Nature has materials to spare; in the mule they have not their natural determination; he is always in a different
                    state of body from that of perfect animals; that which in them is collected and carried off at certain seasons, seems to be
                    diffused at all times through his whole system. Now this cannot be applicable to the mulatto. That the Mamalucos were a bad breed
                    I believe; but it was because they learnt the evil of both races, and the good of neither.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you request him to send me any books which may be printed there.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> That
                        is, William May.</note> Their &#8216;Almanack&#8217; would be curious here. It is not unlikely that a book which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my uncle</ref> long looked for in vain at Lisbon may turn up in Brazil,&#8211;the &#8216;Vida de
                    F. Joam d&#8217; Almeida,&#8217; by P. Simari de Vasconcellos.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sima&#771;o de Vasconcellos
                            (1596&#8211;1671),<title> Vida do Padre Joam d&#8217;Almeida da Companhia de Jesu, na Provincia do Brazil</title> (1658). Almeida was
                        a seventeenth-century English Jesuit missionary to Brazil.</note> Almeida was a disciple of Anchieta,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vasconcellos also published <title>Vida do Vener. Padre Joseph de Anchieta, &#8230; Taumaturgo do Novo Mundo, na
                            Provincia do Brasil</title> (1672). Jos&#233; de Anchieta (1534 -1597) was a Jesuit missionary involved in expelling the
                        French, and their Indian allies, from Brazil.</note> and there is no document the want of which I have regretted so much,
                    because it relates to that portion of time of which there are the fewest records.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is going on well, and, to my great joy, is employing his leisure upon a
                    &#8216;History of the Crusades,&#8217; a project which he long since formed, and in which I have always and earnestly encouraged him. I have
                    good hope of his doing credit both to himself and his name. It was not a little gratifying to me, when I talked to him about this,
                    to perceive how gladly <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">his wife</ref> listened to me, and with what an affectionate
                    ambition she looked on to his labours. He has the advantage of setting out with that system of <hi rend="ital">book-keeping</hi>
                    which I did not discover till after much labour; and he will have all the assistance that I can give him. I cannot, indeed, do so
                    much for him as <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref> has done for me, but it is in my power to do more than
                    any other person could do, from the nature and variety of my pursuits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My uncle is probably in London at this time, and you will have heard news of him from himself. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you give me your opinion respecting life insurances? This business of the &#8216;Register,&#8217;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for 1808&#8211;1810 in James Ballantyne&#8217;s
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> or, in its stead, plans which I have in reserve, if the engagement for it
                    should not be continued, will, I think, enable me, without inconvenience, to insure my life for 1000<hi rend="ital">1</hi>., if
                    such a step be advisable. Upon this subject I will be guided by your advice. I have long thought of writing to you concerning my
                    worldly affairs; that is to say, as to what measures should be taken, in case of my death, with my copyrights and manuscripts, &#8211;
                    the only property which I should at present, or for some years to come, leave behind me. This will require a separate letter, and
                    shall not be delayed longer. Remember us to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">Mrs. May</ref>. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> R. Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>