<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1533</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2655</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Ms Hyde 10 (653), Houghton Library, Harvard University.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 102&#8211;106.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1533" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1533" type="letter">
        <head>1533. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1808-11-11">11 November 1808</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Hale/ Downton/ Wiltshire/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 137. 1808/ Robert Southey/
                        Keswick 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Nover/ recd. 15th d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ansd. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />MS: Ms Hyde 10 (653), Houghton Library, Harvard University<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 102&#8211;106.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter had nearly brought me the first intelligence of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> marriage, &#8211; for his which announced it arrived only by the same post.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s uncle <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref> had recently married <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">Catherine</ref>, daughter of Loveless Bigg-Wither (1741&#8211;1813), a Hampshire
                        landowner.</note> Some eight or nine weeks ago word to this effect had been written me by <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel Peachy</ref>, my summer neighbour here, &#8211; but as he knows nothing of my Uncle,
                    &amp; there are so many Hills in the world, I rather wished his information to be true, than believed it; &#8211; &amp; indeed so
                    totally discredited the rumour as not to think it worthy of mention. I perceive what opinion you are inclined to upon the subject;
                    &#8211; mine, as far as it can be formed in utter ignorance of the age &amp; character of her whom he has chosen, is more favourable.
                    Perhaps selfish considerations contribute to render it so, &#8211; I was not satisfied to feel myself settled so far from my Uncle,
                        <del>xxxx</del> considering the lonely situation in which he was placed; &amp; the thought that his evening of life would be
                    passed in solitariness often came across me, &amp; lay heavy at my heart. But setting that consideration aside, &#8211; one of the main
                    objections to a late marriage, is not applicable to him; &#8211; he has &lt;now&gt; no fixed habits of life which it would be difficult
                    to change or modify, &#8211; they have all been torn up by the roots, &amp; new ones were necessarily to be acquired. One weighty
                    drawback undoubtedly remains, &#8211; should he have children he cannot hope to see them grow up. I trust he feels convinced that in
                    this case, should I survive <del>them</del> &lt;him&gt;, I shall be to them, to the utmost of my power, what <del>they have</del>
                    he has been to me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Surprized however certainly I am, &amp; so surprized as hardly to have thought of any thing else since. To have a
                    new graft upon a family stock is always an important event, &amp; it is especially strange to hear unexpectedly of one who stands
                    in so near a relation, &amp; to know no more of her or her family than of the woman in the moon &amp; hers, &#8211; a woman you know
                    there must be there because the man in the moon has horns. My Uncle tells me her former name, &amp; that she is of the race of old
                    George Wither the poet,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Wither (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, a
                        favourite of Southey&#8217;s.</note> &#8211; who in spite of his long fits of desperate dullness &#8211; is a dear old friend of mine, a right
                    poet in his best moods, &amp; a right honest upright downright Englishman in all his moods. It is curious enough, that I should
                    long have thought of publishing a selection from his works. &#8211; As you may well suppose there are many questions which I should like
                    to have answered, &#8211; &amp; perhaps you can answer some of them. Did he become acquainted with her at Lisbon? What age may she
                        be?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine was thirty-three.</note> What part of Hampshire does her father live
                        in?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manydown is near Basingstoke in Hampshire.</note> has she any brothers,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine had one surviving brother, Harris (1781&#8211;1833). He inherited the estate at Manydown and
                        in 1802 proposed marriage to Jane Austen.</note> &amp; What is become of three elder sisters, for my Uncle calls her the
                    fourth daughter?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine was the fourth of five surviving daughters, of whom the three
                        elder than she had all married in the 1790s.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask me my opinion of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Foxs history.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles James
                        Fox (1749&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A History of the Early Part of the Reign of James II</title> (1808).</note> I have
                    only hastily seen &amp; run it thro. The importance of the subject upon which he treats every body must feel [MS obscured] I know
                    not whether others feel the thorough<del>xx</del> &amp; degrading meanness of all the circumstances recorded, &amp; of all the
                    characters brought forward, with the single exception of Sidney<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Algernon Sidney
                        (1623&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>). Republican executed for involvement in the Rye House plot to assassinate the monarch.</note>
                    (for Russel<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Russell, Lord Russell (1639&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>). Republican
                        executed for involvement in the Rye House plot to assassinate the monarch.</note> was nothing but a martyr) &amp;
                        <del>xxxxxx</del> &lt;probably&gt; of that republican maltster, if we knew more of him,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Rumbold (1622&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>): a former soldier, Rumbold was a maltster of Rye House, near
                        Hoddesdon, Hertfordshire. Rumbold escaped arrest after the discovery of the Rye House plot but was wounded, captured and
                        executed while participating in the Duke of Argyll&#8217;s rebellion in 1685. His last words from the scaffold account for Southey&#8217;s
                        enthusiasm: &#8216;I am sure there was no man born marked of God above another; for none comes into the world with a saddle upon his
                        back, neither any booted and spurred to ride him&#8217; (State trials, 9.873&#8211;81; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; <del>let</del> there
                    is however enough known to <del>xxxx</del> him in my political Kalendar. In recording the events of that age, which no
                    &lt;true&gt; Englishman can remember without &lt;feeling&gt; shame for his country, &amp; almost for human nature, no
                        <del>feel</del> sentiment can be excited except of hatred &amp; disgust which approaches to loathsomeness. England is so sunk
                    so degenerate, so vile &amp; abject, that one can have no national feelings on perusing these annals, &#8211; &amp; the party-spirit
                    which is every where <del>an</del> apparent ill supplies their place. In fact Whig &amp; Tory were alike base, the difference
                    between them was not more than the shade between black &amp; raven-gray, &amp; if this &lt;book&gt; had reached the
                        <del>xxxx</del> time of the Revolution we should have found &amp; felt that even that event went to the tune of
                    Tantararara, or rogues all.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The tantara-raras were, in Southey&#8217;s parlance, the noisy, blaring MPs.
                        <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by John O&#8217;Keeffe (1747&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>); see
                        <title>The Dramatic Works of John O&#8217;Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1798), III, pp. 349&#8211;90. &#8216;Tantara-rara, Fools All
                        Fools All&#8217; was also a popular song from Henry Fielding&#8217;s (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>) play <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> It was the Bishops who saved us &amp; to be saved by such
                    Bishops reminds me of Beelzebub casting out Devils. All this relates to the matter of the history. The manner it were unfair to
                    judge of otherwise than favourably. It appears that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox had right notions concerning the nature of
                    narration, &amp; would have made it plain straight-forward narration without any discussion of disputed points &amp; jarring
                    authorities. The text is now full of these discussions, but it cannot be doubted, that he would have placed them in the notes or
                    appendix. We lose much by the unfinished state of the work, &#8211; yet not so much as if the writer had been a man who stood aloof from
                    parties, &amp; was &lt;not&gt; continually thinking of the situation in which he himself stood. In spite of all M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox can say Whigs &amp; Tories have never meant much more than Ins &amp; Outs or Outs &amp; Ins; a fact &lt;upon&gt;
                    which the last year of his own <del>xxxx</del> life set the great seal. &#8211; I am of the school of Sidney &amp; Hutchinson<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 361&#8211;378, Southey extolled the
                        conduct and morality of Colonel John Hutchinson (1615&#8211;1664; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan commander in the English civil war
                        and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I, as revealed in a posthumously published memoir by his widow, Lucy
                        Hutchinson (1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>): <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806).</note> &amp;
                    Milton, &#8211; public morality has never been produced in any other, &amp; never will be produced where there is a false standard of
                    greatness. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bourgoings is the best statistic account of Spain;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Francois Bourgoing
                        (1748&#8211;1811), <title>Travels in Spain: Containing a New, Accurate, and Comprehensive View of the Present State of that
                            Country</title> (1789; new edition 1808).</note> faithful &amp; full but dull. Fischers the best supplement, giving what
                    lies on the surface of things.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick Augustus Fischer (dates unknown), <title>Travels
                            in Spain in 1797 and 1798. With an appendix on the method of travelling in that country</title> (1802).</note> But Fischer
                    is <del>xx there</del> one of the worst principled men who ever lent his aid to debase demoralize &amp; debilitate human nature.
                    His Picture of Madrid is now on my table, &amp; contains ample proof that he sets all religious &amp; all moral restraint equally
                    at defiance.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Picture of Madrid Taken on the Spot</title> (1808). This work was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1808</title>, 7 (1809), 57&#8211;60.</note> Spain is totally changed since the Countess D&#8217;Anois &amp; Labat described it, &#8211; her
                    account is half a novel;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, Baroness d&#8217;Aulnoy
                            (1650/1651&#8211;1705),<title> Memoires de la Cour d&#8217;Espagne, Relation du Voyage d&#8217;Espagne</title> (1690/1691). These travel
                        accounts were collected and translated as <title>The diverting works of the Countess d&#8217;Anois: author of the Ladies travel to
                            Spain: containing: I. The memoirs of her own life: II. All her Spanish novels and histories: III. Her letters: IV. Tales
                            of the fairies in three parts compleat</title> (1707).</note>
          <hi rend="ital">his</hi> authentic &amp; curious as far as it goes. But there is no country concerning which we have so few
                    tolerable books. No<del>n</del> traveller seems to have known any thing about the country before he went there, &#8211; consequently
                    none have been prepared for the journey.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-11">Nov. 11. 1808.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>