<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1545</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2667</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    111&#8211;114.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1545" type="letter">
        <head>1545. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1808-11-28">28 November
                        1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    111&#8211;114.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-11-28">Nov. 28. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Had I not been very busy in clearing off my annual reviewing, I should sooner have told you that <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> has disclaimed for his house and for Hood&#8217;s<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Hood (d. 1811): a bookseller in Dundee before 1799; partner in Vernor and Hood booksellers, London 1799&#8211;1811.</note>
                    any pretensions of copyright to the &#8216;Life,&#8217;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of <title>The Remains of
                            Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title> (1807) contained a life of White written by Southey.</note> &#8211; so that business is
                    at rest. I thought I had praised the poem concerning which you ask my opinion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So far from having any objection that what you propose should appear in the &#8216;Evangelical Magazine,&#8217; I shall
                    heartily rejoice if it can be effected. That Magazine is a powerful engine, &#8211; the most powerful in this country; unquestionably it
                    can be of the greatest service to the &#8216;Remains,&#8217; and it will be doing no little good to those persons who act according to its
                    directions thus to put something into their hands better than the offal and hog&#8217;s wash with which they are dieted. I have a horror
                    of the presumptuous ignorance and intolerant spirit of that rapidly strengthening sect, and only wish there were more such writers
                    as Cowper<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Cowper (1731&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>), poet and evangelical, whose
                        works Southey would edit.</note> and <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry</ref> whom they might be permitted to
                    read, as the only means of softening them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry that &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps Capel Lofft (1751&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Whig landed gentleman, lawyer and poet, notoriously testy of disposition. Lofft was the patron and editor of Robert Bloomfield
                        (1766&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Kirke White and a number of other writers from poor backgrounds. He was a regular contributor
                        to the <title>Monthly Mirror</title>.</note> is acting so childishly, &#8211; for his own sake, and not for mine. Could I have
                    guessed that the paragraph in question would have appeared objectionable to anybody, it should have gone behind the fire.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> It seems that Lofft was offended by a paragraph in which Southey praised himself, rather
                        than Lofft, for bringing White&#8217;s poetry to notice after the setback of a cruel review. On p. 27 of the &#8216;Account of the Life of
                        H. K. White&#8217; in volume 1 of the 1808 edition of the <title>Remains</title>, Southey states, &#8216;It is not unworthy of remark,
                        that this very reviewal, which was designed to crush the hopes of Henry, and suppress his struggling genius, has been in its
                        consequences, the main occasion of bringing his Remains to light, and obtaining for him that fame which assuredly will be his
                        portion. Had it not been for the indignation which I felt at perusing a criticism at once so cruel and so stupid, the little
                        intercourse between Henry and myself would not have taken place; his papers would probably have remained in oblivion, and his
                        name, in a few years, have been forgotten&#8217;.</note> The remark was made to me by <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, as illustrating how good comes out of evil; he wished I had stated it; and accordingly in the second
                    edition I did state it, with as little thought of &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211; as of the man in the moon. It is lamentable that that good heart of his
                    should be coupled with so bad a judgment and so waspish a temper. I am obliged to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Mr.
                        Hill</ref>, but shall be sorry if this mark of attention towards me should deprive his &#8216;Mirror&#8217; of a respectable
                    correspondent. Mr. &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211; may attack me with perfect impunity. I never condescended to reply to any personal attack but once, which
                    was to Sir Herbert Croft in the &#8216;Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine&#8217;;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Croft wrote a series of letters
                        about accusations, levelled by Southey and others, that he had unfairly obtained manuscripts, for his own gain, from the
                        family of Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>). Croft&#8217;s letters appeared in the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s
                            Magazine</title>, 70 (February&#8211;April 1800), 99&#8211;104, 222&#8211;226, 322&#8211;325. Southey replied in the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s
                            Magazine</title>, 70.1 (March 1800), 226, and the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 9 (April 1800), 253; see <title>The
                            Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Southey to Editor of the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title> 20
                        March [1800] (Letter 497) and Southey to Editor of the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 20 March [1800] (Letter 498).</note> &#8211;
                    then I had begun the war. Mrs. Newton&#8217;s (Chatterton&#8217;s sister&#8217;s)<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Newton (1749&#8211;1804),
                        sister of Chatterton, was the principal beneficiary of the sales of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>, 3 vols
                        (1803) that Southey and <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> edited to relieve Chatterton&#8217;s family from
                        financial distress. In 1803 Southey had reckoned that the publication would clear over &#163;400 for her.</note> interest was
                    implicated; and my reply to a shilling pamphlet<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Croft, <title>Chatterton and &#8216;Love
                            and Madness&#8217;. A letter from Denmark to Mr. Nichols, Editor of the Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine, where it appeared in February,
                            March and April 1800; Respecting an Unprovoked Attack, made upon the Writer during his Absence from England</title>
                        (1800).</note> was made in about fifteen lines. On all such occasions I am a Quaker in literature, as well as in the main
                    foundations of my faith. My thunders and lightnings are reserved for occasions which deserve them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you inform Mr. Park<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Park (1758/9&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>):
                        trained as an engraver, Park became a poet, book-collector, antiquary, bibliographer and editor. He lived in Piccadilly, then
                        Portman Square, and from 1804 at Church Row, Hampstead. Park was editing <title>Works of the British Poets</title>, 42 vols (London, 1805&#8211;8).
                        The poems by Lovell that Southey discovered were published in vol. XLI.</note> that those few poems of poor <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell&#8217;s</ref>, for which I searched in vain, have turned up among some old papers, and that
                    I should have sent them to him, had not his letter led me to believe they would be too late; &#8211; if there be time, they shall still
                    be forwarded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The &#8216;Letters,&#8217; as you may well remember, were printed off in the second edition before I saw Mr. Dashwood; part of
                    his communication was inserted in the &#8216;Life&#8217;;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, the communication of new
                        manuscript correspondence between White and Samuel Francis Dashwood (1773&#8211;1826), a Nottinghamshire clergyman who was one of
                        White&#8217;s early sponsors, came too late for inclusion in the second volume, devoted to letters, of the second edition of
                            <title>Remains</title> (1808). Southey made use of it instead in his &#8216;Account of the Life of H. K. White&#8217; in the first
                        volume, on pp. 41 and 102.</note> the rest as soon as it could be in the third. I am glad he is well pleased with the
                    book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The &#8216;Life of Colonel Hutchinson&#8217; is one of the best books in the English language, or in any other; you must have
                    read it with peculiar interest as being a Nottingham man. It accorded with all my best feelings and dearest principles; and I had
                    the satisfaction of reviewing it in the Annual, in such a manner as to produce a letter of thanks from the editor.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the <title>Annual Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807), 361&#8211;378, appeared Southey&#8217;s notice of
                        Lucy Hutchinson (1620&#8211;1681; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title> (1806), a
                        posthumously published memoir by the widow of Colonel John Hutchinson (1615&#8211;1664; <title>DNB</title>). The Colonel was a
                        Puritan commander in the English civil war and a signatory of the death warrant of King Charles I. The editor thanking Southey
                        was the Rev. Julius Hutchinson (dates unknown), a descendant.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For these reverses in Spain I was prepared, and by them I am not cast down, nor indeed led to abate a jot of my
                    full confidence in the final success of the Spaniards. We have, as usual, done everything in the very worst manner possible, and
                    have been far more mischievous to the Spaniards as friends than we ever could have been as enemies, by that rascally business in
                    Portugal, which appears worse and worse the more it is investigated. But the end will be well; this I said before any person had
                    begun to hope, and this I shall say after every person has ceased to hope, for Joseph will soon be crowned at Madrid, &#8211; is
                    probably by this time.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph-Napol&#233;on Bonaparte (1768&#8211;1844) was the elder brother of
                        Napoleon, who made him King of Naples and Sicily (1806&#8211;1808), and, in August 1808, King of Spain and the Indies as Joseph I of
                        Spain (1808&#8211;1813). Joseph was forced by a revolt to abandon Madrid and did not return until January 1809, after French
                        reinforcements retook the city.</note> Zaragoza will in all likelihood be laid in ashes,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> From December the town of Zaragoza was besieged (for the second time that year) by the French. The siege
                        involved ferocious street fighting, in which the Spanish civilians took full part. When the French finally succeeded in
                        February, 54000 people had died.</note> and Bonaparte will march to Lisbon; still the country win redeem itself, and work out
                    its own redemption. Sir John Moore has a strong country behind him, and if he cannot make head in the field, may secure himself in
                    the fortified towns along the frontier.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant-General Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), commander of British troops in Portugal, had marched into Spain, having been promised support from
                        60,000 to 70,000 Spanish troops, at the beginning of November. The support was not forthcoming and Moore found himself pursued
                        by an overwhelming French force. In December he began a retreat to Corunna that culminated in a defensive battle there in
                        January 1809, at which he was killed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. Remember me to James.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Neville&#8217;s and Henry&#8217;s younger brother
                        James White (baptized 1787&#8211;1885).</note> &#8211; has he received benefit at Brighton?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>