<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1300</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2422</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 71&#8211;72
                        [in part]; Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        441&#8211;444.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1300" type="letter">
        <head>1300. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-03-27">27
                        March [1807]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M. P./ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 71&#8211;72
                        [in part]; Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        441&#8211;444.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> By this time I conclude you are out of office,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of
                        All the Talents, of which Wynn was part, broke up in March 1807.</note> &#8211; &amp; a letter will be no trespass on your time. &#8211;
                    That I am against any indulgence to the Catholicks you know, &#8211; but I am not on that account (&amp; setting all personal
                    considerations aside) the less sorry for this mischievous change of ministry. I cannot persuade myself that the ostensible cause
                    can be the real one; it may have been used as a pretext by those who influence the King, or he may have made it a pretext himself
                    to gratify his resentment against for the Abolition of the Slave T &amp; for the projected reforms. What a precedent &#8211; a ministry
                    changed without any wish for the change having been expressed either by the parliament or the country; but who on the contrary
                    were strong almost beyond example in both; &#8211; from the mere exertion of the prerogative, the mere will of &amp; pleasure of the
                    Sovereign, who chuses to put in their place men of tried &amp; convicted incapacity, with an old woman at their head!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The new Prime Minister was William Henry Cavendish Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; Such a ministry cannot long support itself &#8211; I doubt whether it can command a majority,
                    &amp; if it dissolves parliament doubt whether it can form a new one in its interests.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Looking at your administration in the way in which History will look at it &#8211; that is at those things only which
                    will produce permanent effect &#8211; these are the Limited Service Bill &amp; the Abolition,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> By
                        the first of these measures the government of which Wynn was a member limited the term for which soldiers could enlist; the
                        second was passed into law in March 1807.</note> &#8211; two measures the best which I have seen, or shall live to see. And if you
                    loved the memory of Pitt<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister
                        1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> as little as I do, it would give you pleasure to <del>xxx</del> perceive <del>xxx</del> it
                        <del>xxx</del> now placed beyond a doubt, that he cared nothing about the abolition while <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prime Minister from 1806 to
                        1807.</note> had the business at heart; &#8211; &amp; at heart he will have it to his comfort on his death bed. I half suspect that
                    this is the measure which the King will not forgive.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The only thing which can make you unpopular with the country is the business of Sir Home Popham,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Home Riggs Popham (1762&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer. Popham was the
                        commander-in-chief of the expedition which took the Dutch colony at the Cape of Good Hope for Britain in 1806. He then sailed
                        his squadron across the Atlantic and occupied Buenos Aires&#8212;an occupation Britain proved unable to maintain, despite sending a
                        second, reinforcing expedition, against the hostility of the inhabitants. Popham was reprimanded for acting without proper
                        authority.</note> in which it seems to me you were decidedly right. His conduct has been very mischievous. The more I know of
                    South America the more I am convinced that our policy is to seperate it from Spain, but not to attempt its conquest. Any such
                    attempt can only end eventually in defeat &#8211; &amp; shame, &#8211; tho it may send home dollars at first. &amp; give the existing ministry
                    that patronage which is the game they play for. This subject will occupy the concluding chapter of my Brazil &amp; Paraguay.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810 and
                        did not take this form.</note> &#8211; You perhaps know whether Sir Homes expedition prevents any more extensive scheme &#8211; I suspect
                    it did, &amp; that thus the business of that mission to Lisbon was frustrated. There was something ungracious in the way of
                    receiving the intelligence that the Cape was captured &#8211; which is probably to be imputed to Lord St Vincent<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), former First Lord of the Admiralty (until
                        1804) and, from 1806 until the Grenville ministry fell, Commander of the Channel fleet. In 1806 St Vincent had gone to Lisbon
                        on a diplomatic mission to arrange the evacuation of the Portuguese royal family to Brazil in the event of Portugal&#8217;s invasion
                        by Napoleonic forces, and to discuss British aid.</note> &#8211; one of the worst men living. &#8211; Except this there is no point upon
                    which the late ministry are not popular. And tho any indulgence to the Catholicks cannot be more deprecated by the Bishops than it
                    is by me, on this subject I believe <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is the only friend I have who
                    thinks with me, &amp; all the talking &amp; thinking people are on your side. If there be a cry of no Popery it will be confined
                    to the mob.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My mind has been made up to a settled residence in this place. It became necessary from some arrangements of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref>, that I should either quit <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">the
                        house</ref> soon, or resolve upon abiding in it: &amp; having neither inclination nor means for a &#8230; removal I resolved to
                    stay. Accordingly, after living three years &amp; a half in a house half-finished &amp; half furnished, we are now endeavouring to
                    get as many comforts about us as are within our reach. I have sent for my books which are to come by sea: stocked the garden with
                    currant bushes &amp; such like fruits, &amp; am about to plant a hedge round it, put in a few shrubs &amp; flowers &#8211; &amp; make
                    the whole as ornamental &amp; as convenient as I can. And unless I ever go to settle in Lisbon, few things could excite a wish in
                    me ever to remove from hence. once in two years I purpose visiting London. &#8211; The distance is an evil but not a material one &#8211;
                    especially if I <del>xxx</del> have any friends to halt with on the way. &#8211; The main objection to this place will be removed when
                    my books arrive, which are a very respectable collection. &#8211; the greater part being <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref>. Society I do not want &#8211; of this I can speak from experience, &amp; sure I am that I should be less happy with a
                    coach &amp; four in London than I am when rowing my own boat upon Derwentwater. And when you have it in your power again, let the
                    one thing which you seek for me be the <del>xxx</del> title of Historiographer<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The post of
                        Historiographer Royal was held, until his death, by Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>). Southey was unsuccessful in
                        his bid to succeed Dutens.</note> with a decent pension, if 300&#163; it would satisfy my wishes &#8211; if 400 I should be rich. I have
                    no worldly ambition &#8211; a man who lives so much in the past, &amp; for the future &#8211; can have none. &#8211; it can not be long before a new
                    reign or a plainer fit of insanity will bring you in again. These men without either talents, character or hereditary influence
                    cannot long maintain their posts upon the single ground of the Kings favour. When you are in, do not form higher wishes for me
                    than I have for myself, I <hi rend="ital">am</hi> in that state of life to which it has pleased God to call me &#8211; for which I was
                    formed, in which I am contented: nor is it likely that I could be in any other so usefully, so worthily, or so happily employed.
                    If what I now receive should in the future come from the Treasury<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn succeeded, before
                        he left office, in arranging that the pension he paid Southey from his personal funds was replaced by a government
                        pension.</note> &#8211; I shall not then have any serious wish for any change of fortune &#8211; nor would this be one if you were
                    [wea]lthier &#8211; what more is necessary I get, hardly enough it is true, but still in my own way; and it is not impossible but that
                    some day or other, one of my books may by some accident hit the fashion of the day, &amp; by a rapid sale place me in comparative
                    affluence. I must be a second time cut off, if I do not still inherit an independence: &amp; if after all, I should go out of the
                    world as poor a man as I am at this present, the moment it comes to be &#8216;poor Southey&#8217; &#8211; my name becomes a provision for my wife
                    &amp; children, even tho I had not that reliance upon individual friendship which experience makes me feel. &#8211; I do not know under
                    what circumstances I could have more reason to be happy, &#8211; &amp; that I am so is your doing &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-03-27">March 27</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>