<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1321</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2443</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1321" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1321" type="letter">
        <head>1321. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1807-05-12">12 May 1807</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ with Thomas Wilson Esqr/ Hampstead/ near
                        London<lb />Postmark: 10 o&#8217;clock MY 15 1807 F.N.<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters
                        of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 232&#8211;238.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I humbly beg leave to suggest Senhora that it is much more expedient both for your health &amp; spirits, &amp; for
                    my improvements that you should be at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> than that you should be lodging in
                    London; &#8211; that it will cost you less to travel here than to stay there; &#8211; that if you are for modelling my nose, here is the
                    living one which is better than any picture, &#8211; &amp; that <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Mr Jackson</ref> is making
                    bricks of excellent clay, which may very likely do for other purposes also. London &amp; Little Masters &amp; Great Masters are
                    all very expensive, &#8211; &amp; besides it is not good for woman to be alone (any more than man) when she is not disposed to be in the
                    best good spirits. So be pleased when you leave Hampstead to set your face this way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will perceive that this was written before the arrival of yours this evening, which has been a very welcome
                    letter, as indicating your own wiser projects, &amp; as giving us some news of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>, which will be much relief to <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs Wilson</ref>. Good woman she has been
                    earnestly &amp; anxiously looking to hear what was become of him, which <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his mother</ref> at
                    Bristol did not know &#8211; &amp; Heaven knows when we should have known but for your chance mention of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is in a merchant ship on his way to Lisbon.
                    But if you want a young man, with a good face &amp; a good voice to introduce to your cousins, take compassion upon the <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count</ref>, who is to be found at 42 Princess Street Leicester Square, working now really
                    very hard, &amp; I am afraid out of health &amp; nearly out of spirits. If you were to pay him a visit, &#8211; as you are in the way of
                    visiting gentlemen, I think it would set him in a good humour for a week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The accounts of <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Mrs Peachy</ref> are better than I expected, the news is that
                    she &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">her imperial husband</ref> are to be here in June, with what female companion I
                    know not. You should if possible by any manner of means come early in June, that you many may see the glorious sunsets behind <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, before midsummer, of which you can have no conception.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not know any kickmanjiggery<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s own word for decoration of his
                        house.</note> which we stand in need of &#8211; except it be two <hi rend="ital">bell handles</hi> of spar one for my room, one for
                    the parlour, which already begun to look happy, tho the paperring is at a stand till a farther supply arrives, &amp; none of the
                    bordering is put up. &#8211; I have broken the ivory knife you gave me, &#8211; &amp; this is all I can think of in the way of
                    commissions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> as you remark has been in Italy, &#8211; &amp; by way of showing it he
                    made a point of always addressing Anne<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps a servant at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> by the name of Ann<hi rend="ital">a</hi> &#8211; saying it was not
                    affectation, but he had been so long accustomed to speak Italian that he could not help using the <hi rend="ital">a</hi>. I told
                    him I was quite aware that this must be the reason, &amp; gravely explained to my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> how natural it was! &#8211; I should however have thought more of his judgement in pictures if I had not known that
                    before he went abroad he had no love of them &amp; pretended to none, &amp; if I had not heard him speak of <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> heads in terms which even before me were unwarrantable strong, &amp; when I was
                    not in the room became in the highest degree contemptuous &amp; abusive. There are few men with whom I have so many intellectual
                    points of contact as with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> &amp; none with whom my habits, feelings,
                    morals, &amp; affections are in more direct &amp; almost hostile contrariety. We are so utterly opposite in all the outward &amp;
                    visible signs of men, &amp; in the inward &amp; spiritual grace as well, that in my conscience I do not believe any person whom we
                    both know likes the one, without at the same time not liking, or positively <hi rend="ital">dis</hi>liking the other. We are north
                    &amp; south &amp; if the needle of any ones affections point to the one, it must necessarily turn tail to the other. &#8211; Strange,
                    for two men who have been so closely connected by their opinions, &#8211; &amp; who at this time more nearly agree in opinion upon all
                    subjects with each other than they do with any body else: &#8211; saving upon the subject of divorce &amp; the Trinity, &#8211; the former he
                    defends because it gives him an opportunity of letting people know he is unhappily married as Milton was before him, &#8211; &amp; the
                    latter he affects to believe &#8211; for the sake of making people wonder, &amp; exhibiting the wonderful acuteness of his mind, which
                    loves to make even absurdities appear reasonable.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had returned from Malta and
                        Italy determined upon a separation from his wife, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah</ref>, and having become a
                        Trinitarian.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The small edition of Madoc is on the point of publication.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second,
                        duodecimo, edition of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in 1807.</note> of the first I have heard nothing since my returns of
                    3&#8211;17&#8211;1. &amp; in these cases no news means no sale. Don Manuel is at the Printers mercy, who promises good speed at last, &amp;
                    begins to use it. he has long had the whole copy, &#8211; &amp; it will still be five weeks &#8211; at his fastest rate, before it appears in
                    the world.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) was being printed by
                        Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>).</note> There Senhora will be something for you to smile at. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> says it will be a famous common sense book, &amp; I think Rickmans common sense
                    opinions, thoroughly sound &amp; thoroughly sensible as they always are, worth more than those of almost any, or every body, else.
                    I have had no room for any thing about music or painting. But if this book sells my friend shall travel again &#8211; my memory &amp;
                    mind are not half discharged of their load.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> There were only three editions of
                            <title>Letters from England</title> (1807, 1808 and 1814). Southey never expanded the first edition nor followed it up
                        with a sequel, and Miss Barker&#8217;s information on music and painting was never used.</note> Other news is that Palmerin<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> that is my part of it will be compleated this week; it will be published about the same time as Espriella, or
                    perhaps sooner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you bring <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughter</ref> a box of Tunbridge ware. plain &#8211;
                    i.e. without any paint. This letter has been left unfinished since last night for the sake of recollecting commissions. They are
                    as follows. 1. some cardfish<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Small metal counters used in various card games.</note> &#8211; 3
                    dozen flat fish (I known not under what genus to class them) &#8211; &amp; one dozen round or square ones, to serve as whist-markers,
                    &amp; as half-dozens at other games. 2dly &#8211; Do you remember my ivory tablets which spread like a fan? They have long since been
                    broken &amp; I in consequence long in want of what really was highly useful to me in my walks. You may chuse them either with
                    ivory or tortoise-shell covers at your own taste. They are old-fashioned things, &amp; to be got I believe only at the same shops
                    where they sell chess-men &amp; ivory tackle of other kinds. &#8211; Thirdly &#8211; any kind of kickwomanjiggery<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning fancy work, or decorative materials.</note> necessary for the completion of certain card boxes &amp; not procurable here, fourthly &#8211; a stand
                    of cruets or crewits for heavens knows the orthography of the word. this is an awkward thing to send for, but one cannot get it
                    here &#8211; the plainer &amp; cheaper the better &#8211; one of the red-leather ones. &amp; lastly an urn-rug if such things are to be
                    bought, or if not, the materials for working one, this being a thing of the first necessity. &#8211; There Senhora is a mornings
                    work-full of commissions for you. &#8211; We are beginning to make our habitation decent, looking upon it now as a resting place, &amp;
                    little by little to get every thing decent about us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now the sooner you come the better &#8211; the earlier in June the finer will be the sunsets &#8211; &amp; of these (I repeat
                    it) neither you nor any body can form any conception. The earlier you come the more useful will you be at home in a wet day, &amp;
                    the later may you stay out sketching on a fine evening. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> study
                    will be at your service tho I suppose the <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Beaumonts</ref> will try to take up their
                    lodgement with <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> if they purpose making any stay at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. This however is not very likely, as I believe I am no very great favorite, &amp;
                    not likely to become so. My Lady the first time I saw her put out the horns of her amiability full butt against me &#8211; like a snail
                    after a shower, &#8211; upon which the horns of my agrea-<hi rend="ital">beau</hi>ness instinctively drew in, &amp; I got into my shell:
                    &amp; a plaguey rough shell I dare say she thinks it. And there I sat, when last in town I dined with them one day, open mouthed
                    as an oyster at ebb, &amp; as silent too, being in truth miserably ill. But Senhora I have a good faculty of not talking much to
                    people whom I am not fond of, &#8211; now &amp; then indeed, the Devil has tempted me with his damned Ephthatha,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mark 7:34 &#8211; &#8216;And looking up to heaven, he sighed and said to him, &#8220;Ephphatha&#8221;, which is &#8220;be
                        opened&#8221;&#8217;.</note> but not very often, &amp; not very lately &#8211; &amp; I defy him &amp; all his works.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> A Deos &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-05-12">Tuesday May 12. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>