<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1126</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2248</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                        Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 165&#8211;169. .  Previously  published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        347&#8211;350.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1126" type="letter">
        <head>1126. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1805-11-27">27 November
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/
                        Staffordshire<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                        Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 165&#8211;169. <lb />Previously published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        347&#8211;350.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have written sooner to you but for the daily expectation of hearing farther tidings &#8211; &amp; the
                    uncomfortable uncertainty which the disappointment occasions. &#8211; However it is a wise practical maxim that no news is good news
                    &amp; I shall write in that belief.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> First &amp; foremost we have to thank you for a pine apple &amp; a side of venison which was very good, &amp;
                    indeed is so still, for there is a good hash remaining. If these things come from <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward</ref> himself &#8211; I beg you will make my acknowledgments in suitable phrase.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly I have to request help for D. Manuel Alvarez Espriella.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> Have you
                    a Cookery-Book? there is at the end of Mrs Glass &amp; all her succession, an admirable course of lessons in carving, from which I
                    want the appropriate terms of winging thighing, lifting, displaying &amp;c.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hannah Glasse
                        (bap. 1708&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Art of Cookery Made Plain and Easy</title> (1747). Carving methods are
                        referred to in Letter 73 of <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title>,
                        3 vols (London, 1807), III, p. 334.</note> It would be a woful blunder if I were to lift what I ought to unlace &amp; vice
                    versa. &#8211; In the next place I am going to write a letter about English music &amp; the fugues.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> contains no discussion of English music.</note> This will reach you on
                    Sunday, &amp; it is well you are not going to church, or you would laugh at this during the sermon; &#8211; but Senhora you must give me
                    the criticism &amp; the comparison &amp; I will give you the seasoning, &amp; when they who know me come to a wise dissertation
                    upon the state of our music &#8211; they will never suspect me &#8211; that&#8217;s pretty clear. Besides I have an anecdote or two, &amp; something
                    to say about musical Misses, &amp; the villainous words of the songs, &#8211; so do you supply what I really do not understand, &amp; we
                    will have a very good letter between us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What do you suppose poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has taken it into his head to send me from
                    the West Indies by way of a useful present? &#8211; a turtle!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The turtle did not reach <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, but died in quarantine; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806,
                        Letter 1140.</note> The inconceivable absurdity of sending me a turtle, &amp; the utter dismay of the women to think what was
                    to be done with it kept me full half an hour laughing. Yes &#8211; he tells me a passenger has promised to look to it on the voyage,
                    &amp; see it shipt on board the coach from London to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. I wrote immediately to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> begging him to look after the beast.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 24 November 1805, Letter 1125.</note> &amp; eat him out of my way &#8211; if indeed the
                    Captain has not done it already. Upon my word when I see how venison &amp; turtle &amp; pineapples come in upon me I begin to
                    think I am not in my proper situation, &amp; that I really ought to be Lord Mayor of London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a monthly review of Madoc in which Envy Hatred &amp; Malice are exhibited stark mad and stark naked. &#8211; the
                    work of some unsuccessful author who fancies that I have reviewed him severely.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish physician who practised medicine in Manchester and often contributed
                        articles to the <title>Monthly Review</title>, including this one on Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> (1805). See <title>Monthly
                            Review</title> (October 1805), n.s. 48, 113&#8211;122.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My campaign is now fairly begun, &amp; today the first parcel has been packed off for <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref>. In this the make-weights for the second Vol. of Poems are gone. by the by
                    this puts me in mind to say that in giving the list of my operas to Sir E. you should make him understand that the Poems should
                    not be purchased till this new edition comes out &#8211; else the Vision will be had twice over.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published in 1806, with the &#8216;Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217; &#8211; originally
                        published in the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799) &#8211; printed at the end of the poem. The new 1806 edition of the
                            <title>Poems</title> omitted &#8216;The Vision&#8217; and filled the gap with these &#8216;makeweights&#8217;: &#8216;Translation of a Greek Ode on
                        Astronomy, written for the prize at Cambridge, 1793&#8217; (pp. 3&#8211;9); &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217; (pp. 13&#8211;22); &#8216;To Hymen&#8217; (pp. 25&#8211;39);
                        &#8216;Remembrance&#8217; (pp. 40&#8211;43); &#8216;To Recovery&#8217; (pp. 49&#8211;51); &#8216;Youth and Age&#8217; (pp. 52&#8211;53); &#8216;The Traveller&#8217;s Return&#8217; (pp. 54&#8211;55);
                        &#8216;Autumn&#8217; (pp. 56&#8211;58); &#8216;The Destruction of Jerusalem&#8217; (pp. 59&#8211;62); &#8216;The Spanish Armada&#8217; (pp. 63&#8211;66); &#8216;St Bartholomew&#8217;s Day&#8217;
                        (pp. 67&#8211;69); &#8216;To a Bee&#8217; (pp. 74&#8211;75); &#8216;Metrical Letter&#8217;, pp. 76&#8211;79. For the alterations, see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical
                            Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), I.</note> I say this because any person
                    thus paying twice &#8211; for the same thing might very naturally blame me for an arrangement which is not mine, &amp; which is really a
                    good one. &#8211; So you see I am clearing off, &#8211; &amp; the work goes on with more good will because it is to be the last of the kind.
                    Something has been done to Espriella since you went. &#8211; It seems quite certain that Bedfords delays<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was growing impatient over delays by <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
                        in their jointly-compiled anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> will compel me to go to
                    London as soon as the reviewing is over. The journey will be very unpleasant &amp; attended with some expence; tho when in town I
                    shall find enough business, meaning certainly to show my Spanish friend every thing, that he may relate what he has himself seen.
                    Besides this my resolution is made up about the Cid.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> Any thing which can be spared from my history<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> should be spared for the sake of reducing
                    its bulk. &#8211; &amp; this story will be the better for having room. I am writing to Bristol for the two Chronicles &amp; a book of
                        Ballads,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his letter to Danvers, dated 28 November 1805 (letter 1128), Southey
                        requested the following from Bristol: <title>Chronica de Espana (las Quarto Partes Enteras de la) que Mand&#243; Componer el Rey D.
                            Alfonso el Sabio</title> (1541), a history book written on the initiative of Alfonso X (1221&#8211;1284; King of Castile
                        1252&#8211;1284), which was no. 3338 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043&#8211;1099),
                            <title>Chronica de la Famoso Cavallero Cid Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593), no. 3344 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library; Lorenzo de Sep&#250;lveda (fl. 1551), <title>Romances Sacados de Historias Antiguas de la Chronica de Espana</title>
                        (1566), no. 3448.</note> &#8211; shall do here all that can be done from the chief documents, &amp; hunt in the Museum &amp; in <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Hollands</ref> library for additional notes. This little volume will like
                        Amadis<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> be
                    praised by the Reviews, who are graciously pleased to allow that I do understand Spanish, &amp; can translate very well. This hurt
                    nobody, &#8211; what anybody <hi rend="ital">could</hi> do, anybody may do without incurring the displeasure of the world. Common
                    Readers are the worst of all Levellers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I repented that I had not accompanied you to Kendal &amp; seen you into the mail, &amp; the uncertainty whether you
                    found room in it or not was my punishment. You are missed, &#8211; still more in my study than below stairs. Your litter was become part
                    of the furniture of the room, &amp; I never like to lose what is become familiar. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My
                        daughter</ref> talks of you usually every morning. it is one of her first operations to talk over all her acquaintance, what
                    they gave her, &amp; where they are, with sometimes a trait of their characters &#8211; as in your case. Barter &#8211; tums &#8211; nuff &#8211; don away
                    &#8211; sorry. this is her speech concerning you, &amp; you will perceive in it all the elements of a character &amp; an eulogium. She
                    also talks of you when she looks at the tree on the screen, or the black sealing wax on her box. In addition to her love for the
                    fine arts She has learnt to love story telling, &amp; now the first thing in the morning is like the Sultan of the Indies<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Shahry&#257;r, the Persian king in the popular <title>Arabian Nights</title> who demands that
                        Scheherazade tells him a new story every night.</note> to call upon her bedfellow for one of his pretty stories &#8211; &amp; I am
                    obliged to talk to her &amp; sing to her till I am thoroughly awake. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Take my last song &#8211; </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Over the water, &amp; over the water</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Together we go, papa &amp; his daughter. </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Where do we go-a, where do we go-a? &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Over the water to pretty Lisboa &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Over the water together we go</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> To the land where the grapes &amp; the oranges grow.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> &amp; so God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-11-27">Thursday. Nov. 27. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>