<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1049</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2171</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 71.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 317&#8211;321 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1049" type="letter">
        <head>1049. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1805-03-22">22 March
                        1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ Mar./ 22./ 1805 <lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS 71<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 317&#8211;321 [in
                    part].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I never learnt the Memoria Technica<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A system for assisting the memory
                        pioneered by Richard Grey (1694&#8211;1771) in <title>Memoria Technica, or a New Method of Artificial Memory, Applied to and
                            Exemplified in Chronology, History, Geography, Astronomy, Also Jewish, Grecian and Roman Coins, Weights, etc.</title>
                        (1730).</note> &#8211; but if I should ever have a son he shall. &#8211; When is the earliest mention of the Mariners Compass?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The earliest references date from the second half of the twelfth century in China and
                        Europe.</note> &#8211; I have no better reference than a chronological table at the end of a womans dictionary &#8211; which says invented
                    or improved by Gioia of Naples AD. 1302.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Flavio Gioja or Gioia (c. 1300) was credited with
                        inventing the mariner&#8217;s compass by suspending the needle over a design on which the cardinal points were indicated. Modern
                        scholarship doubts Flavio&#8217;s existence.</note> Now have I just found it mentioned in the Laws of Alonso the Wise, which laws
                    were begun AD 1251 &amp; finished in seven years,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alfonso X (1221&#8211;1284), known as &#8216;El
                        Sabio&#8217; or &#8216;the Wise&#8217;, was king of Castile, Le&#243;n and Galicia from 1252 until his death. The <title>Siete Partidas</title>
                        (Seven-Part Code) or <title>Libro de las Leyes</title>, a comprehensive legal code, was compiled during his reign. No. 3610 of
                        the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was <title>Las Siete Partidas del Sabio Rey Don Alonso el Nono</title> (1789).</note>
                    &#8211; &amp; it is not mentioned as any thing new, but made use of as an illustration &#8211; you can understand the Spanish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; assi como los marineros se guiar en la noche escura por el aguja, que los es medianera entre la piedra e las
                    estrella, e les muestra por do vayan.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish translates as: &#8216;as mariners find their
                        way in the dark night with the needle, which stands between the stone and the stars, and shows them where they are
                        going&#8217;.</note> &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I suspect that this implies a belief in some specific virtue in the North star as if the magnetic influence flowed
                    from it. &#8211; this however is matter for more enquiry, &amp; I will one day look into it in Raymund Lully &amp; Albertus Magnus,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ramon Llull (anglicised as Raymond Lully; 1232&#8211;1315), a Majorcan philosopher, and author of
                            <title>Arte de Navegar</title> (1295) which described the use of compasses in navigation. St Albertus Magnus
                        (1193/1206&#8211;1280), a German Aristotelian philosopher. His <title>Opera Omnia</title> (1651) included works of geography and
                        astronomy.</note> &#8211; likely authors. &#8211; The passage certainly <del>xxx</del> carries the use of the needle half a century
                    farther back than this poor chronology &#8211; but whether I have made what antiquarians call a discovery &#8211; is more than I can tell.
                    Robertson ought to have found it &#8211; for to write his introduction to Charles 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; without reading these Laws,
                    is one of the thousand &amp; one omissions for which he ought to be called rogue <del>to the</del> as long as his volumes
                        last.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Robertson (1721&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>), historian, about whose
                        writings Southey was habitually dismissive. Here he refers to Robertson&#8217;s <title>History of the Reign of the Emperor Charles
                            the Fifth</title> (1769).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These Partidas as they are called are often very amusing.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note
                        4.</note> I am about a quarter thro them &#8211; some way as they fill three folios by help of a <del>xxxxxxx</del> commentary. They
                    are divided into 7 parts for about 7 times 7 such reasons as would have delighted D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Slop,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A character in Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life &amp; Opinions of
                            Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759&#8211;1767) whose arrival at Shandy Hall at the start of the second volume of the novel
                        leads to speculation on the minute divisions of time.</note> &amp; K Alfonso has ingeniously settled the orthography of his
                    name by beginning each of the seven parts with one of the seven letters which compose it, in succession. &#8211; his Majesty gives
                    direction that no young prince should dip their fingers into the dish in an unmannerly way &#8211; so as to grease themselves &#8211; &amp;
                    expatiates on the advantage which they may derive from reading &amp; writing &#8211; if they are able to learn those arts. He was
                    himself an extraordinary man. Too fond of study to be a good king in a barbarous age. &#8211; but therefore not only a more interesting
                    character to posterity, but a more useful one in the long run.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see in the Madociana a story how Alexander went down in a diving bell to see what was going on among the
                    fishes, &#8211; remarkable because it is found in Spanish, German &amp; <hi rend="ital">Welsh</hi> romance of the middle ages.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s discussion of the sources of the story of the diving bell; see Southey to
                        John Rickman, 29 April 1804, Letter 929. The story appears in the notes to <title>Madoc</title>, Part 1, Book 11, 106 where
                        Merlin is credited with having a &#8216;crystal Ark&#8217;. See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda
                        Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, pp. 78, 303&#8211;306, 581.</note> I have since found a similar story of somebody else among the
                    Malays &#8211; who certainly did not get it from Europe &#8211; or Alexander (Iscander)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander the
                        Great (356&#8211;323 BC) was reputed to have used a diving bell. In <title>Madoc</title> Southey cites the thirteenth-century author
                        Joan Lorenzo Segura de Astorga (dates unknown), <title>Libro de Alexandre</title> as a source of the story.</note> would have
                    been their hero also. The number of good stories of all kinds which are common to the Orientals &amp; Europeans, are more likely
                    to have been brought home by peaceable travellers than by the Crusaders. I suspect the Jew-pedlars were the great literary
                    go-betweens. They always went every where. &#8211; all the world over you found Jew merchants &amp; Jew physicians. Wherever there is
                    any thing to be got no danger deters a Jew from venturing. I myself saw two fellows at Evora<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey passed through Evora, Portual, on donkey-back in April 1801. See letter 577 of this edition.</note> &#8211;
                    under the very nose of the Inquisition &#8211; who if they had any noses could not have been mistaken their game &#8211; I knew the cut of
                    their jibs at once &#8211; &amp; upon enquiring what they had for sale was told &#8211; green spectacles. A history of the Jews since their
                    dispersion in the shape of a chronological Bibliotheca would be a very valuable work &#8211; I want an Academy established to bespeak
                    such works, &amp; reward them well according to the diligence wherewith they shall be executed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The abuses &#8211; or main abuses of Printing spring from one evil. it almost immediately made authorship a trade. &#8211;
                        <del>x xxxxxx</del> per sheeting was in use as early as Martin Luthers<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Luther
                        (1483&#8211;1546), Protestant reformer and prolific author, whose works were widely distributed by the then new medium of
                        print.</note> time, who mentions the price, &#8211; a curious fact. The Reformation <del>xxx</del> did one great mischief, &#8211; in
                    destroying the Monastic Orders it deprived us of the only bodies of men <del>xxxxxx</del> who could not possibly be injured by
                    this change which literature had undergone. They could have no <hi rend="ital">peculium</hi>,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Property that, under Roman law, a master allowed his slave, or a father his child, to hold as his own.</note>
                    &#8211; they laboured hard for amusement, &#8211; the society had funds to spare for printing, &amp; felt a pride in this disposing of them to
                    the reputation of their order &#8211; We laugh at the ignorance of these orders, but [MS obscured] the most worthless &amp; most
                    ignorant of them <del>xxxxxx</del> produced more works of <del>xxxx</del> erudition than all the English &amp; all the Scotch
                    Universities since the Reformation, &#8211; &amp; it is my firm belief that a man of learning may at this day find better society in a
                    Benedictine monastery than he could at Cambridge &#8211; certainly better than he could at Oxford. You know I am no friend to Popery or
                    to Monachism. but if the Irish Catholics are to be emancipated, I would let them found Convents &#8211; only restricting them from
                    taking the vows till after a certain age, as Catharine did in Russia.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine II, &#8216;the
                        Great&#8217; (1729&#8211;1796, Empress of Russia 1762&#8211;1796), in a bid to diminish the influence of the church, secularised the property of
                        the Orthodox church in 1764 and placed limitations on Catholics in 1769.</note> tho perhaps it may be as well to encourage any
                    thing which would diminish the <del>xxxxx</del> Patrician<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A pun on the common Irish
                        Catholic Christian name of Patrick.</note> breed. The good would be that they would get the country cultivated, &amp; serve as
                    good inns, &amp; gradually civilise it. As the island unluckily is theirs &amp; there is no getting the Devil to remove it any
                    where else &#8211; we had better employ the Pope to set it to rights.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want to see petitions from the poor people of England against the salt tax. &amp; am sure good use might be made
                    of it to render that wretch unpopular.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806;
                        <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806, and Chancellor of the
                        Exchequer, in which capacity he moved for a bill to raise the duty on salt, on 19 February 1805.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> has forsaken the Critical &#8211; because it has fallen into
                    the hands of one Hunt, an orthodox, conceited, preferment-hunting, Cambridge fellow.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Higgs Hunt (1780&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>) gained, while an undergraduate at Cambridge, the University&#8217;s Browne medal for a
                        Latin ode. He graduated M.A. in 1804, and was elected a fellow of Trinity College. He was joint-editor of the <title>Critical
                            Review</title> from 1805&#8211;1807, with Joseph Mawman (1763&#8211;1827). Southey had been called &#8216;an egregious poetical coxcomb&#8217; in
                        a review of his <title>Metrical Tales</title> (1805) in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 3rd series, 4 (February 1805),
                        118&#8211;121 (118).</note> such is the character he gives of him. My book will suffer by the change.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning <title>Madoc</title> (1805) would be badly reviewed there. Indeed <title>Madoc</title> was negatively
                        reviewed by Charles Valentine Le Grice (1773&#8211;1858) in the <title>Critical Review</title>, new series, 7 (1806), 72&#8211;83.</note>
                    The Annual<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Review</title>, for which Southey worked as a reviewer from
                        1802&#8211;1808.</note> is probably delayed by this insurrection among the printers. authors are the only journeymen who cannot
                    continue, &#8211; too poor to hold out, &amp; too useless to be bought in.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1805 journeymen
                        printers were paid by master printers per job, rather than by the day or week, according to a complicated scale of prices.
                        Disputes about the scale were settled when a joint committee was set up with equal representation of masters and
                        journeymen.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you get the remainder of my books &amp;c from <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref>? &#8211;
                    They are in some danger where they are of being lost or injured. &#8211; And can you send me one or two of the choicer Election reports,
                    &#8211; Aylesbury &#8211; Ivelchester &#8211; &amp; Nottingham. &#8211; for I am at intervals getting together as ways &amp; means extraordinary for the
                    year, all <del>xxxx</del> I know &amp; much of what I speculate about this country of ours, in the form of Travels by Don Manuel
                    Alvares Espriella<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). Letter 48 discusses
                        elections in England.</note> &#8211; translated. This is a secret to every body in London except to you &amp; <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>, &#8211; he is to furnish certain letters,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Duppa wrote several passages of <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807). The description of the monuments in Westminster Abbey, in Letter 23, is an example of his
                        contribution.</note> &#8211; &amp; you shall see the whole &amp; mend &amp; make at your pleasure. It is likely to be a good book,
                    &amp; not a bad adventure. These said reports will furnish good matter for the chapter upon Elections, &#8211; I am sadly in want of
                    topographical history, &#8211; &amp; when I come to London with my work taylor like, shall probably find those Beauties of England
                        useful;<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Beauties of England and Wales</title> (1801&#8211;1818) was a series of lavishly-illustrated accounts of the historical
                        features of Britain, produced by John Britton (1771&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), an antiquary, with his friend Edward Wedlake
                        Brayley (1773&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in such parts of the manu-matter-of-factory, which must have place for
                    verisimilitude-sake, but which must be as brief as may be for every reason.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaven knows what is become of Madoc! the press is a long while parturient with so mighty a birth. &#8211; I reckon upon
                    our expulsion from Lisbon as certain, if Gibralter be besieged.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the event the British
                        garrison and fleet preserved Gibraltar from attack from the French and Spanish fleets. Britain and Portugal remained allied,
                        and it was not until 1807 that French armies invaded Portugal from Spain.</note> It is worth while to take Minorca for the
                    war, &#8211; &amp; I should think Ceuta for ever.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain had invaded and taken Minorca in
                        1798, handing it back to Spain at the Treaty of Amiens in 1802. It did not take Minorca again, instead using Malta as its
                        Mediterranean base. Britain did not take Ceuta, a Spanish town on the African side of the Straits of Gibraltar.</note> Those
                    Gun boats almost drive our sailors mad &#8211; so mischievous in attack &#8211; so insignificant when attacked &#8211; a gnat with a mortal
                    sting.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Vale.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-03-22">March 22. 1805</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>