<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1188</idno><idno type="nines">rce2310</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), III, pp. 40–42 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1188" type="letter"><head>1188. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1806-05-27">27 May 1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: 27 May <del>1826</del> 1806<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), III, pp. 40–42 [in part].</note></head><p rend="indent1"> A discovery of the original language, propounded to the consideration of the worshipful &amp; right worthy Master
                    Bedford</p><p rend="indent1"> There was in old times a King of Egypt who did make a full politick experiment touching this question, as is
                    discoursed of by sundry antique authors; Howbeit to me it seemeth that it falleth short of that clear &amp; manifest truth,
                    &lt;the which&gt; should be the butt of our enquiry. Now methinks, if it could be shown what is the very language which dame
                    Nature, the common mother of all, hath implanted in animals whom we, foolishly misjudging, do term dumb, that were indeed a hit
                    palpable, &amp; of notable import. To this effect I have noted <del>Latin</del> what that silly bird <del>who</del> called of the
                    Latins Anas doth utter in time of affright; for it then thinketh of the water, inasmuch as in the water it findeth its safety,
                    &amp; while its thoughts be upon the water so greatly desired of it, it cryeth qua-a-qua-a-qua, wherefore it is to be inferred
                    that <hi rend="ital">aqua</hi> is the very natural word for water, &amp; the Latin therefore the primitive, natural, &amp;
                    original tongue.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s own words.</note></p><p rend="center">–––———</p><p rend="indent1"> Etymology is of most value when applied to the elements of language &amp; it must be acknowledged that I have
                    &lt;here&gt; hit upon an elementary word. </p><p rend="indent1"> One of those critics, I forget which, who thought proper to review Thalaba<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 3, line 441; see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), III, p. 52.</note> without taking the trouble to understand the story, <del>xxxx xxx</del>
                    noticed, as one of the absurdities of the book that Thalaba was enabled to read <del>as</del> &lt;some&gt; unintelligible letters
                    on a ring by others equally unintelligible upon the head of a locust; an absurdity existing only in their own stupid &amp;
                    careless misconception, for the thing is clear enough. I remember giving myself credit for putting a very girlish sort of thing in
                    Oneizas mouth when I made her call those locust lines Natures own language,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Words spoken
                        by Oneiza, a character in Southey’s poem <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, Book 3, line 441.</note> – for I have heard
                    unthinking people talk of a natural language – &amp; you know the story of the woman with child &lt;by a Dutchman&gt; who was
                    afraid to swear the child to an Englishman because the truth would be found out when the child came to speak Dutch. </p><p rend="indent1"> The inclosed is inclosed<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter to Thomas Southey, for which see Southey
                        to Thomas Southey, 22 May 1806, Letter 1186.</note> because your brother <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref>
                    offered to send it from the Admiralty as a surer conveyance than the very uncertain one of the Packets.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiralty records concerning the court martial of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>.
                        In January 1805 Southey learned that his brother had been found guilty at court martial of contempt of a senior officer and
                        dismissed his ship. The circumstances of the offence were such that Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet
                        (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>), who was in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey served, promptly appointed him to a
                        finer ship.</note> He will know probably if the Amelia be to come with the May convoy, as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has some hopes she may.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey was serving in the West India fleet
                        in HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> under Captain William Charles Fahie (1763–1833).</note> In this case let it lie in your
                    desk till he reaches England.</p><p rend="indent1"> I beseech you to come to me this season. We shall see more of each other in one week when once housed together than
                    during a seven years <del>xx xxxx</del> intercourse in London. And if you do not come this year the opportunity may be gone for
                    ever, &amp; you will never see this country so well, nor so cheerfully, after I have left it. If he were here – would be
                        <del>the</del> &lt;a&gt; thought to damp enjoyment. you would come as a mere Laker, &amp; pay a guide for telling you what to
                    admire. When I go abroad it will be to remain there for a <del>a</del> considerable time, &amp; you &amp; I are now old enough to
                    feel <del>there</del> the proportion which a few years bear to the not-very-many that constitute the utmost length of life. This
                    feeling is the stronger upon me just now, as in <del>x</del> arranging my letters I have <del>seen</del> seen those of three
                        <del>xxxx</del> men <del>who are</del> &lt;now&gt; all in their graves, <del>each</del> of whom produced no little effect upon
                    my character &amp; after life, – <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> – <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> and poor <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>, whom I never remember without the deepest
                    love &amp; veneration. Come you to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> Bedford &amp; make &lt;<del>xx</del>&gt; sure
                    of a few weeks of enjoyment while we are both alive. </p><p rend="indent1"> I wish you would get the Annual Reviews – because without them my Operas are very incompleat.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey contributed to the <title>Annual Review</title> from 1802–1808.</note> my share there is
                    very considerable. <del>xx</del> you would see in many of the articles more of the tone &amp; temper of my mind than you can
                    otherwise get at, &amp; as it is my belief that you would like to know it in all its bearings, so is it my wish that you should.
                    You must be my biographer if I go first. Except <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> nobody has known me so long.
                    &amp; as I am born to be biographized I certainly wish it should be done by one who does know me. Documents you shall have in
                    plenty, if indeed you need more than our correspondence already supplies. This is a subject on which we will talk some evening,
                    when the sun is going down &amp; has tuned us to it. If the harp of Memnon<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Harp of
                        Memnon was thought to be concealed within the statue of an Egyptian pharoah and would make a sound when the first ray of
                        sunlight struck it in the morning.</note> had played in the evening instead of at the uprise, it would have been a sweet
                    emblem of <del>our highest</del> that state of mind to which I now refer – &amp; which indeed I am at this minute enjoying –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> But it is supper time –</salute><signed rend="indent2"> God bless you, Grosvenor!</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-05-27">May 27. 1806.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>