<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1120</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2242</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 353&#8211;354 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1120" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1120" type="letter">
        <head>1120. Robert Southey to Thomas Southey, <date when="1805-11-15">15&#8211;18 November [1805]</date>
          </head><p>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ NOV 21/ 1805<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 353&#8211;354 [in part]. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1805-11-15">Friday. Nov. 15.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two letters have reached me since my last.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 1
                        October 1805, Letter 1108.</note> One of August 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> by packet, four days ago. one with a postscript dated
                        Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 22. by the Africaine<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Royal Navy frigate, HMS <hi rend="ital">Africaine</hi> (or <hi rend="ital">l&#8217;Africaine</hi>) had been captured from the French in 1801, an engagement
                        in which Tom participated.</note> this evening Thank you for the profile, &#8211; it is like, but not very like, &#8211; the failure is in
                    the forehead, &#8211; still it is a likeness &amp; I set more value upon it than I shall express.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &amp; 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Annual Reviews,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey sent copies of the <title>Annual Review</title>, containing his articles, to Thomas. These are for the years 1803 and
                        1804.</note> long delayed for want of opportunity are gone by the Trusty, Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> White, to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jackson Barbadoes, from Bristol.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Trusty</hi> was a Royal
                        Navy 50-gun, fourth rate, ship of the line, built in 1782 and broken up in 1815. Captain White and Mr Jackson are
                        untraced.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> has added a set of Couriers<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Courier</title> newspaper, edited by T. G. Street (dates unknown) and in which <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref> had an interest.</note> to the Parcel. he says he has not heard from
                    you, &amp; really wishes you to write. &#8211; All well must be the first news. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has been returned to Edinburgh about ten days. the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">young one</ref>
                    learns new words &amp; new ways daily &amp; becomes rather an expensive play fellow by encroaching upon her fathers time. I have
                    just begun my campaign with the annual authors,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, his reviewing work for the
                            <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> &#8211; it is to be my last; for if the state of Europe permits, &amp; no ill-fortune
                    should prevent, I go certainly next year to Lisbon, probably not before the autumn.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s intended visit to Portugal did not occur.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> urges this to which I am sufficiently inclined. a stay of between two
                    &amp; three years will enable me to collect all the materials necessary,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, never completed.</note> &amp; well nigh as much as the country can furnish. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> does not like the thought of going, but she goes; as for my daughter she will
                    delight in the figs &amp; oranges, &amp; learn Portugueze to teach her mother.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc has been reviewed in the Edinburgh in a very amusing tone of superiority on the part of the reviewer,
                    softened down with plenty of personal civility &amp; compliment.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis Jeffrey</ref> reviewed <title>Madoc</title> (1805) in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 1&#8211;29.</note> I met the author of this article at Edinburgh, <del>he</del> it was then
                    printed &#8211; but not published he sent it me that I might meet him or not as I felt inclined. this was done in a manly &amp;
                    gentlemanlike way. We met with perfect good humour on my part, &amp; a conversation ensued after supper <hi rend="ital">at</hi>
                    the matter not <hi rend="ital">about</hi> it, in which if <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> himself was not
                    convinced that he was sitting by the side of a man half a foot taller than himself, &amp; as much above him in every thing else, I
                    should conceive that he left the room with a different opinion from others in company. He has been here since &amp; supt with me,
                    &amp; the next time that any of my books come under his hands, in all probability I shall perceive the good effects of this
                    acquaintance. &#8211; In the Supplement to the Monthly Magazine is a longer notice of Madoc than is usually given there of any thing &#8211;
                    by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Taylor reviewed <title>Madoc</title> in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 19 (July 1805), 656&#8211;658.</note> I have in my desk
                    his review of it for the next Annual<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor&#8217;s review of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in
                        the <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806), 604&#8211;613.</note> &#8211; sent for my previous comments, to see how far I
                    consider the criticisms well founded. It is an excellent article, with much of his peculiarity &amp; more of his peculiar genius.
                    &#8211; Of the sale I know nothing since the first tidings, that in six weeks above half have been sold; if the whole 500 be gone in a
                    year, or year &amp; half, or even two years, it will be much for so expensive a book. Its ultimate reputation is certain. Since
                    the Paradise Lost no poem of equal, or comparable merit has appeared &#8211; so says <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>, &amp; I shall not affect not to be of the same opinion. &#8211; A third edition of Joan of Arc
                    is just published &#8211; with the Vision at the end, &amp; many corrections, tho none which you would perceive without comparing it
                    with the former copy.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> was published in
                        1806, with the &#8216;Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217; &#8211; originally published in the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799) &#8211;
                        printed at the end of the poem. For the alterations, see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), I.</note> It is however very materially amended. I am supplying the place of the Vision in
                    the second Vol. of Poems with the Retrospect &amp; sundry smaller pieces of little value.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In the new 1806 edition of the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799), Southey included two poems first published in his
                        and <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Robert Lovell&#8217;s</ref> joint collection <title>Poems</title> (1795), &#8216;The
                        Retrospect&#8217; and &#8216;To Hymen&#8217;, as well as the <title>Monthly Magazine</title> poem &#8216;Hannah, a Plaintive Tale&#8217;. See <title>Robert
                            Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V.</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> sleeps over the Specimens<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s and Bedford&#8217;s jointly edited <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, which was
                        published in 1807.</note> &amp; will probably oblige me to go to London to take them out of his hands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> During the winter, in the intervals of reviewing, the Spaniard will be finished.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> I am well
                    pleased with what is done. it will be a very curious &amp; extraordinary book, but were you at my elbow it would be better. It is
                    also my intention before I leave England to publish the story of the Cid<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published in 1808.</note> in a little volume, &#8211; better so than comprest into an
                    episodical introductory chapter to my history,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, never
                        completed.</note> which wants no matter that can be spared, &#8211; &amp; in a separate form sure of popularity &amp; of sale.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> has left the service a third time, &amp; was strutting about Bristol in
                    regimentals. he told <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> he was to be gazetted in a few days as Lieutenant in
                    the Caermarthenshire militia. &#8211; this was three months ago &amp; may very likely be true. he was then with his precious <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Aunt</ref>, &#8211; but it is no matter where he is, &#8211; there is no good in him, &amp; none can
                    come out of him. So thinks <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; so think I. &#8211; The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">Old Gentleman</ref> never noticed Madoc.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        hoped that his uncle, John Southey, who had accumulated a substantial fortune and was childless, would assist him financially
                        or leave him some of his estate in his will. He thought that favourable reviews of his works, such as <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805), would impress him and assist in this.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Captains name is so thoroughly outlandish that I cannot guess at it in your hand writing with any certainty &#8211;
                    is it Fahie &#8211; for so it seems to be &#8211; &amp; if so what do you call him &#8211; for I cannot tell how to pronounce it.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Charles Fahie (1763&#8211;1833).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have heard of Nelsons most glorious death.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Horatio, 1st Viscount
                        Nelson, 1st Duke of Bront&#233; (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), died at the Battle of Trafalgar on 21 October 1805.</note> The
                    feeling it occasioned is highly honourable to the country. He leaves a name above all former Admirals &#8211; with perhaps the single
                    exception of Blake,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Blake (bap. 1598, d. 1657), army officer and then naval
                        commander who played an important role in the first Anglo-Dutch war of 1652&#8211;1654, and the Spanish war of 1654&#8211;1657.</note> a
                    man who possessed the same genius upon great occasions. We ought to name the two best ships in the navy from these men. As for
                    peace there is no reason to expect it, yet will be none to be <del>xxx</del> surprized at it, if it should take place. In my last
                    I have urged you to get removed if you can &amp; come to Europe. Your chance of promotion was lost when Sir Samuel<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s commanding officer, Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet
                        (1762&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>). He was injured in action in September 1805 and posted back to England.</note> was
                        <del>xxx</del> superseded, &amp; the advantages which the station may possess for cruising are not to be set against the
                    hazards of a climate to which I fear you are not seasoned. Some sacrifice it is worth making to breathe a wholesomer air &amp; to
                    be within hearing &#8211; if not within sight of us. &#8211; If there should be peace while I am abroad I shall advise you to come to me, take
                    a journey in Portugal, &amp; so learn a language which you will find useful when you have a flag ship of your own, &amp; have
                    taken a Spanish Admiral prisoner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is not yet returned. he is even worse off for letters at Malta
                    than you in the West Indies. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has lately taken unto himself a <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Rickwoman</ref>. he tells me I shall have one person more to welcome me when I make my
                    next visit to him. It remains to be seen whether I like the Lady &#8211; &amp; what is the same thing whether she likes me before I can
                    tell whether this will make the house pleasanter to me, or not. But he is not a man to chuse ill, &amp; I know he has not been in
                    a hurry about it. &#8211; My last will have told you how I took up the baseness of your prize money in the Courier, &#8211; was answered by a
                    Spanish merchant &#8211; replied to him &#8211; &amp; was finally assured by the editor that I was mistaken, &amp; that the sailors were not
                    to suffer the slightest loss.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1804, the naval ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, of which Thomas Southey was a lieutenant, had captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and
                        the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden
                        with cotton. It was customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed
                        conflict, but in this case the prize money was contested because the ships were captured before war was officially declared.
                        Southey took up his brother&#8217;s cause to have his share reinstated in <title>The Courier</title> which published a paragraph
                        supporting the sailors&#8217; claim to the prize-money on Saturday 24 August 1805. This was followed by a longer defence of their
                        position in <title>The Courier</title> on 31 August 1805 under the title &#8216;Indemnification to the Spanish Merchants&#8217;. A &#8216;reply from a
                        Spanish merchant&#8217; appeared in <title>The Courier</title> for 6 September 1805. Southey&#8217;s response, that the prize money was
                        being withheld from the sailors in a measure that was &#8216;impolitic, ungenerous and unjust&#8217; was published in <title>The
                            Courier</title> of 25 September 1805, p. 2. This was refuted by an editorial article in <title>The Courier</title> of 28
                        September 1805, where it was stated that there was no truth in Southey&#8217;s assertion.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My trip to Edinburgh was pleasant. I went to accompany <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>. we
                    staid three days with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> at <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Ashiestiel</ref> &#8211; the name of his house, on the banks of the Tweed. I saw all the scenery of his Lay of the Last
                        Minstrel,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805).</note>
                    a poem which you will read with great pleasure when you come to England. I saw also Johnny Armstrongs Castle,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gilnockie tower on the Esk river, built by John (or &#8216;Johnny&#8217;) Armstrong (d. 1530), who was an
                        outlaw in the Scottish borders.</note> pleasant Tiviotdale, &amp; the Yarrow, all ballad ground &#8211; to me as interesting as
                    classical ground. &amp; I went salmon-spearing on the Tweed, in which tho I struck no fish, I <del>did</del> &lt;bore&gt; my part
                    &amp; managed one end of the boat with a long spear. We staid just a week at Edinburgh which is the finest city I ever beheld &#8211;
                    but notwithstanding this I came back blessing God that I was born on the right side of the Tweed. I saw the young Roscius<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Roscius&#8217; is a generic term for an actor, after the Roman actor, Quintus Roscius Gallus
                        (c. 126&#8211;62 BC), but here Southey is referring specifically to William Henry West Betty (1791&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>). He was
                        a child prodigy who made his London debut at Covent Garden in December 1804 and then proceeded on an extremely successful tour
                        of Scotland and England in the summer of 1805. The excitement about him, which led to him being hailed as the &#8216;Young Roscius&#8217;,
                        peaked during the 1804&#8211;1805 season, and then quickly faded.</note> at Edinburgh &#8211; an event in my life &#8211; because the older he
                    grows the less the wonder. Tho a little disappointed still I must say he is incomparably the best actor I have ever seen. &#8211; Having
                    had neither new coat nor hat since the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> was born &#8211; you may suppose I was
                    in want of both &#8211; so at Edinburgh I was to rig myself &#8211; &amp; moreover lay in new boots &amp; pantaloons. Howbeit on considering
                    the really respectable appearance which my old ones made for a traveller, &amp; considering moreover that as learning was better
                    than house or land, it certainly must be better than fine cloaths &#8211; I laid out all my money in books, &amp; came home to wear out
                    my old wardrobe in the winter. My library has had many additions since you left me, &amp; many gentlemen in parchment remain with
                    anonymous backs till you come &amp; bedeck them<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s family members helped to
                        preserve his books by covering them. Because flowered chintz material was often used, Southey referred to these books as his
                        &#8216;Cottonian Library&#8217; after the great library amassed by Sir Robert Bruce Cotton (1571&#8211;1631; <title>DNB</title>) in the
                        seventeenth century, which formed the basis of the British Museum.</note> &#8211; From your last letter I am not without hopes that
                    you may have taken some steps towards getting to Europe &#8211; in that case it is not absolutely impossible that you may yet reach this
                    place before we quit it, &amp; that you may <del>xxx</del> make the circumnavigation of the Lake in my company. I am an
                    experienced boatman, &amp; what is better recline in the boat sometimes like a bashaw<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Anglicised form of the Turkish title &#8216;pasha&#8217;.</note> while the women row me: <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is an excellent hand at the oar. her love.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-11-18">Monday. Nov. 18.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>