<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1183</idno><idno type="nines">rce2305</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1183" type="letter"><head>1183. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1806-05-21">21 May 1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/>Endorsement:
                        21 May 1806<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1806-05-21">Wednesday 21 May 1806 </date></dateline><salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I will answer your letter as soon as I have said what is uppermost in my head. I want of you to do three things for
                    D. Manuel.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella;
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> the one will cost you no more trouble than just to walk into
                    Westminster Abbey, if your memory like mine wants freshening, &amp; describe for me such of the tombs are most remarkable – in
                    particular Sir Cloudesly Shovel<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The death of Admiral of the Fleet, Sir Cloudesley Shovell
                        (1650–1707; <title>DNB</title>), in a shipwreck, is commemorated in Westminster Abbey in a large marble monument. He is
                        depicted lying on a couch dressed in Roman armour, with a relief of the shipwreck at the base of the monument. The monument is
                        not described in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> – M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thynne who is looking out of a coach
                        window,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Thynne (1647/8–1682; <title>DNB</title>) was murdered while travelling
                        in his coach. His body was buried in Westminster Abbey under a large tombstone depicting his murder. The monument is not
                        described in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Nightingale.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In St Michael’s chapel of Westminster Abbey there is a monument commemorating Lady Elizabeth Nightingale
                        (1704–1731), the wife of Joseph Gascoigne (1695–1752), who assumed the surname of Nightingale on becoming heir to his kinsman
                        Sir Robert Nightingale. The monument, by the French sculptor, Louis Francois Roubiliac (1702/1705–1762) was installed in 1761
                        and it depicts Death in the figure of a skeleton aiming a dart at his victim, Elizabeth, while her husband tries to protect
                        her. It is not described in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> I want a brief &amp; sarcastic description. Tell me
                        <hi rend="ital">whose</hi> is the monument abreast of Newtons, that is the one which flanks the other side of the entrance to
                    the choir.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Newton (1642–1727; <title>DNB</title>) was interred in the nave of
                        Westminster Abbey, where an elaborate marble monument to him was erected in 1731. It depicts the reclining figure of Newton,
                        in classical dress, with his books and representative elements of astronomy. The other monument mentioned by Southey
                        commemorates James Stanhope, 1st Earl Stanhope (1673–1721; <title>DNB</title>), army officer, diplomat, and politician, who is
                        depicted reposing in Roman armour. Both designs were by the architect, William Kent (bap. 1686–1748; <title>DNB</title>) and
                        were executed by the sculptor, Michael Rysbrack (1694–1770). The monuments are described in <title>Letters from
                            England</title>, Letter 23.</note> Now do this I beseech you &amp; send me off your letter by tomorrows post, &amp; say
                    any thing of the Abbey besides which you like to say. Letter 18 – which is <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> is
                    the next which goes to press, &amp; I cannot finish the transcription till you add this help.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Letter 18 of <title>Letters from England</title> describes the English theatre.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Secondly write me a letter, <hi rend="ital">the sooner the better</hi>, describing Vauxhall,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Vauxhall Gardens, London, which was opened in 1661 and continued as a popular attraction until
                        1859. It was a venue for musical events, viewing artworks and performers and was famed for its night-time illuminations and
                        firework displays. It is not described in <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> where I have never been &amp; here you
                    may take your Frenchman, &amp; let D. Manuel repeat his remarks, as being thoroughly amused at his ignorance. <hi rend="ital">Date</hi> the letter, as I do not know when Vauxhall opens.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thirdly, go the first Sunday you can to the Swedenborgian – or New Jerusalem Chapel near S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    James’s Square, &amp; write to me about the service.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A religious movement that developed
                        from the teachings of Emanuel Swedenborg (1688–1772), a Swedish scientist and theologian, who claimed to have received a new
                        revelation from Jesus Christ. In 1788 his followers styled themselves ‘The New Church’. Southey’s account of Swedenborgianism
                        is given in Letter 62 of <title>Letters from England</title> (1807).</note></p><p rend="center">________</p><p rend="indent1"> I cannot tell why you prefer <del>blank</del> rhymed specimens to blank verse – use your own judgement about M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Robinson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Robinson (1757–1800; <title>DNB</title>): poet,
                        novelist, woman of fashion, courtesan, who contributed poetry to the <title>Morning Post</title>. She is not included in the
                            <title>Specimens</title>.</note> – only insert the inclosed which is hers, &amp; let me write the sketch.</p><p rend="indent1"> I know nothing of James Marriott<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir James Marriott (1730–1803;
                            <title>DNB</title>), judge and politician, who published verse in Robert Dodsley (1704–1764; <title>DNB</title>), ed.,
                            <title>A Collection of Poems by Several Hands</title>, 6 vols (1748–1758). Extracts of his poetry were included in
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, 375–382.</note> – say merely of him from
                    Poems printed in such a year.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HucksJoseph">Jos Hucks</ref> was a man whom I well knew poor fellow. his poems lie at <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> in the sitting parlour with papers to mark the specimens<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Hucks, the Cambridge undergraduate companion of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> on their walking tour of 1794, which he published an account of
                        in <title>A Pedestrian Tour of North Wales, in a Series of Letters</title> (1795). He also published <title>Poems</title> in
                        1798. Hucks does not appear in the <title>Specimens</title>, though Southey had included verse by him in the <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title>, 2 (1800), p. 50.</note> – <del>xx xxx xxxxxx xxxx xxxxxx xxxxx xxx xxxxxx</del> he died 1800 – &amp; I
                    shall &lt;say&gt; some thing about him.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am going to write for an account of Churchey<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Churchey (1747–1805;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Welsh poet who published <title>Poems and Imitations of the British Poets</title> in 1789. He is not included in
                            <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>
                    who knew something about him, his poems are in the Museum. Boswell<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Boswell
                        (1740–1795; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer, diarist, and biographer of Samuel Johnson.</note> never published any poems, &amp;
                    the three women may be omitted unless they fall in your way.</p><p rend="indent1"> Say of Bryan Edwards that he was the person who dressed up &lt;Mungo&gt; Parks book for the press, &amp; put in
                    those conclusions in favour of the Slave Trade, which made every person who was not in the secret wonder, as the facts in the
                    book, for Park was too honest a man to let them be tampered with, forces irresistibly upon every fair mind a directly opposite
                        conclusion.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bryan Edwards (1743–1800; <title>DNB</title>), planter and politician,
                        who wrote several books of West Indian history. He assisted in the preparation for publication of Mungo Park’s (1771–1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Interior Districts of Africa Performed … in 1795 and 1796</title> (1799).</note> Say also that
                    it was &lt;well&gt; said of B. Edward that he</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Half Penseroso, half allegro<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Allusions to Milton’s ‘L’Allegro’ and ‘Il
                        Penseroso’. Edwards published ‘The Negro’s Dying Speech on his being Executed for Rebellion in the Island of Jamaica’ in the
                        <title>Universal Magazine</title> (November 1777), and it was included in his later collection, <title>Poems, Written Chiefly
                            in the West Indies</title> (1792).</note></l><l rend="indent3"> Writes sonnets on his own dead negro.</l></lg><p rend="indent1">Wm Stevens shall be sent you &amp; <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref> also<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Bagshaw Stevens
                        (1756–1800; <title>DNB</title>), poet and diarist, who published <title>Poems, Consisting of Indian Odes and Miscellaneous
                            Pieces</title> in 1775 and a second volume of<title> Poems</title> in 1782; Amos Simon Cottle, author of <title>Icelandic
                            Poetry, or, The Edda of Saemund, Translated into English verse</title> (1797) which included a dedicatory poem by Southey.
                        Neither writer was included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> – &amp; now have I replied step by
                    step to all your enquiries. Except <del>the</del> to the death of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roberts<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Hayward Roberts (bap. 1734–1791; <title>DNB</title>), poet and Church of England clergyman, whose most
                        notable work was his long poem, <title>Judah Restored: a Poem, in Six Books</title> (1776), which served as inspiration for
                        Southey’s <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801). Roberts published an edition of <title>Poems</title> in 1774. Extracts
                        from his poetry are included in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, pp.
                        345–350.</note> – make a Mem. to desire <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> to ask Hallam this.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Hallam (1777–1859; <title>DNB</title>): historian and reviewer.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am very busy, running a race with the printer, &amp; if I do not keep pace with him the Constable will never keep
                    pace with me. A good reason Mr Bedford for stirring my stumps.</p><p rend="indent1"> Write to me about the Abbey without delay – I have another letter begun to you – which will be finished in course
                    of time, &amp; I will send you all my translations that are worth transcription</p><closer rend="indent1"> God bless you<signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>It would do your heart good just to look out at my window this delightful day.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>