<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1025</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2147</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                    D3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1025" type="letter">
        <head>1025. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-01-24">24
                        January 1805</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Guthrie&#8217;s</ref> Bookseller/ Nicholson Street/ Edinburgh &#8211;/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: JA/ 1805/ 27<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                    D3<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Harry </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thought <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> had misunderstood you, &amp; am glad to find
                    it so. you also misunderstand the <del>xxx</del> &lt;laws&gt; of the English Universities. two <hi rend="ital">terms</hi> &amp;
                    not two <hi rend="ital">years</hi> are saved &#8211; as thus you are permitted to miss two terms in the four years, &amp; it matters not
                    when &lt;you&gt; avail yourself of the privilege, whether at the beginning or end of the time. to graduate the remaining terms
                    must be kept &#8211; which you would find impossible, &amp; therefore the whole expence of entering &#8211; that is of matriculation &#8211; would
                    be thrown away. I am very glad you have given up the idea.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not my fault that you do not receive regular remittances, &#8211; if <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> income were regularly paid in the evil would be remedied, &amp; things are in a train to have this done. what
                    supplies <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> furnishes meantime he himself advances &#8211; meo periculo<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;at my own risk&#8217;.</note> I am doing all I can to hasten the final settlement &amp; ensure
                    you a punctual income &#8211; it vexes me that this should be delayed &#8211; you will however certainly receive the full sum per year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hear <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is on board the Egyptienne frigate<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A 40-gun frigate, captured from the French in 1801, and commissioned into the Royal Navy.</note>
                    &#8211; as the news comes to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> from <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> it is evident that <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> has got him this &lt;third&gt;
                    appointment. <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> tells me that when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John
                        Southey</ref> heard he was at Taunton, he himself being then at his Dorsetshire estate, he told him to go to his house &amp;
                    wait till he came home. What the old man might have done heaven knows &#8211; but the boy with his usual impudence ordered all his bills
                    to be carried in to <del>him xxx xxx</del> the old gentlemen &lt;who&gt; therefore the next morning turned him out of doors. God
                    knows what mischief this may have done. Whether this third embarkation may answer better than the two former remains to be seen,
                    but my conviction of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edwards</ref> character &amp; utter worthlessness is such that I
                    would willingly swap with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Crompton<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Peter Crompton (dates
                        unknown) of Eton House, Liverpool, a radical reformer who supported <ref target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref>
                        in the 1790s and who contested elections at Nottingham (1796, 1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820). Crompton, had
                        visited Southey in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>; see Southey to John Rickman, 6 August 1804, Letter
                        975.</note> &amp; take his ill-looking hound of a son for a brother instead. Meantime there is good news of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Commodore &#8211; or Sir Samuel Hood is his friend, he has made him first Lieutenant of
                    the Amelia &#8211; a finer frigate than the Galatea &amp; speaks of him in the highest terms.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Southey&#8217;s commanding officer, Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762&#8211;1814;
                            <title>DNB</title>), made him lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a finer ship than the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> because she was a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class frigate of the French navy captured in 1796 and then commissioned into
                        the navy.</note> Unluckily the yellow fever is raging on board the ship &#8211; if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>
                    scapes it &#8211; &amp; he writes in good spirits. he thinks himself in a fair way of promotion &#8211; far fairer than ever. I am however
                    anxious to receive another letter on account of the pestilence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The H H look well &#8211; but the seal <del>x</del> wants a frame &#8211; &amp; many new seals which I have seen have the same
                    naked appearance. &#8211; I wish you would look at the Southey arms whereof you told me in the MSS. &amp; should they prove to be ours I
                    will think about raising a seal also. Send me a description of them &#8211; or drawing &#8211; &amp; see if any thing be said of the family to
                    identify them, for how the devil they should get into Scotland puzzles me. the family is doubtless as old as Adam, but it has kept
                    very quiet till the present generation &#8211; the only one who ever signalled himself before being the worthy who committed actual
                    rebellion against James 2.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> James II (1633&#8211;1701; reigned 1685&#8211;1689;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> for which he was very near going to heaven in a <hi rend="ital">string</hi> as the saying is.
                    However it is better to be the beginning of a family than the fag end.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very glad you are acquainted with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>. make my
                    acknowledgements to him for his invitation &#8211; &amp; assure him that one main inducement <del>fo</del> to visit Edinburgh &#8211; would be
                    the wish to see him &#8211; which is the simple truth &#8211; for I have a very sincere respect for him. If his poem be reviewed in this
                    Annual &#8211; it will fall into other hands &#8211; if it be delayed till the next &#8211; I shall apply for it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel, a Poem</title> (1805) was reviewed by <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Anna Laetitia Barbauld</ref> in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3
                        (1805), 600&#8211;604.</note> Sir Tristram is now the only long article remaining to compleat my years work.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of Scott&#8217;s <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of Ercildoune</title> (1804)
                        appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 555&#8211;563.</note> I want to convince <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> that Amadis is originally Portugueze &#8211; which I am sure I could do in half
                    an hours conversation. There occur words in the Spanish which are Portugueze, &amp; would not have been used by a Castilian
                    writing originally &lt;or translating from any other language&gt;. the name Oriana occurs in the oldest poem in the language,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to the poem addressed to Oriana by the twelfth-century Portuguese poet
                        Gonzalo Hermiguez, recorded in Bernardo de Brito (1569&#8211;1617), <title>Chronica de Cister onde se Contam as Cousas Principals
                            Desta Ordem, &amp; Muytas Antiguedades do Reyno da Portugal</title> (1720), Book VI, chapter 1. Southey owned a copy of
                        Brito&#8217;s work. Southey&#8217;s own version of the poem, &#8216;Gonzalo Hermiguez&#8217; (written 1801), appears in <title>The Poetical Works of
                            Robert Southey, Collected by Himself</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), VI, pp. 163&#8211;165.</note> &amp; the names
                    Lisuarte &amp; Briolania were adopted <del>from xxx</del> (as I suppose) <del>xxx</del> from the story, unless they pre-existed in
                    the country in either case, furnishing strong presumptive proof, when added to the positive testimony of Gomes Eannes<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gomes Eanes de Zurara (c. 1410&#8211;1474), Portuguese chronicler, and author of <title>Chronica del
                            Rei D. Joam I de boa Mem&#243;ria. Terceira Parte em que se Contam a Tomada de Ceuta</title> (1644).</note> who wrote only
                    threescore years after Lobeiras<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey attributed <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, which
                        he had translated and published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1803, to Vasco de Lobeira (d.
                        1403) a troubador knighted after the Battle of Aljubarrota (1385). Modern scholars suggest a different Lobeira as the
                        Portuguese copyist of an earlier Castilian story; Scott did not accept the Portuguese origin of the tale in his review of
                        Southey&#8217;s translation for the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 600&#8211;603, and in the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 5 (October 1803), 109&#8211;136.</note> death &#8211; before the Spanish version existed. I accounted for the
                    existence of a Picard version<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the version of the tale in the Picard language of
                        northern France see Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Preface&#8217; to <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, pp. ii&#8211;iv.</note> &#8211; if it exists. Tell him that if he
                    would visit me at the Lakes I would make him almost as fond of certain Portugueze characters as he is of Froissart.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean Froissart (c. 1337&#8211;c. 1405), chronicler of medieval France. Scott reviewed Sir John
                        Froissart&#8217;s <title>Chronicles of England, France, and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II
                            to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans. Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804), in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 10 (January 1805), 347&#8211;362.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> John is well. he is a tenderum &amp; a nonis de vellons.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Terms of mock
                        endearment for John, Southey&#8217;s ass. Punning on Latin and on colloquial Spanish terms for small coins, &#8216;as&#8217; and &#8216;vellon&#8217;, and
                        meaning &#8216;a tender one and not worth a groat/ not a fleecy ass&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-01-24">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 24. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>