<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1530</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2652</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 182&#8211;184 [with omissions].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1530" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1530" type="letter">
        <head>1530. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1808-11-09">9 November 1808</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Endorsements: Nov 9 1808/ 9 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        1808<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ NOV 12/ 1808<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 182&#8211;184 [with omissions].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am ready, desirous &amp; able to bear a part in this said review.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> You will however think it odd that the very subject on which you seem to suppose
                    me most able is one which I should rather avoid. I have not the sort of talent requisite for writing a political pamphlet upon the
                    state of Spain, &#8211; these things require a <del>xxx</del> &lt;kind&gt; of wire-drawing which I have never learnt to perform, &amp; a
                        <del>xxx</del> &lt;method&gt; of logical reasoning to which my mind has never been habituated, &amp; for which it has no
                    natural aptitude. What I feel about Spain you know, &#8211; what I think about &lt;it&gt; is this, &#8211; the country has much to suffer, in
                    all probability there will be many &amp; dreadful defeats of the patriots, &amp; such scenes as have never been witnessed in
                    Europe since the destruction of Saguntum<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Siege of Saguntum, Iberia (219&#8211;218 BC)
                        Hannibal&#8217;s Carthaginian army took the town after severe fighting.</note> &amp; Numantia<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the Siege of Numantia, in Hispania (134&#8211;133 BC) the army of the Roman republic, led by Scipio, destroyed the town after
                        reducing the inhabitants to starvation and cannibalism.</note> may perhaps be renewed there. Joseph will very likely be
                    crowned at Madrid,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Bonaparte (1768&#8211;1844), the eldest brother of Napoleon, who made
                        him King of Spain (1808&#8211;1813).</note> &amp; many of us may give up the cause of Spanish independance as lost. But so surely as
                    God liveth &amp; moveth in the hearts of men, so surely will that country eventually work out its own redemption.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now Grosvenor, understand me clearly. I could not fill half a score of pages by dilating &amp; diluting this; &#8211;
                        <del>but</del> that is I should be a sorry pamphleteer; but I believe my self to be a good reviewer in my own way, which is
                    that of giving a succinct account of the contents of the book before me, extracting its essence, bringing my own knowledge to bear
                    upon the subject, &amp; where occasion serves seasoning it with those opinions which in some degree leaven all my thoughts words
                    &amp; actions. If you had read the Annual Reviews you would comprehend this better by example than I can make you in a letter.
                    Voyages &amp; Travels I review better than any thing else, being well read <del>upon</del> in that branch of literature, better
                    indeed than most men. Biography &amp; History are within my reach, &#8211; upon any of these topics I will do my best. It is just proper
                    to mention that there are now before me for the Annual Drurys Madagascar, &#8211; Clarksons Hist of the Abolition &#8211; Tennants Indian
                    Recreation &#8211; &amp; Zouchs Sir P. Sidney.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s reviews of these books appeared in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), Robert Drury [(1687&#8211;1734?; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>The Adventures of Robert Drury, during fifteen Years Captivity on the Island of Madagascar; containing a Description of that
                            Island; an Account of its Produce, Manufactures, and Commerce; with an Account of the Manners and Customs, Wars, Religion,
                            and Civil Policy of the Inhabitants: to which is added, a Vocabulary of the Madagascar Language. Written by himself, and
                            now carefully revised and corrected from the original</title>, (1807), 253&#8211;263; Thomas Clarkson (1760&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British
                            Parliament</title> (1808), 127&#8211;148; Thomas Zouch (1737&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Sir
                            Philip Sydney</title> (1808), 224&#8211;235. The review of William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Indian
                            Recreations: Consisting Chiefly of Strictures of the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahomedans &amp; Hindoos</title>
                        (1808) appeared on pages 658&#8211;670.</note> &#8211; Any thing else may be sent me &#8211; the Life of Bruce<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Murray (1775&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Account of the Life and Writings of James Bruce ...
                            Author of Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile: in the Years 1768, 1769, 1770, 1771, 1772 &amp; 1773</title> (1808).
                        This was reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809), 263&#8211;270.</note> could not be put into better
                    hands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know my way of thinking upon most subjects. I despise all parties too much to be attached to any. I believe
                    that this country must continue the war while Bonaparte is at the head of France, &amp; while the system which he has perfected
                    remains in force, &#8211; I therefore from my heart &amp; soul execrate &amp; abominate the peace-mongers. I am an enemy to any farther
                    concessions to the Catholicks. I am a friend to the Church establishment, &#8211; not as a Churchman, for I am <hi rend="ital">almost</hi> a Quaker, &#8211; but because an establishment is now, &amp; long will be necessary, &#8211; &amp; the one we have secures
                    toleration to such hereticks as myself. I wish for reform, because I cannot but see that all things are tending towards
                    revolution, &amp; <del>xxx</del> nothing but reform can by any possibility prevent it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This much is said to you, that it may be said thro you. &#8211; To yourself I add that the pay proposed will be
                    exceedingly suitable to my poor finances, &amp; that the more books of travels they send me the better; for that reason. I had
                    almost forgotten to say that if a fit text be sent me the subject of converting the Hindoos is one upon which I am well prepared.
                    It is my belief that they ought to be converted both as a matter of policy &amp; duty, &#8211; &amp; as you know I do not suppose
                    salvation to be exclusively attached to any particular faith, you may be sure that this opinion does not proceed from religious
                    bigotry. Claudius Buchanans book<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Claudius Buchanan (1766&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Memoir of the Expediency of an Ecclesiastical Establishment for British India</title> (1805).</note> would perhaps
                    be the best text, if it be not too old. One two or three articles I could provide by the <del>end</del> new year. this had better
                    be one,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title>, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> &#8211; Bruce another. The place from
                    whence all parcels should be sent, whether by coach or waggon is the Bull &amp; Mouth.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        coaching inn in north London for which mail coaches and wagons left for the north.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Fare well &#8211; &amp; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1808-11-09">Nov. 9. 1808.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Kehama is in great glory.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>