<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1297</idno><idno type="nines">rce2419</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1297" type="letter"><head>1297. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Charles Biddlecombe</ref>, <date when="1807-03-25">25 March
                        1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Biddlecombe Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Burton/ Ringwood/ Hampshire <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ MAR28/ 1807<lb/>Seal: [illegible] red
                        wax<lb/>Watermark: 1801<lb/>MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library <lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Cumberland.</placeName></address><date when="1807-03-25">March 25. 1807.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Biddlecombe</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You will think that I have forgotten you, &amp; forgotten also the stray books &amp; chattels which have been so
                    long trespassing upon your hospitality. The truth is that these very things have been the cause of preventing me from dropping you
                    now &amp; then a letter, because I have been always looking on to fixing myself, &amp; hoping soon that I should write to request
                        <del>that</del> they might be dispatched. That time is come at last. My resolution is taken to become a settled resident here
                    at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, – &amp; as I have been here three years &amp; a half on trial, nobody can say
                    the resolution is a hasty one. I will therefore beg you to consign whatever you have of mine in the shape of books, papers, prints
                    &amp; portraits to the care of <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>: who will forward it forthwith to me by sea, by
                    way of Whitehaven. From this I except a certain portrait of myself (the framed <del>from</del> side face) – which if you think it
                    worthy of retaining a place in your parlour, is very much at your service, &amp; will serve to remind you of one who neither has
                    forgotten, nor <del>wil</del> can forget, many friendly acts of hospitality &amp; good neighbourhood, &amp; many pleasant hours,
                    for which he is indebted to you.</p><p rend="indent1"> Since we met in London I have had an increase to my family, which now consists of a daughter <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, nearly three years old, &amp; a son, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, nearly six months, – both strong, hearty, &amp; fine children – who furnish me with abundant amusement. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is very much improved in health since she was in Hampshire; – nursing agrees
                    wonderfully with her, &amp; she is grown fat &amp; strong. I myself am <del>th</del> as usual – first cousin to a skeleton, – but
                    my skin – &amp; bones <del>x</del> continue to enjoy the same good health &amp; good spirits. I go on as I begun, &amp; am perhaps
                    a closer student than ever; – my main occupation at present is upon a great work respecting South America, – for which I possess
                    very ample &amp; very important manuscript documents.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> which appeared in three volumes from 1810 to 1819.</note> – Now in return for this bulletin – tell me how
                    you &amp; yours go on, – if your good mother be still, as I trust, in the land of the living &amp; enjoying life – &amp; if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleman<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> An acquaintance of Southey’s from his residence at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> in 1797 and 1799.</note> also; – When I travel into the West – as perhaps I
                        <del>shall</del> &lt;may&gt; before the end of the year, I will make a bend out of my way for the sake of seeing <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> &amp; my old friends there. – Perhaps you may one day be disposed to travel Northward
                    – whenever that is the case we shall be very glad to make you feel that you are right heartily welcome, – &amp; to show you the
                    country better than guides can do. Your old acquaintance <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> (who has not forgotten
                    to enquire after you) is settled near <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, – <del>&amp;</del> we have for our
                    summer neighbour a gentleman of whom you may perhaps know something as he was formerly member for Yarmouth in the Isle of Wight –
                    &amp; is I believe either a Hampshire man, or somehow connected with the county – <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">colonel
                        Peachy</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your little girl must by this time be grown a great one: – I suppose what you know of Catholicism does not induce
                    you to side with ministry on the present question.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of All the
                        Talents, of which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was a member, fell because the King would not accede to
                        its plan to introduce an act emancipating Catholics from the civil penalties and restrictions placed upon them.</note> I am
                    decidedly hostile to it, &amp; would <del>x</del> not have the slightest relaxation in the existing laws against <del>Roman</del>
                    a religion, the most monstrous in its pretensions, the most impudent in its assertions, &amp; the most fatal in its tendency that
                    ever human craft imposed upon human credulity. Few persons perhaps understand it better than myself, for I have studied its
                    history, &amp; seen its effects in countries where it flourishes in all its glory. Indeed I have long resolved on writing the
                    History of the Monastic Orders, &amp; have long been collecting knowledge &amp; materials for this purpose: whenever I have
                    leisure this will be the work which I shall pursue, &amp; sure I am that it will give the people of England a very different idea
                    of the Catholic religion from what at present they very generally entertain.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project
                        was never completed.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I see the Christ-Church news in the Monthly Magazine<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rev. William
                        Bingley (1774–1823; <title>DNB</title>), the naturalist, traveller and local historian, was a neighbour of Biddlecombe’s as a
                        curate of Christchurch Priory, Hampshire, from 1802 to 1816. Bingley contributed material on the history of the church and the
                        parish to the <title>Monthly</title>; his <title>Animal Biography; or, Authentic Anecdotes of the Lives, Manners and Economy,
                            of the Animal Creation, Arranged According to the System of Linnæus</title> (1803), reached a third, expanded edition in
                        1805. Its publisher was <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Richard Phillips</ref>, also publisher of the
                            <title>Monthly</title>.</note> – that is news of all the fish, birds &amp; flowers in the neighbourhood, with occasional
                    mention of my old friends the forest flies &amp; the Brinston bucks. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bingley is a useful man, – he is
                    sometimes a little credulous about animals, &amp; should have uniformly given references to the authors <del>from</del> upon whom
                    he relies – but his book<del>s</del> is a very interesting &amp; very valuable one, – &amp; he must be a great acquisition to your
                    society</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be kindly remembered to you – your Mother – &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleman. – My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is still a Lieutenant, &amp; now in the
                    Pallas Frigate,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s ship, launched in 1804, was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate,
                        whose first captain was Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775–1860; <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved
                        in the capture of many French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown).</note>
                    which is off Brest. Should he come to Spithead he would I think be enquiring after you –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>