<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                <title type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                    Era</title>
                <editor>
                    <name>Tim Fulford</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editor">Tim Fulford</editor>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="nines">rce6008</idno>
                <idno type="edition">Wesley</idno>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                <date when="2011-11-01">June 1, 2012</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="a" type="main">From The Life of Wesley, and the Rise and Progress of
                            Methodism</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Robert</forename>
                                <surname>Southey</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m" type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                        <title level="m" type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                            Era</title>
                        <editor>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Tim</forename>
                                <surname>Fulford</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="genre">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
                    <category xml:id="g1">
                        <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g2">
                        <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g3">
                        <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g4">
                        <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g5">
                        <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g7">
                        <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g6">
                        <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g8">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g9">
                        <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g10">
                        <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g11">
                        <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g12">
                        <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g13">
                        <catDesc>History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g14">
                        <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g15">
                        <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g16">
                        <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g17">
                        <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g18">
                        <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g19">
                        <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g20">
                        <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g21">
                        <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g22">
                        <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g23">
                        <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g24">
                        <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g25">
                        <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g26">
                        <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g27">
                        <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g28">
                        <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g29">
                        <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g30">
                        <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g31">
                        <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g32">
                        <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g33">
                        <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g34">
                        <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g4"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
                <date>2012-25-04</date>
                <list>
                    <item>change to RC TEI Headers</item>
                    <item>runs transforms to html</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="extract">
                <head>From Robert Southey, <title>The Life of Wesley, and the Rise and Progress of
                        Methodism</title>, 2nd edn, 2 vols (London, 1820), II, pp. 319-24.</head>
                <p>Among the converts to Methodism at this time were Mr. Berridge, vicar of Everton,
                    in Bedfordshire, and Mr. Hickes, vicar of Wrestlingworth, in the same
                    neighbourhood. These persons, by their preaching, produced the same contagious
                    convulsions in their hearers, as had formerly prevailed at Bristol; and though
                    time had sobered Mr. Wesley’s feelings, and matured his judgment, he was so far
                    deceived, that he recorded the things which occurred, not as psychological, but
                    as religious cases.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editor">The eyewitness
                        accounts that follow are taken from John Wesley’s journal for 20 May 1759.
                        See <title>The Journal of the Rev. John Wesley A.M.</title>, 4 vols (London,
                        1827), II, pp. 429-35.</note> They were of the most frightful and
                    extraordinary kind. An eyewitness described the church at Everton as crowded
                    with persons from all the country round; ‘the windows’, he says, ‘being filled,
                    within and without, and even the outside of the pulpit, to the very top, so that
                    Mr. Berridge seemed almost stifled with their breath; yet’, the relater
                    continues, ‘feeble and sickly as he is, he was continually strengthened, and his
                    voice, for the most part, distinguishable in the midst of all the outcries,—
                    When the power of religion begun to be spoke of, the presence of God really
                    filled the place; and while poor sinners felt the sentence of death in their
                    souls, what sounds of distiess did I hear! The greatest number of them who
                    cried, or fell, were men! but some men and several children, felt the power of
                    the same Almighty Spirit, and seemed just sinking into hell. This occasioned a
                    mixture of various sounds; some shrieking, some roaring aloud. The most general
                    was a loud breathing, like that of people half-strangled, and gasping for life;
                    and, indeed, almost all the cries were like those of human creatures dying in
                    bitter anguish. Great numbers wept without any noise; others fell down as dead;
                    some sinking in silence, some with extreme noise and violent agitation. I stood
                    on the pew seat, as did a young man in the opposite pew, an able-bodied, fresh,
                    healthy countryman; but, in a moment, while he seemed to think of nothing less,
                    down he dropt, with a violence inconceivable. The adjoining pews seemed shook
                    with his fall: I heard afterwards the stamping of his feet, ready to break the
                    boards, as he lay in strong convulsions at the bottom of the pew. When he fell,
                    Mr. B. and I felt our souls thrilled with a momentary dread; as, when one man is
                    killed by a cannon-ball, another often feels the wind of it.—’ Among the
                    children who felt the arrows of the Almighty, I saw- a sturdy boy, about eight
                    years old, who roared above his fellows, and seemed, in his agony, to struggle
                    with the strength of a grown man. His face was red as scarlet; and almost all on
                    whom God laid his hand, turned either very red or almost black’.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The congregation adjourned to Mr. Berridge’s house, whither those
                    who were still in the fit were carried: the maddened people were eager for more
                    stimulants, and the insane vicar was as willing to administer more, as they were
                    to receive it. ‘I stayed in the next room’, says the relater, ‘and saw a girl,
                    whom I had observed peculiarly distressed in the church, lying on the floor as
                    one dead, but without any ghastliness in her face. In a few minutes we were
                    informed of a woman filled with peace and joy, who was crying out just before.
                    She had come thirteen miles, and is the same person who dreamed Mr. Berridge
                    would come to his village on that very day whereon he did come, though without
                    either knowing the place or the way to it. She was convinced at that time. Just
                    as we heard of her deliverance, the girl on the floor began to stir. She was
                    then set in a chair, and, after sighing a while, suddenly rose up, rejoicing in
                    God. Her face was covered with the most beautiful smile I ever saw. She
                    frequently fell on her knees, but was generally running to and fro, speaking
                    these and the like words: ‘Oh, what can Jesus do for lost sinners! He has
                    forgiven all my sins! I am in Heaven! I am in Heaven! Oh, how he loves me, and
                    how I love him!’— Meantime I saw a thin pale girl, weeping with sorrow for
                    herself, and joy for her companion. Quickly the smiles of Heaven came likewise
                    on her, and her praises joined with those of the other. I also then laughed with
                    extreme joy; so did Mr. B. it was more than he could bear; so did all who knew
                    the Lord, and some of those who were waiting for salvation, till the cries of
                    them who were struck with the arrows of conviction, were almost lost in the
                    sounds of joy. Mr. Berridge about this time retired; we continued, praising God
                    with all our might, and his work went on. I had for some time observed a young
                    woman all in tears, but now her countenance changed: the unspeakable joy
                    appeared in her face, which, quick as lightning, was filled with smiles, and
                    became a crimson colour. About the same time John Keeling, of Potton, fell into
                    an agony; but he grew calm in about a quarter of an hour, though without a clear
                    sense of pardon. Immediately after, a stranger, well dressed, who stood facing
                    me, fell backward to the wall, then forward on his knees, wringing his hands,
                    and roaring like a bull.— His face at first turned quite red, then almost black.
                    He rose and ran against the wall, till Mr. Keeling and another held him. He
                    screamed out, ‘Oh, what shall I do! what shall I do! Oh, for one drop of the
                    blood of Christ!’ As he spoke, God set his soul at liberty: he knew his sins
                    were blotted out; and the rapture he was in seemed too great for human nature to
                    bear. He had come forty miles to hear Mr. Berridge.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">‘I observed, about the time that Mr. Coe (that was his name) began
                    to rejoice, a girl eleven or twelve years old, exceeding poorly dressed, who
                    appeared to be as deeply wounded, and as desirous of salvation, as any. But I
                    lost sight of her, till I heard the joyful sound of another born in Sion, and
                    found, upon inquiry, it was her, the poor disconsolate, gypsy-looking child. And
                    now did I see such a sight as I do not expect again on this side eternity. The
                    faces of the three justified children, and, I think, of all the believers
                    present, did really shine: and such a beauty, such a look of extreme happiness,
                    and, at the same time, of divine love and simplicity, did I never see in human
                    faces till now. The newly justified eagerly embraced one another, weeping on
                    each other’s necks for joy, and besought both men and women to help them in
                    praising God’. The same fits were produced by Mr. Hickes’s preaching at
                    Wrestlingworth, whither this relater proceeded; and there also the poor
                    creatures, who were under the paroxysm, were carried into the parsonage, where
                    some lay as if they were dead, and others lay struggling. In both churches
                    several pews and benches were broken by the violent struggling of the sufferers;
                    ‘yet’, says the narrator, ‘it is common for people to remain unaffected there,
                    and afterward drop down in their way home. Some have been found lying as dead in
                    the road; others in Mr. Berridge’s garden, not being able to walk from the
                    church to his house, though it is not two hundred yards’. The person who thus
                    minutely described the progress of this powerful contagion, observes, that few
                    old people experienced any thing of what he called the work of God, and scarce
                    any of the rich; and, with that uncharitable spirit, which is one of the surest
                    and worst effects of such superstition, he remarks, that three farmers, in three
                    several villages, who set themselves to oppose it, all died within a month.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Such success made Berridge glorious in his own eyes, as well as in
                    those of all the fanatics round about. He travelled about the country, making
                    Everton still the centre of his excursions; and he confesses that, on one
                    occasion, when he mounted a table upon a common near Cambridge, and saw nearly
                    ten thousand people assembled, and many gownsmen among them, he paused after he
                    had given out his text, thinking of ‘something pretty to set off with: but’,
                    says he, ‘the Lord So confounded me, (as indeed it was meet, for I was seeking
                    not his glory, but my own,) that I was in a perfect labyrinth, and found that,
                    if I did not begin immediately, I must go down without speaking; so I broke out
                    with the first word that occurred, not knowing whether I should be able to add
                    any more. Then the Lord opened my mouth, enabling me to speak near an hour,
                    without any kind of perplexity, and so loud, that every one might hear’. For a
                    season this man produced a more violent influenza of fanaticism, than had ever
                    followed upon either Whitefield’s or Wesley’s preaching. The people flocked to
                    hear him in such numbers, that his church could not contain them, and they
                    adjourned into a field. ‘Some of them’, says an eyewitness, ‘who were here
                    pricked to the heart, were affected in an astonishing manner. The first man I
                    saw wounded would have dropped, but others, catching him in their arms, did
                    indeed prop him up; but were so far from keeping him still, that he caused all
                    of them to totter and tremble. His own shaking exceeded that of a cloth in the
                    wind. It seemed as if the Lord came upon him like a giant, taking him by the
                    neck, and shaking all his bones in pieces. One woman tore up the ground with her
                    hands, filling them with dust, and with the hard-trodden grass, on which I saw
                    her lie with her hands clinched, as one dead, when the multitude dispersed:
                    another roared and screamed in a more dreadful agony than ever I heard before. I
                    omit the rejoicing of believers, because of their number, and the frequency
                    thereof; though the manner was strange, some of them being quite overpowered
                    with divine love, and only showing enough of natural life to let us know they
                    were overwhelmed with joy and life eternal. Some continued long as if they were
                    dead, but with a calm sweetness in their looks. I saw one who lay two or three
                    hours in the open air, and being then carried into the house, continued
                    insensible another hour, as if actually dead. The first sign of life she showed
                    was a rapture of praise, intermixed with a small joyous laughter’. It may excite
                    astonishment in other countries, and reasonable regret in this, that there
                    should be no authority capable of restraining extravagancies and indecencies
                    like these. </p>
                <p rend="indent1">Berridge had been curate of Stapleford, near Cambridge, several
                    years, and now, after what he called his conversion, his heart was set upon
                    preaching a ‘gospel-sermon’ there, which, he said, he had never done before.
                    Some fifteen hundred persons assembled in a field to hear him. The contagion
                    soon began to show itself among those who were predisposed for it: others, of a
                    different temper, mocked and mimicked these poor creatures in their convulsions;
                    and some persons, who were in a better state of mind than either, indignant at
                    the extravagance and indecency of the scene, called aloud to have those wretches
                    horsewhipped out of the field. ‘Well’ (says the fanatical writer) ‘may Satan be
                    enraged at the cries of the people, and the prayers they make in the bitterness
                    of their souls, seeing we know these are the chief times at which Satan is cast
                    out’.—’ I heard a dreadful noise, on the further side of the congregation, (says
                    this writer,) and turning thither, saw one Thomas Skinner coming forward, the
                    most horrible human figure I ever saw. His large wig and hair were coal-black;
                    his face distorted beyond all description. He roared incessantly, throwing and
                    clapping his hands together with his whole force. Several were terrified, and
                    hastened out of his way. I was glad to hear him, after a while, pray aloud. Not
                    a few of the triflers grew serious, while his kindred and acquaintance were very
                    unwilling to believe even their own eyes and ears. They would fain have got him
                    away; but he fell to the earth, crying, ‘My burden! my burden! I cannot bear
                    it!’ Some of his brother scoffers were calling for horsewhips, till they saw him
                    extended on his back at full length: they then said he was dead; and indeed the
                    only sign of life was the working of his breast, and the distortions of his
                    face, while the veins of his neck were swelled as if ready to burst. He was,
                    just before, the chief captain of Satan’s forces: none was by nature more fitted
                    for mockery; none could swear more heroically to whip out of the close all who
                    were affected by the preaching’. Berridge bade the people take warning by him,
                    while he lay roaring and tormented on the ground. ‘His agonies lasted some
                    hours; then his body and soul were eased’.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">It is to be regretted that, of the many persons who have gone
                    through this disease, no one should have recorded his case who was capable of
                    describing his sensations accurately, if not of analyzing them. Berridge and
                    Hickes are said to have ‘awakened’ about four thousand souls in the course of
                    twelve months. Imposture in all degrees, from the first natural exaggeration to
                    downright fraud, kept pace with enthusiasm. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
