<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3449</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4720</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3449. Robert Southey to John Rickman, 1 March 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3449" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3449.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 391. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles
						Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V,
						pp. 24&#8211;26 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3449" type="letter">
        <head>3449. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1820-03-01">1 March 1820</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman
							Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb /> Stamped:
						KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [partial] 4 MR 4/ 1820<lb /> Seal: black wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb />
						Endorsement: Fr RS./ 1 March 1820<lb /> MS: Huntington Library, RS 391. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles
						Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V,
						pp. 24&#8211;26 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your guess about the parallel roads<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Parallel Roads of
						Glen Roy are lake terraces formed along the shoreline of an ancient ice-dammed lake. They remained the subject of
						much speculation throughout the nineteenth century. Rickman suggested in his letter to Southey of 20 February 1820
						that the Roads were made in the fourteenth century for a &#8216;hunting spectacle&#8217;. Rickman and Southey visited on 20
						September 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp.
						212&#8211;216.</note> has this in its favour. that if Glen-Roy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Glen Roy is an
						Anglicization of the Gaelic Gleann Ruaidh, or &#8216;red glen&#8217;, rather than the French Glen Roi, or &#8216;royal glen&#8217;.</note>
					mean the Kings glen, the word Roy would not have been used before there was an intercourse between the Scotch &amp;
					the French, &#8211; they were never such friends with <del>the</del> our Normans as to have taken it from them. In point
					of time therefore this would suit well. On the other hand in that age chroniclers delighted as much in a good show
					as in a good battle, &amp; Froissart<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Froissart (c. 1337&#8211;c. 1405),
							<title>Chronicles</title> (c. 1370&#8211;c. 1400). <title />Rickman&#8217;s idea about the Parallel Roads was suggested by a
						mention of a hunting party in the Highlands in Froissart&#8217;s <title>Chronicles</title> (Chapter 61).</note> would
					hardly have failed to describe a hunting party upon so grand a scale as that for which these roads were made. It
					appears to me impossible that they should have been made for any other purpose. And when our friends at Corpach
					procure a list of the names of places, &amp; some Gael is found learned enough to translate them, this main fact, I
					have no doubt, will be established.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was convinced by Rickman&#8217;s
						theory that the Parallel Roads were man-made for &#8216;a display of barbarous magnificence in hunting&#8217; and had asked
						Telford and Rickman to obtain the Gaelic names, and translations of the names, of the surrounding hills and glens
						to confirm this idea, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), p.
						216.</note> There is even a possibility that by this means also we may come near the age: not by the language,
					(for <del>it</del> I believe the Gaelic is not &lt;like&gt; the Welsh, in <del>this respect</del>, which the date of a
					composition may be <del>referred with</del> inferred with some certainty by its language) but by the names of
						<del>the</del> some of the party, &amp; perhaps of some of the implements used.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are quite right in thinking funded property better than landed property for charitable
					institutions, as being rather more than less secure, safe from fraudulent management, &amp; requiring no trouble.
					There remains an objection from the uncertainty of the value of money, &#8211; but it appears to me altogether impossible
					that money should ever fall in value <del>x</del> as it has done since the middle ages; &#8211; perhaps even such an
					advance of prices as has taken place within our own recollection, will never again occur; &#8211; I mean as affecting
					every thing, the occurrence of an accidental scarcity <del>is</del> would produce but a temporary effect. In the
					view which I take of the improvement of society, stability is one of the good things <del>xxxxx to xxx</del> to be
					expected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I like your Beguinage scheme in all its parts.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman&#8217;s
						longstanding plan for communities of single women, which owed something to the Beguines, religious communities of
						the medieval Low Countries.</note> Endowments (analogous to <del>f x</del> college fellowships) would grow out of
					it in due course of time. And great part of the business of female education be transferred to these institutions,
					to the advantage of all parties.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The D. of Berry will do more good by his death than he would ever have done by his life.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Ferdinand d&#8217;Artoise, Duc de Berri (1778&#8211;1820), a nephew of Louis XVIII
						(1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824), had been mortally wounded at the Paris Opera on 13 February 1820 by Louis
						Pierre Louvel (1783&#8211;1820), a Bonapartist.</note> I had been saying that such a tragedy &lt;in France&gt; surprized me
						<del>in France</del> much more than it would have done in England. The will I know was not wanting, &#8211; &amp;
					intelligence soon came that the purpose had been formed.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Cato Street
						Conspiracy, to murder the Cabinet at dinner, had been broken up on 23 February 1820, and the conspirators were
						arrested over the next few days.</note> Your Opps. will call this discovery a most unfortunate business, &amp;
					such I trust it will prove for them. The jury who acquitted Thistlewood &amp; Watson,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A group of revolutionaries had attempted to lead part of the crowd at a radical meeting at Spa
						Fields on 2 December 1816 in an attempt to storm the Bank of England and the Tower of London. James Watson
						(1766&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) was charged with High Treason, but acquitted on 16 June 1817 after evidence
						emerged of the role of an agent provocateur. The case against Arthur Thistlewood (1774&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>)
						was then dropped.</note> the opps. in Parliament &amp; out of it who ridiculed the green-bag plot,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1817 the Cabinet had produced legislation to suspend habeas corpus, and a new
						Seditious Meetings Act, to suppress radical agitation. These actions followed Reports from Committees of the House
						of Lords and House of Commons on 18&#8211;19 February 1817, which had examined evidence of revolutionary conspiracies
						that the government claimed existed. The documents had been provided in green bags; hence the name &#8216;green bag
						plot&#8217;.</note> &amp; the subscribers to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hone</ref> &amp; Co,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hone had been acquitted of blasphemous and seditious libel at three
						successive trials on 18&#8211;20 December 1817. His defence fund had been liberally subscribed to by prominent radicals
						and some Whigs.</note> &#8211; are much more deeply implicated in the guilt of this business, than they would like to be
					told, &#8211; they have given every encouragement to traitors, &amp; thereby have made themselves morally art &amp; part
					in the treason. What a fortunate thing that the H Corpus was not suspended, &#8211; in that case these miscreants would
					(most of them) have been in confinement, &amp; the Whigs lamenting over them &amp; promoting subscriptions for them
					as the victims of oppression. The Gallows will now have its due.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Five of
						the Cato Street conspirators were hanged at Newgate Gaol on 1 May 1820: Arthur Thistlewood (1774&#8211;1820;
							<title>DNB</title>); Richard Tidd (1775&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>); James Ings (c. 1785&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>);
						William Davidson (1781&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>); and John Brunt (1782&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211;&#8211;
					Luckily for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, one of his friends in this
					country had just been writing upon the duty of putting down tyrants, &amp; had chosen the choice signature of <hi rend="ital">Bradshaw</hi>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 26 February
						1820, reported a letter in the <title>Westmorland Advertiser and Kendal Chronicle</title>, 12 February 1820,
						signed &#8216;Bradshaw&#8217;, which argued resistance to tyrants was obedience to God. The pseudonym &#8216;Bradshaw&#8217; was probably
						adopted to honour John Bradshaw (1602&#8211;1659; <title>DNB</title>), President of the High Court of Justice that had
						condemned to death Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I finished the Life of Wesley,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
							<title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> &#8211; two bulky octavos. The
						printer<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Andrew Strahan (1749&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), MP for various
						constituencies 1796&#8211;1820 and head of a highly successful printing business.</note> is far behind me, so that the
					book will hardly find its way to you, before I find mine to London, in the first or second week of April.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A highly civilized society seems to be within reach, if the devils who are got into the swinish
					multitude can be cast out; &#8211; &amp; then I suspect our notions concerning government will undergo a considerable
					change. Concerning the press I have no remaining doubt, &#8211; tho I have been reading <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> arguments against a Censorship in the Friend.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Friend</title>, 4&#8211;5 (7&#8211;14 September 1809), 56&#8211;68, no. 630 in the
						sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey had his copies bound in calf-skin.</note> The difficulty in effecting
					this necessary alteration, like most other difficulties, would be found much less than it appears; &amp; I believe
					a minister with Pitt&#8217;s<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime
						Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> courage (the main &#8211; if not the only qualification for a premier which he
					possessed) might effect it. There would be more difficulty in getting at a thorough system of police, &#8211; which ought
					in an improved state of society to be as compleat as it is in Japan.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">In
						Japan under the Tokugawa regime (1603&#8211;1867), appointed town magistrates combined the functions of police,
						prosecutors and judges, assisted by a professional police force. Commoners were organised into &#8216;five family
						associations&#8217;, collectively responsible for the actions of all their members. Southey noted Japan&#8217;s police system
						in his review of Benjamin Haydon, <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for
							the Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;591
						(579).</note>
          <del>Upon the finer xxxxxxxx</del> Our modes of life, <del>are</del> the nature of our large cities,
					&amp; especially of the metropolis oppose great obstacles. But with the authority of Alfred,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Alfred the Great (849&#8211;899; King of Wessex 871&#8211;899; <title>DNB</title>). During his
						reign, groups of ten households were formed into &#8216;tythings&#8217; to protect their property and deliver criminals to
						justice. In effect, members were responsible for each other&#8217;s actions and the community could be fined for
						individuals&#8217; wrongdoing.</note> &amp; an improved parochial system, I do not doubt its practicability. But the
					swine must be exorcised first, &amp; words which have been grossly abused must be restored to their proper meaning.
					&#8211; I hope I shall do something <del>x for</del> towards this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope this letter may arrive before the suspension of franking,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons was dissolved on 29 February 1820, so suspending Rickman&#8217;s power to provide
						official franks for letters until the new parliament met.</note> &#8211; a matter which concerns me much more than the H.
					Corpus. It goes singly for fear.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1820-03-01"> 1 March. 1820.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>