<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3228</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce4499</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
                  disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of
                  criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
                  the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
                  copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the
                  Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this
                  statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior
                  written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                  Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic
                  Circles:&gt; <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address></p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without
                        prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than
                        their current ones.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them
                  on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have
                  uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
                  corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we
                  want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet
                  users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles,
                  subject to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title type="main" level="a">3228. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 1
                     January 1819 </title>
                  <author role="primary"
                           ><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
                  <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
                     <biblScope type="URL"
                        >http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3228.html</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. . Previously published: John Wood
               Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856),
               III, pp. 106–108 [in part].</p>
            <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘,
                  and ' for ’.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                  keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact
                  rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such,
                  the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been
                  encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy
               corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
            <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
            <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David
               Rettenmaier</name><list>
               <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
            </list></change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David
               Rettenmaier</name><list>
               <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
            </list></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3228" type="letter">
            <head>3228. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles"
                  >Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1819-01-01">1 January 1819
                  </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C.
                  Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 3 JA 3/ 1819<lb/> Endorsement: 1 Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>.
                  1819<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously
                  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 106–108 [in
               part].</note></head>
            <opener><salute rend="indent0">My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> Your pencils<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Keswick was a
                  centre of pencil manufacture because of the nearby graphite mines in Borrowdale.
                  Southey had presumably bought some pencils as a gift for Bedford.</note> are on my
               chimney piece, &amp; the next question is how to transport them to yours, – for they
               are of an unfrankable shape &amp; texture, &amp; at this season of the year, no
               opportunity of sending them by a private hand is likely to occur. And unluckily it so
               happens that I never stood more in need of such an opportunity. </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am very much obliged to <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">Shield</ref><note n="2" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">Southey had sent Shield, through Bedford, his ‘Ode on the Death of
                  Queen Charlotte’, the annual New Year’s poem he was required to write as Poet
                  Laureate and which Shield was required to set to music (though New Year’s Odes had
                  not been performed at Court since 1810). Southey’s poem was not published until it
                  appeared in <title>Friendship’s Offering and Winter’s Wreath: a Literary Album,
                     and Christmas and New Year’s Present for MDCCCXXIX</title> (London, 1829), pp.
                  106–108.</note> for his desire of setting my verses to music, – very much
               flattered &amp;c &amp;. And very much obliged to you for your solicitude about them,
               &amp; entirely of your opinion as to the said verses, as far as regards their merit;
               – you know I told you that simple fiddling was not fit for them, – they ought to be
               bum-fiddled. But as for their giving offence, lord help the silly persons who should
               be offended at them! They have no other fault than that of being altogether good for
               nothing, &amp; <del>they</del> no other merit than that of being entirely suitable to
               the subject, that is to say, just as common place. I thought the subject was no
               matter of choice, – the Queens death coming so close upon the end of the year.<note
                  n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Queen Charlotte (1744–1818; <title>DNB</title>)
                  had died on 17 November 1818.</note> Otherwise it is most likely <del>that</del> I
               should taken a general topic, &amp; <del>preferrd</del> &lt;given&gt; a lyrical
               sketch of the State of Europe, which might have been a companion to that Ode of mine
               written four years ago, wherewith I am well pleased.<note n="4" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">Southey’s ‘Ode, Written in December, 1814’, published in
                     <title>Minor Poems</title>, 2 vols (London, 1815), II, pp. 227–238. This poem
                  had proved too controversial to serve as the New Year’s Ode for which it was
                  intended. </note> There is no reason why I should not write &lt;such&gt; an Ode
               still, (except that I am much better employed) – but you yourself say it cannot be in
               time; &amp; so in Cumberland phrase I need not <hi rend="ital">fash</hi> myself.<note
                  n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In Cumbrian dialect ‘to fash’ means ‘to
                  trouble’.</note> – I have done my exercise, a very bad one it is I know, but I do
               not think it will be <hi rend="ital">looked over</hi>, &amp; if it should, &amp; they
               were to sconce me<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A term at the University of
                  Oxford, used to refer to a fine its members were required to pay for a breach of
                  discipline.</note> a quarters salary for it, I can tell them this, that I could
               get 25£ in less time than it would take me to make a better. Nevertheless if any
               thing comes into <del>my</del> &lt;a&gt; head, which is at present far too much
               occupied to have room in it for stray fancies, I will give the Minerva<note n="7"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">Minerva was the Roman goddess of poetic
                  inspiration.</note> birth, – &amp; peradventure it may do as well for next year as
               for this, if all parties concernd should see another new year, &amp; if Europe
               continues for so long at peace. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam"
                  >Shields</ref> is a good-natured man, &amp; really I will in future let him have
               my exercise in full time. He shall have it by the end of November.<note n="8"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">Southey nearly kept his promise – his next New Year’s
                  Ode was sent to Bedford for onward transmission to Shield on 3 December 1819, see
                  Letter 3395.</note> At present I think we are compleatly out of the scrape. </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My dear Grosvenor, why do you speak in such terms of <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HaydonBenjamin">Haydon</ref>, who is even by the
               acknowledgement of those who dislike him most, a man of first rate<del>d</del> powers
               in his art? He may have done &lt;some&gt; foolish things &amp; acted indiscreetly in
               others, – but to speak of him with contempt – &amp; call him a coxcomb is out of all
               reason. He has long since broken off all connection with <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunt</ref> on account of his mischievous
                  opinions,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Haydon and Leigh Hunt had been
                  close friends, but fell out in early 1817. The cause seems to have partly been
                  Hunt’s growing closeness to Shelley and partly a conflict between Haydon’s
                  Christianity and Leigh Hunt’s scepticism. Southey’s review of Haydon, <title>New
                     Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the
                     Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818) appeared in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549–591.</note> – but I have nothing to do with
               his friendships or his enmities, – I know him only as one of those painters, who if
               opportunity were given them, would place this country as much above all others in
               that art, as we are in arms &amp; in poetry, &amp; in the real enjoyments of life. </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Nor do you speak <del>xxxxx</del> in consonance with my feelings
               concerning your friend M<hi rend="sup"><hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Fielding<note
                  n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Fielding (1748–1820), barrister,
                  magistrate and son of the novelist, Henry Fielding (1707–1754;
                  <title>DNB</title>). Southey had been introduced to him in 1817 in St James’s
                  Park.</note> &amp; James Fontaine.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">James
                  Fontaine (1778–1826) had sent Southey a copy of his <title>Eternal Punishment
                     Proved to be not Suffering, but Privation; and Immortality Dependent on
                     Spiritual Regeneration; by a Member of the Church of England</title> (1817),
                  no. 1468 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. See Southey to Grosvenor
                  Charles Bedford, 21 December 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey.
                     Part Five</title>, Letter 3221. </note> If the former is thinking more of the
               world to come than of this, – it is not a mental dram-drinking to which he has taken,
               – but the only proper diet. Fontaine is not a dreamer, but a sober &amp; rational
               enquirer into a subject of no trifling importance, inasmuch as it involves the most
               remarkable objection to our established creed. He has not written well, &amp;
               therefore will provoke little or no effect. The book is far too long, &amp; wants
               method as well as condensation. But he is right, &amp; when I come to town I should
               like to see him. </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My house is dismally silent. <del>Xx</del> <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Tantemagne</ref> (a coinage this moment from the
               mint) went yesterday with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter"
                  >Sara</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref>
               to <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref>, <del>for</del> where
               they will stay about a fortnight. Talking of <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Tantemagne</ref> I threaten her sometimes that I
               will import an Aunt-Eater from Brazil.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A pun
                  on ‘anteater’, a mammal species common in Brazil.</note> – </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I wrote lately to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW"
                  >Wynn</ref>;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Charles Watkin
                  Williams Wynn, 22 December 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey.
                     Part Five</title>, Letter 3223.</note> urging him to stand in Romillys
                  place,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Samuel Romilly (1757–1818;
                     <title>DNB</title>), MP for various seats 1807–1818, Solicitor-General
                  1806–1807, leading Whig proponent of law reform. He had killed himself on 2
                  November 1818.</note> &amp; put himself at the head of that reform in the Criminal
               Laws which must be made, &amp; which he will conduct with more judgement, &amp; upon
               better principles than Sir Samuel. I do not want him to be more in opposition than he
               is, – indeed I would far rather see him with the Government, &amp; this he knows, –
               but I would have him more in the eyes of the country, – &amp; here the way for him is
               open. – </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> If I were not far too well employed, &amp; hastening anxiously
               forward to the completion of my Brazil,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  >Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> I would pay off my
               score to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup"><hi
                        rend="sup">r</hi></hi> Brougham</ref> by reviewing his letter to Romilly
               &amp; the Committee Business.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Letter
                     to Sir Samuel Romilly, M.P. from Henry Brougham, Esq. M.P., F.R.S. upon the
                     Abuse of Charities</title> (1818). Brougham was Chairman of the House of
                  Commons Select Committee on the Education of the Lower Orders 1816–1818, which
                  severely criticised the lack of educational provision for the poor and highlighted
                  abuses in educational charities, including leading public schools. The
                     <title>Letter</title> and Reports of the Committee were among the items
                  reviewed by John Wilson Croker, among others, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  19 (July 1818), 492–569, published 2 February 1819.</note> For never did man lay
               himself more compleatly open, by the haste with which he has propagated false
               accusation the insolence with which he has treated our public schools &amp; the
               persons connected with them &amp; the entire ignorance which he has shown of their
               nature &amp; purpose, – &amp; even of the language of their <del>xxxxxxxxx</del>
                  charters.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham had not been educated
                  at an English public school – he attended the Royal High School in Edinburgh.
                  Southey had attended Westminster School from 1788 until he was expelled in
                  1792.</note> But I must not waste my time upon him. Before I leave home I must
               finish both the Wesley<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note>
               &amp; the Brazil. Proofs of each are on my desk. And I am now going to prepare ‘more
               copy’ for the press. – If the Almanacks are not coming with the Tea, they may come
               from Albemarle Street, with the next QR:<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>; its publisher, Murray, was based at 53
                  Albemarle Street in London.</note> I suppose <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will have to send me <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ButlerCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Butlers</ref> book.<note
                  n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Butler, <title>Historical Memoirs
                     respecting the English, Irish, and Scottish Catholics, from the Reformation, to
                     the Present Time</title> (1819–1821), published by Murray. Southey possessed a
                  presentation copy from Butler, no. 508 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> We have an interchange of this kind &amp; are upon the best terms
               with each other, tho he is the most zealous defender of the Catholics (his own
               persuasion) &amp; I the most zealous <del>of the</del> opposer of that abominable
                  <del>sxpxrs</del> corruption of Xtianity &amp; of the impudent <del>question</del>
               cry of Catholic Emancipation </p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you &amp; give you many a happy new year
                  </salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript>
               <p rend="indent1"> If you ever go into a shop where old books are sold I wish you
                  would buy me a neat copy of Thomas a Kempis. De Imitatione Xte, – of course I mean
                  in the Latin.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas à Kempis
                     (1379/1380–1471), <title>De Imitatione Christi</title> (c.
                  1418–1427).</note></p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
