<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3592</idno><idno type="nines">rce4863</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3592. Robert Southey to Thomas Thompson, 27 December
                  1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3592.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Haverford College, Thomas Thompson Letter Book, MC.975.02.024. An
                  undated copy in an unidentified hand. The original letter seems not to have survived. TR; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3592" type="letter"><head>3592. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ThompsonThomas">Thomas Thompson</ref>, <date when="1820-12-27">27 December
                  1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Haverford College, Thomas Thompson Letter Book, MC.975.02.024. An
                  undated copy in an unidentified hand. The original letter seems not to have survived. TR; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-12-27">27th Decem.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1820.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am obliged to you for your letter and for the memoir of that good man Anthony Benezett.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Roberts Vaux (1786–1836), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Anthony Benezet</title> (1817). Benezet (1713–1784) was a
                  French Protestant who converted to Quakerism in 1727 and emigrated to America, devoting his life to abolitionism and the promotion
                  of education. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> You cannot be more willing nor more desirous than I am to give Edw<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Burroughs<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Burrough (1634–1663; <title>DNB</title>), early Quaker and polemicist.</note> full praise for his great qualities and his
               good ones, nor more disposed to distinguish in all cases, as far as my judgement enables me, between the character of the individual
               and the spirit of the times. At present I am much better acquainted with the writings of the Quakers,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was planning to write a biography of George Fox (1624–1691; <title>DNB</title>), founder of Quakerism; this
                  project was not realised.</note> than with those of their antagonists; in what I have seen of the latter, I have found much
               bitterness of spirit, much credulity, and I have no doubt, some calumny, but yet no specimens of pure railing, that is railing per se,
               unaccompanied with any kind of reasoning. Do not however suppose that effervescences of this kind proceeding in such times from a
               thoroughly honest heart would weigh with me more than a feather in the scale in the general estimate of an eminent character.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your extracts from Ralph Farmer are good in their kind. I have never seen his book. Calamy calls it a good one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Ralph Farmer (d. 1670) was Presbyterian Minister at St Nicholas, Bristol, and a determined foe of
                  the Quakers. He was praised by Edmund Calamy (1671–1732; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Abridgement of Mr. Baxter’s History of His
                     Life and Times: with an Account of the Ministers, &amp;c. who were Ejected after the Restauration, of King Charles II</title>, 2
                  vols (London, 1713), II, p. 609, no. 132 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library: ‘He wrote a good Book call’d, <title>The
                     Mystery of Godliness and Ungodliness</title>, against the <title>Quakers</title>, in 4to. 1653.’</note> I suspect therefore that
               it is written in a fierce puritanical spirit (for the author was a puritan) but not without some ability. I have one of Bugg’s works
               and only one – his Pilgrims Progress, by which it appears that hard words were liberally used on both sides.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Bugg (1640–1727; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Pilgrim’s Progress from Quakerism to Christianity</title>
                  (1700), no. 393 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> But these things are altogether unimportant as affecting
               principles on either side.</p><p rend="indent1"> To conclude then, my intention in writing the Life of your Founder and the Rise and Progress of your Society, is to do
               it diligently, faithfully and charitably, in a Christian Spirit not dissembling my own opinions, but rendering ample justice to the
               opinion of others. If I commit any unintentional errors, let them be pointed out and I will correct them thankfully. If I reason
               falsely let me be confuted – if I wilfully misrepresent any thing, let me be exposed and put to shame.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I remain, Sir yours with respect.</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>