<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3643</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4914</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3643. Robert Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 1
                  March 1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3643" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3643.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text taken from William Knight (ed.),
                     Memorials of Coleorton, 2 vols (London, 1887) .  Previously  published: William Knight (ed.), Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont
                     of Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 201&#8211;205.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3643" type="letter">
        <head>3643. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>,<date when="1821-03-01"> 1
                  March 1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text taken from William Knight (ed.),
                     <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887)<lb /> Previously published: William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont
                     of Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 201&#8211;205.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1821-03-01">1st March 1821.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> Dear Sir George, &#8211;</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My publishers are directed to send you a copy of the <hi rend="ital">Vision of Judgment</hi>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), published by Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme and Brown.</note> which I trust
               you will find on your arrival in Grosvenor Square. It is chiefly as a metrical experiment that I offer it to your notice. You are
               accustomed to the blank verse of Shakespeare and Milton<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Blank verse was used by William
                  Shakespeare (1564&#8211;1616; <title>DNB</title>) and John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), most famously in the latter&#8217;s
                     <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).</note> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>;
               nevertheless, I venture to hope this will not prevent you from feeling that the heroic measure of the ancients retains something of its
               dignity and power in our language, though the English is certainly less fit for it than either the Greek, the Latin, or the German.
               Taking it upon the principle of adaptation which I have followed, it appears to me a fine measure, inferior, indeed, to our blank verse
               (as every other measure is), but possessing in the union of variety and regularity, an advantage peculiar to itself. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The subject is not one which I should have chosen under other circumstances; but when I accepted the Laureateship, it
               was with a hope of being exempted from the ordinary worthless taskwork which degrades the office,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had hoped to escape the Poet Laureate&#8217;s traditional duty of composing annual Birthday Odes and New Year&#8217;s
                  Odes that were set to music and performed at court. However, despite the fact that these performances had been suspended since 1810,
                  he had still been compelled to write a New Year&#8217;s Ode each year since his appointment in 1813 and Birthday Odes in 1820 and
                  1821.</note> and a determination of exerting myself upon other occasions in a manner which, if that hope were gratified, would prove
               that I had no desire to shrink from labour, or, if it were not, might redeem the office from contempt. Time enough has now elapsed
               since the death of the King,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820;
                     <title>DNB</title>) had died on 29 January 1820.</note> and public transactions enough have occurred, to allow of treating the
               subject in an imaginative manner, which could not have been done without some shock to the feelings, while that event was recent, and
               had all the awfulness of immediate reality.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You, I am sure, will perceive a want of keeping in that part where the affairs of the Regency are noticed.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), Canto 3, the spirit of Spencer Perceval (1762&#8211;1812;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1809&#8211;1812, related some of the events of the Regency period of 1811&#8211;1820 to the ghost of
                  George III. During the Regency, George III was incapacitated by madness and thus unaware of crucial events such as the final victory
                  over France in 1815.</note> This fault was unavoidable. I could not offer a tribute of respect to the late King without a just
               compliment of this kind to the present,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. to the nation&#8217;s achievements under the leadership
                  of George IV, George III&#8217;s son and successor and his Regent 1811&#8211;1820.</note> and I hope that, though it was not possible to soften
               or harmonise the transition from fancy to fact, it has been done, where alone it was practicable, when the poem passes from fact to
               fancy, and enters again upon the imaginary world.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was particularly proud of this
                  transition from &#8216;fact to fancy&#8217; at the end of <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), Canto 3, lines 50&#8211;61; see Southey to John
                  Heraud, 15 March 1821, Letter 3653.</note> The measure, and the subject, and what I have said, and what I have left unsaid, will
               bring upon me a hailstone chorus of abuse. It will affect me much less than this abominable east wind, which is now making its way
               through walls, windows, and curtains to my discomfort, and making itself felt in spite of a leathern waistcoat. But against literary
               assailants I am armed at all points, and proof.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two French translations of <hi rend="ital">Roderick</hi> have been lately published.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The two translations of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814) were: Antoine Andr&#233; Brugi&#232;re, Baron de
                  Sorsum, <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title> (1820), no. 2697 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; and Pierre
                  Hippolyte Amillet de Sagrie (1785&#8211;1830), <title>Roderic, Dernier Roi des Goths</title> (1821), no. 2700 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library.</note> One of them has been sent me.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Hippolyte Amillet de Sagrie,
                     <title>Roderic, Dernier Roi des Goths</title> (1821).</note> The translator has not Frenchified it by any additions, but it is
               curious to see how skilfully he has contrived to skip every image and every expression which had any peculiar force or propriety. In
               this respect the version reminds me of what happens among peacocks where a white bird has crossed the breed&#8212;the degeneracy shows itself
               in the eye of the feather, even when all other parts of the plumage remain untainted. It would surprise me greatly if, after all that
               has been done to trim it to the French taste, anything so completely anti-Gallican in style, feeling, and composition, should meet with
               any approbation in France.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I am very busy with the <hi rend="ital">Peninsular War</hi>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). The printer was Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> with which
               the printer is proceeding steadily; and among other works of secondary import, I am going on with a series of dialogues upon the
               progress and the prospects of society.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress
                     and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> These are interspersed with local descriptions of this immediate neighbourhood,
               to relieve the subject, and render a wholesome prescription palatable. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">William
                  Westall</ref> has made half a dozen very beautiful drawings of the scenes which are to be engraved for the book. One of them is a
               view of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">this house</ref>, looking towards Newlands.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Greta Hall, Derwentwater, and Newlands&#8217;, in <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of
                     Society</title>, 2 vols (London 1829), II, before p. 343.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably heard from the Wordsworths<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthMary">Mary Wordsworth</ref>.</note> of the death of my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, which has been a great grief to me, as well as a great shock. We had spent a great deal
               of time together at home and abroad, and had planned other journeys, which it is now painful to think of. I never knew a man more
               thoroughly amiable in all his feelings, indeed I never saw in him the slightest action, nor heard from him a sentence or a word, which
               could lower him in my esteem; and then he bore his cross so meekly, that it was impossible to know him, and not to regard him with some
               degree of admiration as well as with pity. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mrs. S.</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> join in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>.&#8212;Believe me to be, dear Sir George, very truly and respectfully
               yours,</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="right"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>