<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3662</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4933</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3662. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 3 April 1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3662" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3662.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 6p. .  Previously  published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               240&#8211;243.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3662" type="letter">
        <head>3662. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1821-04-03">3 April 1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb /> Endorsements: 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> April 1821/ The zombi; The Zombi; 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> April
                  1821; 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> April 1821 <lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 6p.<lb /> Previously published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               240&#8211;243.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">The King</ref> has desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Knighton</ref> to let me know that &#8220;he has read the V. of
               Judgement twice, &amp; that he is much gratified by the Dedication &amp; pleased with the Poem.&#8221; <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Knighton had presented <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821) to George IV and reported the king&#8217;s reactions
                  back to Southey; see Southey to William Knighton, 30 March 1821, Letter 3661.</note> &#8211; Could you get a copy sent with the dispatches
               to our Minister at Florence,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Fane, Lord Burghersh (1784&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), Envoy
                  Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the Grand Duchy of Tuscany 1814&#8211;1830. He was also a soldier in the Peninsular War, MP
                  for Lyme Regis 1806&#8211;1816, a composer, and the Ambassador to Prussia 1841&#8211;1851 and to Austria 1851&#8211;1855. In 1841 he succeeded as 11th
                  Earl of Westmorland.</note> &#8211; for <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> &#8211; who is at Pisa? I know not in
               what other manner to <del>xxx</del> transmit it to him, &#8211; &amp; this is one of the uses of <del>th</del> an Ambassador. I once received
               at one time three folios thro the Spanish Ambassador from Cadiz.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Jos&#233; Maria de la
                  Cueva, 14th Duke of Albuquerque (1775&#8211;1811), Spanish Ambassador to Britain 1810&#8211;1811. Southey received a great deal of information,
                  newspapers and books concerning the situation in Spain during the Peninsular War from his correspondent Manual Abella, who was based
                  in Cadiz; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 23 March 1811, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter
                  1888.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has only seen the first paragraph which I sent him
               in a letter,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 8 February 1821, Letter 3629.</note> &amp; it has
               made him a convert to the metre; <del>which</del> &lt;this&gt; is no slight conquest, for except <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> I had looked upon him as the person among all my friends least likely to be reconciled
               to it. But the verdict of my peers is most decidedly in its favour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now to a more important subject. You were duly apprized towards the end of the year of Othello&#8217;s death. Since that
               lamented event this house was cat-less, till on Saturday March 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Calvert,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert, n&#233;e Mitchinson (dates unknown), wife of William Calvert.</note> knowing how grievously we
               were annoyed by rats afforded me what she described as a fine full &lt;grown&gt; black cat, who was moreover a Tom. She gave him an excellent
               character in all points but one, which was that he was a most expert pigeon catcher; &amp; as they had a pigeon house, this propensity
               rendered it necessary to pass sentence upon him either of transportation or of death. Moved by compassion (his colour &amp; his Tomship
               also being taken into consideration) I consented to give him an asylum, &amp; on the evening of that day, here he came &#8211; in a sack.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You Grosvenor who are a philogatist &amp; therefore understand more of cat-nature than has been ever attained by the
               most profound naturalists, know how difficult it is to reconcile a cat to a <del>xxxx</del> new domicile. When the sack was opened, the
               kitchen door <del>which leads</del> into the passage was open also, &#8211; &amp; the cat disappeared; not indeed like a flash of lightning,
               but as fast as one, &#8211; that is to say, for all purposes of a simily. There was no chance of his making his way back to the Pigeon House;
               he might have done this had he been carried thrice the distance in any other direction, &#8211; but in this, there was either a river to
               cross, or a part of the town to pass, both of which were such obstacles to his travels that we were quite sure all on this side of them
               was to him terra incognita. Food therefore was placed where he would be likely to find it in the night, &amp; at the unanimous desire
               of the children I took upon myself the charge of providing him with a name, for it is not proper that a Cat should remain without one.
               Taking into consideration his complection as well as his sex, <del>I</del> my first thought was to call him Henrique Diaz,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Henrique Dias (1605&#8211;1662), who led a Portuguese force composed of freed men and slaves against the Dutch
                  in the two countries&#8217; war in Brazil 1621&#8211;1654.</note> a name which <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">poor Koster</ref>
               would have approved had he been living to have heard it: &#8211; but it presently occurred to me that The Zombi<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Zumbi (1655&#8211;1695) was the last leader of the Quilombo dos Palmares, a community of fugitive slaves in Brazil.</note>
               would be an appellation equally appropriate &amp; more dignified. The Zombi therefore he was named.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was soon ascertained that the Zombi had taken possession of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">poor
                  Wilseys</ref> cellar, which being filled with pea-sticks afforded him a secure hiding place, &#8211; the kitchen also of that part of the
               house being forsaken, he was in perfect quiet. Food was laid for him every day, &amp; the children waited impatiently for the time when
               the Zombi would become acquainted with the house, &amp; suffer them to bec&lt;ome&gt; acquainted with him. Once or twice in the evening he
               was seen out of doors, &amp; it was known that he reconnoitred the <del>house</del> &lt;premises&gt; in the night, but in obstinate
               retirement he continued from Saturday till Saturday, seven days &amp; nights, notwithstanding all kind words were used to bring him
               out, &#8211; as if he had been <del>resolved obstinately</del> determined to live &amp; die a hermit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But <del>before</del> between four &amp; five o clock on the Sunday morning, all who had ears to hear were awakened by
               such screams as if the Zombi had been caught in a rat-trap, or had met with some other excruciating accident. You M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford understand cats, &amp; know very well that a Cat-solo is a very different thing from a duet: &amp; that no person
               versed in their <del>own</del> tongue can mistake their expression of pain for any thing else. The creature seemed to be in agonies &#8211; a
               light was procured, that it might be relieved if that were possible, &#8211; upon searching the house the Zombi was seen at the top of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Wilseys</ref> stairs; from whence he disappeared retreating to his strong hold in the cellar
               nor could any traces be discovered of any hurt that could have befallen him; nor has it since appeared that he had received any, so
               that the cause of this nocturnal disturbance remains an impenetrable mystery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Various have been our attempts to explain it. Some of the women who measure the power of Rats by their own fears, would
               have it that he was bitten by a Rat, or by an Association of Rats, but to this I indignantly replied that in that case the ground would
               have been strewn with their bodies, &#8211; &amp; that it would have been the Rats cry, not the Zombi&#8217;s that would have been heard.
               Dismissing therefore that impossible supposition I submit to your consideration in the form of queries the various possibilities which
               have occurred to me, &#8211; all unsatisfactory I confess, &#8211; requesting you to assist me in my endeavours to find out the mystery of this
               wonderful history, as it may truly be called. You will be pleased to bear in mind that the Zombi was the only Cat concerned in the
               transaction; &#8211; of that I am perfectly certain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now then Grosvenor, &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1. Had he seen the Devil?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 2. Was he making love to himself?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 3. Was he engaged in single combat with himself?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 4. Was he attempting to raise the Devil by invocation?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 5. Had he heard me sing, &amp; was he attempting (vainly) to imitate it?</p>
        <p rend="indent0"> These queries, you will perceive all proceed upon the supposition that it was the Zombi who made the noise. &#8211; But I
               have farther to ask</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 6. Was it the Devil?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 7. Was it Jeffery?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Jeffrey&#8217; was the name given to the apparition in an account
                  of a ghost by Emilia Wesley (1692&#8211;1771), sister of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Life of Wesley; and
                     the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 441&#8211;443. She attributed the apparitions she experienced
                  to witchcraft. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 8. Were either of these personages tormenting the Zombi?</p>
        <p rend="indent0"> I have also to add that from that time to this he continues in the same obstinate retirement. &amp; to assure you
               that</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> I remain</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">
                  with the highest consideration</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yours as ever</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert
                  Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent10"> T.O.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">T.O.: In the MS this marks the end of the page, and instructs Bedford
                     to turn over to read the final section of the letter, where the joke is revealed.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">One farther query occurs while I am writing. Sunday having been the first of the month</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> 9. Was he making April fools of us?</p>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1821-04-03">3 April. 1821</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>