<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3333</idno><idno type="nines">rce4604</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3333. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 20 July 1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3333.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 183. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3333" type="letter"><head>3333. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1819-07-20">20 July 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend
						Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 23 JY 23/ 1819; 10 o’Clock/ JY. 23/
						1819 F N<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 183. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.
					</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-07-20">20 July. 1819</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> You probably know what my Scotch movements<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s tour
						of Scotland lasted from 17 August until 1 October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal of a Tour in
							Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> are to be, better than I do myself, &amp;
					will direct <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeathcoteWm">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Heathcote</ref> accordingly, so
					that he may take this place either in his way out, or home. He shall have a hearty welcome, &amp; I would house him
					if he were coming alone; – but neither he nor his fellow traveller<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heathcote
						was touring the north of England with his friends and fellow students at Oriel College, Oxford: Arthur Perceval
						(1799–1853; <title>DNB</title>), later a clergyman and Royal Chaplain 1826–1853; and James Wentworth Buller
						(1798–1865), MP for Exeter 1830–1834, MP for Devon North 1857–1865.</note> shall have any reason to complain of a
					cold reception. – I am glad to hear of this history of Para;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">When the parcel
						containing this work arrived Southey found it to be nothing more than another copy of Manoel Aires de Casal
						(1754–1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Relação Historico-Geografica do Reino do Brazil</title> (1817), no.
						3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey was not, therefore, able to learn any more about the
						expulsion of the Jesuits from Brazil in 1759 or expeditions into the Brazilian interior.</note> – it may very
					likely contain details of the expulsion, &amp; of the first expedition up some of the great rivers – the Tapajos,
					Xingu &amp;c. – I will spare no pains in preparing for a second edition,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A
						second edition of the first volume only of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) was published in
						1822.</note> whether it be called for in my time or not; wanted at some time or other it must be. So let me have
					the MSS when it arrives. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has not yet sent me the last
					sheet of the notes, with the tables of weights &amp;c.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Table of Weights,
						Measures, and Money’, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, p. 900; the ‘conclusion’
						was Southey’s final peroration, see <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, p.
						879.</note> I hope you will like the conclusion.</p><p rend="indent1"> The life of Wesley<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley;
							and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> will not have the same sure popularity &amp;
					consequent sale as the Remains of Kirke White.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Remains of Henry
							Kirke White, of Nottingham</title>, first published in 1807, it reached an eighth edition in 1819.</note> One set
					of readers will be offended that I allow him any merit, – another will be equally displeased that I should find in
					him any fault. For the irreligious <del>it will be too</del> the general tenour of the book will be too devout, –
					for the evangelicals it will be too rational. However it will excite some curiosity &amp; some talk; – &amp; tho I
					have no expectation that it will pay me as well as half the quantity of matter would have done in <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraylemagnes</ref> Review, – the time has been much worthily employed, – &amp; I
					shall be satisfied with 3 or 400 £ for my labour. The sixth sheet of the second volume is now on my desk. It will
					be finished in a few weeks after my return from Scotland.</p><p rend="indent1"> Before I set out I shall finish a paper upon the Monastic Orders<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Thomas Fosbrooke (1770–1842; <title>DNB</title>), <title>British Monachism; or,
							Manners and Customs of the Monks and Nuns of England</title> (1817), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22 (July
						1819), 59–102.</note> – the purport of which is to introduce an account of what Lady Isabella King<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Isabella Lettice King (1772–1845; <title>DNB</title>) founded the Ladies’
						Association at Bailbrook House, near Bath, in June 1816. It provided a home for orphaned gentlewomen with no
						income and was duly praised by Southey in his article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22 (July 1819),
						96–101.</note> is endeavouring to establish, – an institution for single women of the higher degree, – with all
					that is useful in monastic establishment, &amp; free from all their follies &amp; evils. – One of my favourite
					schemes, – if I live to set about it in earnest, is to give a History of the Monastic Orders,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey never completed his ‘History of the Monastic Orders’.</note> not in minute
					detail, – but selecting all which deserves to be prominent. And this I am quite certain would make one of the most
					amusing books that ever was written, &amp; do more good by laying the Catholic system bare, in this country than
					could be done by any other mode of attacking it. I have had this in mind since I was last at Lisbon.</p><p rend="indent1"> If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croft<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Croft, 1st
						Baronet (1778–1862), member of the Croft family of merchants and port producers, scientist and British spy during
						the French campaign in Spain in 1810. He was one of the organisers of the relief operation for Portuguese
						civilians funded by the British government in 1811.</note> comes in my way I shall know what to say to him, &amp;
					be very civil. Burn<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Burn (1750–1821), British merchant whom Southey
						had met on his visits to Portugal in 1796 and 1800–1801.</note> sent me a portfolio of papers concerning that
					subscription</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has lost a cow, – &amp; before half his
					hay is in a deluge is come upon us – it has been raining from an early hour on Sunday morning till this time – (two
					o clock, Tuesday) &amp; tho the glass is rising, the sky looks as if it would rain all the rest of the day. We are
					going to dine at Leathes–Water, six miles off.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear with whom
						the Southeys were dining; it might have been Thomas Stanger Leathes (c. 1778–1838) of Dale Head Hall, a member of
						the Stanger family who had inherited this property on Leatheswater (now part of Thirlmere) and used it as a summer
						home.</note> The idle season is coming on, &amp; I shall have a series of interruptions</p><p rend="indent1"> – But I must go &amp; dress, – or the chaise will be here. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the boys</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> We are going on tolerably well. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">young one</ref> thrives wonderfully</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>