<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3402</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4673</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3402. Robert Southey to [John Wilson Croker], 15
                  December 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3402" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3402.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Brotherton Library, University of
                  Leeds. ALS; 3p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                  York, 1965), II, pp. 208&#8211;209.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3402" type="letter">
        <head>3402. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">John Wilson Croker</ref>], <date when="1819-12-15">15
                  December 1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Ansd<lb /> MS: Brotherton Library, University of
                  Leeds. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                  York, 1965), II, pp. 208&#8211;209.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-12-15">15 Dec. 1819</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for both your letters, &amp; for the Guardian, which I will send wherever there seems a chance of finding
                  subscribers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Guardian</title> (1819&#8211;1824) was advertised as &#8216;a New Weekly Paper,
                  conducted on Principles of Attachment to our present Establishment in Church and State. Published every Saturday Evening&#8217;. It was an
                  attempt, masterminded by Croker, to break the radical hold on the Sunday newspaper market. Southey and William Calvert clubbed
                  together to subscribe to it; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 22 December 1819, Letter 3407.</note> I am too far from
               London to be of any use to such a journal, even were I at leisure so to amuse myself. Indeed I have not infrequently been prevented
               from sending a few lines to the Courier, by considering that before my remarks could arrive in town, the subject which gave occasion to
               them would have lost its freshness, &amp; be grown out of date. You set off with some good squibs.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first issue of the <title>Guardian</title>, 12 December 1819, contained some short satires on public
                  figures.</note> Martins Motto might have been added &#8211; <hi rend="ital">Tam Mercurio quam Marte</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;made for wisdom as much as war&#8217;; an inversion of the motto of the poet George Gascoigne (c. 1535&#8211;1577;
                     <title>DNB</title>).</note> as suited to the <del>xxxx</del> new quarterings &lt;or honorary augmentation&gt; which he has introduced
               into the Stapleton arms.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Bree (1771&#8211;1842), formerly of Braithwaite Lodge near Keswick,
                  changed his name to Stapylton in 1817 to inherit the estates of his uncle, Sir Martin Stapylton (1751&#8211;1817), 8th Baronet, of Myton.
                  He had previously been known as a quack doctor, especially in the treatment of venereal disease, and had engaged in some
                  unsuccessful mining ventures in the Keswick area. He was lampooned in the first issue of the <title>Guardian</title>, 12 December
                  1819. Southey here jokes that Bree has added &#8216;wisdom&#8217; to the existing Stapylton reputation for valour, exhibited previously in the
                  Crusades and the Hundred Years War.</note> This strange fellow endeavoured to establish himself in this neighbourhood some years
               ago, &amp; after making himself sufficiently ridiculous, left it because no person would notice him. He sunk some money here in mining,
               &amp; acted like one who was half-fool, half madman. I am sorry <ref type="m" target="people.html#Greenough">Greenough</ref> should
               have exposed himself, &amp; somewhat surprized at it, having always heard of him as a man entitled to more than common respect for his
               habits &amp; attainments.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Bellas Greenough had resigned his commission in the Light Horse
                  Volunteers of London and Westminster in protest at the &#8216;Peterloo&#8217; Massacre of 16 August 1819. The two letters he sent to his
                  commanding officer were published in both the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 5 November 1819, and the <title>Times</title>, 6
                  November 1819. The first (dated 18 October 1819) described the Massacre as &#8216;an unexampled abuse of magisterial authority&#8217; and set
                  out the reasons for his resignation: &#8216;I cannot consent to serve any longer in a corps, in which the only security I have for not
                  being engaged in civil warfare, is the discretion of the Ministers &#8230; and the magistrates who framed such a declaration&#8217;. The second
                  letter (dated 2 November 1819) gave the reason for deciding to publicise his resignation: &#8216;The dismissal of Lord Fitzwilliam from
                  the Lord Lieutenancy of the West Riding of Yorkshire, for having promoted an inquiry into the unconstitutional proceedings at
                  Manchester, and an addition of 10,000 men to the regular army, for the purpose of intimidating the people, are circumstances which
                  require that the motives of my resignation should be distinctly avowed. The day is come, when the friends of a free Government must
                  speak out, unless they mean to be silenced for ever.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is an ill symptom to see how the importance of the Reporters is acknowledged in Parliament. Of the two tyrannies
               that of the pen appears to me more hateful than that of the sword, as a plague of wild beasts is less dreadful than a plague of insects
               &amp; reptiles, &amp; one would rather fall under a lions paw than be <del>ea</del> devoured alive by vermin. We were approaching
               rapidly to that state, &amp; it remains to be seen whether the present measures, which are very good as far as they go, will save us
               from it. They will, if the press be vigilantly watched. Just now it seems likely that juries would act as they ought to do, &#8211; for
               juries upon political questions must always be expected to act according to the prevailing feeling in their rank of life; &amp; at this
               time a favourable change appears to have taken place. But whatever the popular temper may be, the Law Officers ought never to relax in
               their duty. Another such acquittal as that of <del>Xxxxx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hone</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hone had been acquitted at three successive trials 18&#8211;20 December 1817 of blasphemous and
                  seditious libel.</note> would have justified them in proposing the repeal of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox&#8217;s</ref> law of libel, &#8211; which I consider as one of the most mischievous that ever was enacted.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Libel Act (1792), promoted by Charles James Fox, gave the main responsibility for deciding whether a
                  publication was libellous to the jury in a trial, rather than the judge.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Such a Committee as Bennet<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Grey Bennet (1777&#8211;1836), Whig MP for Shrewsbury
                  1806&#8211;1807, 1811&#8211;1826 and prominent critic of the government. On 9 December 1819 he proposed a select committee to investigate the
                  &#8216;state of the manufacturing districts&#8217;, but was opposed by the government and his motion was lost. Here Southey sets out some of the
                  arguments against such a committee that John Rickman had elaborated in his letter to Southey of 11 December 1819.</note> proposed
               would have done more mischief than any other imaginable measure, for it would have been the means of making Parliament itself circulate
               every kind of inflammatory opinion, &amp; all the ex-parte evidence in favour of the Radicals that could have been raked together. But
               I should have been glad to see such evidence concerning the causes of the existing commercial embarrasments as might be obtained by a
               Committee under proper guidance. I believe it would be found that our machinery has tempted the manufacturers to overstock all their
               markets, &amp; I fear also that that system of knavery which prevails in every branch of trade wherever it can be exercised, has led
               them to export such flimsy goods, that other countries are superseding us with their honester wares. If this latter opinion were
               verified, it is possible that some means of remedy might be applied. Another cause undoubtedly is that commercial embarrasments spread
               from one country to another, &amp; the distress which is felt in America acts upon England.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  &#8216;Panic of 1819&#8217; in the United States was a major financial crisis that had plunged the American economy into depression.</note>
               Where this is to end Heaven knows. I am of a hopeful temper, &amp; believe that most evils may be overcome <del>by</del> if they are
               met manfully &#8211; but I confess that when I consider the infinite complexity of our political system, wheel within wheel, I cannot but
               fear that is too complicated to go on. And I cannot conceal from myself that there is a general tendency toward some great change,
               which however it may end, must be dreadful in the process. However <hi rend="ital">nil desperandum</hi>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;No need to despair&#8217;.</note> should always be an Englishman&#8217;s motto, &amp; as the vulgar proverb says, God&#8217;s above
               the Devil, &#8211; a coarse <del>expression</del> mode of expressing a thought which brings with it more hope than I can find in any other
               consideration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Farewell my dear Sir. I shall hope to see you early in the spring. Meantime I am very busy both in prose &amp;
               rhyme.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert
                  Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>