<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3273</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4544</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3273. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 22 March
                  1819 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3273" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3273.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 178. ALS;
                  4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London,
                  1856), III, pp.124&#8211;127.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3273" type="letter">
        <head>3273. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1819-03-22">22 March
                  1819 </date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Worting/ Basingstoke/
                  Hampshire.<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 25 MR 25/ 1819<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 178. ALS;
                  4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London,
                  1856), III, pp.124&#8211;127.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">New-Englander</ref> here, lately from Lisbon. He tells me
               that the Academy have published two more volumes of the Chronicas Inedites,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Jos&#233; Correia da
                  Serra (1750&#8211;1823), <title>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Livros Ineditos de Historia Portuguesa</title> (1816), published by the Portuguese Royal
                  Academy of Sciences (founded 1779), no. 3361 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> the most Irish title <del>xxx</del>
               surely that ever was affixed to a book. &#8211; Your opposite neighbour Ant: Ribeiro dos Santos<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Ribeiro dos Santos (1745&#8211;1818), Professor at the University of Coimbra, historian, poet and Chief Librarian at the National
                  Library in Lisbon.</note> died last year; &#8211; Muller<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Wilhelm Christian Muller
                  (1752&#8211;1814), Dutch convert to Catholicism and Royal Censor of Books.</note> also is dead. Muller it seems has translated that paper
               of mine upon Portugueze literature in the second number of the Q.R. added some notes to it, &amp; printed it at Hamburgh, for private
               distribution in Portugal;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez; com as
                     Palavras Portuguezas Propriamente Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo d&#8217;Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 1 (May 1809), 268&#8211;292. Muller translated the review as <title>Memoria Sobre a Literatura Portugueza. Traduzida do
                     Inglez. Com Notas Illustradoras do Texto</title> (1809).</note> &#8211; in his official capacity he must have prohibited it. If I could
               have foreseen this the sketch should not have been so imperfect. &#8211;Some of the Portugueze <del>have xxxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;I hear&gt;
                  spoke<del>x</del> of my Brazil<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
               with great interest, wondering how the materials could possibly have been collected, &amp; expressing a great desire that it should be
               finished. &#8211; They will wonder much more when they see the last volume. My <del>xxx</del> &lt;visitor&gt; saw a good deal of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellJohn">John Bell</ref>, but little of the other English. &#8211; Verdier<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Timoteo Lecussan Verdier (1754&#8211;1831), Portuguese industrialist and literary editor, of French descent. Southey had attempted to
                  contact him when he visited Paris in May 1817.</note> is living in a garret at Paris, without his family, poor, &amp;
               broken-hearted. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is the third New Englander<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The other two New Englanders were Edward Everett
                  and Joseph Green Cogswell (1786&#8211;1871), bibliographer and educationist.</note> who has visited me within twelve months (&#8211; I had met
                  <del>xxxx this</del> &lt;one&gt; indeed at Paris,) &#8211; &amp; two of them are by far the most accomplished &amp; intelligent travellers whom
               I have ever fallen in with. This one is now returning home, after a four <del>x</del> years absence, during which time he has been
               living in the best society that France, Italy, Germany, Spain, Portugal &amp; England could <del>afford</del> boast. <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettEdward">Another of them</ref> is gone to Greece, meaning to visit Jerusalem &amp; Egypt, &amp; probably
               to return by way of Constantinople &amp; Moscow. They have been buying books largely. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">One of them</ref> has sent home 1000 volumes from Spain, among them a good Catalan collection. Madrid it seems is now the only
               place where books are to be found. There are none at Seville, nor at Cadiz. &#8211; &lt;nor at Zaragoza &#8211; nor at Barcelona.&gt; And Lisbon which
               was so good a place in our days has been drained <del>xxxx</del> by English purchasers. The famous archives of Simancas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The General Archive of Simancas, founded in 1540, and the first official archive of the Crown of
                  Castile.</note> have at last been put in order, &amp; all the American papers regularly arranged, from Columbus&#8217;s first
                  commission.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Columbus (1450/1451&#8211;1506), Italian explorer who was commissioned by
                  the Spanish Crown to sail west across the Atlantic in 1492 and discovered America rather than Asia.</note> Among these a very
               interesting document has come to light. <del>xx</del> A petition from Cervantes for a place in the America,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In a petition to the Council of the Indies, dated 21 May 1590, the writer Miguel de Cervantes (1546&#8211;1616) applied for
                  no fewer than four vacant posts in Spanish America. He was unsuccessful.</note> with a detailed account of <hi rend="ital">sus
                  servicios</hi>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;his services&#8217;.</note> at great length. &#8211; Montserrat<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Mountain and abbey near Barcelona.</note> he tells me is in no respect comparable to Cintra for beauty, or
               singularity. I was glad to hear this. &#8211; A masterly edition of the Fuero Juzgo<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Fuero
                     Juzgo en Latin y Castellano</title> (1815); a codex of Spanish laws issued in 1241.</note> has been published. I know a channel
               by which I can send for this &#8211; &amp; by the same means I shall endeavor to get a <del>catalogue</del> list of their new publications. &#8211;
               The south of Spain is dreadfully unsafe. In many parts there is no travelling without an escort. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I come to you at Worting, if you could get your Church supplied for one Sunday, I should very much like to go
               round the Isle of Wight with you. Starting from thence, it would be an easy excursion. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have extracts from some Rio Almanachs &#8211; Where were those Almanachs printed? It is said in the Correio
                  Braziliense<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808&#8211;1822), a Portuguese journal published
                  in London, no. 3203 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> that there was no printing press in Brazil, till one was sent
               from England in 1808. I rather think there would be one for printing Almanachs &amp; Edicts, <del>xxx</del> though it was not used for
               any other purpose. My concluding chapter<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 44, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 696&#8211;879, a review of the state of Brazil at the time the Portuguese court fled there in
                  1807&#8211;1808.</note> must be a summary view of Brazil at the time of the removal, &amp; I shall get to it in the course of a week. What
               a satisfaction to be so near the end! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your news respecting <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> will be true ere long.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The news that Scott would be made a Baronet, as eventually happened in 1820.</note> He has
               received not less than fourscore thousand pounds for his writings, &#8211; &amp; 70,000 more have lately fallen to his children by the death
               of his wifes brother.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Scott had married Charlotte Genevieve Carpenter in 1797. Her brother,
                  Charles Carpenter (d. 1818), was Commercial Resident for the East India Company at Salem, Madras. He left the interest on his
                  fortune of &#163;40,000 to his wife, Isabella Carpenter, n&#233;e Fraser (d. 1862), but Scott&#8217;s children, Sophia Scott (1799&#8211;1837), Walter
                  Scott (1801&#8211;1847), Anne Scott (1803&#8211;1833) and Charles Scott (1805&#8211;1841), were to inherit the capital after her death.</note> But I
               very much fear that poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> will not long live to enjoy his honour &amp; his
               fortune. For the last two or three years he has been subject to cramps in the stomach, &#8211; a disease which has proved fatal to several of
               his family. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">My Yankee friend</ref> left him under one of these seizures. They have
               already in great measure broken him down so that he is said to <del>Xx</del> &lt;have grown&gt; full ten years older within the last two,
               &amp; he is become quite grey, &#8211; tho a light haired man, &#8211; who had not I think a gray hair in his head four years ago, when I saw him
               last. I am very sorry for this. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>
          <del>is the least of a Scotchman of any
                  of</del> has none of the bad parts of the Scotch character. He is a warm hearted, friendly, generous creature, &amp; Fortune for
               once did well when she <del>put the</del> &lt;gave him the&gt; golden pap spoon <del>in his mouth</del> at his birth. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I of the wooden spoon,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">An award given each year to the student who received the
                  lowest third class degree at the University of Cambridge, and, hence, an award to someone who comes last.</note> am likely to become
               popular in New England by my next long poem.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished epic, set in New England. The
                  completed sections were published after Southey&#8217;s death in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other
                     Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;90.</note> That poem is now in a fair way I have begun the fourth book, &amp;
               always the farther I get on a journey the faster I travel. &#8211; I like the conception <del>of the poem</del>, &#8211; &amp; am not dissatisfied
               with the execution as far as it has gone. &#8211; Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-03-22">22 March 1819. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>