<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3470</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4741</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3470. Robert Southey to Edith May Southey, 25&#8211;29 April 1820 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3470" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3470.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public
						Library. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 36&#8211;37 [in part; dated 25 April 1820].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3470" type="letter">
        <head>3470. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1820-04-29">25&#8211;29 April 1820 </date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss
						Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland <lb /> Postmark: [partial] AP 29 1820 <lb /> MS: Berg Collection, New York Public
						Library. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 36&#8211;37 [in part; dated 25 April 1820].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Shrewsbury.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-04-25"> Tuesday 25 April. 1820</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent0"> Having nothing else to do, for a dismal hour or two, I sit down to write to you, in such rhymes
					as may ensue, be they many or be they few, according to the cue, which I happen to pursue. I was obliged to stay at
					Llangedwin till to day: tho I wishd to come away, <del>yet</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> would make me delay, my departure yesterday, in order that he &amp;
					I might go to see, a place whereof he once sent a drawing to me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now I&#8217;ll tell you why, it was proper that I should go thither to espy the place with mine own
					eye. Tis a Church in a vale,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">St Melangell&#8217;s Church, Pennant Melangell. The
						medieval <title>Historia Divae Monacellae</title> describes how St Melangell, a seventh-century Irish princess,
						protected a hare from a local prince&#8217;s huntsmen. He was so impressed that he gave her the land for the church and
						the hare became her symbol. The story is represented on a series of panels on the church&#8217;s rood screen.</note>
					whereby hangs a tale, how a hare being prest by the dogs &amp; much distrest, the hunters coming nigh<del>xx,</del>
					&amp; the dogs in full cry, lookd about for some one to defend her, &amp; saw just in time, as it now comes pat in
					rhyme, a Saint of the feminine gender. <del>If you can xxx xxxxxx the story you may find</del> The Saint was buried
					there, &amp; a figure carved with care, in the church yard is shown as being her own; but tis used for a whetstone
					(like the stone at our back door) till, the pity is the more, (I should say the more&#8217;s the pity, if it suited with
					my ditty) <del>xxxx</del> it is whetted half-away, lack a day &#8211; lack a day!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They show a mammoths rib (was there ever such a fib!) as belonging to this Saint Melangle.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A large bone, more than four feet in length, displayed in the church. It is a
						whale bone.</note> It was no use to wrangle. &amp; tell the simple people that if this had been her bone, she must
					certainly have grown to be three times as tall as the steeple.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Moreover there is shown a monumental stone as being the tomb of Jorwerth Drwndwn;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The reputed tomb of Iorwerth Drwyndwn (1145&#8211;1174), son of Owain Gwynedd (c. 1100&#8211;1170;
						Prince of Gwynedd 1137&#8211;1170). In <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Iorwerth was the eponymous hero&#8217;s brother; and Madoc
						visits the Church of St Melangell at <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part One, Book 10, lines 144&#8211;190.</note> (w you
					must know serves in Welsh for long o.) In the portfoli<hi rend="ital">o</hi>, there are drawing of these tombs
					&amp; of the Church also. This Jorwith was killed six hundred years ago. Nevertheless as perhaps you may guess, he
					happened to be an acquaintance of mine &amp; therefore I always have had a design, to pay him a visit whenever I
					could, &amp; now this intention at last is made good.</p>
        <p rend="indent0"> Ludlow. <date when="1820-04-29">Saturday. 29 April</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thus far I had gone, ding dong <del>xx</del> rhyming on, till at last I myself was grown tired of
					the song; poor I was sleep<hi rend="ital">y</hi>, the hours were too slow &amp; gladly I went to beabo. And now
					twill be better, in plain prose to hasten &amp; finish my letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There being no coach to London from this place either on Saturday or Monday I am obliged to take
					my place for the Sunday, which makes my stay here a day longer than I had intended. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kenyon</ref> had given a full account of all our goings on
					at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. He said a great deal I find of you my Lady, but I
					shall not tell you what he said, farther than that <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">Kenyon</ref> would
					be as good a name as Kennaway,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836).
						Two of his sons had visited Southey in October 1819: John Kennaway (1797&#8211;1873) of Trinity College, Cambridge (B.A.
						1821), who later succeeded to his father&#8217;s baronetcy; and <ref type="m" target="people.html#KennawayCharlesE">Charles Edward Kennaway</ref>, a student at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge (B.A. 1822).</note> if I could but find
					as good a rhyme to it. &#8211; Our good friends here have given me some seeds of the vegetable marrow for your <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Aunt Lovell</ref>. They are to be raised like cucumbers &amp; planted
					out on a hot bed, but when the frosts have ceased they need no covering, they spread largely, bear abundantly,
					&amp; two plants will furnish as <del>many</del> much produce as we can desire, till about the month of October. No
					time should be lost in sowing the seeds. I will send them in a frank from London &amp; the best way will be to give
					them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrothersMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Crothers</ref> ask her to raise
					them, &amp; to give us two or three of the plants. They are said to be one of the best vegetables, either plain
					boiled, or stewed. It is a small gourd, &amp; is best when about the size of a small cucumber.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A small packet for <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your Mamma</ref> was given me
					yesterday, &amp; in London I am to receive a packet for your Ladyship, containing a watch, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.</ref> has desired a friend to purchase at Paris for you.
					Should this prove, as probably it will handsomer than your own, yours shall be consigned to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, &amp; the sum which you paid for it added to the capital of your
					private fortune. When I was asked why I did not bring you, as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> B.</ref> had
					so often desired, I said you would not come: that you were a very obstinate, odd sort of girl, &amp; I gave you a
					very bad character, as you deserve.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The weather is very cold. I start at six o clock tomorrow, &amp; shall have to wait three or four
					hours at Worcester for the Mail. But I shall reach town to breakfast on Monday &#8211; We dine to day at D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nicholls,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Whitlock Nicholl (1786&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>),
						physician and biblical scholar, resident in Ludlow 1816&#8211;1826.</note> a pleasant man. &#8211; love to all &#8211; I wish Pappa
					&amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">his Cuddy</ref> could go into the study. We would
					not mind any thing that might happen in the way of a misfortune.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>