<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3498</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4769</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3498. Robert Southey to Edith Southey, 25 June 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3498" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3498.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry
						(ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
					214&#8211;215.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3498" type="letter">
        <head>3498. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1820-06-25">25 June 1820</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland<lb /> Postmark: [partial] o&#8217;clock/ 26/ N<hi rend="sup">T</hi>
            <lb />
						Stamped: [illegible]<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry
						(ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
					214&#8211;215.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent1"> If we travel in chaises we shall hardly arrive before evening. I should very much prefer
						the mail, but the fatigue would perhaps be too much for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my
							Aunt</ref>. &amp; moreover we could not be sure of places, or likely to get them. This being the case you may
						look for us on Sunday evening. Perhaps I may write a few lines from Birmingham.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">If we travel &#8230; Birmingham: the postscript is written upside down at the top of fol.
						1r.</note>
          </salute>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-06-25">Sunday 25 June. 1820</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your account of the children<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert Southey</ref>.</note> is <del>xxx</del> rather what might be expected than wished. I dare say summer,
					bathing &amp; ripe fruit will soon set them to rights. The main thing with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> must be to attend to his bowels, &#8211; teething will
					account for his increased irritability (which must also be looked for at his age) &amp; for the redness in his
					face, which I believe is no bad symptom at that time. I suppose you have introduced him to the strawberry bed,
					which will prove a useful as well as agreable acquaintance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If it had not been for one expression in your letter, I should have thought it was written in an
					uncomfortable tone of feeling. With regard to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; his
					family I need no vexation beyond what the certain prospect before them must needs give me whenever that distressing
					subject is presented.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had seven children: Margaret Hill Southey
						(b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815&#8211;1864);
						Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816&#8211;1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818&#8211;1850); and Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834),
						born on 8 May 1820. They were followed by Sophia Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859) and Thomas Castle Southey
						(1824&#8211;1896).</note> I do not see any chance of fortune which can prevent them from being a heavy burthen, &amp; a
					sore grief to me as long as I live, unless he were to make up his mind to leave the kingdom, &amp; remove with them
					to the Cape,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">There were no fewer than six different state-aided emigration
						schemes in 1815&#8211;1826 to Canada and the Cape of Good Hope, including a grant of &#163;50,000 in July 1819 to send 4,000
						settlers to South Africa.</note> or some place where the larger the family, the better the settler fares; &amp;
					this is a thought which probably has never entered his mind. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I have often talked the matter over. This boarder, if we can succeed in the negociation, will
					give him a good lift, but only for a time.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger, Mary
						Laetitia Wilbraham (b. 1799), daughter of Randle Wilbraham (1773&#8211;1861) of Rode Hall in Cheshire. She later married
						Joseph-Harrison Tryer (b. 1797) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Although Southey found her harmless, even
						comical, Tom and his wife disliked her intensely, causing a great deal of tension in their household; see Southey
						to Henry Herbert Southey, 15 October 1821, Letter 3735.</note> It is not likely that she will remain more than
					half a year; that however is something, &amp; in as far as it is gain to him, must be a saving to me; for you must
					well know that when <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> is in want, however much I may
					blame him for marrying with such wilful &amp; premeditated imprudence, I cannot but assist him to the extent of my
					power. In such a case I must do as <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> would have
					wished me to do, had she been living. &#8211; It may put me occasionally to some inconvenience &amp; may deprive me of
					some luxuries which would otherwise be within my reach: &#8211; hardly this. But how little should I deserve the abundant
					blessings with which it has pleased God to favour me if I dealt &lt;otherwise&gt; towards him <del>xxxxxxxxxxx</del>
					&amp; withheld assistance which it might be in my power to bestow? He however will be guilty of the most
					unpardonable imprudence if he goes on relying upon what he can draw from me, from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> (to whom I find he is in the habit of applying.) All these
					resources must be casual. We have none of us too much for ourselves &amp; with our lives all our assistance must
					fail. My family will be provided for in the event of my death, but I can make no provision for any other
					persons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whenever that event may take place, my Will will be found in my desk (the upper part of it) in a
					sealed paper. It leaves every thing to you for your life, &amp; afterwards divides it equally among the children.
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother Henry</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville
						White</ref> are, with their <del>xxxx</del> consent, appointed executors &amp; trustees. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> assures me that my insurance of 4000&#163; is at this time worth <hi rend="ital">six</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had taken out a policy with the Equitable
						Life Assurance Society (founded 1762), of which John May was a Director.</note> I undervalue my property therefore
					in stating it at ten thousand pounds, were I to die this day: &#8211; twelve would be nearer the mark. And if I live
					&amp; do well I shall from this time forward begin to accumulate property rapidly, having, I may say, engaged for
					work which will <del>xx xxxxxx xxxx xxxx xxxxxx xxxxx</del> &lt;enable me to lay by at least 500&gt; a year.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had agreed to write for John Murray a <title>History of the Peninsular
							War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824), <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on
							the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829), and a series of (unrealised) biographical
					studies.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let us then my dear Edith, be thankful. You have a kind heart &amp; have never wanted the will to
					do good according to your means. The means hereafter will be more correspondent to the will. I will not fill this
					paper with telling you what my plans are, farther than saying that I have my choice of three works for each of
					which I <del>xxx</del> &lt;may&gt; have at the rate of a thousand guineas for a quarto volume;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and two
						unrealised projects that Southey had discussed with Murray. The notes for the first survived and were posthumously
						published as &#8216;Collections for the History of Manners and Literature in England&#8217;, <title>Common-Place Book</title>,
						ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 439&#8211;578; see Southey to John Rickman, 7 July 1820,
						Letter 3508. The second project was a biography of Warren Hastings (1732&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>),
						Governor-General of Bengal 1773&#8211;1785, which Southey eventually declined to undertake.</note> &amp; that I have
					refused 1500&#163; for Oliver Newman, with two contingent payments afterwards of 50&#163; each.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished epic, set in New England. The completed sections were published after
						Southey&#8217;s death in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical Remains</title>
						(London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;90.</note> Wesley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of
							Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). It was also proving profitable for Southey,
						selling out quickly and going into a second edition in 1820.</note> has raised my reputation to the highest pitch.
					About all these things we will talk in another weeks time. Places for <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> &amp; myself will be taken in the Birmingham Mail for Wednesday next. &amp; if we proceed by chaises
					from thence, as I suppose we shall, in order to make the journey easier for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref>, we shall reach home on Sunday. I should far rather have run down
					by myself directly in the mail. But it will suit them<del>x xx</del> much better to travel in my company, &amp; you
					know I am not in the habit of considering myself alone. You will easily manage about beds, when once you set about
					it. John Cockbaine<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cockbaine (1786&#8211;1873), Keswick draper and
						tailor.</note> with some blue paper, or Glover<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Glover (1767&#8211;1849;
							<title>DNB</title>), the watercolour painter who owned Blowick Farm in Patterdale, on Ullswater. </note> with
					some water colours, could make the lumber room fit for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> might occupy their chamber. This would be better than doing any
					thing with the damp wing room. Your wish to have me for a few days at least to yourself, I take kindly, as it is
					meant. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> you know is not like a visitor. He will open his
					portfolio, &amp; fall to work, like one of the family, in All Saints Chamber,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The room at Greta Hall that contained Southey&#8217;s copy of the <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>
						(1643&#8211;1794), a massive 53-volume compendium of hagiographies, which he had bought in Brussels in 1817, no. 207 in
						the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> while I work in my own room &amp; in my own way. And <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> will make herself happy by endeavouring to make herself useful. She
					is an excellent woman. &amp; it is really a great gratification to me that she is coming to visit us at last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a great deal to tell you when we meet. In my last I hinted at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartleys</ref> misconduct.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John
						Taylor Coleridge had been told by the clergyman and poet John Keble (1792&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>) that his
						cousin Hartley Coleridge had lost his Fellowship at Oriel College, Oxford, on 30 May 1820, the end of his
						probationary year, on the grounds of intemperance. John Taylor Coleridge had then forwarded Keble&#8217;s letter to
						Southey, who had to break the news to Hartley&#8217;s mother and friends in the Lakes.</note> Whether he will break the
					matter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his mother</ref> before he comes down I know not, &#8211; but I
					own it surprizes me that he should think of coming down under such circumstances. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> is in town, &amp; dined with us yesterday at <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref>
					&amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> G.</ref> return to London tomorrow. the
					latter &amp; the children much the better for Tunbridge air. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> is grown stout &amp; seems in excellent health. I breakfast tomorrow with <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T Ackland</ref>, at Mitcham, &amp; on Tuesday get to town as early as I
					can having still much to buy &amp; to do. I hope you will like your scarf. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill</ref> sends <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> what I suppose to be a gown-piece of worked muslin. I am afraid
					it would be useless to open the parcel in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref> to
					look for her shoes &amp; gloves, because I should not know them from yours, or any others. It is odd that I have
					not received the watch for her.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Wade Browne had ordered a watch for Edith
						May Southey from Paris.</note> &#8211; What a relief it will be to feel myself once more quietly at home, among my books
					&amp; papers! As for poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuddys</ref> being disimproved,
					I suppose it is wholly owing to the effect of the measles, &amp; to the eruption which frequently attends teething.
					Tell him that I am going tomorrow to buy pretty things. In a very few hours he will learn to remember me, I
					warrant, especially when I speak the rhinoceros-language. &#8211; The weather is excessively hot. &#8211; Perhaps I may find
					time this morning to write a letter to the children, which I would have done oftener if I could.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel
							Southey</ref>, 26 June 1820, Letter 3499.</note> My love to them. God bless you &#8211; yr affectionate RS.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>