<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3390</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4661</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3390. Robert Southey to Humphrey Senhouse, 17 November 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3390" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3390.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Department of
						Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey
						Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3390" type="letter">
        <head>3390. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1819-11-17">17 November 1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Humphrey
						Senhouse Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Fingest Grove/ Stoken Church/ Oxfordshire<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />
						Seal: red wax, design illegible<lb /> Watermark: G W/ 1816; embossed seal with crown, BATH<lb /> MS: Department of
						Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey
						Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-11-17">17 Nov. 1819.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear
					Senhouse</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will probably have heard or seen that an Address of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wallace&#8217;s
					composition has been substituted for that which I sent to you, -<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Following
						the &#8216;Peterloo&#8217; Massacre of 16 August 1819, Whigs in Cumberland organised a County Meeting on 13 October 1819 to
						protest at the local authorities&#8217; actions and send an Address to the Prince Regent. Southey drew up a conservative
						response &#8211; an Address to the Prince Regent denouncing the radicals and calling for curbs on the press; see Southey
						to Humphrey Senhouse, [15 October 1819], Letter 3366. The tone and content of the Address were objected to by
						moderate supporters of the government in the Lake District, led by Thomas Wallace (1768&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>),
						MP for various seats 1790&#8211;1828, including Cockermouth 1813&#8211;1818, member of the Board of Control 1807&#8211;1816,
						Vice-President of the Board of Trade 1818&#8211;1823, and later 1st Baron Wallace. Southey&#8217;s Address was suppressed and
						Wallace drew up a replacement, which was published in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> on 29 October 1819; it
						was notably circumspect in its reference to events at &#8216;Peterloo&#8217;. </note> the objections which struck you having
					occurred to him, &amp; to others also. It is not therefore worth while to enter into an explanation of what was
					laid aside: &#8211; in all such cases to need explanation is fault enough. The fault at Manchester, according to what I
					have heard, was in employing the yeomanry instead of the regular troops.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">When the Manchester magistrates ordered the arrest of the main speakers at the meeting at St Peter&#8217;s Field on 16
						August 1819, the task was delegated to the Manchester and Salford Yeomanry, a body of upper-class local
						volunteers; they began to attack the crowd indiscriminately, and the crowd responded by throwing brickbats at the
						Yeomanry. Finally, the meeting was dispersed by regular troops, primarily the 15th Hussars.</note> This was
					obviously done as appearing <del>the</del> least obnoxious But after bearing a great deal of outrage &amp; injury,
					they lost their temper, which disciplined soldiers would not have done, &amp; did more mischief than was necessary
					in dispersing the rascally rabble. This account is probable, &amp; came to me upon good authority. I do not believe
					that the Magistrates committed any other error. The illegality of the meeting, if any meeting can be illegal, is
					plain; &amp; the civil power was not sufficient to execute the warrant. But enough of this. Whether the crisis of
					this distemper is at hand we shall soon see. The sooner it comes the better, for I have not that confidence either
					in the foresight, or in the resolution of the Ministers to believe that that they will take such measures as might
					avert it. My advice would be not to suspend the Habeas Corpus,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas corpus
						is the legal principle that prevents detention without trial; it was suspended for one year from March
						1817.</note> because it can only be a temporary measure, &amp; therefore the good which it might produce would be
					temporary also; but to make banishment the punishment for sedition &amp; blasphemy, &amp; to prosecute libels as
					fast as they appear, to make new laws with regard to seditious meetings, &amp; to prevent all delay in bringing
					offenders to trial.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">When parliament reassembled on 23 November 1819, the
						government produced its proposals for the &#8216;Six Acts&#8217; to suppress radical agitation. Among this legislation, the
						Criminal Libel Act (1819) made banishment the punishment for a second offence and anyone breaching the sentence
						was to be transported for 14 years. The original version of the Bill had made transportation for seven years the
						punishment for a second offence and death the punishment of last resort. The government also produced a new
						Seditious Meetings Act (1819).</note> The press might then be kept within some bounds, &amp; if that evil were
					checked there might be some hope that the country would recover <del>xx</del> a healthy state of feeling.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been at Whitehaven, for the first time.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Whitehaven
						Castle, a mansion owned by William Lowther, Earl of Lonsdale. Southey visited in mid-October 1819.</note> Sir
					Joseph Senhouse<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Joseph Senhouse (1743&#8211;1829), Senhouse&#8217;s uncle. He had
						spent time as Comptroller of Customs in Dominica, acquired a small coffee plantation on the island, and returned
						to England in 1779. At this time he managed the Lowther family&#8217;s electoral interests in Carlisle.</note> dined at
					the Castle while I was there, &#8211; a fine old man. He told me that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> had never been forsaken before,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">While Netherhall was
						being renovated, Senhouse had been living abroad and at Fingest House in Buckinghamshire.</note> &amp; said so
					with a subdued feeling which set him high in my good graces. If other nations have no word for <hi rend="ital">home</hi>, we have no single one which can convey the meaning of the <hi rend="ital">solar</hi> of the Spaniards,
					in which as many good feelings have their root, &amp; those of a high order. Yours is unquestionably one of the
					oldest in this kingdom. &#8211; Nothing in Scotland<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s tour of Scotland had
						lasted from 17 August until 1 October 1819. For his comments on Highland burial grounds, see <title>Journal of a
							Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp. 127&#8211;128, 176.</note> pleased me
					more than the family burial grounds in the Highlands, &#8211; there is something about them so sacred &amp; solitary, &#8211;
					&amp; so well in keeping with the severe <del>xxxxx</del> character of the country. But I admired them also as
					tending to keep up that love of the natal soil, which all the circumstances of society in this age tend to
					weaken.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are in daily expectation of seeing <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">Kenyon</ref>
					here. He buried his wife at Naples, in the spring.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Susan Kenyon (d.
						1818).</note> This is but an unfavourable season for <del>revisiting</del> &lt;coming into&gt; the country after an
					interval of thirteen or fourteen years;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Kenyon had visited Southey in 1804;
						see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 21 November 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
							Three</title>, Letter 991.</note> but a sunshiny day will do wonders even in November; &#8211; &amp; long as that
					interval is, he is not yet far enough advanced into the yellow leaf of life<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Macbeth</title>, Act 5, scene 3, line 23.</note> to feel more of pain than of pleasure
					in revisiting scenes which he formerly enjoyed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Fisher of Cockspur Street<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Fisher (c. 1773&#8211;1819),
						member of a Borrowdale farming family and a gold and silversmith in Cockspur Street, London, had bought Greta Hall
						in June 1817. However, legal complications arising from the previous landlord&#8217;s debts had halted the
						purchase.</note> whose purchase of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">this house</ref> was suspended by
					proceedings in Chancery, is dead; &#8211; &amp; has left 50,000&#163; to his brother at Seatoller &#8211; in Borrodale.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Fisher (c. 1760&#8211;1835), a wealthy farmer, of Seatoller House in Borrowdale.</note>
					This enormous accession of wealth has turned his head; &#8211; the care I suppose, &amp; the bustle of thought which it
					brought with it, having called into action a constitutional tendency to mental derangement. &#8211; My landlord<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Tolson, Junr (dates unknown). He had been imprisoned for debt in
						Carlisle gaol in 1817, leading to the abortive sale of Greta Hall to Isaac Fisher. However, Tolson retained the
						ownership of Greta Hall until after Southey&#8217;s death.</note> is out of jail. I know not by what means, &#8211; &amp;
						<del>I app</del> it is not unlikely that another sale of the property may take place, as Chancery suits cannot be
					kept up without considerable expence. &#8211; I have myself <del>the</del> &lt;some&gt; prospect of an evil of this kind,
					arising from the death of Lord Somerville.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville, 15th
						Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), agricultural reformer and third cousin of Southey, had died on 5
						October 1819. This produced a further round of legal tangles over the Fitzhead estate in Somerset that Somerville
						had inherited.</note> Estates of about a thousand a year were bequeathed to him in his infancy by his mothers
					Uncle; with the intention that they should revert to the Southeys in case of his dying without issue.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Somerville&#8217;s mother was Elizabeth Cannon Lethbridge (d. 1765), the daughter of Mary
						Southey (1704&#8211;1789) and niece of John Cannon Southey (d. 1768). The latter had inherited the Fitzhead estate from
						his mother Mary Cannon (1678&#8211;1738). On his death, John Cannon Southey had left a complex, ill-advised will which
						named Somerville as his primary heir, and, if he should die without heirs, Southey&#8217;s father and two uncles as the
						residuary legatees, their rights passing, in turn, to their children. Of the three Southey brothers only Southey&#8217;s
						father married, leading the poet to believe (after the death of his father and paternal uncles) that he and his
						brothers were now the rightful heirs to the Fitzhead estate.</note> Lord Somerville notwithstanding the entail
					sold the whole property, &amp; I have now to ascertain whether or not it can be recovered. The will in question has
					been more than once pronounced to be one of the most confused that ever was made.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cannon Southey&#8217;s will had been the subject of earlier judicial hearings, all of which had
						struggled with the will&#8217;s complexities; for example, on 27 March 1807, Thomas Erskine, 1st Baron Erskine
						(1750&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1806&#8211;1807, had delivered a judgment in the Court of Chancery in
						the case of Southey <title>v</title>. Lord Somerville.</note> At present I am seeking advice upon the subject, &#8211;
					&amp; certainly I must be very strongly advised before I shall venture to incur the great &amp; certain evil of
					engaging in law.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey eventually decided not to pursue legal
						action.</note> Lord S. died at Vevay,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Somerville died &#8216;At Vevay, in
						Switzerland, on his return home, having spent the previous winter in Italy, and the last summer in France, for the
						recovery of his health&#8217;, <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>, 89 (October 1819), 370.</note> &#8211; his life would have
					been thought a better one than mine. My relationship to him is very remote, &#8211; that of third cousin, &#8211; but he had no
					nearer in that line. &#8211; <del>I had xxxxxxxxx &amp; xxxxxx that my</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I saw Scotland to the best advantage, &#8211; in delightful weather, &amp; every where with persons in
					our suite who knew every thing about the country.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s companions
						included <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Thomas Telford</ref>. </note> How strikingly the character of the country
					seems to accord with that of the people! &#8211; Have you seen Peters Letters?<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Lockhart was the author of <title>Peter&#8217;s Letters to His Kinsfolk</title> (1819), no. 2223 in the sale catalogue
						of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey had been given his copy in Edinburgh on 17 August 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in
							Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), p. 4.</note> &#8211; the joint composition of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">Wilson of Ellory</ref>, &amp; the Isle of Palms,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Wilson&#8217;s <title>The Isle of Palms, and Other Poems</title> (1812).</note> &amp; a <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockhartJohnG">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lockhart</ref>, &#8211; both also being the great writers in
					Blackwoods Magazine.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Blackwood&#8217;s Edinburgh Magazine</title>
						(1817&#8211;1980); it had originally been named the <title>Edinburgh Monthly Magazine</title>. It was owned and managed
						by William Blackwood.</note> It is a clever book, written with very considerable talents, but there is something
					hateful to me in serving up living characters, <del>at the table of</del> whether they are peppered &amp; grilled
					for satire, or have the oil of flattery for their sauce.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Peter&#8217;s
							Letters</title> was narrated by the fictional Welshman Peter Morris, and provided pen-portraits of key
						individuals in contemporary Scottish cultural life, including Francis Jeffrey and Walter Scott.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to the Miss Woods &amp; the children, <del>x</del>
          <note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Senhouse&#8217;s cousins, Mary Anne Wood (1781&#8211;1860) and Frances Wood (dates unknown); and Senhouse&#8217;s
						children, Elizabeth (1805&#8211;1890), Catherine (d. 1853), Ellen (1808&#8211;1838) and Humphrey (1809&#8211;1834).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0"> Can you learn where I may direct to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, &#8211; which I have neglected so long that I know not where to find him now.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>