<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3712</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4983</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3712. Robert Southey to William Westall, 12 August 1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3712" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3712.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Massachusetts Historical Society.
						ALS; 4p. (c). .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3712" type="letter">
        <head>3712. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">William Westall</ref>, <date when="1821-08-12">12 August 1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ William
						Westall Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 19. Mornington Place/ Hampstead Road<lb /> MS: Massachusetts Historical Society.
						ALS; 4p. (c).<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>. Maryport.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1821-08-12"> 12 Aug. 1821</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0">My dear
					Westall</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter followed me to this place, whereby one day was lost on the road, &amp; a second in
					consequence of the hour at which the post arrives here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of the many things which I have to say, let me begin by thanking you for your new number; which
					is a very good one, &amp; for the two marvellous proofs; marvellous they may rightly be called, because the effect
					in both is so perfectly produced.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear which prints Westall had
						sent to Southey, but they might have been proof impressions from his <title>Views of the Lake and of the Vale of
							Keswick</title> (1820) and his new publication, <title>Four Views of Windermere</title> (1821), advertised in
							<title>Lancaster Gazette</title>, 16 June 1821.</note> I should heartily wish that the Journal in which your
					prints are called catchpenny<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Parry&#8217;s (1790&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Journal for the Voyage of Discovery of a North-West Passage from the Atlantic to the Pacific; Performed in the Years 1819&#8211;20</title> (1821) contained 20 plates derived from sketches by Westall.  A notice of the book had described these plates as &#8216;paltry, catch-penny things&#8217;, <title>The London Literary Gazette, and A Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Sciences, etc. </title> (19 May 1821), 314.</note> were prosecuted, if it was
					not for the vexation &amp; expence which you would incur in the course of a prosecution: for law proceedings
					occasion almost as much evil to a plaintiff as to a defendant. There is however a sort of malice which defeats
					itself, &amp; this stupid criticism is of that kind. I am very glad you find your account in having learnt to
					engrave, but indeed the first samples made your success sure. I do not doubt your succeeding with the coral
						reef,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This reference is unclear. Westall had contributed plates to <title>A
							Voyage to Terra Australis</title> (1814), including &#8216;View of the Reef-Wreck Bank Taken at Low Water&#8217;.</note> nor
					indeed in any thing, where what you aim at representing is within the reach of the art.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now concerning the plates. Much as I should be gratified by seeing some illustrations of
					Roderick, from your hand &amp; your brothers, yet when you tell me that the whole speculation rests upon yourself,
					I cannot but intreat you to weigh the risk well, before you venture so large a sum upon it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The proposal was for Richard and William Westall to produce illustrations for Southey&#8217;s
							<title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814); these could then be inspected and purchased by readers and
						bound into their copies of the poem. The result was a set of engravings based on drawings by Richard Westall
						(1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>) and entitled <title>Illustrations of Roderick, the Last of the Goths. A Poem, by
							Robert Southey, Esq. from the Drawings of R. Westall R.A.</title> (1824). </note> The fact that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> would not venture upon such a speculation is some presumption
					against the probability of its success. Morever the poem no longer comes under the useful description of &#8220;<hi rend="ital">something new</hi>&#8221;. About 6000 copies have been sold:<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This
						figure was based on all of the first four editions of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> printed
						between 1814 and 1816 having sold out, but did not take any account of sales of the fifth edition of 1818.</note>
					&amp; of the possessors of those copies, many who would have bought the prints with the book, or while the
					impression of the book was fresh, will not buy them now when the volumes are bound, &amp; laid to repose upon the
					shelf. You see I am arguing like the Devils Advocate in a cause of Canonization, against my own desires.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In the canonisation process in the Catholic Church, the Promoter of the Faith is a
						canon lawyer, whose role is to argue against the canonisation of the candidate.</note> But indeed you must not
						re<del>x</del>ly upon the reputation of the poem; the question is whether there are persons enough who collect
					your brothers works, to cover the expence of such an undertaking; for the main dependence must be upon such
					purchasers. If you continue in your purpose, I will propose any thing which you desire to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &amp; do what I can to promote the sale among my own friends,
					but this is not much. The French translation which has been sent me is in octavo. I do not know the size of the
					other. -<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Hippolyte Amillet de Sagrie (1785&#8211;1830), <title>Roderic,
							Dernier Roi des Goths</title> (1821), no. 2700 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; and Antoine Andr&#233;
						Brugi&#232;re, Baron de Sorsum, <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title> (1820), no. 2697 in the sale catalogue of
						Southey&#8217;s library. Both were in octavo. Southey had been sent the version by Sagrie. </note> The same post which
					brought your letter last night, brought one from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my
						brother</ref> telling me that Alexander the Ventriloquist<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexandre
						Vattemare (1796&#8211;1864), celebrated French ventriloquist who used the stage name &#8216;Monsieur Alexandre&#8217;. Trained as a
						surgeon, he was refused a diploma after making cadavers appear to speak. Between 1815 and 1835, he visited 550
						cities with an act that involved him staging plays in which he voiced all the characters. In later life he
						developed the first system by which museums and libraries could loan items from their collections to each
						other.</note> has been looking for me in London, with an introduction from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">a member</ref> of the Dutch Institute whose wife has translated Roderick
					into Dutch.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Bilderdijk was a former President (1809&#8211;1811) of the Royal
						Netherlands Institute of Science, Letters and Arts (founded 1808), to which Southey had been elected an Associate
						of the Second Class in 1817. His wife was Katherina Bilderdijk, n&#233;e Schweickhardt (1776&#8211;1830), whose translation
							<title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title> was published in 1823&#8211;1824, no. 2701 in the sale catalogue of
						Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As soon as we return home which will be either on Saturday or Monday next, I will see if there be
					any armour of Rodericks age which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> can trace: I think
					can find some among German monuments &amp; great seals. &lt;But that which was used in England at the same time,
					would be equally proper. I believe there was little or no difference.&gt; I like the notion of landscape subjects,
					treated by your hand. With regard to other subjects, your brother is much better able to determine upon what
					situations are best suited to his art, than I can be: the error which I should be likely to commit is that of
					mistaking dramatic passion for scenic effect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the pains you have taken about M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenan.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Keenan (d. 1838), wife of John Keenan. Southey had first met her in Exeter in
						1799. She and her daughter had recently stayed with the Southeys at Keswick. Westall had made enquiries about
						whether she was entitled to any payments from the Artists&#8217; Benevolent Fund (founded in 1810); see Southey to
						William Westall, 7 July 1821, Letter 3701.</note> Her husband certainly was not a man to be respected, when he was
						known.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Irish portrait painter John Keenan (d. 1819), who had painted
						Southey in 1802.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am here with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her mother</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> at the house of my friend &amp; fellow traveller<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Senhouse
						had accompanied Southey on his May&#8211;August 1817 continental tour.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref>, for the double purpose of visiting [MS missing] him, &amp;
					giving Edith &amp; Cuthbert the advantage [MS missing] of sea bathing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want to send a proof set of your Lake Views<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Either Westall&#8217;s
							<title>Views of the Lake and of the Vale of Keswick</title> (1820), for which Southey had written an
					introduction, or Westall&#8217;s <title>Four Views of Windermere</title> (1821). Subscribers could send for a proof and then sign up for some or all of the forthcoming set.  By this means, artists and engravers reduced some of the risk entailed in the high upfront costs of printing high-quality engravings.</note> to America. Will you have the goodness to send the four numbers (&amp; the subsequent ones
					as they appear) to this direction, <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">George Ticknor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
          </ref> &#8211; to the care of Samuel Williams Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>. 13. Finsbury Square: &#8211; they
					will then regularly find their way to Boston.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Williams (d. 1841),
						born in Salem, Massachusetts, and educated at Harvard, had come to England in 1796 and established himself as a
						banker. He provided advice and support for American merchants and tourists, allowing the latter to collect mail at
						his London residence. After his firm, Williams &amp; Welles, was forced into bankruptcy, Williams returned to
						America in 1828. He died a poor man in Boston in 1841. </note> And I will desire <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to turn his horses head some Exchequer holy day in your
					direction &amp; pay for them, or to send the payment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The two Ediths<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
							Southey</ref>.</note> desire their kindest remembrances</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">The Americans have made me a member of the Massachusetts Historical Society,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Massachusetts Historical Society (founded 1791) is the oldest historical society
							in the United States. It is based in Boston, and collects and preserves documents on American history. Southey
							had been elected a member.</note> &#8211; the greatest literary honour that America has to bestow. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>