<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3393</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4664</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3393. Robert Southey to John May, 23 November
                  1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3393.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                  Austin. ALS; 4pp. .  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                     1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 180&#8211;182.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3393" type="letter">
        <head>3393. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1819-11-23">23 November
                  1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: [2 illegible]<lb /> Watermark: G W/ 1816<lb /> Endorsement: 209. 1819/ Robert Southey/ Keswick
                     23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> November/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                  Austin. ALS; 4pp.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                     1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 180&#8211;182.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-11-23">23 Nov. 1819.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your solicitude concerning me. A few weeks can make little or no difference in an infirmity like mine,
               &#8211; which is now a chronic one, &amp; which if it should not be cured may probably be prevented from growing worse, &amp; rendered very
                  bearable.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was suffering from a rectal prolapse; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey,
                  3 October 1819, Letter 3356.</note> My journey cannot be accelerated on that account, for I must not leave home before the life of
                  Wesley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>
                  (1820).</note> is finished &amp; before provision is made for my ways &amp; means in the Q. R.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> At present my finances are in a worse state than they have been for some
               years, owing to the great expence of time upon the Brazilian history,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume
                  of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) had appeared in October 1819. It ran to 950 pages.</note> &amp; to the
               harvest of Roderick being over.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In autumn 1818 Southey had estimated that <title>Roderick, the
                     Last of the Goths</title> (1814), had so far &#8216;brought me not less than 700&#163;&#8217;; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 18 September 1818,
                     <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3195. The poem went into a new edition in October of
                  the same year. Although it took a little while for this to recoup its expenses, Southey&#8217;s claim here, in 1819, that he could not
                  rely on <title>Roderick</title> to augment his finances was somewhat misplaced. The poem continued to sell at reduced levels, but
                  still better than others of his works. For example, between June 1820&#8211;June 1821, 330 copies sold, bringing Southey profits of &#163;85
                  16s 3d; see Longman Archive, University of Reading, Joint Commission and Divide Registers, 2D.</note> Things will soon be in a
               better train, &#8211; &amp; by making good use of my time <del>xx</del> now I may look for a spring tide in due season. Wesley will be
               finished for publication in January, &#8211; I hope to set out at the end of that month, &amp; as soon as I return, the Peninsular War goes
               to press.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask my opinion respecting the present state of things. The persons who are mainly to blame are the Law Officers for
               the last ten years, <del>who I</del> Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Garrow especially.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                  Garrow (1760&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>) Solicitor General (1812&#8211;1813) and Attorney General (1813&#8211;1817). In these offices he had the
                  main responsibility for deciding whether to prosecute radical publications for sedition or blasphemy.</note> By their criminal
               negligence the press has been suffered to become the most powerful engine of mischief that ever was brought to bear against the welfare
               of society. I know nothing of the course which Ministers mean to pursue, &#8211; except that they have no intention of suspending the H.
                  Corpus.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas corpus is the legal principle that prevents detention without trial; it was
                  suspended for one year from March 1817. Parliament reconvened on 23 November 1819 to pass the &#8216;Six Acts&#8217; suppressing radical
                  agitation &#8211; habeas corpus was not suspended.</note> They are wise in this, because the temporary advantage is not worth the outcry
               that would be raised against it. Not that I would regard outcry &amp; unpopularity for the sake of any permanent good: but the
               suspension of this <del>Bill</del> Act would only procure a suspension of danger, &#8211; you would shut up a dozen or a score of miscreants,
               who <del>in</del> &lt;under&gt; any other government would be hanged as they richly deserve, &#8211; &amp; at the end of the term they would be let
               loose to return to their old work. The great object is to check the abuse of the press by providing an effectual punishment for
               sedition &amp; blasphemy; that punishment should be fugitation for life &#8211; banishment is better than transportation.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Among the &#8216;Six Acts&#8217;, the Criminal Libel Act (1819) made banishment the punishment for a second offence
                  and anyone breaching the sentence was to be transported for 14 years. The original version of the Bill had made transportation for
                  seven years the punishment for a second offence and death the punishment of last resort. </note> If the offences are not
               sufficiently defined by the law, new laws should be made: <del>xx</del> every work of the kind should be prosecuted, without exception,
               &amp; as soon as a prosecution is commenced, the sale should be suspended, &#8211; as when an injunction is moved for. These measures would
               be effectual if juries were found to do their duty. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With regard to the Radicals I have heard enough, from the testimony of men who would willingly think otherwise, to
               convince me that the disturbed districts ought to be put under military law. They are not very numerous at Carlisle, but they have
               their propagandists about the country, &amp; the language which they hold is to the last degree atrocious. They make no secret of their
               intention to begin by cutting off those persons whom they regard as their enemies, &#8211; nor even of designating the men whom they have
               proscribed. I heard yesterday of a fellow who said he should have his first shot at a certain magistrate for whom he had formerly
               worked. That these Yahoos<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Swift (1667&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gulliver&#8217;s
                     Travels</title> (1726), Part 4 described a race of beings called the Yahoos, who were ignorant, coarse and incapable of reason.
                  They closely resembled human beings. Here Southey uses the term to refer to the mob.</note> will soon be reduced to submission I
               have no doubt, &#8211; they may commit a few murders first (I should be sorry to live near them -) &amp; in that cursed manufacturing
               district round about Manchester there may very probably be riots which will not be suppressed without &lt;much&gt; bloodshed. But the result
               is certain. The soldiers are not yet seduced (if they were all would be over, &#8211; &amp; inevitably they will be, if the press is not
               curbed) &#8211; &amp; in the present state of popular feeling, it is felt to be cotton versus corn, &#8211; &amp; corn has the stronger party as
               well as the better cause. &#8211; <del>Gov</del> The crisis has arrived in good time, &amp; Government I believe will find itself stronger
               than usual. I know that in this country the Whigs have lost <del>their most respectable</del> some of their most respectable adherents.
               If any thing indeed could render that party more odious &amp; contemptible than they already were for their whole conduct during the
               war with Buonaparte,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).
                  Southey felt the Whigs had favoured Bonaparte during Britain&#8217;s war with France 1803&#8211;1814, 1815.</note> it would be the manner in
               which they have endeavoured to <del>xxxx the</del> form a left-handed marriage<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A morganatic
                  marriage between a royal or noble groom and a bride of lesser status, as in the alliance between upper-class Whigs and plebeian
                  radicals.</note> with the Radicals.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the Manchester business,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Peterloo&#8217; Massacre on 16 August 1819, when
                  at least eleven people were killed after local magistrates ordered the dispersal of a huge radical meeting in Manchester.</note> it
               is preposterous to consider that as any thing more than an accident (in the school meaning of the term.)<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may be suggesting that the &#8216;Peterloo&#8217; incident was a distraction from the essential question of the times,
                  which was whether a revolution could be prevented, as in the distinction in Greek philosophy between the &#8216;essential&#8217; and
                  &#8216;accidental&#8217; qualities of a thing.</note> I have no doubt that the meeting was illegal, &#8211; no doubt that it ought to have been
               dispersed, &#8211; &amp; any man who [MS missing]self for a moment in the situation of the Magistrates will be convinced that <del>they
                  could</del> their meaning was good, &amp; that they were acting according to the best of their judgement. They erred in ordering the
               yeomanry to support the civil power, instead of employing the hussars.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">When the Manchester
                  magistrates ordered the arrest of the main speakers at the meeting at St Peter&#8217;s Field on 16 August 1819, the task was delegated to
                  the Manchester and Salford Yeomanry, a body of upper-class local volunteers; they began to attack the crowd indiscriminately, and
                  the crowd responded by throwing brickbats at the Yeomanry. Finally, the meeting was dispersed by regular troops, primarily the 15th
                  Hussars.</note> For the yeomanry after bearing a great deal, lost their temper, which tried soldiers would not have done. But right
               or wrong should be left to the laws as a separate point; &amp; &lt;this business&gt; ought never to have diverted the public attention from
               that disposition in which the meeting originated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thus much for the immediate state of things. How long &amp; how surely I have seen it coming on, you well know. Enough
               upon that subject is said in Espriella, in the Ed: Register &amp; in the Q.R.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey lists a
                  series of works in which he warned of the dangers from industrialisation and revolution. See, for instance: <title>Letters from
                     England: By Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, p. 133; <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 229; &#8216;Inquiry into the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note>
               to justify a confidence in my own foresight, &#8211; which I should be very glad if I did not feel at this time. For tho the Yahoos will in
               all likelihood be presently quieted, &amp; kept quiet by some salutary law respecting public meetings, &#8211; I cannot conceal from myself
               that all things in this country are tending to Revolution, &amp; that nothing but the Providence of God can save us from it.
               Nevertheless, it is as it was in the days of Noah,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title> 6&#8211;9, Noah was
                  ordered to build an ark to save representatives from all species from a universal flood.</note> with me as well as other people. If
               the cataclysm comes it will find me in my usual occupations. I can do nothing to avert the evil, except by pointing it out, &#8211; but I
               shall be the last man to despair.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> lately he will have told you that
               the death of Lord Somerville gives me some prospect of a &#8211; lawsuit.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville,
                  15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), agricultural reformer and third cousin of Southey, had died on 5 October 1819.
                  This produced a further round of legal tangles over the Fitzhead estate in Somerset that Somerville had inherited.</note> The
               relationship was very remote, &#8211; (that of third cousin) &#8211; but the property which was bequeathed to him by his mothers Uncle<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Somerville&#8217;s mother was Elizabeth Cannon Lethbridge (d. 1765), the daughter of Mary Southey (1704&#8211;1789)
                  and niece of John Cannon Southey (d. 1768). The latter had inherited the Fitzhead estate from his mother Mary Cannon (1678&#8211;1738). On
                  his death, John Cannon Southey had left a complex, ill-judged, will which named Somerville as his primary heir, and, if Somerville
                  died without heirs, Southey&#8217;s father and two uncles as the residuary legatees, their rights passing, in turn, to their children. Of
                  the three Southey brothers only Southey&#8217;s father married, leading the poet to believe (after the death of his father and paternal
                  uncles) that he and his brothers were now the rightful heirs to the Fitzhead estate. </note> was intended to revert to the Southeys,
               in case of his dying without issue.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Somerville had died unmarried. His title was inherited by
                  Mark Somerville, 16th Lord Somerville (1784&#8211;1842), a half-brother who was unconnected to the Southeys or the Fitzhead
                  inheritance.</note> It is about 1000&#163; a year, Lord S sold the whole, &amp; whether I shall be able to recover any part of it is very
               doubtful. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> is enquiring into the business at present, &amp; I shall have
               the best advice. If it comes into a court of justice, &#8211; the property lies in <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> circuit, &amp; I should <del>xxx</del> be well pleased to trust my cause in his hands.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">As the Fitzhead estate was in Somerset it fell into the geographical area covered by John Taylor
                  Coleridge, who had been called to the Bar on 26 June 1819 and had joined the western circuit and Exeter sessions. May had financed
                  Coleridge&#8217;s legal studies, including loaning him &#163;1000 earlier in 1819 to support his career at the Bar. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My family are rather in an ailing state, &#8211; not yet braced for the season. Three of them are at an anxious age &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> in his first &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> in her second teething. And <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your
                  god daughters</ref> constitution is settling. She is looking pale &amp; thin, &#8211; &amp; I wish we were within reach of her <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Uncle Henry</ref>. Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &#8211; my next shall be about Scotland &#8211; as you desire.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  tour of Scotland lasted from 17 August until 1 October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in
                     1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;yrs affectionately &#8211; R Southey </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>