<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3601</idno><idno type="nines">rce4872</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3601. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford, 5 January 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3601.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS
						Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
							Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 54–56 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3601" type="letter"><head>3601. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford</ref>, <date when="1821-01-05">5 January 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
						Postmark: [partial] E/ JA/ 1821<lb/> Endorsement: 5 Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1821<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS
						Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
							Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 54–56 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-01-05">5 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1821.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> If I could ever be induced for fear of exciting a ludicrous association, to leave undone what I
					had intended to do, or to make any alteration contrary to my judgement in what I had done, I should be as heartily
					ashamed of myself, as the Ape is in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cha-Cupn’s</ref>
					favourite print, who is asking the Fox to spare him a portion of his brush,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">An illustration of the fable ‘The Ape and the Fox’, derived from fifteenth-century additions to Phaedrus (fl. 1st
						century AD), <title>Fabulae Aesopiae</title>. Cuthbert Southey had possibly been looking at the print in the
						engraver Thomas Bewick’s (1753–1828; <title>DNB</title>) <title>The Fables of Aesop and Others</title> (London,
						1818), p. 319.</note> with an appeal to the necessity of the case expressed so excellently in his gesture, that
					you will be as much amused at it as <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">your Godson</ref>
					when I shew it you. Both Odes shall be published with the Vision, the twenty pages which they will make, being
					twenty good reasons for that measure.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Warning Voice. Ode I’ and ‘The
						Warning Voice. Ode II’, the New Year’s Odes for 1820 and 1821, were not published until they appeared in
							<title>The Englishman’s Library: Comprising a Series of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title>
						(London, 1824), pp. 381–389. They were not published with <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821). Bedford was
						providing Southey with advice about ‘Ode II’.</note> – As for altering the movement of the six stanzas, you may as
					well ask me for both my ears, or advise me to boil the <del>x</del> next haunch of venison I may have, which, next
					to poaching a Simorghs egg,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The simurgh was a fabulous bird in Iranian
						mythology. It appeared prominently in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> would, I conceive, be
					the most inexpiable of offences. I cast them purposely in that movement, &amp; with fore thought. And as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &lt;says&gt; I am sure, if you were to <del>xxxx
						me</del> hear me read them, you would feel how justly the tenor was pitched.</p><p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">In Nomine Domini</hi><note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘In the name of
						God’.</note> why should the rest of the world think meanly of me for offering a &lt;deserved&gt; compliment to
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#HaydonBenjamin">Haydon</ref>?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A
							Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), Canto 11, line 45, where Haydon appeared among ‘The Young Spirits’. Southey’s
						most recent publication in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was a review of Benjamin Haydon, <title>New
							Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title>
						(1818), which appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549–591.</note> or for what possible
					reason consider it as a piece of flattery to a man who might fancy it his interest to flatter me, but whom I can
					have no imaginable motive for flattering? – This point however you will press no farther when I tell you that the
					very day after the passage was written, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HaydonBenjamin">Haydon</ref> himself
					unexpectedly appeared; – that I read him the poem as far as it had then proceeded, &amp; that he, who from the
					nature of his profession desires contemporary praise more than any thing in the world, except abiding fame, values
					it quite as much as it is worth. – You have shown me that I was mistaken about Handel: yet I think the lines may
						stand<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">stand: written over ‘stay’.</note> because the Kings patronage of his
					music is an honourable fact.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Georg Friedrich Handel (1685–1759;
							<title>DNB</title>), German-born composer, appeared as one of ‘The Worthies of the Georgian Age’ in <title>Vision
							of Judgement</title> (1821), Canto 10, lines 7–8, where George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820;
							<title>DNB</title>) was described as Handel’s ‘munificent pupil and patron’. However, Handel had died before
						George III became King, and Handel had never taught the young monarch or received any payments from him. Southey
						here suggests that the lines are intended to mean that George III was a patron and student of Handel’s music,
						which was undoubtedly true.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have to insert Sir P Sidney among the elder worthies, &amp; Hogarth among the later, perhaps
					Johnson also,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The poet Sir Philip Sidney (1554–1586; <title>DNB</title>) did
						not gain entry into ‘The Elder Worthies’ (Canto 9) of <title>A Vision of Judgement</title>, nor did the writer
						Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) make it into ‘The Worthies of the Georgian Age’ (Canto 10), where
						the artist William Hogarth (1697–1764; <title>DNB</title>) was a last-minute addition (lines 11–12).</note> if I
					can so do &lt;it&gt; as to satisfy myself with the expression, &amp; not to seem to give him a higher praise than
					he deserves. Offence I know will be taken that the name of Pitt<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt
						(1759–1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783–1801, 1804–1806.</note> does not appear there. The King would
					find him among the eminent men of his reign, but not among those whose rank will be confirmed by posterity. The
					Whigs too will observe that none of their idols are brought forward: – neither Hampden, nor their Sidney, nor
						Russell,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hampden (c. 1595–1643; <title>DNB</title>), Algernon Sidney
						(1623–1683; <title>DNB</title>) and William Russell, Lord Russell (1639–1683; <title>DNB</title>), opponents of
						the power of the Stuart monarchs. Sidney and Russell were executed for their part in the ‘Rye House Plot’; Russell
						was from the same family as the Dukes of Bedford, staunch Whigs.</note> – I think of the first as ill as Lord
					Clarendon did,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon (1609–1684;
							<title>DNB</title>), upholder of the Stuart cause, was notably critical of Hampden in his <title>The History of
							the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England</title> (1702–1704).</note> – of the last no better than I do of his
					descendants &amp; concerning Algernon Sidney, it is certain that he suffered wrongfully, but that does not make him
					a great man. If I had brought forward any man of that breed it should have been old Oliver himself,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>). He did not
						make an appearance in <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821). Cromwell’s body had been disinterred from
						Westminster Abbey in 1661, posthumously executed and hanged in chains at Tyburn. His skull was on display on a
						pole outside Westminster Hall until 1685, by which time, as Southey suggests, its ‘bleaching’ should have been
						completed.</note> – &amp; I had half a mind to do it, as his bleaching must be over by this time, &amp; his
					greatness nobody can call in question.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> lives at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2.
					Duchess Street. Portland Place; very near <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the
					Dogstars</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have finished the explanatory part of the Preface, touching the metre, – briefly, fully,
					clearly, &amp; fairly. It has led me (which you will think odd, till you see the connection) to pay off a part of
					my obligations to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MooreThomas">T. Moore</ref>, by some observations upon the tendency of their poems (especially
					D Juan)<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The first two Cantos of Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819),
						published by Murray. The coruscating and hilarious ‘Dedication’, which attacked Southey and others, had been
						suppressed (and was not published until 1833), but Southey knew of its existence. </note> – which they will
					appropriate to themselves in what proportion they please.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision
							of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey denounced ‘the Satanic school’ of
						poetry without naming any one poet.</note> This I know, that the passage will do me credit in every way, &amp; may
					possibly produce some good. – If <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> knew how much his
					character has suffered by that transaction about D Juan, I think he would hang himself; &amp; if <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> knew what is said &amp; thought of the QR. for its silence
					concerning that infamous poem, I verily believe it would make him ill. Upon that subject I say nothing. The passage
					is a powerful one, &amp; will be felt &amp; talked of</p><p rend="indent1"> Tomorrow I hope for a proof sheet. I am in good humour with the Vision, &amp; with the Ode. – I
					long to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> drawings: he is to chuse his own
					engraver for them.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall produced the following six sketches of Lake
						District scenes that were engraved for <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of
							Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829): vol. I: ‘Druidical Stones near Keswick’, ‘Derwentwater,
						Bassenthwaite-water, and Skiddaw, from Walla Crag’, and ‘Derwentwater from Strandshagg’; and vol. II: ‘Crosthwaite
						Church and Skiddaw’, ‘Greta Hall, Derwentwater, and Newlands’, and ‘Tarn of Blencathra’. A variety of engravers
						was employed.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>