<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3305</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4576</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3305. Robert Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 29
                  May 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3305.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 342&#8211;343 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3305" type="letter">
        <head>3305. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1819-05-29">29
                  May 1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London June three 1819/ The Revd
                  Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devonshire/ C W Williams Wynn<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 3 JU 3/ 1819<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 342&#8211;343 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-05-29">29 May. 1819</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> So long a time had elapsed without my hearing from you or by any accident of you, that I began to fear what might have
               been the cause of this long silence, &amp; was really afraid to enquire. I am very sorry that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bush<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably James Bush (1791&#8211;1849), Lord Byron&#8217;s fag at Harrow and graduate of Oriel College, Oxford; in
                  1819 he was Curate at Stockleigh Pomeroy, Devon, and thus a near neighbour of Lightfoot. </note> did not make use of your name when
               he was at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> last summer: &#8211; he could have brought with him no better
               introduction, &amp; I have always time to perform offices of attention &amp; hospitality to those who are entitled to them. He left a
               good impression here, as an excellent preacher; &#8211; indeed I have seldom <del>he</del> or never heard a more judicious one. The account
               which he gave you of my way of life is not altogether correct. &#8211; I have no allotted quantum of exercise, &#8211; but, as at Oxford, sometimes
               go a long while without any, &amp; sometimes take walks which would try the mettle of a younger man. And a great deal more of my time
               is employed in reading than in writing; &#8211; if it were not, what I write would be of very little value. But that I am a close student is
               very true, &amp; such I shall continue to be as long as my eyes &amp; other faculties last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must apply in time if you design to place <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">your son</ref> at
               Oriel, &#8211; it is now no easy matter to obtain admission there, nor indeed at any College which is in good reputation.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prideaux Lightfoot entered Exeter College, Oxford, in 1820. </note> I almost wonder that you do not
               give the preference to old <ref type="m" target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref>, for the sake of old times, now that the
               College has fairly obtained a new character, &amp; is no longer the seat of drunkenness, raffery &amp; indiscipline, as it was in the
               days of <hi rend="ital">the Apostles</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Balliol College&#8217;s reputation had suffered
                  disastrously under the long reign of Theophilus Leigh (d. 1785), Master of Balliol 1726&#8211;1785, and the College was almost bankrupt by
                  1780. Its revival was due to the discovery of coal under some of its estates in Northumberland, and the leadership of John Parsons
                  (1761&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), Master of Balliol 1798&#8211;1819, who reformed both the College tutorship system and the University&#8217;s
                  examinations. It is not clear who &#8216;<hi rend="ital">the Apostles</hi>&#8217; were.</note> It is <del>xxxx</del> even doubtful whether if I
               were an undergraduate now, I should be permitted to try my skill in throwing stones for the pleasure of hearing them knock against your
               door. Seriously however, altered as the College is, there would be an advantage in sending your son there, where you have left a good
               name &amp; a good example. Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoweThomas">Thomas Howe</ref> I believe led but a melancholy life
               after he left College, without neighbours, without a family, without a pursuit, he must have felt dismally the want of his old routine,
               &amp; sorely have missed his pupils, the Chapel Bell, &amp; the Common Room. A Monk is much happier than an old fellow of a College who
               retires to reside upon a <del>x</del> country living. And how much happier are you at this day, with all the tedium which your daily
               occupation must bring with it, than if you had obtained a fellowship, &amp; then waited twenty years for preferment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It has pleased God to give me another <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">son</ref>, &#8211; born in
               February last. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">My youngest child</ref> being more than seven years old I had ceased to
               consider such an event as anyways probable. &amp; now I build a<del>s</del> little upon hope as nature will allow me. <del>xx</del> The
               child is doing well, &#8211; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">mother</ref> has had a succession of serious complaints, &#8211;
               from which I trust she is now recovering, but still far from being in good health. The four girls<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> are well as could be wished, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the eldest</ref>
               is just fifteen, &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bush&#8217;s antagonist at chess &#8211; just such a chess player as I was, with a hawks eye for the
               game, &amp; a greyhounds speed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am upon the eve of compleating the History of Brazil, &#8211; the greatest labour of my life. the last chapter is in the
                  press,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 696&#8211;879.</note>
               &amp; as soon as it is finished I set off for London, &#8211; for a two months absence from home. The business which calls me away is to
               examine &amp; collect the contents of certain papers relative to the peninsular war before I put my great work upon that subject to the
               press, which will be as soon as I return.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I have a life of John Wesley in hand, which includes that of Whitefield, &amp; is indeed the history of the Rise
               &amp; Progress of Methodism, &#8211; a curious subject, the whole importance of which perhaps few persons as yet comprehend.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp.
                  48&#8211;56, 136&#8211;154, dealt with the significance of George Whitefield (1714&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), as well as discussing the life of
                  John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>).</note> One volume is printed, &amp; the second in the press, but its progress must be
               suspended during my absence. &#8211; About six years I think, if it please God that I should live &amp; preserve my faculties so long, would
               enabl[MS torn] me to bring to a conclusion the works which I have undertaken; &#8211; not all that I had dreamt of &amp; in part prepared
               for, but those upon which a considerable stock of labour has been actually expended. I am within ten weeks of compleating the 45<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of my age. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">My father</ref> died at 48, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> at 50. &#8211; You I believe are about two years my senior. How many of our
               contemporaries have we outlived! It is five &amp; twenty years since we saw each other last. Every body else whom I cared for in this
               world I have seen somewhere or other in that interval, &amp; most of them many times. But I have both the hope &amp; the intention of
               seeing you, whenever I can make time for it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What the question was concerning my god daughter<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Jane (Fanny) Lightfoot
                  (1806&#8211;1882).</note> to which you give me an answer &#8211; I have totally forgotten; &#8211; &amp; this is your fault, for not replying to it
               when it was fresh in recollection. I will forgive you, when you tell me what it was, &amp; not till then; so <del>rexxxxxx</del>
               remember, you are under my displeasure until you write again. Give my love to her meantime, &amp; tell her we shall not always remain
               strangers. Present my best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Bridget Prideaux (b.
                  1778), whom Lightfoot had married in 1801.</note> &amp; believe me my dear Lightfoot</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours affectionately, &#8211; as in old times</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>