<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3550</idno><idno type="nines">rce4821</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3550. Robert Southey to Messrs Longman and Co., 8 November 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3550.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856) .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                     Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 213–214.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3550" type="letter"><head>3550. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Messrs Longman and Co.</ref>,<date when="1820-11-08"> 8 November 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 213–214.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1820-11-08">Nov. 8. 1820.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have had a visit from Mrs. Fry upon the subject of George Fox, for my intention has made a stir among the
                  Quakers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Quaker philanthropist and prison reformer Elizabeth Fry (1780–1845;
                     <title>DNB</title>) had visited Southey. She had been prompted to do so by news that he planned to write a life of George Fox
                  (1624–1691; <title>DNB</title>), founder of the Society of Friends. When Fry failed to change Southey’s mind, she offered him access
                  to sources for his book; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 27 October 1820, Letter 3544.</note> The first wish (I think) was
               to dissuade me from the undertaking; but that being in vain, every offer of assistance is made. I thought it proper to show Mrs. Fry
               the introduction which I had written, that she might see in what light I viewed the subject, and that I should neither dissemble the
               errors of the Society and its founder, nor detract from their just merits. And having made it clearly understood that I shall write
               with perfect freedom, as well as perfect sincerity, I shall avail myself without scruple of all the advantages and facilities which are
               offered me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have already got a number of useful books, among others the <hi rend="ital">second</hi> edition of G. Fox’s Journal,
               by which I perceive that the <hi rend="ital">language</hi> has<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Warter’s text has ‘bas’; we have
                  corrected it to ‘has’.</note> been altered in the third, but I know that there are more important alterations from <hi rend="ital">the first</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Ellwood (1639–1714; <title>DNB</title>) edited <title>A Journal or
                     Historical Account of the Life, Travel, Sufferings, and Christian Experiences of that Ancient, Eminent and Faithful Servant of
                     Jesus Christ, George Fox</title> (1694). The second edition was published in 1709 and the third edition in 1765.</note> I am now
               master enough of the subject to judge of the extent of the work as well as its distribution, and have no doubt of its making two
               volumes, though they may be somewhat smaller than “Wesley.”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The comparison is with Southey’s
                     <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820) in two volumes. The study of Fox was not
                  written.</note> Look out for me for Gough’s “History of the Quakers,”<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gough (1720–1791;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>A History of the People Called Quakers from their First Rise to the Present Time</title>
                  (1789–1790).</note> (which I cannot proceed without), the Lives of “Thomas Elwood,” “Richard Davis,” and “Richard Claridge,”<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Three autobiographies by early Quakers: Thomas Ellwood (1639–1713; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     History of the Life of Thomas Ellwood</title> (1714); Richard Davies (c. 1635–1708; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of the
                     Convincement, Exercises, Services and Travels of that Ancient Servant of the Lord Richard Davies</title> (1710); and Richard
                  Claridge (1649–1723; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Posthumous Works of Richard Claridge; being Memoirs and Manuscripts
                     relating to His Experiences and Progress in Religion</title> (1726).</note> Rutty’s “History of Friends in Ireland,”<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Rutty (1697–1775; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the Rise and Progress of the People called
                     Quakers in Ireland</title> (1751), no. 3126 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Margaret Fox’s “Journal,”<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Fox’s wife Margaret (1614–1702; <title>DNB</title>), née Askew, who played an important
                  role in early Quakerism. She did not write a journal, but her ‘The Testimony of Margaret Fox concerning her Late Husband’ was
                  included in Thomas Ellwood (1639–1714; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Journal or Historical Account of the Life, Travel, Sufferings,
                     and Christian Experiences of that Ancient, Eminent and Faithful Servant of Jesus Christ, George Fox</title> (London, 1694), pp.
                  i–ix.</note> the “Book of Extracts,” and J. W. Chiting’s “Catalogue of Friends’ Books.”<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Extracts from the Minutes and Advices of the Yearly Meeting of Friends in London from its First Institution</title>
                  (1802), no. 2354 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; and John Whiting (1656–1722; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Catalogue of
                     Friends’ Books; Written by Many of the People, Called Quakers</title> (1708), no. 555 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The first chapter must be a retrospective view of the history of religious opinions and parties in England. Prepared as
               I am for the subject, it will yet cost me a good deal of reading. You must let me have Neal’s “History of the Puritans,” the original
               work, (not the abridgement in two volumes which was published a few years ago);<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Neal
                  (1678–1743; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the Puritans</title>, first published in four volumes 1732–1738, the version
                  Southey wanted (no. 2023 in the sale catalogue of his library). A two-volume abridgement had been published in 1811 by Longman and
                  his partners.</note> and a lately published volume about Non-conformity in Wales, containing a Life of Vavasor Powell.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Williams (1749–1818), <title>The Welsh Nonconformists’ Memorial; or, Cambro-British
                     Biography</title> (1820), which contained a life of the Independent minister, Vavasor Powell (1617–1670; <title>DNB</title>).
                  Southey’s copy was no. 2441 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> That is a curious volume which you sent me of “Tracts against the Quakers.”<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Longman had sent a miscellaneous volume of twelve tracts against early Quakers; no. 2353 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library. It included: <title>A Faithful Discovery of Treacherous Design of Mystical Antichrist Displaying Christ’s Banners</title>
                  (1653), <title>A Northern Blast, or the Spiritual Quaker Converted</title> (1655), <title>The Perfect Pharise Under Monkish
                     Holiness</title> (1654), <title>An Exact History of the Life of James Naylor</title> (1657), and <title>A Merry Device, called
                     the Troublesome Travel of Time, and the Dangerous Delivery of Her Daughter Truth</title> (1660–1664).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I see that the last edition of “Lardner”<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably an edition of the
                     <title>Works</title> of Nathaniel Lardner (1684–1768; <title>DNB</title>), the Presbyterian minister and patristic scholar; a
                  five-volume set from 1815 is no. 1613 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> is to be had for 6<hi rend="ital">l</hi>.
                  6<hi rend="ital">s</hi>.; please to send it me by waggon.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Yours very truly,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R. SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>