<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3524</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4795</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3524. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor,
						14 August 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3524.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National
						Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 34. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
							Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
					205&#8211;208.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3524" type="letter">
        <head>3524. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>,
						<date when="1820-08-14">14 August 1820</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter
						Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re_</hi>/ Pisa./ Italy<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE; CHAMBERY;
							CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTER DA GENOA<lb /> Postmarks: F/ 261/ 20; [partial] SETTEMBRE<lb /> MS: National
						Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 34. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
							<title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
					205&#8211;208.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ere this I trust you will have received <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> Peter Bell, his Waggoner, &amp; his sonnets on the river Duddon &amp;c, &#8211; the last volume of
					the Hist. of Brazil &amp; the Life of Wesley.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Peter
							Bell, A Tale in Verse</title> (1819), <title>The Waggoner. A Poem. To Which are Added Sonnets</title> (1819) and
							<title>The River Duddon, A Series of Sonnets: Vaudracour and Julia: and Other Poems</title> (1820); and Southey&#8217;s
							<title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820) and the third and final volume
						of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819). See Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 20 February 1820, Letter
						3443.</note> They were detained some time for the chance that your brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorRobertEyres">Robert</ref> might have occasion to send any thing in the same package.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> After <del>xx</del> having been nearly three months from home, you may suppose with what pleasure
					I returned to my own family, my own fire side, &amp; my own pursuits. During my absence to gratify others rather
					than myself I went to Oxford to receive an honorary degree<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been
						awarded an honorary Doctorate of Civil Law at the University of Oxford on 14 June 1820.</note> &#8211; except that I
					passed it thro it twice in stage coaches, once after the inhabitants were gone to bed, &amp; once before they had
					got up, I had not been there since I left it in 1794, with the intention of bidding farewell not to the University
					alone, but to England &amp; to Europe, &amp; trying an Utopian scheme in the back-settlements of the United
						States.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. Southey&#8217;s and Coleridge&#8217;s scheme of Pantisocracy.</note> After
					the business of the Theatre<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Sheldonian Theatre (built 1664&#8211;1668), the
						main centre for ceremonies at the University of Oxford.</note> was over I went into Christ Church Walk, &amp;
					there chewed the cud of remembrance. Except <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore</ref>
					the Professor of Law, I did not meet with one contemporary, of whom I have had even the slightest knowledge. In the
					evening, or rather at night, I dined in <ref type="m" target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol Hall</ref> with
					the Master<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Jenkyns (1782&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), Master of
						Balliol College, Oxford (1819&#8211;1854), where Southey had been an undergraduate 1792&#8211;1794. Southey had, of course,
						never completed his studies and left without a degree.</note> &amp; Fellows, all being so much my juniors that the
					Master himself did not enter the College till some years after I had left it. There was no person to recognize me
					but the porter, a poor fellow who in my time had served as hair-dresser, &amp; supplied the College with fruit. His
					wife had been my laundress, &#8211; &amp; the poor infirm old woman sate up till midnight, that she might see me when I
					was let out.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The porter was called Adam.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ill as you think of the rabble, &amp; of the Whigs, who have long since proved that it is
					possible to be at the same time odious &amp; contemptible, &#8211; you cannot but marvel at the effect which the modern
						Messalina<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline of Brunswick (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), the
						estranged wife of George IV, had returned to England on 5 June 1820. Her arrival and the series of events that
						followed, as attempts were made to deprive her of the title of Queen and to dissolve her marriage to the King,
						made her a figurehead for radicals, and also triggered public protests in her support. Southey, who was
						ferociously opposed to Caroline, here compares her to Messalina (c. AD 17/20&#8211;48), the infamously dissolute wife of
						Claudius (10 BC&#8211;AD 54; Emperor of Rome AD 41&#8211;54).</note> has produced in London. Ballad singers go about the
					streets proclaiming the Queens title to the throne, &amp; in doggrel rhyme declaring that she shall speedily be
					seated there, &amp; reign by the peoples free election. There is every probability of a more tremendous explosion
					than that which Lord George Gordon<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The anti-Catholic riots triggered in
						London in June 1780 by Lord George Gordon&#8217;s (1751&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>) call for the repeal of the Catholic
						Relief Act (1778). Nearly 300 people were killed.</note> brought about in our childhood, &amp; no reliance can be
					placed upon the soldiers. For they are not only <del>xx</del> duped by the devilish newspapers to believe that the
					Queen is an innocent &amp; injured woman, but they are infected by the moral pestilence of the age, since the
						armies<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Initially &#8216;army&#8217;.</note> in Spain &amp; Naples have chosen to
					interfere in state affairs.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Military revolts in Spain in January 1820 and
						in Naples in June 1820 had led to the creation of liberal regimes.</note> Before this letter can reach you the
					crisis will in all likelihood have come on. It will be a trial between the Government supported by the civil power
					alone, &amp; the mob, with the traitorous Whigs &amp; the press <del>&amp; their troops</del> on their side, &#8211; the
					troops being worse than doubtful. Of course care is taken to send away such regiments as have given the plainest
					indication of their determination &#8220;to see the Queen thro it&#8221;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A battalion of
						the 3rd Regiment of Guards in King&#8217;s Mews had mutinied on 15 June 1820, complaining of poor conditions. Queen
						Caroline was reported to be very popular in Guards Regiments. The 3rd Regiment was sent to Portsmouth on 16&#8211;17
						June 1820.</note> as they express themselves.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Initially &#8216;themself&#8217;.</note>
					My comfort is that as things must be worse before they can be better, the sooner the abscess bursts, the more
					strength there will be in the constitution to throw <del>xx</del> off &amp; struggle thro the disease. The only
					chance of getting safely thro the affair is that the evidence against the woman may convince the honest persons who
					now believes her to be innocent; but as the villainous part of her partizans outnumber the others ten times told,
					this is but a poor hope.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Being blessed with good spirits &amp; chearful opinions, I have a habit of looking on with a
					resolute hope, however unfavourable <del>all</del> may be the aspects. One of my occupations at this time is a
					series of Dialogues, upon a plan which was suggested by Boethius.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">This
						became <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829). Southey&#8217;s
						model was Anicius Manlius Severinus Boethius (c. 480&#8211;525), <title>De Consolatione Philosophiae</title>, a dialogue
						between the author and the character of Lady Philosophy, consisting of both prose and verse.</note> The motto will
					explain their object, &#8211; it is three words which I found somewhere quoted from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernard, &#8211;
					Respice, aspice, prospice.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Look to the past, the present, the future&#8217;,
						words attributed to St Bernard of Clairvaux (1090&#8211;1153). This motto appeared on the title page [unpaginated] of
						vol. 1 of <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London,
						1829).</note> I am going to press quam celerrime<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;as fast as
						possible&#8217;.</note> with the History of the Peninsular war.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History
							of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> In poetry I have done little, but must take up those poems
					which have been so long in hand, in good earnest ere long &amp; go thro with them. The difficulty of Spensers
					stanza has I think very much impeded my progress in the Tale of Paraguay,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825), which used the stanzaic form pioneered by Edmund Spenser (c.
						1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; tho with what <del>I have done</del> is done I am very much pleased my
					self.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My little boy</ref> is now a year &amp;
					half old, as healthy, as intelligent &amp; as good-natured as one could wish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will scarcely know London when you return to it, &#8211; that is if there be any such city left a
					few years hence, which is rather doubtful as our Catalines<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e.
						contemporary equivalents of Lucius Sergius Catalina (c. BC 108&#8211;62), a Roman senator who attempted to overthrow the
						Roman Republic.</note> have more than once intended to set it on fire in sundry places. What with pulling down
					narrow streets &amp; lanes, &amp; building wide streets, circles &amp; heaven knows what, they are making it a very
					fine place; &amp; when the inhabitants are taught to consume their smoke in the fire, instead of letting it go up
					the chimney, we shall again have as clean (tho not as clear) an atmosphere as our neighbours on the continent, &#8211;
					which was the case before pit-coal came into use.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Direct the books<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor&#8217;s letter of May 1820 had promised
						to send Southey a consignment of books from Italy, John Forster, <title>Walter Savage Landor, a Biography</title>,
						2 vols (London, 1869), I, p. 459.</note> to the care of Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, Hurst, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref>,
					Orme &amp; Brown &#8211; London. &amp; they will find their way to me. The duty is <del>not as</del> no object except for
					voluminous works in folio.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1820-08-14">14 Aug. 1820.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>