<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3585</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4856</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3585. Robert Southey to John Taylor Coleridge,
						19 December 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3585.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by
						Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, Studia Germanica Gandensia, 6 (1964),
					115&#8211;118.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3585" type="letter">
        <head>3585. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>,
						<date when="1820-12-19">19 December 1820</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J.
						T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 2. Pump Court/ Middle Temple/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
						Postmark: E/ 22 DE 22/ 1820<lb /> Endorsement: 1820/ Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>/ R. Southey.
						Keswick<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by
						Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964),
					115&#8211;118.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If your friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lloyd<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lloyd
						(1784&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman and Fellow of Christ Church, Oxford. He was appointed Regius Professor
						of Divinity in 1822 and Bishop of Oxford in 1827. A zealous and influential tutor and lecturer, he was credited
						with reviving theological studies at the University. A high churchman, Lloyd was initially opposed to civil
						liberties for Catholics, but in 1829 joined <ref type="m" target="people.html#Peel">Robert Peel</ref>, his former
						student, in supporting Catholic relief. His move infuriated conservatives in church and state, and he was publicly
						snubbed by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">George IV</ref>. Lloyd might have wished to
						research monastic history in his role as preacher at Lincoln&#8217;s Inn 1819&#8211;1822, or to use it for his academic
						researches on the roots of Anglican liturgy and dogma.</note> were here I could put into his hands books which I
					am afraid he will not easily meet with, monastic history having hitherto been thought of very little value in
					protestant countries, tho in itself exceedingly curious &amp; interesting on many accounts. The work of easiest
					access to which I can refer him is Helyot&#8217;s Histoire des Ordres Monastiques in 8. vol. 4to.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Hippolyte Helyot (1660&#8211;1716), <title>Histoire des Ordres Religieux et Militaires</title> (1792),
						no. 1183 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; it is a work of authority &amp; useful as a
					compendium but is barren in details, &#8211; which are only to be found in the chroniclers of the respective Orders. If
					he would see in what light modern Catholics represent their orders Alban Butlers Lives of the Saints, &amp;
					Berringtons historical works should be consulted, but the genuine Romance is <del>only</del> kept out of sight
						there.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Alban Butler (1709&#8211;1773; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lives of the
							Fathers, Martyrs and other Saints</title> (1759). Joseph Berington (1743&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) was a Roman
						Catholic priest and religious controversialist, who pursued a liberal argument in favour of Catholic emancipation
						that stressed the compatibility between Catholicism and the English constitution. He emphasised an approach based
						on reason and toleration, criticised the temporal power of the papacy, and argued for reform of clerical celibacy
						and the liturgy. His publications included <title>The State and Behaviour of English Catholics from the
							Reformation to the Year 1780, with a View of their Present Number, Wealth, Character</title> (1780),
							<title>History of the Reign of Henry II, and of Richard and John, His Sons</title> (1790) and <title>The Memoirs
							of Gregorio Panzani, giving an Account of His Agency in England in the Years 1634&#8211;5&#8211;6 </title>(1793). In 1813,
						the latter was incorporated into <title>The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Catholic Religion in
							England, During a Period of Two Hundred and Forty Years from the Reign of Elizabeth to the Present Time;
							including the Memoirs of Gregorio Panzani</title>; Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 269 in the sale catalogue of his
						library.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis occupies half a volume of the Acta Sanctorum.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53 volumes (Brussels and Antwerp, 1643&#8211;1794), October,
						II (1768), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, contained a great deal of material on St Francis of
						Assisi (1181/2&#8211;1226), founder of the Franciscan order.</note> But the great history of the Seraphic Order is by
					Luke Wadding, an Irish Brother, written in Latin, &amp; extending with its continuation, to more than twenty
						folios.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The historian of the Franciscans (the &#8216;Seraphic Order&#8217;) Luke
						Wadding (1588&#8211;1657; <title>DNB</title>). Southey acquired a copy of Wadding&#8217;s <title>Annales Minorum, cum
							Continuatione J. W. de Anona, ab Anno 1208 ad 1564, et Vita L. Waddingii</title> (1731&#8211;1745), with continuations,
						in 19 volumes; no. 2904 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I have long been looking for this work
					in vain, intending one day to give a Sketch of the History of the Monastic Orders, for which I have made
					considerable collections.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write his proposed history of the
						monastic orders.</note> &#8211; Any Flos Sanctorum<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A compendium of lives of the
						saints, available in many different editions. Southey owned ones by Pedro de Ribadeneyra (1527&#8211;1611) and Alonso de
						Villegas (1534-c. 1615); nos 2397 and 3805&#8211;3806 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> will be of use to
						M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lloyd in giving him a general notion of the founders &amp; heroes of the Mendicant Orders:
					&amp; he should look for the Liber Conformitatum, &#8211; or parallel between S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis &amp; our
					Saviour! of which marvellous book I have a copy.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartholomaeus de Rinonico
						(d. c. 1401), <title>Liber Aureus. Inscriptus Liber Conformitatum Vitae Beati ac Seraphici Patris Francisci ad
							Vitam Jesu Christi Domini Nostri</title> (1385&#8211;1399). Southey owned an edition of 1590, no. 472 in the sale
						catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not think <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> can know
					any thing more of Kebles letter than what has been repeated to him by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his Mother</ref> from my report of it.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The clergyman and poet John Keble (1792&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>) had written to John Taylor Coleridge to inform
						him that Hartley Coleridge had lost his Fellowship at Oriel College, Oxford, at the end of the probationary year
						on grounds of intemperance. John Taylor Coleridge had then forwarded Keble&#8217;s letter to Southey, who had to break
						the news to Hartley&#8217;s mother and friends in the Lakes.</note> I spoke of the letter, as I thought, as written with
					a right &amp; proper feeling, &amp; every way honourable to the writer. You will not wonder however that offence
					has been taken. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> I understand says that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> was more than once picked up dead drunk in the
					streets, &#8211; &amp; this <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> denies; &amp; it is
					upon this specific point I suppose, that he rests his appeal. He denies also that he received any warning, &amp;
					confesses only to a few acts of occasional inebriety, few in number &amp; trifling in degree. He talks of a system
					of espionage carried on by means of scouts &amp; bedmakers, &amp; represents himself as the victim of a conspiracy.
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> offered him 300&#163;, but this has been
					indignantly refused.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The money was eventually accepted when it was made
						clear that acceptance did not imply surrender either by Hartley Coleridge or his opponents; see H. Coleridge,
							<title>Poems, with a Memoir of His Life by His Brother Derwent Coleridge</title> (London, 1851), p.
						LXXXVI.</note> &#8211; As for spies &amp; conspiracies. I should think better of his case, if <del>the</del> such words
					had not been used in his defence. It is very likely that he has been dealt with according to the rigour of the law,
					&amp; that his manners may have contributed greatly to this. But I cannot believe that there has been any
					intentional injustice. How the matter will proceed I know not, but I <del>would</del> rather think that an appeal
					to the Visitor is intended;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Visitor of Oriel College, Oxford, was the
						monarch. Visitors of charitable and religious institutions, like Oxford colleges, were ultimately responsible for
						overseeing their conduct and could intervene in their affairs, though usually their role was only
						ceremonial.</note> if the charge of being picked up in the streets cannot be proved, the failure of proof in that
					case, is a complete acquittal on that point; but it is very possible that <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone&#8217;s</ref> language may have been translated into a stronger meaning
					than it was intended to bear. &#8211; I hear from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his Mother</ref> of his
					writing a tragedy, &amp; having a volume of poems ready for the press,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge did not publish a volume of poems, though he did write poems for the <title>London
							Magazine</title> at this time. His play was the unfinished &#8216;Prometheus&#8217;.</note> &#8211; this of course is with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">his fathers</ref> advice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> has had no other motive for
					clipping your article<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s appraisal of the following
						volumes by Felicia Hemans (1793&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Restoration of the Works of Art to
							Italy</title> (1815); <title>Tales and Historic Scenes in Verse</title> (1819); <title>Translations from Camoens
							and Other Poets, with Original Poems</title> (1818); <title>The Sceptic, a Poem</title> (1820); <title>Stanzas to
							the Memory of the Late King</title> (1820). The article, which offered a highly positive survey of Hemans&#8217;s
						career and achievements to date, appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (October 1820), 130&#8211;139,
						published 19 December 1820.</note> than the desire of making it into two, &amp; of exercising <del>that</del>
					&lt;his&gt; editorial authority. He has as much pleasure in mutilating an unhappy paper, as an experimental surgeon
					has in an operation. I dislike the conduct of the review as much as you do, but I <del>xxxxxxx</del> continue to
					write in it notwithstanding, because there is no other means of obtaining the same attention to hints of practical
					value &amp; immediate importance. I have heard of more than one instance in which my papers have given young men a
					right direction in their political opinions, when the bias of their minds inclined the other way. It will be very
					difficult to supply <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford&#8217;s</ref> place, whenever he may drop:
					but it would not be difficult to conduct it with more decorum, more consistently &amp; in a better temper. &#8211; Did
					you review <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley&#8217;s</ref> Revolt of Islam? If you did, I
					will send you copies of some letters which he has addressed to me upon that subject, &amp; of my answers.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile
						review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and
							<title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos </title>(1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The
							Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358&#8211;359. This had
						appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 460&#8211;471. Its author was, indeed, John Taylor
						Coleridge, to whom Southey had sent copies of Shelley&#8217;s letters of 26 June and 17 August 1820, and of his replies
						to them; see Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820] (Letter 3517) and 12 October 1820 (Letter 3538);
						and Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, [19 January 1821] (Letter 3611).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin&#8217;s</ref> book,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Godwin&#8217;s <title>Of Population. An Enquiry Concerning the Power of Increase in the
							Number of Mankind, Being an Answer to Mr. Malthus&#8217; Essay on That Subject</title> (1820). It refuted the arguments
						about population growth advanced in Thomas Robert Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Principle of
							Population</title> (1798).</note> nor heard of it except from you. A[MS missing] the things for which I never
					could forgive Godwin was the readine[MS missing] with which he assented to Malthus&#8217;s monstrous theory when it was
					first advanced, &amp; the coolness with which he proposed his damnable remedy.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey particularly objected to Godwin&#8217;s <title>Thoughts Occasioned by the Perusal of Dr Parr&#8217;s
							Spital Sermon</title> (1801), which he saw as an endorsement of abortion; see Southey to Charles Biddlecombe, 17
						August 1801, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 598.</note> That the theory
					was false, I knew at once, as certainly as that there is a God by whom all things are ordered, &amp; I never knew
					any man to whose judgement I looked with deference, who did not agree with me in thoroughly despising his book; &#8211;
					for instance &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> may be named, &#8211; the latter of whom long ago assured me that Malthus&#8217;s premises were as inaccurate
					as his conclusion is monstrous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> is what I should
					have expected to hear of him. I saw him soon after the death of his son,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Gooch&#8217;s son, Robert Knighton Gooch (1815&#8211;1820).</note> &amp; heard him bitterly, &amp; in tears, regret the
					&#8220;cursed education&#8221; &#8211; these were his words, which he had received among the <hi rend="ital">liberal</hi> dissenters,
					whose religion differs hardly a hairs breadth from unbelief.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Unitarianism.
						Gooch had attended a day school in Great Yarmouth until he was fifteen, but Southey may be referring to the
						influence on Gooch&#8217;s early youth of Cornelius Girling Harley (c. 1768&#8211;1843), a blind man who was the centre of an
						intellectual circle in Yarmouth; and of William Taylor.</note> There is among them a total want of religious
					feeling, &amp; when that is wanting, the heart has nothing to support it in affliction. I have often have resolved
					to put together, for the sake of men who are in the same state of unsettled opinions as <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> was, a view of the moral &amp; historical, &#8211; that is of the
					internal &amp; external evidences of Xtianity; as briefly &amp; as forcibly as I could. <del>X xxx</del> Whether I
					shall ever muster resolution for the task, or find time for it, God knows. But I have long thought of it, &amp;
					sometimes feel dissatisfied with myself, for not girding myself for the work; because many persons would read it as
					coming from me, who will not read the abundant proofs that are already before them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C. &amp; the infant continue to go on well. No doubt you feel how
					frail an infants life is, &#8211; the frailest of all frail things.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge&#8217;s
						wife Mary (1788&#8211;1874), n&#233;e Buchanan, had given birth to their second child, John Duke (1820&#8211;1894;
							<title>DNB</title>), on 3 December. Their first child Mary Dorothy Frances (1819&#8211;1820) had died as an
						infant.</note> I never look at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> without
					feeling it. At present, thank God, he is in fine health &amp; strength, &amp; promises as well as is possible at
					his age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The hexameters<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of
							Judgement</title> (1821).</note> of which you saw the beginning are now finished, &amp; going forthwith to the
					press. In a few weeks you will find a copy of them at your chambers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, &amp; tell him that
						the late high winds have gone to my heart, for the love of the strong beer which is at sea.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Remember me &#8230; sea: inserted at the top of fol. 1r. Southey was eagerly awaiting a
							barrel of strong beer, sent to Keswick by John May; see Southey to John May, 15 November 1820, Letter
							3556.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>