<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3477</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4748</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3477. Robert Southey to Katharine
                  Southey [fragment], 4 May 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3477.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856) .  Previously  published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                  (London, 1856), III, pp. 192&#8211;195.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3477" type="letter">
        <head>3477. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Katharine
                  Southey</ref> [fragment],<date when="1820-05-04"> 4 May 1820</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb /> Previously published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                  (London, 1856), III, pp. 192&#8211;195.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-05-04">Thursday, May 4. 1820.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Kate,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since I have been in London I have very often wished that you, and
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> were with me for
               a little while, to see what a number of strange things there are to be seen in this
               great overgrown town. London is so large a place that if the whole lake of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, and the whole vale from the
               end of the Lake to Bassenthwaite, and from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> and Latrigg on one side to the foot of the mountains on the other
               were covered with houses, altogether would not make so great a city as London by one
               half. Think then what a huge place it must be; and all full of streets, with no
               gardens or fields; nothing to be seen but buildings on every side, and stone
               pavements under your feet, and such a smoky air overhead that you can hardly see what
               a blue sky is. And then such a number of carts and carriages, going all day long
               through the streets, and almost all night too; and such thousands and ten thousands
               of people; from morning till night the great streets are as full as <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is upon fair-day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I arrived in London on May Day, which is a holiday for the chimney
               sweepers. All the chimney sweepers, little and great, on that day are dressed as fine
               as they can make themselves, with ribbons of all colours, and a great deal of gilding
               about them, and feathers in their caps; and they go about the streets with a wooden
               thing in one hand (such as the churchwardens carry about in church to collect money
               for a brief), and their brush in the other; and with these they make a clatter, and
               beg money from those who stop to look at them. They have generally a green man in
               company who is also called &#8220;Jack in the Bush,&#8221; because he is in the middle of a green
               bush, which covers him all over, head and all, so that you can see nothing but his
               feet, and he goes dancing with the rest. This bush is ornamented with ribbons, and I
               have seen them in former times half covered with bright pewter pots and dishes, which
               it must have been a great fatigue to carry about and dance under their weight,
               especially in a hot day, and being so shut up from the air. This Jack in the Bush is
               a comical sight, but I am sorry to say that it does harm by frightening horses: a
               poor curate in the adjoining parish of Tooting, the other day was thrown in
               consequence under the wheels of a stage coach, and it is not yet known whether he
               will recover from the dreadful hurts which he received.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Samuel Curlewis Lord (c. 1791&#8211;1867), who was from
                  Tooting and was Curate of Tooting Graveney before becoming Vicar of West Barsham
                  1818&#8211;1853 and Rector of Farnborough 1853&#8211;1867.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But how would you like to see these chimney sweepers that are so very
               fine! I have seen you and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bell</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> look somewhat like them when you had dressed yourselves up;
               but you were never half so fine, because you had no gilt finery about your clothes.
               Moreover the sweeps beautify their faces in a remarkable manner. I will tell you how
               to do it if you wish to be as fine as they are. You know their faces are very smutty:
               they let the smut stay that they may be known for chimney sweepers: therefore to be
               like them you must first rub some soot upon your faces. Next, you must rub some
               whiting upon your cheeks and forehead, that there may be great white patches in the
               middle of the smut; and then upon the white you must rub a little rose pink, and upon
               that again here and there you must stick some beaten gold, so that the face may be
               black and white, and purple, and gilt: if you do this, you will then be as fine as so
               many chimney sweepers on the first of May. I must not forget to observe that the
               chimney sweepers make a feast with the money which is given them; and they are so
               fond of their holiday that they make the first of May last the whole of the week; so
               you may tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> that her birthday is not yet over in London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I were to describe the extraordinary things which I have seen in
               the shops only while walking along the streets, a whole letter would not afford
               sufficient room. I will only tell you, that in one window I saw a great many
                  shaddocks,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The pomelo fruit.</note>
               fresh from the West Indies, which fruit is like an orange, but as big as <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert&#8217;s</ref>
               head; and that I saw two horns of the narwhale or sea-unicorn, one on each side of a
               shop door.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I came here yesterday, and return to town tomorrow, when I am to
               breakfast with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">Miss
                  Wordsworth</ref> on the way. There is no room here to tell you about your
               little Welsh uncles, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillAlfred">Alfred</ref>
               and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillRobertSouthey">Southey</ref>, nor
               about your little Welsh aunt, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillGeorgiana">Georgiana</ref>. It is <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel&#8217;s</ref> turn to have the next letter, and then I will write all
               about them, and about my little god-daughter, Bertha Vardon,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Emily Bertha Vardon (1819&#8211;1891), Southey&#8217;s god-daughter.</note>
               who is your rival for the love of <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Mr.
                  Nash</ref>, and calls him <hi rend="ital">mon ami</hi>. However, don&#8217;t you be too
               jealous; I shall bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Mr. Nash</ref>
               home with me, and that will be a great advantage for you. ...</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear child.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Your affectionate father,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>