<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3772</idno><idno type="nines">rce5043</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3772. Robert Southey to John May, 28 December 1821–21 April
                  1822</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3772.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 51–58.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3772" type="letter"><head>3772. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,<date when="1821-12-28"> 28 December 1821–21 April
                  1822</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 51–58.</note></head><opener><date when="1821-12-28">Dec. 28. 1821</date></opener><p rend="indent1"> I remember poor Flower<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The school at Corston that Southey attended 1781–1782 was
                  run by Thomas Flower (d. 1799), an expert on astronomy, a subject on which he gave public lectures and took private pupils.</note>
               with compassion &amp; not without respect, as a man who in more auspicious circumstances might have past his life happily for himself
               &amp; perhaps honourably as well as usefully for his country. His attainments &amp; talents, were I have no doubt, very considerable in
               their kind, &amp; I am sure that his temper &amp; disposition were naturally <del>very</del> good. I never saw so little punishment in
               any school. There was but one flogging during my stay there, it was for running away, which was considered as the heaviest of all
               offences; the exhibition was made as serious as possible; the instrument was not a rod but a scourge of packthread; but tho punishments
               in private schools were at that time I believe always much more severe than at public ones, I do not remember that this was remarkable
               for severity. We stood in awe &amp; respect of him, rather than fear. If there was nothing conciliating or indulgent about him, there
               was no rigour; but his manner was what you might suppose in one who was habitually thoughtful, &amp; who when <del>he</del> not engaged
               in abstruse studies had reason enough for unhappiness in his domestic circumstances. For his school was declining, he was about fifty
               years of age, &amp; having lost his first wife, had <del>lately</del> married one of his maids,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Flower had married Sarah Parker (dates unknown) in 1778.</note> who took to drinking; the house therefore was in disorder,
               the servants were <del>xxxx</del> &lt;allowed&gt; to take their own course, &amp; the boys were sadly neglected. In every thing which relates
               to personal cleanliness, they were left to take care of themselves. I had a profusion of curly hair; just before the holydays it was
               thought prudent to examine into the state of its population; which was found to be prodigiously great; my head therefore was plaistered
               with black-soap,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A liquid soap, made from lime and potash; it was a common treatment for head
                  lice.</note> &amp; in that condition I was sent home &amp; with such sores &lt;there&gt; in consequence of long neglect, that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> wept at seeing them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our morning ablutions, to the entire saving of all materials, were performed in a little stream which ran thro the
               barton, &amp; in its ordinary state was hardly more than ankle deep. We had porridge for breakfast in winter, bread &amp; milk in
               summer. My taste was better than my appetite, the green leeks in this porridge gave me a dislike to that plant which I <del>have
                  never</del> retain to this day, &lt;S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> David<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">St David (6th century), the
                  patron saint of Wales; the leek is often used as a national symbol for Wales.</note> forgive me!&gt; &amp; if it were <del>greasy</del>
               swimming with fat, as it usually was, I could better fast till the hour of dinner, than do violence to my stomach, by swallowing this
               greasy potion. The bread &amp; milk reminds me of an anecdote connected with the fashion of those days. Because I was indulged with
               sugar in my bread &amp; milk at home, when I went to school I was provided with a store, carefully tied up in paper. I had a cocked hat
               for Sundays, during the rest of the week it lay in my box upon the top of my clothes, &amp; when the paper of brown sugar was reduced
               in bulk, I deposited it in the cock of the hat. As you may suppose, my fingers found their way there whenever I went to the box, &amp;
               the box was sometimes opened for that purpose, <del>x</del> thus the sugar was by little &amp; little strewn over the hat. It was in a
               sweet clammy condition the first time I was sent for by <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt &lt;Tyler&gt;</ref> to
               visit her at Bath; &amp; as the cocked hat was then in the last stage of its fashion, mine was dismissed to <del>the hatter</del> be
               rounded by the hatter, &amp; I never wore one again till I was at Madrid, where round hats were prohibited.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Large round hats that concealed the features of the wearer were banned in Madrid as part of the government’s attempt
                  to reduce crime. The measure was deeply unpopular and was one of the triggers for the Esquilache riots 1766. Southey visited Madrid
                  in 1796.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> One day in the week we had bread &amp; cheese for dinner, or when baking day came, a hot cake with cheese or a small
               portion of butter at our choice. This to my taste was the best dinner in the week. Some of the boys would split their cake, lay their
               cheese in thin layers between the two halves, &amp; then place it under the press, so as to compress it into one mass. This rule of
               going without meat one day in the week was then, I believe, general in country schools, – retained perhaps, for motives of frugality,
               from Catholic times.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The tradition in many Christian communities of abstaining from meat on
                  Fridays in remembrance of the crucifixion.</note> – One of the <del>wo</del> servants had the privilege of selling gingerbread &amp;
               such things. We had bread &amp; cheese for supper, &amp; used to raise sallads for this meal, in little portions of garden, into which
               what had been the flower border of the great garden in better times, was divided; these were our property &amp; transferable by sale.
               We raised mustard &amp; cress, raddishes &amp; lettuces. When autumn came we had no lack of apples, for it is a country of orchards.
               The brook which has <del>before</del> &lt;already&gt; been mentioned past thro one immediately before it entered the barton where our
               ablutions were performed; the trees on one side grew on a steepish declivity; &amp; in stormy weather we constructed dams across the
               stream to stop the apples which were brought down. Our master had an extensive orchard of his own, &amp; employed the boys to gather in
               the apples; there was of course free license to eat on that day, &amp; a moderate <del>deg</del> share of pocketting would have been
               allowed, – but whether original sin was <del>more</del> peculiarly excited by that particular fruit, or not,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The fruit in the Garden of Eden which Adam and Eve were forbidden from eating was often interpreted as being the
                  apple, <title>Genesis</title> 2: 16–17. The disobedience of Adam and Eve was the original sin that descended to all people.</note>
               so it was, that a subtraction was made enormous enough to demand inquiry, the boxes were <del>opened</del> &lt;searched&gt; in consequence,
               &amp; the whole plunder was thus recovered. The boys were <del>allowed</del> &lt;employed&gt; also to <hi rend="ital">squail</hi> at the <hi rend="ital">bannets</hi>, – that is, being interpreted, to throw at his walnuts, when it was time to bring them down, – there were
               four or five fine trees on the hill side above the brook. I was too little to bear a part in this, which required considerable
               strength, but for many days afterward I had the gleaning among the leaves with which the ground was covered, – &amp; the fragrance of
               those leaves in their incipient decay is one of those odours which I can recall at will, &amp; which whenever it occurs, brings with it
               the remembrance of past times.</p><p rend="indent1"> One very odd amusement, which I never saw or heard of elsewhere, was greatly in vogue at this school. It was performed
               with snail shells – by placing them against each other, point to point, &amp; pressing till the weaker was broken in; that was called
               conquering, &amp; the shell which remained unhurt acquired <del>glory</del> esteem &amp; value in proportion to the number &lt;over&gt; which
               it had <del>conquered</del> &lt;triumphed&gt;, an accurate account being kept. A great conqueror was prodigiously prized &amp; coveted, &amp;
               two of this description would seldom have been brought to contest the palm, if both possessors had not been goaded to it by reproaches
               &lt;&amp; taunts&gt;. The victor <del>always added to his score</del> &lt;had the&gt; number <del>that</del> of its opponents &lt;conquests added to
               its own&gt;, thus when one conqueror of fifty conquered another &lt;which had been as often victorious,&gt; it became conqueror of an hundred
               &amp; one. Yet even in this, fame was sometimes obtained upon false pretences. I found a boy<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> one day who had fallen in with a great number of young snails, so young that their shells were still
               transparent, – <del>in fact</del> a nest probably which had not been hatched more than two or three days, – &amp; he was besmearing his
               fingers by crushing these poor creatures one after another against his conqueror, counting away, with the greatest satisfaction at his
               work. He was a good-natured boy, so that I (who had been bred up to have a sense of humanity,) ventured to express some compassion for
               the snails, &amp; to suggest that he might as well count them &amp; lay them aside unhurt. <del>I should have prevailed if it had not
                  been for a point of honour or of conscience:</del> – he hesitated &amp; seemd inclined to assent, till it struck him as a point of
               honour, or of conscience, &amp; then he resolutely said no, that would not do, – for he could not then fairly say he had conquered
               them. – There is a surprizing difference of strength in these shells, which might be partly estimated by the appearance of their
               points, or tops (I do not know what better term to use) – the strong ones were usually clear &amp; glossy there, &amp; white, if the
               shell were of the large coarse mottled brown species. The top was then said to be petrified, &amp; a good conqueror of this description
               would triumph for weeks or months. I remember that one of the <del>most succesful ones</del> &lt;greatest heroes&gt; bore evident marks of
               having once been conquered; it had then been cast away in some lucky situation where the poor tenant had leisure to repair his
               habitation, or rather where the restorative power of nature repaired it for him, &amp; the wall was thus made <del>x</del> stronger
               than it had been before the breach. But in general I should think the resisting power of the shell depended upon the geometrical nicety
               of its form.</p><p rend="indent1"> One of the big boys<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Jack Steel (dates unknown).</note> one day brought down a
               kite <del>xx</del> with an arrow, from the play ground which I think a more extraordinary thing than Apollos killing Python,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The slaying of Python by the Greek god Apollo was a popular subject for classical sculpture.
                  Representations include the Apollo Belvedere, rediscovered in the late fifteenth century and now in the Vatican, hence Southey’s
                  humorous comparison with the feats of the schoolboy archer, Jack Steel. </note> tho a Belvedere Jack Steel (this was the
                  <del>heros</del> &lt;archers&gt; name) would not make quite so <del>noble</del> &lt;heroic&gt; a statue. We had a boy<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> there who wore Midshipmans uniform, &amp; whose pay must have more than maintained him at
               school, his father was a purser, &amp; such things were not uncommon in those days. – While I was at this school, the Corporation of
               Bristol invited Rodney<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The naval officer and politician George Bridges Rodney, 1st Baron Rodney
                  (c. 1718–1792; <title>DNB</title>). In April 1782 he was victorious over a French fleet in the Battle of the Saints, thus preventing
                  a French and Spanish invasion of Jamaica. On 15 November 1782, Rodney received a ceremonial welcome from the Mayor and Corporation
                  of Bristol, a day that witnessed a parade, the firing of cannon and the ringing of bells, and that culminated in a civic dinner,
                  loyal toasts, illuminations, fireworks and a ball. </note> from Bath to a public dinner, after his great victory, &amp; we were all
               marched down to the Globe at Newton, by the road side, to see him pass &amp; give him three cheers. They were returned with great good
               humour from the carriage window. Another circumstance &lt;has&gt; made me remember the day well, – looking about for conquerors in Newton
                  Churchyard,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The churchyard of Holy Trinity, Newton St Loe.</note> I saw a slow-worm get into
               the ground under a tomb-stone; &amp; on consequence when I met, no long time afterwards, with the ancient opinion that the spinal
               marrow of a human body produces a serpent,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">This view is found in, for example, Publius Ovidius
                  Naso (43 BC–AD 17/18), <title>Metamorphoses</title>, Book 15, line 389, and Pliny the Elder (AD 23–AD 79), <title>Naturalis
                     Historia</title>, Chapter 86. </note> this fact induced me to &lt;long&gt; believe it without hesitation, upon the &lt;supposed&gt; testimony
               of my own eyes. </p><p rend="indent1"> Tho I had a full share of discomforts at Corston, I recollect nothing so painful as that of being kept up every night
               till a certain hour, when I was dying with sleepiness. Sometimes I stole away to bed, – but it was not easy to do this; &amp; once I
               was missed at bed-time, a hue &amp; cry was presently made, &amp; I was discovered fast asleep in a certain building, which tho
               appropriated for <hi rend="ital">ease</hi>, was never intended for a sleeping place. But I dreaded nothing so much as Sunday evening in
               winter. We were then assembled in the hall to hear the Master read a sermon, or a portion of Stackhouses History of the Bible.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Stackhouse (1677–1752; <title>DNB</title>), <title>New History of the Holy Bible from the
                     Beginning of the World to the Establishment of Christianity</title> (1737). </note> There I sat at the end of a long form, in
               sight but not within feeling of the fire, my feet cold, my eyelids heavy as lead, &amp; yet not daring to close them, kept awake by
               fear alone, in total inaction, &amp; under the operation of a lecture more soporific than the strongest sleeping dose. – Heaven help
               the wits of those good people who think that children are to be edified by having sermons read to them!</p><p rend="indent1"> After remaining here about twelvemonths, I was sent for home upon an alarm that the itch<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Scabies, a contagious skin infection, caused by the mite <title>Sarcoptes scabiei</title>.</note> had broken out
                  <del>in the school</del> &lt;among us&gt;. Some of the boys communicated this advice to their parents in letters which Duplanier<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Du Planier (dates unknown), was a French expatriate who ran a school in Bristol and taught
                  part-time at Southey’s school at Corston. He returned to France in 1790.</note> conveyed for them, all others of course being
               dictated, &amp; written under inspection. The report whether true or false, accelerated the ruin of the school – A scandalous scene
               took place of mutual reproaches between father &amp; son,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Flower (d. 1799) and his son,
                  Charles Flower (dates unknown), who taught at his school.</note> each accusing the other for that neglect the consequences of which
               were now become apparent; – the dispute was renewed with more violence after the boys were in bed; the next morning the master was not
               to be seen, Charley appeared with a black eye, &amp; we knew that father &amp; son had come to blows! Most, if not all the Bristol
               boys, were now taken away, &amp; I among them, to my great joy. But on my arrival at home I was treated as a suspected person, &amp;
               underwent a three days purgatory in brimstone.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Sulphur: it was the standard treatment for
                  scabies, usually in the form of a powder or ointment.</note></p><closer><dateline><date when="1822-04-21"> Apr. 21. 1822.</date></dateline></closer></div></body></text></TEI>