<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3337</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4608</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3337. Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend
					[fragment], [c. 28 July 1819]</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3337" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3337.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
							Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 352&#8211;354 [in part;
						misdated 20 July 1819]. Dating note: The letter survives only in the version published by Cuthbert Southey.
						However, the content makes it clear that he misdated it, mistaking the &#8216;28&#8217; July for &#8216;20&#8217;; this is understandable
						given that Robert Southey&#8217;s &#8216;0s&#8217; and &#8216;8s&#8217; are very similar and thus easily confused. The content of the letter
						shows that it belongs to shortly after 24 July 1819, the date on which the quotations from Don Juan
						mentioned in the letter text appeared in the Carlisle Patriot.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3337" type="letter">
        <head>3337. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Hare Townshend</ref>
					[fragment], <date when="1819-07-28">[c. 28 July 1819]</date>
          </head><p>MS:
						MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
							Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
							<title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 352&#8211;354 [in part;
						misdated 20 July 1819].<lb /> Dating note: The letter survives only in the version published by Cuthbert Southey.
						However, the content makes it clear that he misdated it, mistaking the &#8216;28&#8217; July for &#8216;20&#8217;; this is understandable
						given that Robert Southey&#8217;s &#8216;0s&#8217; and &#8216;8s&#8217; are very similar and thus easily confused. The content of the letter
						shows that it belongs to shortly after 24 July 1819, the date on which the quotations from <title>Don Juan</title>
						mentioned in the letter text appeared in the <title>Carlisle Patriot</title>.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-07-20">July 20. 1819.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear
						Chauncey,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> . . . . . . . . . . I have not seen more of Don Juan than some extracts in a country paper,
					wherein my own name is coupled with a rhyme which I thought would never be used by any person but myself when
					kissing one of my own children in infancy, and talking nonsense to it, which, whatever you may think of it at
					present as an exercise for the intellect, I hope you will one day have occasion to practise, and you will then find
					out its many and various excellencies.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first two cantos of Byron&#8217;s
							<title>Don Juan</title> (1819&#8211;1824) had been published anonymously on 15 July 1819. The rhyme Southey dismisses
						is: &#8216;Thou shalt believe in Milton, Dryden, Pope;/ Thou shalt not set up Wordsworth, Coleridge, Southey;/ Because
						the first is crazed beyond all hope,/ The second drunk, the third so quaint and mouthy:&#8217; (Canto 1, stanza 205,
						lines 1&#8211;4). These lines were printed in the <title>Carlisle Patriot</title>, 24 July 1819.</note> I do not yet
					know whether the printed poem is introduced by a dedication to me, in a most hostile strain, which came over with
					it, or whether the person who has done <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> the irreparable
					injury of sending into the world what <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">his own publisher</ref> and his
					friends endeavoured, for his sake, to keep out of it, has suppressed it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Murray published <title>Don Juan</title>, but without printing his firm&#8217;s name on the title page. The
						&#8216;Dedication&#8217; to Southey was not included in 1819, but it soon became very well known. It was eventually published
						in 1833.</note> This is to me a matter of perfect unconcern. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord
						Byron</ref> attacked me when he ran amuck as a satirist;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. in
							<title>English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</title> (London, 1809), pp. 9&#8211;10, which had advised Southey to &#8216;cease
						thy varied song!/ A bard may chaunt too often and too long&#8217;.</note> he found it convenient to express himself
					sorry for that satire, and to have such of the persons told so whom he had assailed in it as he was likely to fall
					in with in society; myself among the number. I met him three or four times on courteous terms, and saw enough of
					him to feel that he was rather to be shunned than sought.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron had
						apologised for his satire on Southey through Richard Sharp, and Byron and Southey had met on friendly terms at
						Holland House on 26 September 1813; see Southey to Edith Southey, 28 September&#8211;[1 October] 1813, <title>The
							Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2309. Byron had admired <title>Roderick, the Last
							of the Goths</title> (1814) and Southey told his friends &#8216;Lord Byrons commendations are repeated to me from all
						quarters&#8217;; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 December 1814, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert
							Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2516.</note> Attack me as he will, I shall not go out of my course to break a
					spear with him; but if it comes in my way to give him a passing touch, it will be one that will leave a scar.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The third and last volume of my Opus Majus will be published in two or three weeks; they are
					printing the index.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
						1810&#8211;1819); the &#8216;Index&#8217; covered the entire work (III, pp. [903]&#8211;950). </note> What effect will it produce? It may
					tend to sober the anticipations of a young author to hear the faithful anticipations of an experienced one. None
					that will be heard of. It will move quietly from the publishers to a certain number of reading societies, and a
					certain number of private libraries; enough between them to pay the expenses of the publication. Some twenty
					persons in England, and some half dozen in Portugal and Brazil will peruse it with avidity and delight. Some fifty,
					perhaps, will buy the book because of the subject, and ask one another if they have had time to look into it. A few
					of those who know me and love me, will wish that I had employed the time which it has cost in writing poems; and
					some of those who do not know me, will marvel that in the ripe season of my mind, and in the summer of reputation,
					I should have bestowed so large a portion of life upon a work which could not possibly become either popular or
					profitable. And is this all? No, Chauncey Townshend, it is not all; and I should deal insincerely with you if I did
					not add, that ages hence it will be found among those works which are not destined to perish; and secure for me a
					remembrance in other countries as well as in my own; and that it will be read in the heart of S. America, and
					communicate to the Brazilians, when they shall have become a powerful nation, much of their own history which would
					otherwise have perished; and be to them what the work of Herodotus<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The
						classical historian Herodotus (c. 484&#8211;425 BC), whose <title>Histories</title> were often seen as the first works
						of academic history.</note> is to Europe. You will agree with me on one point at least, &#8211; that I am in no danger
					of feeling disappointment. But you will agree also that no man can deserve or obtain the applause of after ages, if
					he is too solicitous about that of his own.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you!</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>