<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3665</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4936</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3665. Robert Southey to John May, 7 April&#8211;1 September
                  1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3665.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 5p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 32&#8211;41 [in
               part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3665" type="letter">
        <head>3665. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1821-04-07">7 April&#8211;1 September
                  1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 5p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 32&#8211;41 [in
               part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1821-04-07"> April 7. 1821.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not whether Digges<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Atwood Digges (1742&#8211;1822), of Maryland;
                  expatriate and embezzler. Digges and Tyler had met in Lisbon in 1774. </note> withdrew upon discovering that <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> fortune was very inferior to what he had expected, judging from her appearance
               at Lisbon, or whether a discovery to the same effect was made on her side, but for one or other of these reasons, or perhaps for both
               an end was put to an intimacy which <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> from the beginning had strongly
               disapproved, &amp; which gave my Grandmother<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill, n&#233;e Bradford (1710&#8211;1782).</note>
               much uneasiness while it continued in England. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> then took a house at
               Bath, &amp; there my earliest recollections begin, great part of my earliest childhood having been past there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The house was in Walcot parish, in what five &amp; forty years ago was the skirts of the city. It stood alone in a
               walled garden, &amp; the entrance was from a lane. The situation was thought a bad one, because of the approach, &amp; because the
               nearest houses were of a mean description: in other respects it was a very desirable residence. The house had been quite in the country
               when it was built; one of its fronts looked into the garden, the other <del>xxxxxxx</del> into a lower garden, &amp; over other garden
               grounds, to the river, Bath wick fields &#8211; (which are &lt;now&gt; covered with streets,) &amp; Claverton Hill, with a grove of firs along its
               brow, &amp; a sham Castle in the midst of their long dark line: &#8211; I have not a stronger desire to see the Pyramids, than I had to visit
               that sham Castle<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sham Castle, Bathampton, built as an eye-catcher in 1762.</note> during the
               first years of my life. There was a sort of rural freshness about the place. The dead wall of a dwelling house which formed one side of
               the garden-enclosure was covered with fine fruit trees; the way from the garden door to the house was between that wall &amp; a row of
               espaliers, behind which was a grass plat, interspersed with standard trees &amp; flower beds, &amp; having one of those green rotatory
               garden seats, shaped like a tub, <del>because I suppose</del> &lt;<del>that</del> where&gt; the contemplative person within may like
               Diogenes, be as much in the sun as he pleases.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek philosopher Diogenes (c. 400&#8211;325 BC).
                  He reputedly told Alexander the Great (356&#8211;323 BC, King of Macedon 336&#8211;323 BC) to move out of the way because he wished to continue
                  sitting in the sun.</note> There was a descent by a few steps to another garden, which was chiefly filled with fragrant herbs, &amp;
               with a long bed of lilies of the valley. Ground rent had been of little value when the house was built, the kitchen looked into the
               garden, &amp; opened into it; &amp; by the kitchen door was a pipe supplied from some &lt;of the&gt; fine springs with &lt;with which the
               country about Bath abounds, &amp; -&gt; a little stone cistern beneath. The parlour door also opened into the garden &lt;it was bowered with
               jessamine&gt;, &amp; there I often took my seat upon the stone steps.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">My Aunt</ref> who had an unlucky taste for such things, fitted up the
               house at a much greater expence than she was able to afford. She threw two small rooms into one, &amp; thus made a good parlour, &amp;
                  <del>converted</del> built a drawing room over the kitchen. The walls were covered with a plain green paper, the floor with a Turkey
               carpet; there hung her own picture by Gainsborough<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The fashionable portrait painter, Thomas
                  Gainsborough (1727&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>). The portrait was painted c. 1775 and was commissioned by John Bateman, 2nd Viscount
                  Bateman (1721&#8211;1782), of Shobdon Court. It is currently in private hands.</note> with a <del>gauze</del> curtain to preserve the
               frame from flies &amp; the colours from the sun; &amp; there stood one of the most beautiful pieces of old furniture I ever saw,&#8212;a
               cabinet of ivory &lt;ebony&gt; &amp; tortoise shell, in an ebony frame. It had been left her by a Lady of the Spencer family, &amp; was said
               to have belonged to the great Marlborough.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The army officer and politician, John Churchill, 1st
                  Duke of Marlborough (1650&#8211;1722; <title>DNB</title>), whose younger daughter, Anne (1683&#8211;1716), married Charles Spencer, 3rd Earl of
                  Sunderland (1675&#8211;1722). Their daughter, Lady Anne Spencer (1702&#8211;1769), married the Whig politician William Bateman, 1st Viscount
                  Bateman (1695&#8211;1744). The Batemans lived at Shobdon Court and were on excellent terms with Herbert Bradford (1701&#8211;1768), Curate of
                  Shobdon 1728&#8211;1768, and his niece, Elizabeth Tyler. The &#8216;Lady of the Spencer family&#8217; who left the ornate cabinet to Elizabeth Tyler
                  was therefore probably Anne Bateman.</note> I may mention as part of the parlour-furniture a square screen with a foot-board &amp; a
               little shelf, because I have always had one of the same fashion myself, for its convenience; a French writing table, because of its
               peculiar shape, which was that of a cashew-nut or a kidney, the writer sate in the concave, &amp; had a drawer on each side; &#8211; an armed
               chair made of fine cherry wood, which had been M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bradfords,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth
                  Tyler&#8217;s uncle, Herbert Bradford.</note> &amp; in which she always sate, &#8212;because if any visitor who was not in her especial favour
               sate therein, the leathern cushion was always sent into the garden to be aired &amp; purified before she would use it again; &#8211; a
               mezzotinto print of Pope&#8217;s Eloisa,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The print was based on Alexander Pope&#8217;s (1688&#8211;1744;
                     <title>DNB</title>) verse epistle &#8216;Eloisa to Abelard&#8217; (1717).</note> because of its supposed likeness to herself; &#8211; two prints in
               the same stile of engraving from Angelica Kauffman one of Hector &amp; Andromache, the other of Telemachus at the court of
                  Menelaus,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The prints were probably of the following paintings by Angelica Kauffman
                  (1741&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>): <title>Hector Taking Leave of Andromache</title> (a version of this was exhibited at the Royal
                  Academy, London, in 1769) and <title>Telemachus at the Court of Sparta</title> (c. 1773).</note> because they were in frames of
               Brazilian wood; &amp; the great print of Pombal, &lt;o grande Marquez&gt;,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The great Marquis&#8217;;
                  Sebasti&#227;o Jos&#233; de Carvalho e Melo, Marquess of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777.</note> in a similar frame,
               because this was the first portrait of any great man with which I became familiar. &#8211; The <del>xxx</del> establishment consisted of an
               old man servant, &amp; a maid, both from Shobdon.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> The old man used to <hi rend="ital">feed</hi> the crickets, &amp; died in her service. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here my time was chiefly past from the age of two till six. I had many indulgences, but more privations, &amp; those of
               an injurious kind, &#8211; want of playmates, want of exercise, &#8211; never being allowed to do any thing in which by possibility I might dirt
               myself, &#8211; late hours in company, that is to say late hours for a child, which I reckon among the privations (having always had the
               healthiest propensity for going to bed betimes) &amp; late hours of rising, which were <del>in every respect far</del> &lt;less painful
               perhaps but in other respects&gt; worse. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">My Aunt</ref> chose that I should sleep with
               her, &amp; this subjected me to a double evil. She was in the habit of having her bed warmed, &amp; during the months while this
                  <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del>, &lt;practice was in season,&gt; I was always put into Mollys<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Miss Tyler&#8217;s
                  maid, unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> bed first, for fear of an accident from the warming pan, &amp; removed
               when <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> went to bed, &#8211; so that I was regularly wakened out of a sound
               sleep. This however was not half so bad as being obliged to lie till nine &amp; not unfrequently till ten in the morning, &amp; not
               daring to make the slightest movement that could disturb her during the hours that I lay awake, longing to be set free. These were
               indeed early &amp; severe lessons of patience. My poor little wits were upon the alert at those tedious times of compulsory idleness,
               watching the light from the crevices of the window shutters, &#8211; till it served me at last &lt;by its progressive motion&gt; to measure the
               lapse of time ), &#8211; wondering at the motes in the &lt;slant&gt; sunbeam, &#8211; &amp; fancying figures &amp; combinations of form in the curtains.
               Thoroughly injudicious as my education under <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> was, no part of it was
               so irksome as this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was inoculated at Bath at two years old, &amp; most certainly believe that I have a distinct recollection of it, as
               an insulated fact, &amp; the precise place where it was performed.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">* &#8216;See p. 5&#8217; [Southey&#8217;s
                  note, to indicate the insertion that follows, &#8216;My Mother &#8230; D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Schomberg&#8217;, can be found on the fifth manuscript
                  page of the letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.]</note> &lt;<ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> sometimes fancied that my constitution received permanent injury from the long preparatory lowering regimen upon
               which I was kept. Before that time, she said, I had always been plump &amp; fat; but afterwards became the lean lank greyhound-like
               creature that I have ever since continued. She came to Bath to be with me during the eruption; except the <del>xxxx</del> spots upon
               the arm I had only one pustule; afraid that this might <del>xx</del> not be enough she gave me <del>one</del> &lt;a single&gt; mouthful of
               meat at dinner, &amp; before night above an hundred pustules were produced, &#8211; with fever enough to frighten her severely. The disease
               however was very favourable. A year or two after I was brought to the brink of death by a fever, &#8211; &amp; still remember the taste of
               one of my medicines, &amp; the cup in which it was administered. On both these occasions D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Schomberg &amp;c&gt; D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Schomberg attended me, &#8211; an unlucky man whose literary attempts were not creditable to him, &amp; who was
               afterwards obliged to leave Bath upon a charge of pocketing money <del>one day</del> at the Church door when he held the plate &lt;for
               some charitable collection.&gt;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Ralph Schomberg (1714&#8211;1792; <title>DNB</title>), a German-born
                  physician and prolific writer (and plagiarist) on medical and literary subjects, who established himself in medical practice in Bath
                  in c. 1761. He was notorious for his avarice, and even, in 1747, instigated a legal case against his own father, the physician Meyer
                  L&#246;w Schomberg (1690&#8211;1761; <title>DNB</title>), for a fictitious debt. In 1778 Ralph Schomberg was accused of stealing money from a
                  church collection plate. His accuser was an equally colourful character, the quarrelsome travel writer Philip Thicknesse (1719&#8211;1792;
                     <title>DNB</title>). Schomberg left Bath under a cloud, eventually settling in Reading, where he died in 1792.</note> The
               accusation was made upon the spot, it is very possible that he <del>xxx</del> had put some of the money in his pocket, lest it should
               fall from the plate, &amp; being thus rudely accused, in an <del>x</del> evil moment thought it better to deny the fact, than state the
               simple truth, which malice would immediately &lt;have&gt; construed into an excuse, &amp; proclaimed as a confession. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">My Aunt</ref> believed that there was an intention of purloining, because Schomberg was
               notoriously fond of money; but she considered the inhumanity of exposing him, &amp; thereby bringing shame &amp; misery upon his
                  family,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Schomberg had married the heiress Elizabeth Crowcher (1719&#8211;1807). They had ten
                  children, most of whom died in childhood.</note> as a greater crime, &amp; she was one of the few persons who did not in consequence
               renounce their acquaintance. I mention this to her honour. One of his sons was the midshipman who was much talked of some forty years
               ago for having fought Prince William Henry, then one of his shipmates. I think he is the author of a history of our naval
                  achievements.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The naval officer and historian Isaac Schomberg (1753&#8211;1813;
                  <title>DNB</title>). In 1786 he had been appointed First Lieutenant of HMS <title>Pegasus</title>, then in the West Indies. Part of
                  his role was to act as mentor to the ship&#8217;s commander, the inexperienced Prince William (1765&#8211;1837; King of the United Kingdom
                  1830&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>). The two men clashed repeatedly and matters came to a head when the station commander, Horatio Nelson
                  (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), had Schomberg arrested and confined in his cabin until a court martial could be held. This did not
                  take place and Schomberg was returned to England. He resumed active service in 1788, and held his last command in 1794&#8211;1795. In
                  retirement he wrote a five-volume <title>Naval Chronology, or, An Historical Summary of Naval and Maritime Events from the Time of
                     the Romans to the Treaty of Peace, 1802</title> (1802). He also had charge of the sea fencibles, the naval militia, from Southend
                  to Harwich (1801) and Hastings (1803&#8211;1808), and was a Commissioner of the Royal Navy 1808&#8211;1813.</note> Alexander another son was a
               fellow of Corpus, &amp; died in 1790 or 91,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;1,&#8217; is written over &#8216;2,&#8217;.</note> having lost the
               use of his lower limbs by a stroke of the palsy.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Crowcher Schomberg (1756&#8211;1792;
                     <title>DNB</title>), poet and writer on jurisprudence. He was educated at Winchester College and Magdalen College, Oxford, and
                  was a Probationary Fellow of Magdalen (not Corpus Christi) 1782&#8211;1792. His works included <title>Ode on the Present State of English
                     Poetry</title> (1779) and <title>An Historical and Chronological View of Roman Law</title> (1785). He died in Bath and was buried
                  in the Abbey. </note> I had the mournful office of going often to sit by him as he lay upon his back in bed, when he was vainly
               seeking relief at Bath. Boy as I was, &amp; till then a stranger to him, he was glad of the relief which even my presence afforded to
               his <del>friendless</del> &lt;deplorable&gt; solitude, &#8211; for he had no friend with him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> had a numerous acquaintance, such as her person &amp;
               talents (which were of no ordinary kind) were likely to attract. The circle of her Herefordshire connections extending as far as the
               sphere of the three Music Meetings in the three diocese of Hereford, Worcester, &amp; Gloucester,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The Three Choirs Festival, founded in the early eighteenth century.</note> she became intimate with the family of Mr
                  Raikes,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Raikes (c. 1690&#8211;1757; <title>DNB</title>), co-founder and printer of the
                     <title>Gloucester Journal</title>, which commenced publication on 9 April 1722.</note>
          <del>a pr</del> the printer of the
               Gloucester Journal, one of whose sons introduced Sunday Schools*<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">* I know not where or when
                  they were first instituted, but an Ordnance of Albert &amp; Isabel, in 1608 speaks of them as then existing in the Catholic
                  Netherlands, &amp; enjoins the Magistrates to see to their establishment &amp; support, in all places where they were not yet set on
                  foot. [Southey&#8217;s note.] [Editors&#8217; note: Isabella (1566&#8211;1633) and Albert of Habsburg (1559&#8211;1621) were joint sovereigns of the Spanish
                  Netherlands, 1598&#8211;1621.]</note> into this country, &amp; others became India Directors Bank Directors &amp; so forth in the career
               of mercantile prosperity.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Raikes&#8217;s eldest son Robert (1736&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>) took over
                  the <title>Gloucester Journal</title> and the printing company from his father, and was famed for his promotion of Sunday schools,
                  where children from poorer backgrounds could receive religious instruction. The following of Raikes&#8217;s brothers were London
                  merchants: William Raikes (1738&#8211;1800); Thomas Raikes (1741&#8211;1813), Governor of the Bank of England 1797&#8211;1799; and Charles Raikes
                  (1745&#8211;1828). Richard Raikes (c. 1753&#8211;1823) was, however, a clergyman.</note> A daughter who was <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunts</ref> friend, married Francis Newberry<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary
                  Raikes (1748-c. 1829) married the publisher Francis Newbery (1743&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>) on 29 May 1770.</note> of St Pauls
               Church Yard, son of that F. N.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Newbery was the son of John Newbery (c. 1713&#8211;1767;
                     <title>DNB</title>), the first publisher to create a dedicated list of books for children. </note> who published Giles
               Gingerbread, Goody Two shoes, &amp; other such worthy histories in sixpenny books for children splendidly bound in the <del>gilt Dutch
                  paper</del> flowered &amp; gilt Dutch paper of former days. As soon as I could read, which was very early, Mr Newberry presented me
               with a whole set of these books, more than twenty in number, which I dare say were in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> possession at her death, &amp; in perfect preservation; for she taught me never to spoil nor injure any thing.
               This was a rich present, &amp; may have been more instrumental than I am aware of, in giving me that decided determination to
               literature which manifested itself from my childhood upwards. I can trace with certainty the rise &amp; direction of my poetical
               pursuits: it grew out of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunts</ref> intimacy with <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Palmer<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">John Palmer (1703&#8211;1788).</note> (her father)
               acquired considerable property as a wax &amp; tallow chandler at Bath, &amp; vested great part of it in a very curious manner for an
               illiterate tradesman. He had a passion for the stage, which he indulged by speculating in theatres. One he built at Birmingham, one at
               Bristol &amp; one at Bath. Poor man he outlived his reasonable faculties, &amp; was when I knew him a pitiable spectacle of human
               weakness &lt;&amp; decay&gt;, hideously ugly, his nose <del>having</del> grown out in knobs &lt;&amp; bulbs&gt; like an underground artichoke, his
               fingers crooked &amp; knotted with the gout; dirty, irascible, <del>&amp; weaker than</del> &lt;helpless as&gt; an infant <del>in xxx
                  reason</del> &lt;&amp; feebler than one in mind&gt;. In one respect this was happy for him. His wife,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Jane Palmer, n&#233;e Long (1714/5&#8211;1783).</note> a kind, plain-mannered domestic woman, <del>xxx</del> &lt;caught&gt; her
               cloathes on fire, ran into the street in flames, &amp; was burnt to death; &amp; he tho in the house never knew what had befallen her.
               He survived her several years, &amp; would frequently say she had been gone more than a week to Devizes, &amp; it was time she should
               come back. He lived with his two daughters <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref>, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bartlett<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Bartlett (1748&#8211;1830).</note> (a widow) at Bath, in Galloways
               Buildings, in a house at which I often visited during fifteen of my life, sometimes for weeks at a time with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref>. And I was sometimes taken to see this deplorable old man, the sight of whom
               always excited in me a mingled feeling of <del>fear</del> &lt;horror&gt; &amp; disgust, not to be recalled without some degree of pain. &#8211;
                  <del>Xxxx</del> In consequence of his incapacity the property of the Bath &amp; Bristol theatres devolved upon his children, &amp;
               was <del>managed</del> &lt;administered&gt; by his son,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">John Palmer (1742&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>),
                  theatre proprietor and postal reformer; MP for Bath 1801&#8211;1808. He devised a postal system that used fast and secure mail
                  coaches.</note> who by the institution of the Mail Coach has contributed so large to change almost the very constitution of society.
               He was in truth a remarkable &amp; rememberable person, even if he had not struck out so efficient &amp; operative a plan.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He must have been about five &amp; thirty when I first remember him, a man of <del>fine</del> great talents &amp; fine
               person, with a commanding air &amp; countenance, kind in his manners &amp; in his nature, &#8211; yet there was an expression in his eyes
               which I felt before I ever heard of physiognomy, or could have understood the meaning of the word. It was a wild <del>xxxxxxxless</del>
               unquiet look, a sort of inward emanating light, as if all was not as it should be within I should pronounce now that it was the eye of
               a man predisposed to insanity, &amp; this I believe to have been the fact, tho the disease manifested itself not in him, but in his
               children. They indeed had double reason to apprehend such an inheritence, for their mother was plainly crazed with hypochondriacism
               &amp; fantasticalness. She was a widow &amp; an actress when he married her,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Palmer married
                  Sarah Mason (dates unknown), a widow, on 24 August 1769. The couple had six children. </note> &amp; her humours soon made any place
               more agreable to him than home. The children were my playmates at the rare times when I had any. The eldest son<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">John Palmer (1773&#8211;1851), the eldest recorded son of John Palmer, did attend Charterhouse, but his later
                  career did not follow the trajectory outlined by Southey; Palmer attended Trinity College, Cambridge, and became a clergyman, ending
                  his career as Rector of Peldon, Essex, 1817&#8211;1851.</note> was taken from the Charter House literally because he was almost killed
               there by the &lt;devilish&gt; cruelty of the boys; &#8211; they used to lay him before the fire till he was scorched, &amp; shut him in a trunk
               with saw dust. The Charter House at that time was a sort of Hell upon earth for the under boys. He was of weak understanding, very like
               his mother in person, &amp; I believe died insane as did one of his sisters who <del>was his</del> perfectly resembled him. Two other
               boys were at Eton,*<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">* Charles the second of these is at present member for Bath; &#8211; that Col:
                  Palmer who appeared in the prosecution of Col. Quintin. [Southey&#8217;s note.] [Editors&#8217; note: Charles Palmer (1777&#8211;1851;
                     <title>DNB</title>) was educated at Eton (1791&#8211;1793) and at Oriel College, Oxford. He served in the army, rising to the rank of
                  Major-General, and sat as Whig MP for Bath (1808&#8211;1826, 1830&#8211;1837). He inherited his father&#8217;s theatrical concerns and also owned
                  vineyards in the Gironde. In 1814 Colonel George Augustus Quintin [also &#8216;Quentin&#8217;] (1760&#8211;1851) of the 10th Hussars, or Prince of
                  Wales&#8217;s Own regiment, was court-martialled on three counts of neglect of duty and one of general laxity of discipline. He was found
                  guilty on part of the first charge, for which offence he was reprimanded. Quintin&#8217;s wife was rumoured to be the Prince Regent&#8217;s
                  mistress, and the verdict was felt in many quarters to be the result of influence and favouritism. The officers who had accused
                  Quintin were, in contrast, treated more harshly. They were ordered to leave the regiment and were distributed among other cavalry
                  regiments. They included Charles Palmer, who on 23 November 1814, used his position as an MP to attack the verdicts in
                  parliament.]</note> Tom,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Palmer (b.1775/1776) attended Eton and was admitted to
                  Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1793, moving to Trinity Hall in 1795. He joined Lincoln&#8217;s Inn in 1794. His date of death is not
                  recorded. </note> the elder of the two had one of the most beautiful countenances I ever remember to have seen, &#8211; only that it had
               his fathers eyes, &amp; a more fearful light in them. He was a fine, generous, &lt;overflowing&gt; creature, but you could &lt;not&gt; look &lt;at
               him&gt; without fearing &lt;that&gt; some disastrous <del>xxx</del> fate would befall one so rash, so thoughtless, &amp; withal so keenly
               susceptible. When he was at Cambridge he gave orders to his Gyp by blowing a French horn, having a tune for every specific command,
               till <del>this</del> &lt;so noisy &amp; unacademical&gt; practise was forbidden. <del>His dismal history</del> There he ran wild, &amp;
               contracted debts in all imaginable ways, which his father, the most indulgent of fathers, again &amp; again discharged. On the last of
               these occasions, when a large sum had been paid for him where his conduct had been highly culpable, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Palmer did
               not utter a single reproach, but in the most affectionate manner entreated him to put away all painful <del>recollec</del> thoughts of
               the past, &amp; <del>consider</del> &lt;look upon&gt; himself as if he were only now beginning life. The poor fellow could not bear his
               father kindness, &amp; <del>blew out his own brains</del> &lt;knowing perhaps too surely, that he could not trust his own resolutions to
               amend his life, blew out his own brains.&gt;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had not seen him for several years before his death. When we were boys I admired him for his wit, his <del>xxxxx
                  xxxxxxx spirits</del> &lt;hilarity, his generous temper&gt; &amp; his countenance which <del>I</del> might better be called <hi rend="ital">radiant</hi> than described by any other epithet: but there was <del>in</del> something which <del>prevented</del>
               &lt;precluded&gt; all desire of intimacy. If we had been thrown together in youth, there would have been an intellectual attraction between
               us, &#8211; but intellect alone has never been the basis of my friendships, except in a single instance, &#8211; &amp; that instance proved the
               sandiness of such a foundation. &#8211; Yet we liked each other, &#8211; &amp; I never think of him without a hope, &#8211; or rather a belief, &#8211; an
               inward &amp; sure persuasion &#8211; that there is more mercy in store for human frailty than even the most liberal creed has authorized us
               to assert.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In what manner my acquaintance with this family was the means of leading</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">My favoured footsteps to the Muses Hill, </l>
          <l rend="indent3">Whose arduous paths I have not ceased to tread </l>
          <l rend="indent3">From good to better persevering still, &#8211; <note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                        Waterloo</title> (London, 1816), &#8216;Proem&#8217;, lines 122&#8211;124.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent0"> shall be shown in the next letter.</p>
        <closer>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1821-09-01">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1. 1821. </date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>