<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3231</idno><idno type="nines">rce4502</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3231. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 6 January
                  1819 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3231.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3231" type="letter"><head>3231. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1819-01-06">6 January
                  1819 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey.<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 9 JA 9/ 1819; [partial] 10 o’Clock/ JA. 9/ 1818 F<lb/> Seal: [trace] red wax<lb/> MS:
                  Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 174. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> It is very long since I have heard from you, – &amp; now I should be &lt;more&gt; than usually glad to receive a letter, in
               the hope of hearing that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> <del>was</del> is thoroughly recovered.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> when he informed me of the event in his own family,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Post</title>, 21 December 1818, announced the death of Emma, the infant daughter of
                  Mary Anne March, née Gonne (b. 1792), sister of Louisa Southey.</note> told me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> illness, – but that he was doing well. </p><p rend="indent1"> My household is very much reduced. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <del>with</del>
               her cousin <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> have been at <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> for
               the last week, &amp; will remain there about a week longer. – I thought myself as secure from all interruption during the winter, as a
               bear in his den, retired upon his paws: – but yesterday came a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> to say he should be here this week. I am always glad to see him, – but if he had come during the
               idle season, it would have suited better with my inclination &amp; convenience. </p><p rend="indent1"> I shall send you the conclusion of the current Chapter in a day or two.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter
                  39, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 442–504.</note> – You see I am drawing near the close of
               this arduous work. The next chapter relates to the operations concerning the Treaty on the side of Maranham, &amp; the expulsion of the
               Portugueze Jesuits.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 40, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819),
                  III, pp. 505–547, dealing with the redrawing of Brazil’s boundaries following the Treaty of Madrid in 1750 and the expulsion of the
                  Jesuits from Brazil in 1759.</note> Then come Pombals other measures relating to Brazil, – the exclusive Companies, the diamond
               contract &amp;c – the war of 1762– &amp; the final cession of Colonia.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 41,
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 548–602. It focused on the Brazilian policies of Sebastião
                  José Carvalho e Melo, Marquis of Pombal (1699–1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750–1777. These included: the establishment of
                  exclusive trading companies in Maranhao (1755) and Pernambuco (1759); direct government control of the diamond mining district
                  (1771); the Spanish-Portuguese War of 1762–1763; and the status of the Portuguese settlement of Nova Colonia do Santissimo
                  Sacramento in Uruguay, which was ceded to Spain by the Treaty of Madrid (1750), receded to Portugal by the Treaty of El Pardo (1761)
                  and finally ceded to Spain by the Treaty of Ildefonso (1777).</note> The expulsion of the Spanish Jesuits – the projected revolution
               in M Geraes,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapters 42–43, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III,
                  pp. 603–695, dealing with the expulsion of the Jesuits from Spanish America in 1767; and a planned insurrection in Minas Geraes in
                  1789, with the aim of creating a Brazilian Republic. Chapter 43 concluded with the flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil in
                  1807–1808.</note> &amp; a concluding chapter upon the state of Brazil at the time of the removal of the seat of Government.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 44, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 696–879.</note>
               Four chapters &amp; not long ones, I think, will comprize the whole. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles papers have been of considerable
               use, especially the extracts from his predecessors dispatches<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole (1736–1810;
                     <title>DNB</title>) was the British envoy to Portugal 1771–1800; Southey had been sent Walpole’s papers by John May.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have been endeavoring in vain to find when Gomes Freyre (of the Treaty)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Gomes
                  Freire de Andrade, Conde de Bobadela (1685–1763), Governor and Captain-General of Rio de Janeiro 1733–1763. He commanded the
                  Portuguese and Spanish troops that defeated the Guarani troops in the Guarani war (or War of the Seven Reductions) in 1754–1756.
                  Southey strongly sympathised with the Guarani, who refused to move from their lands when they were shifted from Spanish to
                  Portuguese control by the Treaty of Madrid (1750).</note> died, – whether it was before the <hi rend="ital">Relaçam Abbreviada</hi>
               was published.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A history of the War of the Seven Reductions, largely written by Pombal:
                     <title>Relação Abbreviada da República que os Religiosos Jesuítas das Províncias de Portugal e Espanha Estabeleceram nos Dominios
                     Ultramarinos das Duas Monarchias </title>(1756).</note> Because it appears to me plain that after he had got to the Reductions
               &amp; become personally acquainted with the Jesuits his opinion concerning them &amp; their conduct was totally different from that
               which is expressed in the extracts from his correspondence given in the <hi rend="ital">Relaçam</hi>. Unluckily none of these
               genealogical books are of so late a date, – nor is his name among your MSS additions to the Grandes de Portugal.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Caetano de Sousa (1674–1759), <title>Memorias Historicas, e Genealogicas dos Grandes de
                     Portugal</title> (1755), no. 3739 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This copy contained ‘17 pages of MS.
                  additions’.</note> It is however a matter of little consequence. </p><p rend="indent1"> The worst of all these lives of Pombal is certainly the French one,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Administration du Marquis de Pombal</title> (1786), no. 2280 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> for if
               the author had any materials furnished him by the family he seems to have made no use of them, &amp; there is nothing to be collected
               from his book. In point of meagerness it stands almost unrivalled. All the others tho malicious &amp; libellous to the last degree of
               malignity, have got a foundation of facts. A certain George Moore Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> – has lately published a life of Pombal,
               with those of Alberoni &amp; Ripperda,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">George Moore (1770–1840), <title>Lives of Cardinal
                     Alberoni, the Duke of Ripperda, and Marquis of Pombal, Three Distinguished Political Adventurers of the Last Century</title>
                  (1806, 3rd edition 1819), no. 1993 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was a joint biography of Pombal with Cardinal
                  Giulio Alberoni (1664–1752) and John William, Baron Ripperda (1684–1737), two leading figures in Spanish politics. Moore was a
                  landowner in County Mayo, a historian and a member of the Whig Holland House circle. His father, George Moore (1729–1799), had been
                  a merchant trading with Spain.</note> – he got his materials from Lord Sligo,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Browne,
                  1st Marquess of Sligo (1756–1809); he had died at Lisbon in 1809.</note> – you may judge therefore <del>how</del> upon how scanty a
               stock he set up. At present I have nothing to do with his general administration, &amp; shall leave the general question concerning the
               Jesuits for the history of Portugal,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> saying
               no more than is indispensable for making the transactions in Brazil understood. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CoxeWilliam">Coxe</ref> intended to write the history of King José.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">José I (1714–1777; King of Portugal 1750–1777). Coxe did not write this book.</note> – I hope he may
               execute this intention; – like all his books it will be made up of diplomatic material &amp; instead of forestalling me, he will smooth
               the way for like a pioneer. I am reading his Memoirs of Marlborough,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of
                  William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke of Marlborough, with his Original Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at
                     Blenheim, and Other Authentic Sources. Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818–1819) appeared in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (May 1820), 1–73.</note> – a very interesting book, – by far the most valuable of all his
               publications. As soon as the third volume is published I shall set about reviewing it, – not without a suspicion that the reviewal may
               grow into a separate publication like the life of Nelson.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Life of
                     Nelson</title> (1813) grew out of his article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218–262.</note> It is highly
               gratifying to find Marlboroughs<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650–1722;
                     <title>DNB</title>), politician and army commander. Southey did not write his biography.</note> character rise in proportion as
               it is laid open. </p><p rend="indent1"> We have had no snow in the valley yet, &amp; altho the mountain tops have twice or thrice been powdered, the snow has
               never remained there four &amp; twenty hours. The general temperature has been as mild as fine spring weather so that I have not yet
               taken to my flannel drawers. Your fogs are things of which we know nothing, this house has not been enveloped in one three times during
               the fifteen years that I have resided in it. – Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the
                  boys,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The Hills’ sons.</note> &amp; happy new years to all. </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-01-06">6 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1819</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>