<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3554</idno><idno type="nines">rce4825</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3554. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 13 November 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3554.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856),
                  III, pp. 217–220.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3554" type="letter"><head>3554. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1820-11-13">13 November 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
                  M.P./ Llangedwin/ near/ Oswestry<lb/> Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb/> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
                  Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856),
                  III, pp. 217–220.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1820-11-13">13 Nov. 1820</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#NealeCornelius">Cornelius Neale</ref> dedicated a tragedy called Mustapha to me, some
               five or six years ago.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Cornelius Neale, <title>Mustapha: a Tragedy</title>
                  (1814).</note> I afterwards breakfasted with him at the house of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah
               Conder</ref>, proprietor, editor, &amp; at that time publisher of the Eclectic Review. Neales father<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Neale (c. 1740–1814), china and glass merchant and co-owner of Neale &amp; Wilson, pottery manufacturers, of
                  Church Works, Staffordshire. He was one of the founders of the London Missionary Society in 1795.</note> kept the great china shop
               in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls Church Yard, by the gateway <del>of</del> &lt;leading to&gt; Doctors Commons, – &amp; he himself has married
               a daughter of John Mason Good.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Cornelius Neale married, in 1816, Susanna Good (dates unknown),
                  daughter of John Mason Good (1764–1827; <title>DNB</title>), physician, linguist and poet.</note> He is a little, mild, religious
               man, with a great deal of poetical feeling, which he knows how to express, – <del>but</del> not, I think, with much power of mind, –
               but free from all prevailing faults either of manner or morals in his writings</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me the Sketch Book, the author of which I met in his
                  room.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Washington Irving (1783–1859), <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.</title>
                  (1820), a collection of stories set in New England. Murray was the English publisher.</note> It is a very pleasing, clever book.
               What the writer says concerning the Indians, is more creditable to his humanity than to his judgement. It is quite an ex parte view of
               the case. Philip of Pokanoket,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Metacomet (c. 1639– 1676), Sachem of the Wampanoag people. He
                  used the name ‘Philip’ in his dealings with the New England settlers and was the native American leader in King Philip’s War of
                  1675–1676 with the settlers. This war formed the background to Southey’s unfinished epic poem, set in New England. The completed
                  sections were published after Southey’s death in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical
                     Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1–90. This conflict was also dealt with in the story ‘Philip of Pokanoket’ in Irving’s
                     <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), II, pp. 169–196.</note> with whom I shall make
               you better acquainted than Irving seems to be, had all the treachery of a true savage, as well as some of a savages virtues. His Indian
               name was Massasoit<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is incorrect here: Massasoit (c. 1581–1661) was Metacomet’s
                  father.</note> (not Kawnacom) &amp; the historical grounds of my poem, are as Irving supposes, to be found in the main events of
               what is called Philips War.</p><p rend="indent1"> I know not what to think of this termination of the Queens business,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Under
                  extreme pressure from George IV, the Cabinet had reluctantly agreed to introduce a Bill of Pains and Penalties into the House of
                  Lords to deprive the King’s wife, Caroline of Brunswick (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), of the title of Queen and to dissolve her
                  marriage to the King. On the Third Reading of the Bill on 10 November 1820, the government majority was only nine votes and it
                  seemed very unlikely the Bill could pass the House of Commons. Lord Liverpool, the Prime Minister, therefore announced the Bill
                  would be withdrawn.</note> except that it is plain enough the reign of terror has begun, &amp; where it is to end God knows. The
               Queens lawyers<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Primarily Henry Brougham and Thomas Denman (1779–1854; <title>DNB</title>), Whig
                  lawyer and MP for various seats 1818–1832, Lord Chief Justice 1832–1850.</note> as well as her radical friends, have stuck at no
               means to serve her, &amp; they have succeeded in deceiving some of the Lords, &amp; in intimidating others, – which with the help of
               the thorough–paced Opps, &amp; a few ricketty consciences has enabled them to obtain a most disgraceful triumph, – disgraceful as
               affecting the character of the nation. Never let us wonder again at the madness in the days of Titus Oates, or of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sacheverel.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Titus Oates (1649–1705; <title>DNB</title>), originator of the mythical
                  ‘Popish Plot’ that convulsed England 1678–1681; and Henry Sacheverell (1674–1724; <title>DNB</title>), whose anti-Whig sermons led
                  to riots and a political crisis in 1710–1711.</note> The essential spirit of faction is the same in Whig &amp; in Tory, &lt;&amp; in
               all times.&gt; If Bergami<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartolomeo Pergami (1783/4–1842), the member of Queen Caroline’s
                  entourage in Italy who was accused of being her lover.</note> were to come to England I should not wonder if they were to present
               him with the freedom of the city in a gold box. By the bye one of the Italian worthies at the Lord Mayors entertainment<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Lord Mayoralty had just passed to the pro-Caroline John Thomas Thorp (1776–1835), haberdasher and MP
                  for the City of London 1818–1820, from the anti-Caroline George Bridges (c. 1762–1840), wine merchant and MP for the City of London
                  1820–1826. The celebrations at the Guildhall on 9 November 1820 were attended by several of the Italian witnesses who had supported
                  Queen Caroline, including Colonel Alessandro Olivieri (dates uknown) and Carlo Vassalli (dates unknown), the Queen’s Equerry,
                     <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 10 November 1820.</note> has a reputation which would have entitled him to stand for the office
               of Lord Horse in that <del>xxxx</del> &lt;remarkable&gt; city of which no vestige now remains, &amp; no record will be transmitted to
                  posterity.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Southey’s long-standing series of jokes about a mythical character
                  called ‘the Butler’, which he shared with Grosvenor Bedford and some of which became part of <title>The Doctor</title>
                  (1834–1847).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The matter will not end here, even if the Q. should be desirous, as probably she will be, of taking her allowance &amp;
               returning to her continental indulgencies.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Queen Caroline accepted an increased allowance of
                  £50,000 per annum, but she showed no signs of going abroad.</note> The example of bearding the Sovereign &amp; defying the laws has
               been set, &amp; the possibility of intimidating the legislature has been proved. The question of the liturgy<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The question of whether Queen Caroline’s name should be included in the Church of England’s liturgy as a member of
                  the Royal Family for whom worshippers would be asked to pray. George IV had successfully excluded her name. </note> will be <del>xx
                  xxxxx</del> taken up; the ferment will continue; &amp; things will go on from bad to worse, till the press has effected a thorough
               Revolution, or till Government has subdued the press. I fear that in another century our constitution will be held up as a warning for
               its defects, not as an object of admiration for other nations. And I am as sure as it is possible to feel concerning future events,
               that in the course of fifty years (perhaps in less than half that time) there will not be a free press in <del>xxx xxxx</del>
               Europe.</p><p rend="indent1"> King Mob demands an illumination here to night,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">To celebrate Queen Caroline’s
                  triumph, many radicals put candles in their windows.</note> – according to the <hi rend="ital">tallow-chandler</hi>, &amp; great
               disturbances are threatened. In that case my windows may suffer. – there is however no appearance of any stir as yet (between 7 &amp; 8
               o clock) – &amp; tallow chandlers are suspicious authorities in such <del>thi</del> matters.</p><p rend="indent1"> There is a book advertised about New Britain,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title>, 25
                  October 1820, advertised <title>New Britain, a Narrative of a Journey, to a Country so called by its Inhabitants, Discovered in
                     Missouri. Together with a Brief Sketch of their History</title> (1820). This was an anonymous novel, which described how the
                  descendants of a group of sixteenth-century English colonists had been ‘discovered’ in Missouri. It was, therefore, only distantly
                  related to the plot of Southey’s <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> which from the advertisement I suppose to be an Utopian Romance
               founded upon the story of Madoc. Do you know any thing of it?</p><p rend="indent1"> I have nearly finished another book of Oliver Newman,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The fifth book, ‘The
                  Portrait’, of Southey’s unfinished epic poem, set in New England.</note> &amp; shall take it up now in the hope of getting over one
               of those difficult passages in which I stick for a long time, – passages in which a reader discovers no difficulty, but a writer feels
               the greatest.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish you could have given me a better account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Wynn</ref>. – We are going on tolerably well. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> is as
               fine a creature as you could desire to see, &amp; begins to mispronounce mutilated words most delightfully. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert</ref> he makes into Cha–Cupn.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>