<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3352</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4623</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3352. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 21 September 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3352.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and
						Art Gallery, WC 186. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3352" type="letter">
        <head>3352. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1819-09-21">21 September 1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Keswick Museum and
						Art Gallery, WC 186. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline> Fort William. <date when="1819-09-21">Tuesday 21 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
					1819</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> After a long route we have come thus far on the way homewards. We left Edinburgh on the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of last month. The course we took was to Stirling, Callendar, Loch Kattern, Loch Earn Head,
					Killin, along the side of Loch Tay to Kenmore or Taymouth, Dunkeld, Perth, Dundee, &amp; so up the coast to
					Aberdeen. Then across the country to Banff, &amp; again along the coast to Elgin. From thence we struck inland to
					Grantown one day, &amp; to the coast at Forres the next, Inverness, Dingwall &amp; up the coast as far as Fleet
						Mound,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Fleet Mound was a massive causeway, commissioned in 1803, designed
						by Telford, and built between 1814&#8211;1816, to carry the road over Loch Fleet. It comprised an earthwork, and a
						bridge with self-regulating sluice gates that allowed the waters from the river to flow out, but prevented
						seawater from coming in.</note> which is near Lord Staffords<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George
						Leveson-Gower, 1st Marquess of Stafford (1758&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), created 1st Duke of Sutherland in 1833.
						His marriage in 1785 to Elizabeth Gordon, Countess of Sutherland (1765&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), added Dunrobin
						Castle and most of Sutherland to his estates.</note> seat at Dunrobin, &amp; within sight of the Ord of Caithness.
					We returned, in part by a different road to Dingwall, sent the Ladies<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref>; her two youngest children, William Charles
						Rickman (1812&#8211;1886) and Frances Rickman (dates unknown, she married Richard Brindley Hone (1805&#8211;1881), Vicar of
						Halesowen 1836&#8211;1881, in 1836); and their companion, Emma Pigott. It is difficult to be sure of Miss Pigott&#8217;s
						identity, but she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown), younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d.
						1822) of Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. Fitz-Hall was only five miles from Susannah Rickman&#8217;s home at Harting. Emma
						Pigott married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen Hill, Berkshire.</note> to Inverness, &amp; crost
					to the Western sea at Jeantown. Back to Inverness, &amp; thence along the line of the canal to this place. Tomorrow
					we move southward, &amp; expect to reach Inverary on Friday. I believe it will be thought best to <del>keep</del>
					keep clear of Glasgow &amp; the mob-countries, &amp; therefore to go from Dunbarton to Stirling, &amp; so by cross
					roads to Lanark. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> parts company from us at Carlisle,
					&amp; the Rickmans<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
							Rickman</ref> and his wife.</note> go on with me to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,
					where I hope to arrive in the course of a fortnight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The weather &amp; indeed every thing else has been hitherto as favourable as possible. And the
					only unpleasant circumstance which occurred is ending well. That <del>xxx</del> excrescence on my head which the
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Duke</ref> &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Marquis</ref> will remember by the name of Skiddaw, is gone. It became
					troublesome the day I left Edinburgh, &amp; suppurated shortly after. I showed it to a physician with whose family
					I happened to be acquainted at Perth,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey arrived in Perth on 24 August
						to see Edward Collins (c. 1777&#8211;1841), Captain in the 21st Light Dragoons and the brother of Charles Collins,
						Southey&#8217;s old schoolfriend. Southey missed seeing him, as Collins had travelled south to deal with matters arising
						from the death of his father, William Collins (c. 1751&#8211;1819), naval engineer and inventor, on 23 April 1819 at his
						home in Maize Hill, Greenwich. Southey did see Collins&#8217;s wife, Margaret (d. 1852), and her uncle, James Wood (d.
						1825), of Keithick, Perthshire. Dr Wood was &#8216;a delightful old man&#8217; who &#8216;set me at ease concerning one of the
						tumours on my head&#8217;, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London,
						1929), pp. 49&#8211;50.</note> &amp; afterwards to one surgeon at Aberdeen<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">George
						Kerr (1771&#8211;1826).</note> &amp; another at Inverness.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Fortunately for
						Southey, he was treated by one of the most eminent doctors in the north of Scotland: William Kennedy (c.
						1761&#8211;1823), Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, first President of the Medical Society of the
						North and one of the founders of the Royal Northern Infirmary, Inverness.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> drest it for me morning &amp; evening. The tumour is now entirely
					gone, the sack has been discharged, &amp; the wound is almost healed, so that I expect to reach home with a whole
					skin</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I found two books at Edinburgh of which I had long been in search, the Relations concerning
					Madagascar &amp; Brazil<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois Cauche (1616&#8211;1699), <title>Relations
							Veritables et Curieuses de l&#8217;Isle de Madagascar et du Bresil</title> (1651), no. 2363 in the sale catalogue of
						Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which you had sight of once, &#8211; &amp; Gombervilles translation of Acu&#241;as voyage<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Marin le Roy de Gomberville (1600&#8211;1674), <title>Relation de la Rivi&#232;re des
							Amazones</title> (1682), no. 7 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; the book was a translation of
						Crist&#243;bal Diatrist&#225;n de Acu&#241;a (1597&#8211;c. 1676), <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title>
						(1641). </note> &#8211; four small volumes in two, &#8211; a very neat copy. They are by this time at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My opportunities of seeing the great works which are carrying on along the coast &amp; throughout
					the north of Scotland have been very favourable. Every where we have had <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">the person</ref> with us under whose direction they are executed. I believe it
					may safely be said that so much was never done by any Government for the improvement of a country in the same
					length of time. Above 1000 miles of the finest roads in the world have been pasd thro tracts which were
					inaccessible before, &amp; 1500 bridges &#8211; great &amp; small have been erected. Harbours of all sizes have been made
					&amp; are making &#8211; from small piers which cost only a few hundred pounds, to such enormous ones as require an
					expence of 70 or 80,000. And the canal which I have now seen along its whole course, &amp; in every stage of its
					progress, is truly a stupendous work. The locks are large enough for a 32 gun frigate, &amp; at this end there are
					eight in succession, with a rise of eight feet in each, &#8211; lifting the vessel 64 feet in a distance of 500
						yards.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Neptune&#8217;s Staircase at Banavie, near Fort William, completed in
						1811. This is a staircase lock on the Caledonian Canal, comprising eight locks, which raise (or lower) boats 64
						feet in a distance of 180 feet. It is the longest staircase lock in the United Kingdom. Southey visited it on 19
						September 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929),
						pp. 202&#8211;207.</note> Where the canal is full it is like a fine river, &amp; where the excavation is still going on,
					the scene of human activity &amp; power exceeds any thing which I ever beheld elsewhere. The dredging machine which
					is employed for deepening the small Lake (Loch Oich) brings up 800 tons in a day. If this had been one of
						Buonapartes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French
						1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> works half the English would have gone to see it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I suppose my third volume<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume of
						Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) was delayed by a missing proof and was not published until
						after his return from Scotland.</note> has been published long ere this, &#8211; but we are out of the world of news
					&amp; of newspapers, &#8211; &amp; all we know is from a provincial paper &#8211; now &amp; then. This is enough to show the
					danger of the times<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Peterloo&#8217; Massacre of 16 August 1819, when the
						magistrates&#8217; decision to break up a public meeting at St Peter&#8217;s Fields, Manchester led to at least eleven deaths,
						had produced an enormous public outcry.</note> &amp; the miserable imbecillity of the Government, all whose
					measures are just calculated to bring itself into contempt, when two or three wholesome laws would instantly put
					all to rights, &#8211; for instance a law declaring all public meetings unlawful unless the requisition for them were
					signed by a certain number of persons, holding a certain qualification, &#8211; &amp; making those persons responsible
					for the proceedings of the meeting; &#8211; a law making transportation the punishment for sedition; &#8211; &amp; another
					demanding sureties from the publisher of every newspaper &amp; journal. &#8211; We shall get at the same end by worse
					means. For <del>xxxxx</del> things are so bad, that the property of the country are taking the alarm, &#8211; &amp; when
					one of these cursed manufacturing towns has been set on fire, &#8211; or that a regular action has taken place in its
					streets, I suppose the good sense of the country will begin to show itself, &amp; originate in Parliament those
					measures which the Ministers have not courage to <del>xxxxx</del> set on foot themselves. The virulence of the
					disease has shown itself so decidedly <del>xxx</del> in time that I augur well of the event.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeathcoteWm">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Heathcote</ref> would have
						found me if he had taken <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> in his way out. He was at
						Dunkeld on his way back, two days before me. I saw his name there,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">On 23
							August Southey visited Dunkeld and walked in the grounds of Dunkeld House, the home of John Murray, 4th Duke of
							Atholl (1775&#8211;1830). He wrote his name in the visitors&#8217; book at the porter&#8217;s lodge and saw the names of Heathcote
							and his travelling companion, Arthur Perceval (1799&#8211;1853; <title>DNB</title>), later a High Church clergyman and
							Royal Chaplain 1826&#8211;1853.</note> &#8211; &amp; heard of him at Bran Castle from a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hare, &#8211; a
						friend of Blackstones.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">On 11 September 1819 Southey had called at Brahan
							Castle, home of James Alexander Stewart Mackenzie (1784&#8211;1843). There he had met Augustus William Hare (1792&#8211;1834;
								<title>DNB</title>), a Fellow of New College, Oxford, and later a clergyman and writer. Hare was a friend of
							Frederick Charles Blackstone (1795&#8211;1862), a relation by marriage of Hill. Blackstone&#8217;s mother was Margaret
							Bigg-Wither (1768&#8211;1842), a sister of Hill&#8217;s wife Catherine. Blackstone became Rector of Worting, Hampshire,
							1819&#8211;1831, Southey&#8217;s uncle Herbert Hill having held this living since 1815 until such time as Blackstone wished
							to take it up.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>