<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3694</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4965</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3694. Robert Southey to John May, 15 June 1821 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3694.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom
                  Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                     Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 254&#8211;258.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3694" type="letter">
        <head>3694. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1821-06-15">15 June 1821 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb /> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ JU 19/ 1821 F.N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; [partial] E/ 19 <lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 220 1821/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June/<lb /> rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 25<hi rend="sup">h</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>&#8217;<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom
                  Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                     <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 254&#8211;258.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1821-06-15">15 June. 1821</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> The public news from Brazil has made me look daily with much anxiety for tidings concerning you, &#8211; in what manner these
               revolutionary movements may have affected your interests. As they have neither been hasty, nor unforeseen, I should hope there had been
               time to extricate your property from the precarious hands in which it was placed, &#8211; but then I call to mind how much easier it is to
               run into danger than to withdraw from it, &amp; that tottering Governments <del>xxxxxx xxxxxx xxxx xxxxxxxxx</del> are too much alarmed
               &amp; perplexed to pay much regard to their engagements. On the other hand it occurs to me that the Government would endeavour to
               fulfil its engagements to British subjects, in preference to any others, because the Kings intention of returning to Portugal must have
               for one chief motive, the desire of feeling himself within reach of British protection.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">An army
                  revolt in Porto on 24 August 1820 had established a junta to run Portugal; it declared its intention of organising elections to a
                  Cortes, which were held in December 1820, and demanded John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826) return from Brazil, where the
                  court had fled in 1807&#8211;1808. The king reached Portugal on 3 July 1821. It was feared in Brazil that his return would signal an
                  attempt to put Brazil firmly under Portuguese control and this led directly to the separation of the two countries in
               1822.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think of writing a paper upon the state of Portugal &amp; Brazil for the Q.R.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was not written.</note> The separation of the two countries can hardly be
               prevented now, indeed the wisest conduct could only have delayed it, &amp; brought it about quietly &amp; amicably, by a division of
               the kingdoms, fixing one son at Lisbon, &amp; the other branch at the Rio.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Despite Southey&#8217;s
                  fears, Brazil did not become a republic or disintegrate, but remained a monarchy under John VI&#8217;s eldest son, Pedro I (1798&#8211;1834;
                  Emperor of Brazil 1822&#8211;1831). The &#8216;other branch&#8217; is probably a reference to Pedro&#8217;s younger brother, Miguel I (1802&#8211;1866; King of
                  Portugal 1828&#8211;1834), who did indeed gain the throne of Portugal, but only by briefly usurping it from Pedro&#8217;s daughter, Mary II
                  (1819&#8211;1853; Queen of Portugal 1826&#8211;1828, 1834&#8211;1853).</note> But the tendency of all commercial colonies is towards republicanism, &#8211;
               the foundations upon which monarchy rests are <del>not to</del> wanting. It is to be expected that the Brazilians will form a
               Constitution in imitation of the American States, &#8211; without any regard to the difference of their habits, character, &amp; former
               institutions. Disputes &amp; divisions between the great Captaincies will be the next step, &amp; while the great <del>cxx</del> cities
               undergo as many revolutions as Buenos Ayres,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish Viceroyalty of the Rio de la Plata,
                  with its capital at Buenos Aires, had been effectively independent since 1810, but was torn by conflict between centralists and
                  federalists.</note> the interior will be at the mercy of troops of Banditti, as bad as the worst of the old Paulistas.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Portuguese settlers in the Sao Paulo region, who carried out expeditions into the Brazilian interior in
                  the seventeenth century, in search of slaves and gold. </note> I can see but one motive which may perhaps alarm the revolutionary
               party, &amp; possibly keep them within some bounds: a fear of the negros, who in case of civil war may renew in most of the great
               cities the tragedy of S Domingo.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The French colony of Saint-Domingue. Negro slaves had risen in
                  revolt in 1791, eventually establishing the independent state of Haiti in 1804.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The prospect in Portugal is not so bad. The revolution there may be prevented from going the same lengths as in
                  Spain,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A revolution in Spain in 1820 had restored the liberal Constitution of 1812.</note> by
               the situation of Lisbon, where England would not suffer the King to be put to death &amp; whither an Austrian force might be
               transported from Naples, if the throne were in danger.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Austrian troops had crushed the liberal
                  revolution in Naples in March 1821.</note> The Portugueze reformers appear to mistake the nature of the political disease in that
               country, which was less in the form of their government than in its corruptions &#8211; &amp; the abuse of the laws. Had the laws been
               regularly administered they would not have had occasion to try their hands at making a constitution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am bestowing great pains upon the first vol. of Brazil, the reprinting of which will soon be finished.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1822).</note> A
               great many curious facts &amp; details I have got at by means of books &amp; papers which have come to my hands since its first
               publication, &#8211; particularly from a History of the West India Company in Dutch by Joannes de Laet.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Historie ofte Iaerlijk Verhael van de Verrichtinghen der Geoctroyeerde
                     West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644). Southey had bought a copy in Brussels in 1817; it was no. 1671 in the sale catalogue of
                  his library. </note> The additions which I have made amount to a tenth of the volume as far as the printing has proceeded. &#8211; Thirty
               sheets of the Peninsular War are printed, &#8211; this is my main business at present.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; I must work the closer at it, having suspended it lately
               to write a view of Oliver Cromwells life for the Q.R.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Life of Cromwell&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 25 (July 1821), 279&#8211;347, an assessment of the life of Oliver Cromwell (1599&#8211;1658; Lord Protector 1653&#8211;1658;
                     <title>DNB</title>).</note> This I have just finished, &amp; count upon its produce for my Midsummer bills. It is a fine subject,
               but the limits of a review will not allow room for doing it justice. One of these days I shall enlarge it for insertion in the
               projected series of biography.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not fulfil his plan of writing a full-scale
                  biography of Cromwell for a series that Murray was planning.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Richmond must be at this time in full beauty. So indeed is <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &#8211;
               summer is come at last. &amp; the delight of bathing draws me out of doors when nothing else would. In this library of mine, I very
               often think of yours, as the only room which may fairly vie<del>x</del> with it. If we could but bring the two within a reasonable
               distance of each other, it would add very much to my enjoyments.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> writes in good spirits, so that I hope he has
               recovered from the effects of his long &amp; miserable confinement at Bristol. I hear a very good account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">his eldest son</ref>, from Knox, the Usher of his boarding house,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John William Knox (1784&#8211;1862), an usher at Westminster School 1806&#8211;1821, where Edward Hill was a pupil.</note> who in
               kindness for me, takes more interest in, &amp; more pains with him, than money could purchase. The boy has good talents, is not wanting
               in diligence, &amp; has the best possible disposition. It is a great source of satisfaction to me that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> children promise so well. If it please God that he should live to the age of
               his elder brother,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-Colonel Edward Hill (d. 1824), Herbert Hill&#8217;s older half-brother,
                  with whom he had fallen out in early life.</note> he may by that time see the three eldest<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill was born in 1809, Herbert Hill Jnr, in 1810 and Errol Hill in 1812.</note> so forward in the way of life, that they
               will only have to proceed regularly in the course before them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You could not have fixed your son<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s son, John (1802&#8211;1879). He entered
                  Exeter College, Oxford, on 2 February 1822.</note> at a better college than Exeter: &#8211; perhaps it has one advantage over Oriel, that
               it does not hold itself quite so high. My old friend &amp; fellow collegian <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> has lately placed a son<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prideaux Lightfoot.</note> there, by <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestones</ref> advice, who could not find room for <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">him</ref> at Oriel,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Oriel College, Oxford, where
                  Copleston was a Fellow.</note> that is <hi rend="ital">more suo</hi>,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In his own
                  manner&#8217;.</note> he preferred some body of more consequence to the son of an old acquaintance in humble life. &#8211; Your next care
               respecting John will be the choice of a profession for him.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">John May became a clergyman &#8211; as
                  did Charles Cuthbert Southey.</note> This is a very anxious subject, &#8211; I shall be an old man before it comes upon me, if my poor
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> should live to grow up, &amp; if I should live to see, &#8211;
               two contingencies each of which has the chances very much against it. At present thank God he thrives, &amp; is as happy as the day is
               long. The others are doing well. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your god daughter</ref> took the field to day with
               a sketch-book in proper form. Poor dear <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> was always urging her to this. &#8211; Have
               you got your portrait?<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">One of Nash&#8217;s portraits of Edith May Southey; see Southey to John May, 8
                  April 1821, Letter 3667.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is the beginning of a letter-biographical in my desk, the date whereof makes me ashamed.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The latest of Southey&#8217;s autobiographical letters; see Southey to John May, 7 April&#8211;1 September 1821, Letter
                  3665.</note> &#8211; Remember me most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp;
               your daughters<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805&#8211;1885) and
                  Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> &#8211; &amp; to John also if he be at home. The two Ediths<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
                     Southey</ref>.</note> desire me to present their remembrances. <del>xxxx xx</del> Pray let me hear from you soon &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> yrs most affectionately</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>