<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3444</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4715</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3444. Robert Southey to John Kenyon, 21 February 1820
                  </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3444" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3444.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.235. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                     from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.183&#8211;185.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3444" type="letter">
        <head>3444. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">John Kenyon</ref>,<date when="1820-02-21"> 21 February 1820
                  </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Kenyn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 76 Oxford Street/
                  London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 24 FE 24/ 1820<lb /> Seal: black wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb />
                  MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.235. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                     from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.183&#8211;185.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-02-21">21 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1820</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0">My dear
               Kenyon</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Immediately on the receipt of your letter the order for the char was given, &amp; accepted; so that I thought myself
               sure of executing the commission. But I now learn that the fish would not be caught, &amp; that it was not thought desirable to catch
               them; the fish, the fishermen, &amp; the fish-potters being <del>xxx</del> unanimously of opinion that this is not the season. The
               proper months are October &amp; November.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The fishing season for charr in the Lake District is
                  now July&#8211;October.</note> Give me any directions for that time, &amp; they shall be punctually observed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a world of events since the date of your letter, tho it is scarcely a month old! <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">A new King</ref>, &#8211; an ugly question about the new Queen, &#8211; the preparations for a new
               Parliament, which bring on a relapse of the Election fever, before this part of England has recovered from the ill blood which the last
               left behind it, &amp; this assassination in France!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain
                  1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) had died on 29 January 1820, leading to the succession of his eldest son, George IV, who was
                  desperate to divorce his estranged wife, Queen Caroline (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>). The death of a monarch automatically
                  triggered a general election, which occurred between 6 March and 14 April 1820. The previous general election in 1818 had produced a
                  bitter contest in Westmorland, where Henry Brougham had attempted to break the Lowther family&#8217;s hold on both seats. Finally, Charles
                  Ferdinand d&#8217;Artoise, Duc de Berri (1778&#8211;1820), a nephew of Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824), had been mortally
                  wounded at the Paris Opera on 13 February 1820 by Louis Pierre Louvel (1783&#8211;1820), a Bonapartist.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be compelled, sooner or later, to agree with me concerning the Press, &amp; you cannot be more unwilling to
               come to that opinion than I have been. There will be no security for government or society, till the constituted authorities all over
               Europe have the controul of the Press. The question is whether this shall be conceded to an equitable Government, which consults the
               public good, &amp; regards public opinion, &#8211; as the means of preventing revolution, &#8211; or whether it will be taken by the military
               Autocrat <del>to xxxx xxxxx xxxx they who escape from</del> &lt;who will put an end to&gt; the series of massacres proscriptions &amp; civil
               wars which this miserable country must inevitably undergo, unless the Press be curbed. We have no statesman courageous enough to
               venture upon the remedy, tho I cannot believe any of our statesmen can be so blind as not to understand the danger. What then is to
                  <del>preserve</del> &lt;save&gt; us? Perhaps a premature rebellion, before the army is corrupted: this is not so likely as it was three
               months ago, when a day for the attempt was fixed, &amp; when any government but ours would have caught the ring leaders in a trap.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Radicals in London certainly discussed revolution at this time, and the opening of parliament by
                  the Prince Regent on 23 November 1819 was mentioned as an opportune moment.</note> &#8211; Perhaps some frightful tragedy like this of the
               Duc de Berri, &#8211; &amp; I will own to you that such a thing would surprize me less in this country, than it has done in France. It has
               already been twice attempted, &#8211; once on the late King, &#8211; once on <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the
               Regent</ref>; &amp; on both times because the murderer missed his aim the newspapers made a jest of it!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">James Hadfield (c. 1771&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>) had attempted to shoot George III at the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane
                  on 15 May 1800, but missed; he was acquitted of High Treason by reason of insanity. When the Prince Regent was travelling to the
                  Palace of Westminster to give the speech opening parliament on 28 January 1817, his carriage had been pelted with rotten fruit and
                  stones and a window broken. Conservatives claimed the window had been broken by a shot in an attempt to assassinate the Prince
                  Regent. </note> Infatuated as we are I believe that the shot which should take effect would be fatal to our accursed newspaper
               press. &#8211; I can imagine another means. It is among my uncomfortable speculations that a country which has been so long without any
               visitation of pestilence as England has been, has some right to expect it: so long a time never having elapsed without one before &#8211; ,
               &amp; it being certain that we are not preserved from it by any improvement in the healing art, nor by any precautions, nor by any
               change in our climate.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">There had been no major plague epidemic in Britain since that of
                  1665&#8211;1666.</note> It is a frightful thought, &#8211; but it has occurred to me who believe in the moral government of the world, (&amp; it
               has made an impression upon me,) that Providence may send pestilence among us at once to punish us, &amp; to preserve us from the only
               evil that would be greater, &#8211; <del>xx xx</del> Do you know that John Hunter was of opinion that our manufactories would engender for us
               some new plague?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hunter (1728&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>), scientist and surgeon. Southey had
                  made this statement in his &#8216;Inquiry into the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (December 1812), 338. </note> &#8211;
               Specific diseases many of them produce. But as yet the only plague which they have generated is a moral &amp; political one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My departure for the South is delayed for about a month, &#8211; chiefly because of the Kings death. I must produce some <hi rend="ital">ex officio</hi> verses.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">These verses became <title>A Vision of Judgement</title>
                  (1821). It is not clear how they were influenced by Kenyon.</note> When you see them you will perceive that you have <del>xxx</del>
               influenced them, in a very material point.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All here desire their kindest remembrances</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>