<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3421</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4692</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3421. Robert Southey to [Henry Crabb
						Robinson], 18 January 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3421" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3421.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
						University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 2p. .  Previously  published: Thomas Sadler (ed.), Diary, Reminiscences,
							and Correspondence of Henry Crabb Robinson, 3rd edn, 2 vols (London, 1872), I, pp. 341&#8211;342 [dated
						&#8216;January 20&#8217;]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3421" type="letter">
        <head>3421. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Henry Crabb
						Robinson</ref>],<date when="1820-01-18"> 18 January 1820</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: H. C. Robinson Esq: 3 Kings Bench Walk Temple<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
						University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 2p.<lb /> Previously published: Thomas Sadler (ed.), <title>Diary, Reminiscences,
							and Correspondence of Henry Crabb Robinson</title>, 3rd edn, 2 vols (London, 1872), I, pp. 341&#8211;342 [dated
						&#8216;January 20&#8217;]. </p>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0">My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall not easily get your letter out of my thoughts.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robinson&#8217;s letter contained the news that Elton Hamond had killed himself on 1 January 1820.</note> Some years
					ago I dined with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HamondElton">Elton Hammond</ref> at <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch&#8217;s</ref> &amp; perfectly remember his quiet, melancholy, meditative
					manner. The two letters which he addressed to me respecting his papers were very ably written, &amp; excited in me
					a strong interest.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In early 1819 Hamond had asked Southey to act as his
						literary executor. For the latter&#8217;s replies, see Southey to Elton Hamond, 5 February 1819, Letter 3240; and
						Southey to Elton Hamond, 2 March 1819, Letter 3256.</note> Of course I had no suspicion who the writer could be;
					but if I had endeavoured to trace him (which probably would have been done had I been in town) <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> is the person whom I should have thought most likely to have helped
					me in the enquiry. The school which you indicate is an unhappy one.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Religious scepticism.</note> I remember seeing a purblind man at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref> two &amp; twenty years ago,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. May 1798, when Southey had
						visited the Norfolk coastal town of Great Yarmouth.</note> who seemd to carry with him a contagion of such
					opinions wherever he went. Perhaps you may have known him &#8211; his name I think was Harley.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Cornelius Girling Harley (c. 1768&#8211;1843). Henry Crabb Robinson had visited Great Yarmouth in 1797;
						the &#8216;main inducement&#8217; for the visit &#8216;was to read to Harley, a blind man I became acquainted with through Miss
						Maling. An interesting man in humble circumstances&#8217;, <title>Diary, Reminiscences, and Correspondence of Henry
							Crabb Robinson</title>, ed. Thomas Sadler, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, p. 42. Sarah Jane Maling (c. 1780&#8211;1839),
						later Wimbridge, was an old friend of Robinson&#8217;s. Harley had also been an early friend of Robert Gooch, who grew
						up in Great Yarmouth &#8211; Gooch left Harley &#163;100 in his will &#8211; and he was well known to William Taylor. The best
						description of Harley is in Charles John Palmer, <title>The Perlustration of Great Yarmouth, with Gorleston and
							Southtown</title>, 3 vols (Great Yarmouth, 1872), I, pp. 225&#8211;227.</note> The morbific matter was continually
					oozing out of him; &amp; where it passes off in this way, or can be exploded in paradoxes &amp; freaks of intellect
					as by <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, the destructive effect upon the heart
					is lessened or postponed. But when it meets with strong feeling, &amp; an introspective, introactive mind, the Aqua
						Tofana<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A strong poison reputedly widely used in Naples and Rome in the late
						seventeenth century.</note> is not more deadly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Respecting the papers I can only say at present that I will do nothing with them that can be
					either injurious to the dead or the living. When I receive any application upon the subject I shall desire them to
					be deposited at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref>, to wait my arrival in
					town, where I expect to be early in March, &amp; to continue about two months, some ten days excepted. Before that
					time I could not command leisure for inspecting them to any purpose, &#8211; &amp; it is better that they should be in
					London, where I can consult with you. You will see by his letters to me (which I will take with me to town) what
					his wishes were. Consistent with those wishes, with his honour, &amp; with the feelings of his friends I hope it
					may be possible to record this melancholy case for wholesome instruction. He says to me &#8216;You may perhaps find an
					interest in making a fair statement of opinions which you condemn, when quite at liberty, as you would be in this
					case, to controvert them in the same page. I desire no gilt frame for my picture, &amp; if by the side of it you
					like to draw another, &amp; call mine a Satyr,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, creatures
						who were companions of the god Dionysus and addicted to physical pleasure.</note> &amp; your own Hyperion,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, one of the Titans, and father of the deities of the sun, the
						moon and the dawn. He could thus be thought of as a celestial opposite to an earth-bound satyr, as in
							<title>Hamlet</title>, Act 1, scene 2, line 140.</note> you are welcome. A <hi rend="ital">true</hi> light is all
					that I <hi rend="ital">require</hi>; a <hi rend="ital">strong</hi> light all that I <hi rend="ital">wish</hi>.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Having no suspicion of his intentions, I supposed him to be in the last stage of some incurable
					disease, &amp; addressed him as one who was upon the brink of the grave. If one [MS obscured]ts pencil sentences
					which you have transcribed, were written since February last, it would show that my last letter had made some
					impression upon him, &#8211; for I had assured him of my belief in Ghosts, &amp; rested upon it as one proof of a future
					state. &#8211; There was not the slightest indication of insanity in his communications to me, &#8211; &amp; there was an
					expression of humility, under which I should never have suspected that so very different a feeling was concealed. &#8211;
					God help us, frail creatures that we are!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As my second letter was not noticed by him, I had supposed that it was received with displeasure
					&amp; perhaps with contempt. It rather surprizes me therefore that he should have retaining the intention of
					committing his papers to my disposal, little desirous as I was of the charge. Nevertheless I will execute it
					faithfully, &#8211; &amp; the best proof <del>proof</del> that I can give of a proper feeling upon the subject is, to do
					nothing without consulting you.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">After this consultation Southey decided not
						to edit Hamond&#8217;s writings.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs with much
						esteem</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-01-18">18 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1820.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>