<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3360</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4631</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3360. Robert Southey to William Peachy, 10 October 1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3360.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published:
						Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
						199&#8211;202. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3360" type="letter">
        <head>3360. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1819-10-10">10 October 1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletion and
						readdress in another hand] To/ Major-General Peachy/ <del>Yarmouth</del>/ <del>Norfolk</del>./ &lt;Mrs Halls/ North
						Gate/ Bury&gt;<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published:
						Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
						199&#8211;202. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            <date when="1819-10-10"> Oct. 1819</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My
						dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter found me just after my return from a long northern expedition, in company with my old
					friends <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Telford the Engineer</ref>. I joined them at Edinburgh,
					&amp; we performed a journey of six weeks under the pleasantest circumstances of every kind, especially in the
					important point of weather.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s tour of Scotland lasted from 17 August
						until 1 October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed.
						Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> We went by Linlithgow &amp; Stirling to Loch Kattern, then by Loch Earn
					head, Killin, &amp; Kenmere to Dunkeld, &amp; so to Perth &amp; Dundee. From Dundee up the coast to Aberdeen,
					across <del>the B</del> to Banff, &amp; along the coast to Elgin. Then while the Ladies went on to wait for us at
					Nairn we struck inland up the Strathspey road to Grantown, crossing Craig Elachie Bridge upon the way, &#8211; a
					cast-iron bridge, equally remarkable for the beauty of its structure, &amp; of its situation. The next day we
					returned to the coast at Forres. From Nairn we looked at Fort George, &amp; went on to Inverness, the fine scenery
					on the Varrar &amp; the Strathglas road which is called the Dream, &#8211; Dingwall, Tain, Bonar-Bridge &amp; Fleet Mound
					which was our farthest point toward the north. This mound which is in sight of <del>Dunb</del> Dunrobin Castle is
					one of the greatest works that have been executed <del>for the improv</del> by the Commissioners.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Fleet Mound was a massive causeway, commissioned in 1803, designed by Telford, and
						built between 1814&#8211;1816, to carry the road over Loch Fleet. It comprised an earthwork, and a bridge with
						self-regulating sluice gates that allowed the waters from the river to flow out, but prevented seawater from
						coming in.</note> It is 990 yards in length, extending across an estuary. Lord Gower<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Earl Gower was a subsidiary title, held by the heir to the Marquessate of Stafford, but Southey is
						probably referring to the Marquess himself, George Granville Leveson-Gower (1758&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), 2nd
						Marquess of Stafford and (from 1833) 1st Duke of Sutherland. The latter&#8217;s marriage to Elizabeth Sutherland
						(1765&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), Countess of Sutherland in her own right, gave Stafford control of enormous
						Scottish landholdings. </note> gains by it about 400 acres from the sea; but the great advantage is that you go
					over a fine road instead of having to cross a ferry. We returned by the Fearn road to Dingwall, over the fells
					instead of along the coast; sent the Ladies<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref>; her two youngest children, William Charles Rickman
						(1812&#8211;1886) and Frances Rickman (dates unknown, she married Richard Brindley Hone (1805&#8211;1881), Vicar of Halesowen
						1836&#8211;1881, in 1836); and their companion, Emma Pigott. It is difficult to be sure of Miss Pigott&#8217;s identity, but
						she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown), younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d. 1822) of
						Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. Fitz-Hall was only five miles from Susannah Rickman&#8217;s home at Harting. Emma Pigott
						married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen Hill, Berkshire.</note> to Inverness, &amp; crossed the
					island to the western sea at Jean town, intending there to have crossed Loch Carron, &amp; return to Inverness by
					Glenelg &amp; Glenmoriston; but the new ferry boat upon which we had depended was not launched, <del>so we</del>
					&amp; as there was no means of getting the carriage across we retraced our steps. We remained three days at
					Inverness, &#8211; one morning was given to the Vitrified Fort, &amp; another was past in going up the Caledonian Canal
					to Loch Ness. Then we proceeded to Fort Augustus, &amp; remained two days there, inspecting the works of the canal
					which are in progress between that place &amp; the head of Loch Lochy. We were three days at Fort William, &#8211; one
					day was employed in inspecting the canal from its western end to the end of Loch Lochy, &#8211; another in visiting the
					Parallel Roads in Glen roy, &#8211; &lt;one of&gt; the greatest curiosities in Scotland, &#8211; or perhaps in any other country.
					Balachulish ferry was our next stage, thence by Glencoe &amp; Tyandrum to Inverary, &amp; so by Glencroe, &amp;
					Loch Lomond to Glasgow, Lanark &amp; Carlisle.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On the part of my two companions this was a journey of business, to inspect the piers, roads
					&amp; bridges constructed by the Commissioners, &amp; the Caledonian Canal.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman was Secretary to the Commission for Highland Roads and Bridges, and to the Commission responsible for
						constructing the Caledonian Canal 1803&#8211;1822; Telford surveyed and designed these works.</note> The latter work I
					had the satisfaction of seeing in all stages of its progress, &#8211; for it is compleated at the two ends, &amp; in the
					intermediate portion the excavations &amp; other operations are going on. It is truly a stupendous undertaking,
					&amp; perhaps its magnitude can be fully felt by those only who like myself have seen the extent of masonry which
					will be concealed under water, when the whole is finished. The locks are made large enough for a 32 gun frigate,
					&amp; at the western end there are eight of these in immediate succession. The whole length is 500 yards, the whole
					ascent 64 feet. When we saw it the water was falling from one lock to another, in so many smooth cascades, shining
					&amp; sparkling like polished steel, &#8211; more resembling a scene in a pantomime than any thing real. The workmen have
					given this place the name of Neptunes stair case.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Neptune&#8217;s Staircase at
						Banavie, near Fort William, completed in 1811. This is a staircase lock (the longest in the United Kingdom) on the
						Caledonian Canal, comprising eight locks, which raise (or lower) boats 64 feet in a distance of 180 feet. Southey
						visited on 19 September 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford
						(London, 1929), pp. 202&#8211;207.</note> There is a certain character of sublimity about it, which is felt the more
					because you have at the same time the greatest natural object in Great Britain in sight &#8211; Ben Nevis. But the most
					astonishing sight is the off-let for lowering the canal, if the waters should at any time flow into it faster than
					they carried off by the ordinary outlet. Three sluices each 4 feet by 3 open into a strong arch about 25 feet high,
					which is built upon a rock, &#8211; &amp; needs indeed such a foundation. For when these sluices are opened the incumbent
					weight forces out the water with such scarcely conceivable velocity that the whole part of the canal between the
					stair-case &amp; the regulating lock, six miles in length may be lowered one foot in <del>an</del> one hour. They
					were opened for us, &amp; I never saw any thing comparable to the prodigious force with which the water filled the
					whole arch, &amp; formed in a few minutes a torrent which would have swept away the strongest swimmer into the
					river Lochy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must not begin to describe the Highland Roads, &#8211; this paper has not [MS torn] left for entering
					upon a description of them. You know perhaps that a mail coach goes to Thursoe, &#8211; &amp; that the most beautiful
					roads in the world are those in the Highlands of Scotland.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On my return I found that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> had
					been at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. By the time you receive this he will probably
					have returned to Fingest Grove.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Netherhall, Senhouse&#8217;s residence in
						Cumberland, was being extensively renovated, so he had temporarily rented Fingest House, near High Wycombe,
						Buckinghamshire. </note> A large flight of Cantabs have past the season here, &#8211; among them two sons of Sir John
						Kennaway,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836). The two sons who
						visited Southey were: John Kennaway (1797&#8211;1873) of Trinity College, Cambridge (B.A. 1821), who later succeeded to
						his father&#8217;s baronetcy; and <ref type="m" target="people.html#KennawayCharlesE">Charles Edward Kennaway</ref>, a
						student at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge (B.A. 1822).</note> who brought introductions to me, &#8211; both very pleasant
					men. &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Denton<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758&#8211;1820), Vicar of
						Crosthwaite, Keswick 1786&#8211;1820, whom Southey often called the &#8216;Reverend Porpoise&#8217;.</note> has had a slight
					paralytic stroke; &#8211; about eight weeks ago. He preached for the first time since his recovery to day, &#8211; but the
						Clerk<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Anthony Gibson (dates unknown), the long-serving Parish Clerk at
						Crosthwaite Church.</note> read the lessons for him, &#8211; &amp; he faltered sometimes in a manner which it was
					painful to witness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your friend the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bishop of London</ref> favoured
					me with a call in the month of August, &#8211; his Lady<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Frances Howley, n&#233;e
						Belli (1783&#8211;1860).</note> was with him. He regretted that you were not here. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morritt of
						Rokeby,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bacon Sawrey Morritt (1771&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>),
						traveller, classical scholar and member of the Society of Dilettanti. He had gained the nickname &#8216;Troy&#8217; for his
						endeavours to prove that the city had been a real place, not an invention of Homer. He owned the Rokeby estate,
						where he entertained a large circle, including Humphry Davy, Walter Scott and Southey.</note> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gurney the Counsel<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gurney (1768&#8211;1845;
							<title>DNB</title>), barrister and later Baron of the Exchequer 1832&#8211;1845. In 1793&#8211;1794 he had served as defence
						counsel in a number of trials of radicals for sedition and treason. By this time his views were distinctly
						conservative and in 1820 he conducted the successful prosecution of two of the Cato Street conspirators. </note>
					had been here during my absence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your kind invitation to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref>.
					You will probably have moved your quarters before I shall be able to leave home. For I shall now in all likelihood
					delay my movements till the best season; &amp; aim at being in London in February &amp; March. &#8211; I learn that there
					is a talk of calling Parliament together before Christmas, God knows it is high time that some efficient measures
					should be taken!<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Parliament reassembled on 23 November 1819, mainly to pass
						the &#8216;Six Acts&#8217; to suppress radical agitation.</note> &#8211; I know not whether I am more indignant at the inefficiency
					&amp; inconsistency of Ministers, &#8211; or at the villainy of the Opposition who for the sake of annoying
					Administration, are acting in favour of the veriest wretches that ever defied &amp; deserved the gallows. However
					things are becoming so bad that the Country is beginning to see its danger.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Ladies<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara
							Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> desire their kindest
					remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>, &#8211; present mine
					also, &amp; believe me my dear Sir</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>