<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3769</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce5040</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3769. Robert Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 21 December 1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3769" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3769.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 5p. .  Previously  published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir
                  John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, Studia Germanica Gandensia, 6 (1964), 119&#8211;120.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3769" type="letter">
        <head>3769. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1821-12-21">21 December 1821</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Taylor Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 2. Pump Court/ Middle Temple<lb /> Endorsement: 1821/ Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ R. Southey
                  Keswick<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 5p.<lb /> Previously published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir
                  John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 119&#8211;120.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1821-12-21">21 Dec. 1821.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0">My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">A neighbour of mine</ref> who has <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertJohnM">one son</ref> at Oriel, &amp; intends to place another<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Raisley Calvert (1803&#8211;1838), later a clergyman; he did not attend Oriel, but went instead to Queen&#8217;s College, Oxford.</note> there,
               has enquired of me what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnolds<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Arnold (1795&#8211;1842;
                     <title>DNB</title>), a close friend of John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s since their university days. Arnold had been elected to a
                  Fellowship at Oriel College in 1815 and had augmented his income by private tuition of undergraduates. A crisis of faith decided him
                  against taking holy orders, and he took on a private school, in partnership with his brother-in-law, at Laleham, Middlesex.</note>
               terms would be for giving this second youth a years preparation; &#8211; no readier way of obtaining the information occurs to me than by
               applying to you for it. &#8211; The youth in question has been always under private <del>xxxxxxx</del> tutorage, &#8211; is of slow capacity, but
               of the best disposition in the world. The elder brothers tutor<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> has advised
               this measure, to which the father is much inclined having seen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnold when he was in this country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since the commencement of the revolution in Portugal, I have dreaded its consequences in Brazil for <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref> sake.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in Porto in August 1820 led
                  to the election of a Cortes in December 1820 and demands that the monarchy return from Brazil, where it had fled in 1807&#8211;1808
                  following the French invasion. John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826) arrived back in Lisbon on 3 July 1821 and eventually
                  agreed to a new liberal Constitution in October 1822. John VI appointed his son, Pedro (1798&#8211;1834; Emperor of Brazil 1822&#8211;1831), as
                  Regent in Brazil and Pedro summoned an elected advisory council to represent the different Brazilian provinces. These events
                  eventually led to the separation of Portugal and Brazil on 7 September 1822, but Brazil did not become a republic or
                  disintegrate.</note> The evil has fallen upon him, &amp; there is this comfort that when the worst has happened, then hope begins
               again upon a new score. I do not say to him how incorrigibly imprudent his brother appears to have been, &amp; how unpardonably
               regardless of his welfare &amp; happiness.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), May&#8217;s younger brother
                  and business partner in Brazil.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a melancholy consideration it is that the Spanish Americans would at this time, from the state of the mother
               country, have acquired all that they wanted, without a struggle, &#8211; &amp; that the unutterable crimes &amp; miseries of the last twelve
               years might have been spared!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The French invasion of Spain in 1808 had severed many of the
                  mother country&#8217;s links with its Latin American colonies and, from 1810 onwards, a series of conflicts had been waged to secure the
                  colonies&#8217; independence from Spain.</note> &#8211; They were, as the Brazilians are now, in a situation wherein they had nothing to do, but
               to let things take their course, the event, as far &lt;as&gt; they were concerned, not being doubtful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just reprinted the first volume of my Brazilian history, having I hope materially improved it, at great expence
               of labour.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised second edition of volume one of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810&#8211;1819) was published in 1822. The other two volumes of the <title>History</title> did not go into second editions.</note> The
               corrections which I had to make were very few, the additions very considerable, <del>fr</del> chiefly from documents which were either
               not published, or not accessible to me, when it was first composed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now nearly finished the first volume of the Peninsular War, &#8211; which I suppose the booksellers will publish
               without waiting for the other two; but this depends upon them, &#8211; it is to me a matter of indifference.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> The first volume comes down no farther
               than the battle of Coru&#241;a, the events of that year requiring more detail than those of any other two.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823) ended with the evacuation of British
                  troops from Corunna in January 1809.</note> There is a great deal which will be altogether new to the English reader.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am also about to send to the press the long promised Book of the Church, &#8211; which is a sketch of our Church
                  History.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Genevese beauty was much admired here.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">An unidentified acquaintance of
                  John Taylor Coleridge from Geneva, a city he had visited in 1814.</note> They came in an unlucky season, but made good use of the
               few lucid intervals that the weather afforded. We have had a succession of storms since August, &#8211; never (I think) three days together
               without one; &amp; with more rain than was ever remembered. &#8211; If I recollect rightly the Great Storm at the beginning of the last
                  century<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Great Storm&#8217; of 26 November 1703, caused significant damage and loss of life in
                  the south of England. It was attributed to, amongst other things, divine vengeance and was the subject of Daniel Defoe&#8217;s
                  (1660?&#8211;1731; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Storm, or, a Collection of the most Remarkable Casualties and Disasters which happened
                     in the late Dreadful Tempest, both by Sea and Land</title> (1704).</note> was preluded by such a succession of heavy gales.
               Whether I shall see you in the spring is doubtful. I am not willingly locomotive, &amp; therefore more disposed to feel that I cannot
               without inconvenience be so long absent from my desk. &#8211; You are going on well I hope. We are as well as could be wished &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">my little boy</ref> promising &amp; thriving to my hearts content. He never can be to me
               what <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">his brother</ref> would have been, &#8211; the course of years renders that
               impossible. &#8211; But I am thankful indeed for him, &amp; only hope that I may not be too full of hope, &#8211; &amp; build with too much
               confidence upon the sand.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.
               </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>