<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3556</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4827</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3556. Robert Southey to John May, 15 November 1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3556.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                  Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4pp. .  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey
                     to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 188&#8211;189.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3556" type="letter">
        <head>3556. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,<date when="1820-11-15"> 15 November 1820</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb /> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: E/ 18 NO 18/ 1820; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ NO.18/ 1820 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 215 1820/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> December<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                  Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4pp.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey
                     to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 188&#8211;189.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-11-15">15 Nov. 1820</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The bells are ringing. <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is illuminated in honour of our
               immaculate Queen,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Under extreme pressure from George IV, the Cabinet had reluctantly agreed to
                  introduce a Bill of Pains and Penalties into the House of Lords to deprive the King&#8217;s wife, Caroline of Brunswick (1768&#8211;1821;
                     <title>DNB</title>), of the title of Queen and to dissolve her marriage to the King. On the Third Reading of the Bill on 10
                  November 1820, the government majority was only nine votes and it seemed very unlikely the Bill could pass the House of Commons.
                  Lord Liverpool, the Prime Minister, therefore had announced the Bill would be withdrawn. Parts of Keswick were, to Southey&#8217;s
                  disgust, celebrating this news.</note> &amp; whether I may get thro this letter without having my windows saluted by a few stones,
               is by no means certain. Let that pass. Happy <del>will</del> &lt;would&gt; it be for us if nothing worse were to be expected from the
               Mobocracy which is now established in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A half finished letter of autobiography<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The third of the autobiographical
                  letters Southey was writing for May; see Southey to John May, 16 August&#8211;18 November 1820, Letter 3526.</note> in my desk, which day
               after day I have intended to finish &amp; as often have been prevented from finishing either by the necessity or the inclination for
               doing something else, &#8211; has been the real cause of my long silence, &#8211; a silence indeed longer than I had supposed it to be, till you
               have brought the date of my last epistle before my eyes. &#8211; Another cause has been that I expected to have had 100&#163; paid into your hands
               ere this, part of a sum which I am earning by composing a piece of private biography, or rather panegyric, &#8211; the history of which you
               shall have hereafter.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been paid for writing a &#8216;private biography&#8217; of David Pike
                  Watts (1754&#8211;1816), a fabulously rich wine merchant and philanthropist, who had been an important supporter of Andrew Bell&#8217;s
                  educational schemes and owned the Storrs Hall estate on Windermere. He was also the uncle of the painter John Constable (1776&#8211;1837;
                     <title>DNB</title>). The work had been commissioned by Watts&#8217;s daughter and heiress, Mary Watts-Russell (1792&#8211;1840), who had
                  married, in 1811, another heir to a business fortune, Jesse Watts-Russell (1786&#8211;1875), MP for Gatton 1820&#8211;1826. They lived at Ilam
                  Hall in Staffordshire and had eight children.</note> But a most unlucky &amp; vexatious mistake has been made respecting this
               payment (not on my part, &amp; without any blame attaching anywhere) which has disappointed me for a while, &amp; given me no little
                  chagrin.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had mistakenly entered the wrong sum on the bill of exchange he had arranged
                  to present in order to receive payment, and Pole &amp; Co., the bankers of Mary Watts-Russell, had refused to pay the bill; see
                  Southey to Andrew Bell, 14 November 1820, Letter 3555. </note> &#8211; You have given me a spur now, &amp; the third letter shall be sent
               off in the course of the week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The strong beer, the very thought of which puts my palate in tune for a glass, may be directed to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cookson, Kendal,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Cookson (1771&#8211;1833), Kendal wool merchant and friend of
                  Wordsworth.</note> &#8211; nothing more, &#8211; without my name. Being directed to him it will come safer &amp; at less cost.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not apprehend any immediate change in Brazil<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in Porto,
                  Portugal, on 24 August 1820 had established a junta to run the country; it declared its intention of organising elections to a
                  Cortes, which were held in December 1820, and demanded John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826) return from Brazil, where the
                  court had fled in 1807&#8211;1808. These events led to the separation of Brazil and Portugal in 1822.</note> which would be likely to
               affect you; but your brother<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Henry May (1785&#8211;1849), May&#8217;s younger brother and business
                  partner in Brazil.</note> will do well to extricate himself as soon as possible from all dependence upon that Government. Jupiter
               seems to have besotted the Governments of all other countries, &amp; the people of this.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">As in
                  the phrase &#8216;whom Jupiter wishes to destroy, he first makes mad&#8217;.</note> I am like you of a hopeful disposition, &amp; like you I
               have a firm belief that Providence will everywhere educe good out of evil. But I am not without my fears for what we may have to endure
               in the process, &amp; very much apprehend that if you &amp; I should reach the allotted age of man we shall outlive the liberties of
               England. They will either be lost (inevitably) as the consequence of a radical revolution, &#8211; or to prevent that evil, we must part with
               more of them than can safely be spared, &amp; so perish by a chronic instead of an acute disease.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">My good little friend</ref> is just returned to town, &amp; whenever you chuse to call
               upon him you may see his portfolio, &amp; chuse between two portraits<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The identity of the portraits is unclear, but they are probably those depicting Edith May in three different dresses, lilac, red and uncoloured, described in Southey to John May, 8 April 1821, Letter 3667. The location of the &#8216;lilac&#8217; portrait is unknown; the &#8216;redder&#8217; one is probably the pencil and watercolour sketch now in the collections of the Wordsworth Trust, Grasmere; and the &#8216;uncoloured&#8217; one is in Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.</note> of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughter</ref>, both very good, but concerning the comparative merits of
               which opinions are divided. The one has more of the character, the other more of the features, <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> will tell you which I like best. He will show you also a delightful picture of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, &amp; a drawing of such a mountain party as we will have
               whenever you &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> will pay us a visit at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &amp; accept such hospitality as we can offer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> is at this time with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson (M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wordsworths sister)</ref> at <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref>. When she returns she shall copy for you <ref type="m" target="people.html#LatrobeChristianI">Latrobes</ref> two letters. I did not reply to the second, because I had nothing more to say,
               &amp; neither leisure nor inclination for controversy, even in so friendly spirit as this.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Latrobe had written to Southey earlier in 1820 complaining about the portrayal of the Moravians in the <title>Life of Wesley; and
                     the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). For Southey&#8217;s reply, noting that no offence had been intended, see Southey to
                  Christian Ignatius Latrobe, 3 June 1820, Letter 3491. Latrobe had clearly not been pacified, and wrote again.</note> I made no
               transcript of my own letter, for want of time. &#8211; You will not be sorry to hear that I have begun a Life of George Fox<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write his proposed life of George Fox (1624&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>), founder of the
                  Religious Society of Friends (Quakers).</note> upon the same plan as that of Wesley. The intention has got wind sooner than I meant,
               &amp; it has put all Quakerdom in commotion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are all in tolerable health. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My good Aunt</ref> I trust will winter
               with us. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>, &amp; me also to the rest of
               your family &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear friend</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>