<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3663</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4934</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3663. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn,
						4 April 1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3663.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
						(ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
						244&#8211;246.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3663" type="letter">
        <head>3663. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>,
						<date when="1821-04-04">4 April 1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W
						Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Whitehall/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 7
						AP 7/ 1821<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter
						(ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
						244&#8211;246.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I did not omit Henry 5 from any remains of prejudice, but because I wished not to lengthen a
					muster roll which was likely to be too long, &amp; is indeed disproportionate to the other parts of the poem.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry V (1387&#8211;1422; King of England 1413&#8211;1422; <title>DNB</title>) did not
						appear in Canto 8, &#8216;The Sovereigns&#8217;, of <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821). Southey had a youthful
						antipathy to the monarch, expressed in <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796) and &#8216;King Henry and the Hermit of Dreux&#8217;,
							<title>Morning Post</title>, 24 September 1798.</note> Yet certainly I cannot agree with you in thinking that
					Coeur de Lion<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard I (1157&#8211;1199; King of England 1189&#8211;1199;
							<title>DNB</title>), named as one of &#8216;The Sovereigns&#8217;, <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), Canto 8,
						lines 17&#8211;28.</note> might be displaced to make room for him, for Richard must ever be one of the heroes of
					romance. Madam Stael<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Louise Germaine de Sta&#235;l-Holstein (1766&#8211;1817),
						Swiss writer; Southey had met her a number of times in London in September&#8211;October 1813.</note> told me she meant
					to make him the hero of a prose epic. His taste for Saracens heads<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">In the
						fourteenth-century romance, <title>Richard Coer de Lyon</title>, the king is represented as enjoying eating his
						Saracen enemies during the Third Crusade (1189&#8211;1192).</note> was something like that for <hi rend="ital">Irish
						bacon</hi> which prevailed in Wales about the same time,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An allusion to the
						twelfth-century <title>Vita Griffini Filii Conani</title>&#8212;the Life of Gruffudd ap Cynan (c. 1055&#8211;1137; Prince of
						Gwynedd 1081&#8211;1137), in which Southey had interpreted a phrase to suggest that the corpse of the leader of an
						invading force from Ireland was literally used as bacon. The unfortunate subject of this story was Trahaern ap
						Caradog (d. 1081; Prince of Gwynedd 1073&#8211;1081), who was killed fighting Gruffudd ap Cynan at the Battle of Mynydd
						Carn in 1081.</note> &amp; belonged rather to the age than to the individual. But Richards you know was only a
					display to frighten the Saracens, whereas the bacon was no doubt for use. Barbarous customs kept their ground
					longer in this island than historians seem to have observed. Did I tell you that in Galloway something like the
					polyandrian system of the ancient Britons appears to have prevailed as late as the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
					century? So at least I interpret a passage in the Acta Sanctorum.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
						mentioned this idea in a note to his <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of
							Society</title> (London, 1829), II, p. 290. Southey&#8217;s source was the <title>Vita</title> of St Aelred (1110&#8211;1167;
							<title>DNB</title>), misattributed to John Capgrave (1393&#8211;1464; <title>DNB</title>), and inserted in <title>Acta
							Sanctorum</title>, 68 vols (Antwerp and Brussels, 1643&#8211;1940): January, vol. I, p. 750. Julius Caesar (100 BC&#8211;44
						BC), <title>Commentarii de Bello Gallico</title>, Book 5, lines 8&#8211;12, claimed the British tribes he encountered in
						his invasion of 54 BC practised polyandry. Modern commentators tend to interpret this passage as propaganda to
						discredit the British as barbarians.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You speak of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> in one of your letters.
					When you saw him at Bristol I was in habits of the greatest intimacy with him; &#8211; <del>but</del> that intimacy has
					fallen off, less from remoteness of place &amp; dissimilarity of pursuits, than because of the effect which high
					life &amp; prosperity have produced upon him; an <del>xxx</del> effect &lt;which&gt; has been such, that for many
					years I have felt more pain in his company from remembering what he was than any pleasure to be derived from his
					conversation could compensate. A great man most unquestionably he is in one line, but in that line he would be even
					greater than he is if the world had less hold upon him. It has made him vain, selfish &amp; sensual, &#8211; &amp; weaned
					him from all his old friends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Old friends are the best of all possessions, &amp; there is nothing in this world which can
					supply their loss.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">The King</ref> sends me word<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to William Knighton, 30 March 1821, Letter 3661.</note> that he has read
					the Vision of Judgement twice, is much gratified with the Ded. &amp; pleased with the poem. The Ded. was a good one
					as it originally stood, for I had touched upon the state of the press <del>in it</del> in a way which pleased
					myself both as to the matter &amp; the form.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Vision of
							Judgement</title> (London, 1821), &#8216;Dedication&#8217;, pp. [v]&#8211;viii. The &#8216;Dedication&#8217; was undoubtedly controversial, not
						only praising Britain&#8217;s victory in the war against France, but stating: &#8216;The same perfect integrity has been
						manifested in the whole administration of public affairs&#8217; (vi), not a view the Whig opposition endorsed. However,
						the earlier draft of the &#8216;Dedication&#8217;, in Huntington Library, San Marino, HM 2733, shows Southey had intended to
						go much further and urge that &#8216;adequate remedy should be applied to that intolerable licentiousness of the press &#8230;
						either by the vigorous application of existing laws or by the enactment of such new ones as the suspension of the
						abuse may render necessary&#8217;.</note> This was not struck out from any fear of the obloquy which it would provoke,
					but because I thought it might seem out of its place, &amp; as it were, intruded where I had no business to
					introduce it. &#8211; Concerning the metre I have the full &amp; entire concurrence of the Poets whom <del>have</del> I
					know, &amp; of the female readers. Nor indeed have I heard as yet of any repugnance to it, except from you, whom as
					you know I expected to <hi rend="ital">ride upon an insurmountable obstacle</hi>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A joke played on Wynn at Westminster School. His theme &#8216;Pride is an insurmountable obstacle&#8217; was
						corrected by a friend (possibly Southey) to &#8216;I ride an insurmountable obstacle&#8217;. Wynn then proceeded innocently to
						read out the amended version to the class, causing him much embarrassment.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now taking up the Tale of Paraguay<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of
							Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> with the determination of going thro with it, &#8211; for the most cogent of all
					reasons. &#8211; And I shall have to send you ere long that history of Lope de Aguirre which was inserted in the E Ann.
					Register, reprinted in a little volume making the 34<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of my operas in that size<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821),
						originally intended to be part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and first published in
							<title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i&#8211;l. It was published in duodecimo, making it, by
						Southey&#8217;s calculation, the thirty-fourth edition of any of his works in this format.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is the second vol. of the Scriptores Rerum Hibern: published? I [MS missing]ver it is. I will, if
					I possibly can, review it, in the hope of bringing it into notice or at least of giving to the Editor that
					commendation to which he is so fully entitled.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles O&#8217;Conor (1764&#8211;1828;
							<title>DNB</title>), <title>Rerum Hibernicarum Scriptores Veteres</title>, 4 vols (1814&#8211;1826), no. 2112 in the
						sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. O&#8217;Conor was a priest from a well-known family of Irish scholars. His book was
						an edition of some of the Irish manuscripts in the library at Stowe, where he worked as chaplain to Mary,
						Marchioness of Buckinghamshire (d. 1812), the sister-in-law of Wynn&#8217;s uncle, Lord Grenville. O&#8217;Conor also edited
							<title>Bibliotheca MS. Stowensis. A Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts in the Stowe Library</title>, 2 vols
						(1818&#8211;1819). Southey did not review these works in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1821-04-04"> April 4. 1821.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>