<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3724</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4995</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3724. Robert Southey to John May, 2 September&#8211;13 November
                  1821</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3724" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3724.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 41&#8211;51.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3724" type="letter">
        <head>3724. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1821-09-02">2 September&#8211;13 November
                  1821</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation,
                  River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 41&#8211;51.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1821-09-02">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 2. 1821.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Bath &amp; Bristol Theatres were then &amp; for many years afterwards what in trade language is called &#8216;one
                  concern.&#8221;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Old Orchard Street Theatre in Bath was built in 1750 and owned by John Palmer
                  (1703&#8211;1788), who also acquired the Theatre Royal in Bristol. He was the father of Miss Palmer. The same repertory company performed
                  at both theatres.</note> The performers were stationed half the year in one city, half in the other. When they played on Mondays,
               Wednesdays &amp; Fridays at Bristol, they went to Bath on the Saturday in two immense coaches big as a caravan of wild beasts, &amp;
               returned after the play! When the nights of performance at Bath were Tuesdays Thursdays &amp; Saturdays they went to Bristol on the
               Monday. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, thro her intimacy with <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> had the command<del>s</del> of orders for free admission; she was exceedingly fond
               of theatrical representations, &amp; there was no subject of which I heard so much, from my earliest childhood. &lt;It <del>xxxx</del>
               &lt;&lt;brought upon&gt;&gt; me once a most severe reprehension for innocently applying to the Church, a phrase which I then learnt to my cost
               belonged only to the Playhouse, &#8211; &amp; saying one Sunday on our return from morning-service, that it had been a very <hi rend="ital">full House</hi>.&gt; When I was taken to the theatre for the first time I perfectly well remember my surprize at not finding the Pit
               literally a deep hole, into which I had often puzzled myself to think how, or why, any people could possibly go. You may judge by this
               how very young I must have been. I recollect nothing more of that first visit, except that the play was the Fathers, a comedy of
               Fieldings, which was acted not more than one season, &amp; the farce was Coxheath Camp: &#8211; this recollection however, by the help of
               that useful book the Biographia Dramatica, fixes the date to 1778, &#8211; when I was four years old.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Fielding (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Fathers; or, The Good-Natur&#8217;d Man</title> (1779) and Richard Brinsley
                  Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Camp</title> (1778); David Erskine Baker (1739&#8211;1767?; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Biographia Dramatica. A New Edition</title>, 2 vols (London, 1782), I, p. 163 (Fielding); and II, p. 41
               (Sheridan).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A half sheet of reminiscences written one &amp; twenty years ago at Lisbon, has recallen this &amp; a few other
               circumstances to my recollection, which might otherwise have been quite obliterated. Yet it surprizes me to perceive how many things
               come to mind which had been for years &amp; years forgotten! It is said that when earth is flung to the surface in digging a
                  <del>pit</del> well plants will <del>generally</del> spring up <del>then</del> which are not found in the surrounding country, seeds
               having quickened which had been buried there during unknown ages: &#8211; no unapt illustration for the way in which forgotten things are
               thus brought up from the bottom of ones memory.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was <del>then</del> introduced to the Theatre before it was possible for me to comprehend the nature of the drama so
               as to derive any pleasure from it, except from the mere spectacle. What was going on upon the stage, as far as I understood it,
               appeared real to me &amp; I have been told that <del>upon</del> one night when the Critic<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sheridan&#8217;s <title>The Critic; or, A Tragedy Rehearsed</title> (1779), a satire on the contemporary theatre. Central to the action
                  is a rehearsal of a play on the Spanish Armada (1588), one of the main characters in this is based on the courtier, explorer and
                  author Sir Walter Ralegh (1554&#8211;1618; <title>DNB</title>). </note> was represented, &amp; I heard that Sir W Raleghs head was to be
               cut off, I hid mine in Miss Mary Delameres<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Delamare (1740&#8211;1820) was one of the sisters of
                     <ref type="m" target="people.html#DolignonElizabeth">Elizabeth Dolignon</ref>, and a friend of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Elizabeth Tyler</ref>, Southey&#8217;s aunt.</note> lap, &amp; could not be persuaded to look up,
               till I was assured this dreaded scene was over. &lt;It was not long before I acquired a keen relish for the drama, but at this time&gt; My
               greatest pleasure was a walk in the fields, especially if we crost the <del>xxxx</del> river in the ferry boat at Walcot, or at the
               South Parade. Short as the passage was I have not yet forgotten the delight which it used to give me. There were three points beyond
               all others which I was desirous of reaching, the sham-Castle on Claverton Hill, <del>&amp;</del> a summer-house on Beechen clift,
                  <del>xxxx</del> &amp; the grave of a young man, whom &lt;a gambler by name&gt; Count Rice (I think) had killed in a duel.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">On 18 November 1778, two visitors to Bath, a Captain Rice (dates unknown) and Vicomte Jean Baptiste Du
                  Barre (1749&#8211;1778), fought a duel over a gambling dispute. Although Rice killed his opponent, at the subsequent trial at Taunton
                  Assizes in 1779 he was acquitted of murder.</note> The two former objects were neither of them two miles distant: <del>xxxx only
                  xxxxxx thxx xxxx</del>; &#8211; but they were up-hill, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> regarded it
               as an impossibility to walk so far. I did not reach them therefore till I was old enough to be in some degree master of my own
               movements. The grave was at Bath Weston, &amp; we reached it once: but the usual extent of our walks into the country (which were very
               rare) was to a cottage in an orchard about half way. It was always a great joy &lt;to me&gt; when I was sent for home, tho <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my fathers</ref> house <del>stood</del> &lt;was&gt; in then &lt;one of the busiest&gt; streets of a
               crowded city. I had more liberty, &amp; was under no capricious restrictions; &#8211; &amp; I had more walks into the fields, tho still too
               few. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My Mother</ref> sometimes, &amp; sometimes <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt Mary</ref>, would walk with me to Kingsdown, &#8211; to Brandon Hill, &#8211; Clifton, or that &lt;bank of
               the river which&gt; is called the Sea Banks, <del>I know nobody</del>. And we often went to my grandmothers,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Bradford (1710&#8211;1782), who lived at Bedminster.</note> where I liked best to be, because I had there a
               thorough enjoyment of the country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> whose ascendency over <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> was always that of an imperious elder sister, would not suffer me to be
               breeched till I was six years old, tho I was tall of my age. I had a fantastic <del>dress</del> &lt;costume&gt; of nankeen, for highdays
               &amp; holydays, trimmed with green fringe, &#8211; it was called a vest &amp; tunic, &#8211; or a jam. When at last I changed my dress it was for
               coat waistcoat &amp; breeches, &#8211; for there was no intermediate form of <del>dress</del> &lt;apparel&gt; in use. I was then sent as a day
               scholar to a school on the top of S Michaels hill, which was then esteemed the best in Bristol, kept by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Foot, a
               dissenting minister.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Foot (d. 1781), Bristol Baptist minister, schoolmaster and author
                  of <title>A Plain Account of the Ordinance of Baptism</title> (1756&#8211;1758). He ran a school at the top of St Michael&#8217;s Hill, Bristol.
                  General Baptists differed from Particular Baptists in believing that all people possessed the free will to be saved, with God&#8217;s
                  grace, and none were predestined to damnation. At this time many General Baptists held unorthodox views of the Trinity, and Southey
                  suggests Foot was at least a follower of Arius (250&#8211;336 AD) in believing that Jesus was a divine being created by, and subordinate
                  to, God. &#8216;Socinian&#8217; (after Fausto Sozzini 1539&#8211;1604) was a means of describing Unitarianism, and some Unitarians believed Jesus was
                  merely a divinely inspired man.</note> He was <del>a General Baptist</del> of that community who are called General Baptists, in
               contradistinction to the Particular Baptists, &amp; like most of his denomination had passed into a sort of Low Arianism, if indeed he
               were not a Socinian. With this however I had nothing to do, nor did my parents regard it. He was an <del>very</del> old man, &amp; if
               the school had ever been a good one, it had woefully deteriorated. I was one of the least boys there, &#8211; I believe the very least, &amp;
               certainly both as willing &amp; as apt to learn, as any teacher could have desired: yet it was the only school where I was ever treated
               with severity. <del>The</del> Lessons in the grammar which I did not comprehend, &amp; yet would have learned well enough by rote under
               gentle discipline, were frightened out of my head, &amp; then I was shut up in a closet at the top of the stairs, with just light
               enough thro some bars to see my lesson by. Once he caned me cruelly, &#8211; the only time that any master ever laid his hand upon me: &#8211;
               &amp; I am sure he deserved a beating much more than I did. There was a great deal of tyranny in the school, from the worst of which I
               was exempted because I went home <del>at</del> in the evening: but I stood in great fear of the big boys, &amp; saw much more of the
               evil side of human nature than I should ever have learnt in the course of domestic education.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had been there not more than twelve months when the master died. He was succeeded by <ref type="m" target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Estlin</ref>, a Socinian Minister, with whom <del>I</del> in after years
               I was well acquainted, &#8211; a good scholar, &amp; an excellent man. Had I continued at the school, he would have grounded me well.
               Unfortunately <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref> (I know not for what reason) thought proper to remove
               me upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Foots death, &amp; placed me at a school nine miles from Bristol, in a village called Corston, about a
               mile from the Globe at Newton, a well known public house on the road between Bath &amp; Bristol. The stage was to drop me at that
               public house, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref> to accompany it on horseback, &amp; consign me
               to the masters care. When the time for our departure drew nigh, I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                  Mother</ref> weeping in her chamber. It was the first time I had ever seen her shed tears; &#8211; the room (that wherein I was born) with
               all its furniture, &amp; her <del>attitude</del> &lt;position&gt; &amp; look at that moment, are as distinct in my memory as if the scene had
               occurred but yesterday; &#8211; &amp; I can call to mind with how strong &amp; painful an effort it was that I subdued my own feelings. I
               allude to it in the Hymn to the Penates.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Hymn to the Penates&#8217; (1796), lines 42&#8211;45: &#8216;When first/
                  A little one, I left my father&#8217;s home, I can remember the first grief I felt,/ And the first painful smile that cloathed my front/
                  With feelings not its own&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of my earliest extant poems (the Retrospect) describes &lt;this school, &amp;&gt; a visit which I made to <del>this
                  school at the dozen years</del> &lt;it&gt;, in the year 1794 &lt;after it had ceased to be one&gt;.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The
                  Retrospect&#8217; (1794), published in Southey&#8217;s and Robert Lovell&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> (Bath, 1795), pp. [1]&#8211;15.</note> The House had
               been the mansion of some decayed family, whose history I should like to trace if Collinsons Somersetshire were to fall in my way.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey added a prefatory note from John Collinson (1757&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     History and Antiquities of the County of Somerset</title>, 3 vols (Bath, 1791), III, pp. 341&#8211;347, to the revised version of &#8216;The
                  Retrospect&#8217; published in his <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London 1837&#8211;1838), II, pp. 263&#8211;264, and added that the house
                  (now Manor Farm) was, by 1837, a farmhouse.</note> There were vestiges of former respectability &amp; comfort about it, which young
               as I was, impressed me in the same manner as such things would do now: walled gardens, summer houses, gate<del>x</del> &lt;pillars&gt;
               surmounted with huge balls of stone, a paddock, a large orchard, walnut trees, &lt;yards &amp;&gt; outhouses upon an opulent scale. I felt
               how mournful all this was in its fallen state, when the great walled garden was converted into a playground for the boys, the gateways
                  <del>xxxxx</del> broken, the summer houses falling to ruin, &amp; grass growing in the interstices of the Lozenged pavement of the
               fore court. The features within I do not so distinctly remember, not being so well able to understand their &lt;symbols of better days&gt;,
               only I recollect a black oaken staircase &lt;from the hall,&gt; &amp; that the school room was hung with faded tapestry, behind which we used
               to hoard crabs.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here one year of my life was past <del>xxx</del> unprofitably, &amp; with a good deal of suffering. There could not be
               a worse school in all respects. <del>Xxxxxxx</del> &lt;Thomas <del>xxxx</del>&gt; Flower<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                  Flower (d. 1799); he also gave public lectures on astronomy and took private pupils.</note> the Master was a remarkable man, worthy
               I believe of a better station <del>of</del> &lt;in&gt; life, but utterly unfit for that in which he was placed. His whole delight was in
               mathematics &amp; astronomy; &amp; he had constructed an orrery upon so large a scale, that it filled a room. What a misery it must
               have been for such a man to teach a set of stupid boys, year after year, the rudiments of arithmetic! And a misery he seemed to feel
               it; when he came into his desk, even there he was thinking of the stars, &amp; <del>seemed always</del> &lt;looked as if he were&gt; out of
               humour &lt;not from ill-nature, but&gt; because his calculations were interrupted. But for the most part he left the school to the care of
               his son Charley,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Flower (dates unknown), son of Thomas Flower.</note> a person who was
               always called by that familiar diminutive, &amp; whose consequence you may appreciate accordingly. Writing &amp; arithmetic were all
               they professed to teach; but twice a week a Frenchman came from Bristol to instruct in Latin the <del>few</del> small part of the boys
               who learnt it, &#8211; of whom I was one. Duplanier<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Du Planier (dates unknown) ran a private school
                  in Bristol, next door to the one that Southey attended in 1782&#8211;1786.</note> was his name, &#8211; <del>a very good natured man</del>. He
               returned to France at the commencement of the Revolution, &amp; a report obtained credit at one time that <del>xx</del> resuming his
               own name there, he went into the army, &amp; became no less a personage than General Menou, of Egyptian notoriety.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The French General Jacques-Fran&#231;ois de Menou, Baron de Boussay (1750&#8211;1810), commander of French forces
                  in Egypt 1800&#8211;1801. The story that he was actually Du Planier, (who had returned to France in 1790) was widely reported, for
                  example, <title>Albion and Evening Advertiser</title>, 13 September 1800.</note> For Duplaniers sake, who was a very good-natured
               man, I am glad the story was disproved.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That sort of ornamental penmanship which now, I fear, is wholly gone out of use, was taught there. The father as well
               as Charley excelled in it. They could adorn the heading of a rule in arithmetic in a cyphering book, not merely with common
               flourishing, but with an angel, a serpent, a fish or a pen, formed with an ease &amp; freedom of hand which was to me a great object of
               admiration; but unluckily I was too young to acquire the art. In the course of my life I have seen two historical <del>subjects</del>
               &lt;pieces&gt; produced in this manner <del>by the pen</del> &lt;<del>with</del> worthy of remembrance as notable specimens of whimsical
               dexterity&gt;; one was David killing Goliah, -<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">1 <title>Samuel</title> 17.</note> it was in a
               Brokers shop at Bristol &lt;I would have bought it if I could have afforded at that time to expend some ten shillings <del>on the
                  xxxxxxx</del> upon it&gt;; &#8211; the other was a portrait of Joam 5<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">John V (1689&#8211;1750; King of
                  Portugal 1706&#8211;1750), nicknamed &#8216;the Magnificent&#8217;. Southey saw the portrait when he visited Manuel de Cen&#225;culo, Bishop of Beja in
                  April 1801.</note> on horseback, in the bishops palace at Beja. They taught the beautiful Italian &lt;or Ladies&#8217;&gt; hand used <del>by
                  Ladies</del> in the age of our parents, &#8211; &amp; engrossing<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The writing out of the final form
                  of a legal document after successive drafts.</note> (which may be called a Rascal<del>ly</del> hand <del>for</del> &lt;considering&gt; the
               use to which it is appropriated, but which I suppose was devised to insure distinctness &amp; legibility) &amp; some varieties of
               German text, worthy for their square, massy, antique forms to have figured in an Antiquarians title page.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Twice during the twelve months of my stay, <del>much</del> great interest was excited throughout the <del>school</del>
               &lt;commonwealth&gt; by a grand spelling match, for which poor Flower deserves some credit, if it was a device of his own, to save himself
               trouble &amp; amuse the boys. Two of the biggest boys chose <del>for</del> their party, boy by boy alternately, till the whole
                  <del>number</del> &lt;school&gt; was divided between them: they then hunted the Dictionary for words unusual enough in their orthography
               to puzzle ill-taught lads, &amp; having compared lists, that the same word might not be chosen by both, two words were delivered to
               every boy, &amp; kept by him profoundly secret from all on the other side till the time of trial. On a day appointed we <del>all</del>
               were <del>xxxx</del> drawn up in battle array, quite as anxious <del>for</del> &lt;on&gt; the <del>moment</del> &lt;occasion&gt; as the members of
               a Cricket Club for the <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;<del>xxxxxx</del> result&gt; of a grand match against all England, &#8211; ambition &#8211; that &#8220;last
               infirmity of noble minds&#8221;<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>),
                  &#8216;Lycidas&#8217; (1637), line 71.</note> had something to do with this anxiety, &amp; to increase the excitement &#8211; each person had waged a
               halfpenny upon the <del>victory</del> &lt;event&gt;. The words were given out in due succession on each side from the biggest to the least,
               &amp; for every one which was spelt &lt;rightly&gt; in its progress down the enemys ranks, the enemy scored one. The party in which I was
               engaged <del>won</del> &lt;lost&gt; one of these matches &amp; won the other. I <del>can still</del> remember that my words for one of them
               were Chrystallization &amp; coterie, &amp; that I was one of the most effective persons in the contest, which might very easily be.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Charley &amp; his father frequently saved themselves some trouble by putting me to teach bigger boys than myself. I got
               on with Latin here more by assisting others in their lessons than by &lt;my&gt; own, <del>for Duplanier only</del> &lt;when the master&gt; came
                  <del>twice a week</del> &lt;so seldom&gt;; this assistance was not voluntary on my part, it was a tax levied upon me by the law of the
               strongest &lt;a law which prevails as much in schools as it did in the cabinets of the Emperor Napoleon &amp; of Louis 14,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815); and Louis XIV (1638&#8211;1715; King of
                  France 1643&#8211;1715).</note> &amp; does in that of the United States of America&gt;; but the effect was that I <del>xx</del> made as much
               progress myself as if my lessons had been daily. At Mr Foots I read Cordery &amp; Erasmus,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Editions of Mathurin Cordier (1479&#8211;1564), <title>Colloquium Scholasticorum Libri Quator</title>, and Desiderius Erasmus
                  (1466&#8211;1536), <title>Adages</title> (1500) or <title>Colloquies</title> (1516).</note> each with a translation in &lt;a&gt; parallel column
               which was doubled down at lesson time. Here I got into Ph&#230;drus,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Phaedrus (fl. 1st century),
                     <title>Fabulae Aesopiae</title>, a Latin collection of fables.</note> without a translation, but with the help of an Ordo
                  verborum,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Order of words&#8217;; an aid designed to help with the translation of Latin.
                  </note>
          <del>designated</del> indicated by figures in the margin. But I am at the end of my paper, &amp; the slip beside me has items
               enough concerning Corston for another letter.</p>
        <closer>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1821-11-13"> Nov. 13.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>