<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3436</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4707</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3436. Robert Southey to Mary Barker, 10&#8211;12 February
                  1820</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3436" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3436.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The
                  Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 457&#8211;460 .  Previously  published:
                  John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 178&#8211;180 [in
                  part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3436" type="letter">
        <head>3436. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1820-02-12">10&#8211;12 February
                  1820</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The
                  Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 457&#8211;460<lb /> Previously published:
                  John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 178&#8211;180 [in
                  part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1820-02-10">Feb. 10. 1820.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> Dear Senhora,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received your note yesterday in a frank from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, which
               covered a proof sheet. For a very long while I had been intending and intending to write to you. You know some old divine has said that
               Hell is paved with good intentions.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A proverbial saying. It has been attributed to St Bernard of
                  Clairvaux (1090&#8211;1153).</note> But you know also, that the longer I live the more I have to do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Wesley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820).</note> is not finished yet. My part will be completed in the course of this month, and the printer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Andrew Strahan (1749&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), MP for various constituencies 1796&#8211;1820 and owner
                  of a highly successful printing business.</note> will not be long behind me. There is time, therefore, for you to tell me how it may
               be sent from London, and I will give directions for sending it with the last volume of &#8220;Brazil&#8221;.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> Perhaps the readiest way would be to entrust it to the Paris
               diligence from London, and direct it to your uncle.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Jeremiah Homfray (1759&#8211;1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), a Welsh ironmaster and speculator in mineral rights, living in Boulogne since being declared bankrupt in
                  1813. </note> But you will let me know.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I meant to have left home early in March. The King&#8217;s death<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">George III
                  (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) had died on 29 January 1820.</note> will delay my departure two or
               three weeks, for I must of course produce something on this subject, and if I begin my journey before the poem is finished, the funeral
               verses will come out just in time for the coronation.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Vision of Judgement</title>
                  (1821), produced by Southey in response to George III&#8217;s death, was published in early March 1821. The coronation of George IV was on
                  19 July 1821.</note> You know how little inclination I have to task my poor brains upon such hackneyed subjects as this, especially
               too when every man, woman, and child, who can grind a verse, is likely to be at work upon it. However, if any person sets his verses to
               the same tune as mine, I think I may very safely say that I would consent to be hanged.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You probably know that Lord Somerville is dead, and I believe you know that I was related to him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), agricultural reformer and
                  third cousin of Southey, had died on 5 October 1819. This produced a further round of legal tangles over the Fitzhead estate in
                  Somerset that Somerville had inherited.</note> He was my third cousin, and distant as this connection is, it may possibly give me a
               right to a suit in Chancery to recover property bequeathed to him and his issue by his mother&#8217;s uncle &#8211; a certain John Cannon Southey,
               whose heir-at-law I am, in consequence of Lord Somerville&#8217;s demise. The old Cannon was but an old blunderbuss, and made a most confused
                  will.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Somerville&#8217;s mother was Elizabeth Cannon Lethbridge (d. 1765), the daughter of Mary
                  Southey (1704&#8211;1789) and niece of John Cannon Southey (d. 1768). The latter had inherited the Fitzhead estate from his mother Mary
                  Cannon (1678&#8211;1738). On his death, John Cannon Southey had left a complex, ill-advised will which named Somerville as his primary
                  heir, and, should he die childless, Southey&#8217;s father and two uncles as the residuary legatees, their rights passing, in turn, to
                  their children. Of the three Southey brothers only Southey&#8217;s father married, leading the poet to believe (after the death of his
                  father and paternal uncles) that he and his brothers were now the rightful heirs to the Fitzhead estate. </note> Lord S. has done
               all he could to cut off my rights, and though I believe the <hi rend="ital">equity</hi> of the case is as clear as noonday, the <hi rend="ital">law</hi> may be very doubtful. The estates in question amount to about a thousand a year. The matter is in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner&#8217;s</ref> hands, and of course the best opinions will be taken on the
               subject. You know as much about it now as I do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now let me make you angry. A rascally bookseller in London is at this time publishing, in sixpenny numbers, a Life of
               the King, by Robert Sout<hi rend="ital">hy</hi>, Esq.; printed for the Author. &#8220;Observe, to order Southy&#8217;s Life of the King, to avoid
                  imposition.&#8221;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Authentic Memoirs of Our Late Venerable and Beloved Monarch, George the
                     Third &#8230; by Robert Southy, Esq.</title> (1820). The identity of the publisher is unclear. See Southey to Messrs Longman &amp; Co,
                  8 February 1820, Letter 3434.</note> The rascal expects that by mispelling the name, he can evade the law. Whether he can or not is
               one question, and whether it be worth my while to be at the expense of any proceedings against him is another of equal importance,
               which I shall leave <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> to decide. But do not you think that a cart&#8217;s tail might be worthily employed upon this occasion?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the punishment in which a felon was tied to a cart&#8217;s tail and paraded through the streets while
                  being whipped. It was still in force in Britain (the last case was in 1822).</note> With a little trouble, I could work myself into
               a passion about this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref> is with us. The winter has tried <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs. Wilson</ref> sorely, and she will not stand such another trial. It has been very severe, but the
               frost was never accompanied with wind; and though the glass was never lower since we have been in this country, I have often felt it
               much colder in the house. We are now enjoying a genial February.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The children,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                     May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert Southey</ref>.</note> thank God, are well. I have made a surprising progress
               in spoiling <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>. He has long since found out the attractions of
               the study, and would look at pictures by the hour, if anybody would continue to exhibit. But I bear the bell as an exhibitor, because
               on such occasions I speak the language of all the birds in the air, and all the beasts in the field. He has often had bilious attacks,
               and one very severe one. At present he seems strong and healthy, just as sweet a creature as can be, and as tyrannical as you would
               wish to see him, &#8211; very forward with his tongue, and backward with his feet. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother
                  Tom</ref> has another child on the stocks!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had six children: Margaret Hill
                  Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815&#8211;1864); Eleanor
                  Thomasina Southey (1816&#8211;1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818&#8211;1850). Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834) joined them on 8 May 1820, and
                  was followed by Sophia Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859) and Thomas Castle Southey (1824&#8211;1896).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We were much shocked, as you may suppose, at hearing of Mr. Brewer&#8217;s death.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> I heard at the same time of Mr. Lewis&#8217;s. But he was a man in years.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> Edward<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Edward Barker (dates unknown), a nephew of Mary
                  Barker.</note> is here to day (Saturday the 12th), in excellent health. All here desire their love. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>