<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2017-01-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3302</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4573</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3302. Robert Southey to James Gooden, 25 May
                  1819</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3302.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Department of Rare
                  Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS;
                  4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3302" type="letter">
        <head>3302. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#GoodenJames">James Gooden</ref>, <date when="1819-05-25">25 May
                  1819</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ James Gooden Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Woburn Place/
                  Russel Square/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 28 MY 28/ 1819<lb /> Seal: [partial] red wax<lb /> Watermark: T.S.
                  STAINS 1815. A small embossed stamp in the upper left corner of 1r, positioned vertically. Crest. BATH <lb /> MS: Department of Rare
                  Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS;
                  4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1819-05-25">25 May. 1819</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0">My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am really ashamed when I think how long your letter has remained unanswered. &#8211; It arrived at a time when <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> was exceedingly ill after her confinement, &#8211; &amp; the
               length of time that that illness, &amp; other accompanying anxieties rendered me unfit for ordinary business, must be in part my
               apology.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have an opportunity pray express my thanks to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Constable<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Preface&#8217; to <title>History of Brazil</title> (1822) [unpaginated], thanked Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Scottish publisher, bookseller and stationer, for &#8216;a collection of original dispatches from the home
                  Government to D. Luiz de Sousa, during his administration of Brazil&#8217;. Luis de Sousa, Conde do Prado (c. 1580&#8211;1643) was
                  Governor-General of Brazil 1617&#8211;1621 in the reign of Philip III (1578&#8211;1621; King of Spain and Portugal 1598&#8211;1621). James Gooden had
                  brought this manuscript to Southey&#8217;s attention. Constable had agreed to purchase it and let Southey make use of it for his
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>.</note> for his civility. I will write to thank him when I have examined the manuscript, which I
               hope to do in three or four weeks from this time. You will wonder that my third volume should have been so long delayed, but the delay
               will be accounted for when you see to what a bulk it has grown under my hands.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and
                  final volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) ran to 950 pages.</note> We are printing the final chapter, which
               contains a view of the whole country, province by province, <del>xxxx</del> &amp; the general state of manners &amp;c, such as it was
               at the time of the removal; &#8211; as far as my materials enable me to describe it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 696&#8211;879, which described Brazil at the time the Portuguese court fled there
                  in 1807&#8211;1808.</note> How imperfect it must needs be I well know; but this ought not to deter me from doing what I can, nor induce me
               to withhold the information which it has been in my power to obtain. Abused as the Brazilians &amp; the Portugueze have been, I verily
               think that the progress of Brazil during the eighteenth century is more surprising than that of the United States, &#8211; &amp; that the
               Brazilians have accomplished more in proportion to their means than the Anglo Americans. The <del>retrospective xx</del> prospect is
               still more favourable; &#8211; no change in the government is required, only a return to its true principles, &amp; the enforcement of good
               laws, &#8211; equally to the advantage of the subject &amp; the sovereign.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of
                  Portugal 1816&#8211;1826).</note> The spirit of the age tends to this, &amp; the new Minister<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to Pedro de Sousa Holstein, Conde de Palmela (1781&#8211;1850), Portuguese Ambassador to the United Kingdom,
                  1812&#8211;1817. He had been appointed Foreign Minister of the United Kingdom of Portugal and Brazil, but declined to make the journey to
                  Brazil to take up his post until 1820.</note> may be expected to keep pace with it. A great deal has been done since the Removal of
               the Court,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil in 1807&#8211;1808.</note> in establishing
               posts, opening roads, chartering towns, &amp; reducing the last savages who impeded the progress of civilization: &#8211; these I speak of as
               acts of the Ministry &lt;independent of&gt; ; &#8211; the impulse which <del>xxxx</del> &lt;has&gt; been given to industry &amp; enterprise by
                  <del>the</del> free trade.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Brazil had been opened to the trade of other nations in
                  1808.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They are likely soon to have a press at Recife.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A printing press had been
                  imported into Pernambuco in 1815, but a royal licence to publish material had only just been issued before a revolutionary
                  government took over Recife, the provincial capital, in March&#8211;May 1817. The new regime made extensive use of the press in producing
                  proclamations, but on its defeat the press was closed and its type sent to Rio de Janeiro. A new printing press was built at the
                  local arsenal in 1821 to produce official pamphlets and a pro-government newspaper.</note> This they would have had two years ago,
               if the miserable attempt at revolution had not been made; &#8211; &amp; the moving mind of that conspiracy, P. Joam Ribeiro might at this
               time have been employed in diffusing useful knowledge among his countrymen by its means, if he had not drawn down destruction upon
               himself &amp; others.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo Montenegro (1766&#8211;1817) was a priest who was a
                  member of the provisional government set up by the revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8 March&#8211;18 May 1817. He committed suicide in the
                  town of Paulista after the defeat of the revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife, the provincial capital.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had no share in the paper upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> &amp; the
               Education Committee, certainly one of the most compleat exposures that ever was laid before the public.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring to the review of, among other items, <title>A Letter to Sir Samuel Romilly, M.P. from Henry
                     Brougham, Esq. M.P., F.R.S. upon the Abuse of Charities</title> (1818) and the Reports of the House of Commons Select Committee
                  on the Education of the Lower Orders 1816&#8211;1818 (chaired by Brougham), which severely criticised the lack of educational provision
                  and highlighted abuses in educational charities, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (July 1818), 492&#8211;569, published 2 February
                  1819. The reviewer was John Wilson Croker, with assistance from others.</note> It seems to have done its work. I perceive that you
               entirely coincide in with me in opinion upon this financial question by which the commercial concerns of the country are so
                  <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;wantonly&gt; dislocated.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons was debating legislation to
                  recommence the convertibility of paper currency to gold, which had been suspended since 1797. The legislation passed on 2 July 1819
                  and convertibility was restored on 1 May 1821, but the period 1819&#8211;1821 witnessed a fall in commodity prices and rising
                  unemployment.</note> Thus it is, &#8211; we must be making difficulties for ourselves, when there were no existing ones, &#8211; building a
               wall, as Sheridan said, for the purpose of running our heads against it.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of a <hi rend="ital">bon mot</hi> said to be the response of Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) to the fall of the
                  Ministry of Talents in March 1807: &#8216;I have heard of people running their heads against a brick wall before, but I never heard of any
                  other people building a wall on purpose.&#8217; For a visual representation, see the satirical print <title>The Groans and Dissolution of
                     All the Talents</title> (1807) by Charles Williams (<hi rend="ital">fl.</hi> 1797&#8211;1830).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the offer of Montenegro. I picked up a copy some years ago in London.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably an edition of writings by Benito Jer&#243;nimo Feij&#243;o y Montenegro (1676&#8211;1764), Benedictine monk and essayist
                  whose works, notably <title>Teatro Cr&#237;tico Universal</title> (1726&#8211;1739) and <title>Cartas Eruditas y Curiosas</title> (1742&#8211;1760),
                  cover a range of subjects, including natural science, law, education, philology, and popular superstition. Southey owned two
                  editions, nos 3297 and 3298 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; You will shortly receive the whole of your books &amp;
               MSS with which you entrusted me.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey thanked Gooden for lending him &#8216;the Life of F. Joam
                  d&#8217;Almeida, among other books, and a manuscript Apology for the Jesuits in Paraguay and Maranham, of great importance&#8217; in his
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. [v].</note> As soon as this work is thro the press I shall
               set off for London, &#8211; where, if you do not take wing during the summer season, I hope to see you in the course of three or four
               weeks.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> fare well my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent1"> &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs
                  faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>