<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3827" type="letter"><head>3827. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-04-20">20 April 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/>
               Endorsements: 20 April 1823; 20 April 1823<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: The endorsements incorrectly date this to ‘1823’. Southey’s authorial dating and the letter’s content indicate it was written on 20 April 1822.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> The sooner you can let me have 50 £ the better; when the next quarter is received, this will &#60;leave&#62; enough in your hands for the frames, &#38; the taylors bill. – I shall not want clothes this year, which is well, because Hydes<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Hyde (d. 1820) had been Southey’s tailor in London. His successor was J. McCallan &#38; Co., tailors of Leicester Square, London.</note> successor chuses to dandify me, &#38; I must therefore look for a taylor who will not make his mistake.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I used to get my vegetable-marrow seed from Ludlow. But I have lost my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Mr Browne</ref>, who supplied me with it. It is an excellent thing, – &#38; <hi rend="ital">ought to be in the ground by this time</hi>. We stew them in cream, in a way which you will like.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> goes, I believe, next week to Harrogate. I have great hope that it will be of great service to her. You will be pleased to see with what freedom &#38; spirit she sketches &#38; how excellently well she uses her hands in any thing where design is required.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> is a little out of order at present. I assure you, you will not be for taking him to <hi rend="ital">kill-brat</hi> when you see him. – I have many things to show you, much to talk about, &#38; many pleasant schemes dependent <del>xxx</del> upon your presence. The boat is under the painters hands<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southeys’ boat the <title>Royal Noah</title>, which they used on Derwentwater.</note> –</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3">  RS</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
           <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-04-20"> 20 Apr 1822.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
