<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3870" type="letter"><head>3870. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#BensonChristopher">Christopher Benson</ref>], <date when="1822-07-17">17 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850)<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 119–120.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1822-07-17">July 17. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Dr. Channing,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Ellery Channing (1780–1842), Minister of the Federal Street Church in Boston 1803–1842, and foremost spokesman for Unitarian opinion in the United States.</note> of Boston, in New England, is equally distinguished in his own country by the fervour and eloquence of his preaching, and the primitive virtues of his life. I take the liberty of introducing him to you, because you will feel yourself in accord with him upon many of the most important points, and because I am very desirous that he should see and converse with one who holds as high a rank in Old England as he does in America. I have learnt from him with some surprise that, under the name of Unitarianism, Arianism<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The theology that claimed Christ was a being created by and subordinate to God.</note> is the prevailing doctrine in the Massachusetts’ states, and that he himself is of that persuasion. But I have told him that he will find himself much more in sympathy with our clergy than with the Dissenters, and this he already apprehends. He is in opulent circumstances, and has devoted, and almost spent, himself in the ministerial duties.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I need say no more of him; his conversation and the truly Christian temper of his mind, notwithstanding the doctrinal errors which he holds, will sufficiently recommend him. But I feel the necessity of apologising for the liberty which I am taking with you. You will, I trust, impute it to the true cause, and not be offended, if, in excuse for it, I say to you that having had the good fortune once to hear you in the pulpit,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had heard Benson preach one of his Hulsean Lectures on the ‘evidences of Christianity’ at St Mary’s University Church, Cambridge, on 28 May 1820.</note> and having since perused with the greatest satisfaction the series of your discourses,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Benson, <title>Twenty Discourses Preached before the University of Cambridge in the Year 1820: at the Lecture Founded by the Rev. John Hulse</title> (1820), no. 263 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> I earnestly wish that this excellent American should receive the most favourable impressions of the English Church. When I spoke of you to him last night, and put your volume into his hands, I did not know whether you were in this or in a better world. To-day, by mere accident, I learn that you have happily resumed your labours,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Benson gave a second series of Hulsean Lectures in 1822.</note> and yielding to the first impulse I offered this introduction to Dr. Channing with as much pleasure as he manifested at receiving it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">When you visit this your native county,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Benson was from Cockermouth.</note> you would gratify me greatly by giving me an opportunity of personally repeating an apology for this intrusion, and offering you such hospitality as my means afford.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">Believe me, dear Sir,</salute>
               <salute rend="indent1">Yours with the highest esteem and respect,</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
            
            
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
