<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3880" type="letter"><head>3880. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">[William] Westall</ref> [fragment], <date when="1822-08-02">2 August 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on MS: The lower half of fol. 1 is missing.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear Westall</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I write by this post to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Herbert Hill, 30 July–[continued on 2 August] 1822, Letter 3878.</note> desiring him either to send you what he calls his <hi rend="ital">scratch</hi> of Elvas, unless he is able to call with it &#38; explain it, which he wishes to do.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A medieval castle on the Portuguese-Spanish border; it was captured by France in 1807 and then successfully besieged by Anglo-Portuguese forces in 1808.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Neither of the three sketches which you mention can be referred to the first volume.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall was preparing <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey’s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &#38;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> – The references I will send as soon as the clean sheets whereto they relate reach me; &#38; these I expect every day. [MS missing]</p>
<lb/>            
            <p rend="indent1"> but I shall have another opportunity in the course of a fortnight, or three weeks, by my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, whom I expect this day.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802–1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August–2 September 1822.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Present my best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Westall &#38; my godson.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ann Westall, née Sedgewick (1789–1862), and her eldest son, William Westall (1821–1901), later a clergyman.</note> I hope to see them in the course of the winter. All here desire their kindest remembrances. It would please you to see what a progress <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> has made in sketching.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
              <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-08-02">2 Aug. 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
