<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3917" type="letter"><head>3917. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>], <date when="1822-11-13">13 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Nov 13 1822/ Rob Southey Esq<lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Herewith I inclose my list;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A list of those whom Southey wished to receive a complimentary copy of the first volume of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> – the larger number of these copies are in acknowledgement for materials offered me; – the rest are on the score of private feeling.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Secure for me, I pray, the proofs which I now return, – or <del>any other</del> &#60;another&#62; set, in case of any mutilations in the article.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – I hope that either the proofs, or the ms. of my paper on Camoens<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Adamson, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820), no. 10 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1–39, published 4 July 1822.</note> may be recovered, – many parts essential to it, as a piece of literary history, having been cut out.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I will prepare an American article, – as a matter which is really of political importance in its consequences.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752–1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821–1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1–40, published 17 April 1824.</note> There is no country <del>which</del> with which it so materially concerns us to cultivate a good understanding, – &#38; this can be done at the easiest &#38; cheapest rate, by abstaining from all insult, &#38; treating them with courtesy &#38; justice.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">But my next paper will be upon the Rise &#38; Progress of Infidelity, taking Gregoires Hist. of the Theophilanthropists for a text.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> If the execution be answerable, as I hope, to the design, my time will be well employed. Procure for me if you can by any means a book published some years ago – by William Hamilton Read upon the Infidel Societies in London<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hamilton Reid (d. 1826), <title>The Rise and Dissolution of the Infidel Societies in this Metropolis</title> (1800).</note> I want the facts which are to be found there.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Miss Coleridge</ref> will be in town, I should think, about Christmas, – she is now visiting on her way there. She will be at first with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">her father</ref> at Highgate, &#38; you will hear of her arrival.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am very glad that you see <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> qualifications &#38; character in the same light that I do. There is no person in whom I could more entirely confide for discretion, judgement, &#38; that probity which is produced by the union of honourable feelings &#38; virtuous principles.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was campaigning for John Taylor Coleridge to succeed William Gifford as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The mention of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DouglasHoward">Sir Howard Douglas</ref> reminds me of his book.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">General Sir Howard Douglas, <title>Observations on the Motives, Errors and Tendency of M. Carnot’s System of Defence</title> (1819), which offered a detailed critique of Lazare Nicolas Marguerite Carnot’s (1753–1823), classic work on fortifications, <title>Traite de la Défense des Places Fortes</title> (1810), on issues such as the effectiveness of vertical fire by defending forces. Douglas had provided information for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) and Southey was in return attempting to get Douglas’s book reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11 February 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3438.</note> You can bear witness how often &#38; urgently I have represented the propriety of having it reviewed, in justice to him, &#38; to the military reputation of the country which is concerned in having it made widely known that in the theory of war we are as much superior to the French, as in the practise. – The list which he offers will be very useful to me.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Please to get a copy bound for <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref>, &#38; send it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A specially bound copy of the first volume of the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) to present to George IV, to whom the book was dedicated.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">farewell my dear Sir &#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">   Yrs truly</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-11-13">13 Nov. 1822.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
