<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3926" type="letter"><head>3926. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard Barton</ref>], <date when="1822-11-29">29 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note>
            </head>
            
           <opener><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  I should not be satisfied with myself if I allowed a day to elapse without advising you not to publish these verses. They can do you no good &#38; they may do you a great deal of harm.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> When a book is dedicated to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernard Barton, <title>Napoleon, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), p. [v] was dedicated to George IV. Barton may have been offended not to receive any acknowledgement of his dedication and had written some verses expressing his disappointment.</note> it is a rare thing for the author to hear any thing of its acceptance. If he presents it himself at a levee, he is thanked at the time, – &#38; there the matter ends: – or if it is presented by any friend for him the acknowledgment is made in the same manner. After my Vision<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> had been presented some weeks, it was thought a mark of great graciousness in <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> that <del>he</del> at a levee he told <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> he was obliged to me for it &#38; had read it with pleasure.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to John Rickman, 18 May 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3687.</note> – To write a letter of thanks would be as much out of the course of things, as for him to pay me a visit.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It is very likely that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> may never have seen your book. It is &#60;also&#62; possible that you may be brought to his notice if <del>you</del> he has not, or to his recollection, if he has, – in some favourable way; – &#38; thereby be led to make some enquiry concerning it. But if these verses get abroad they will effectually mar any such possibility: – &#38; you will be set down for a person who formed rash expectations, &#38; had not discretion enough to conceal your mortification at finding yourself disappointed.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I advise you also not to offend your own society.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Society of Friends, or Quakers.</note> They will be proud of you in time, – &#38; in time too for you to profit by their good opinion What I have said <del>you</del> of you in the QR.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1–46, published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey included (pp. 4–5) a lengthy recommendation of Barton’s poetry for its ‘pure and religious spirit’ and quoted Barton’s poem ‘The Pool of Bethesda’, from <title>Napoleon, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. [182]–185 in its entirety.</note> (if <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">the Editor</ref> does not strike it out – which I shall be sorely displeased if he does) – may accelerate this. But in writing what is there written, I have not shown a more sincere desire for your good than in giving you the present advice</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">Yours in haste</salute>
              <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1822-11-29">29 <del>Xxx<hi rend="sup">y</hi></del> Nov. 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
