<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3929" type="letter"><head>3929. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#DibdinThomasFrognall">Thomas Frognall Dibdin</ref>], <date when="1822-12-09">9 December 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc MS 3912. ALS; 1p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-12-09">9 Dec. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">You tempt me with a proposal<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Dibdin had proposed that Southey should undertake a continuation of Thomas Warton (1728–1790; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of English Poetry from the Close of the Eleventh to the Commencement of the Eighteenth Century</title> (1774–1781). Southey did not take up the offer and a new edition appeared in 1824, edited by Richard Price (1790–1833; <title>DNB</title>), no. 2986 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which accords very well with my inclinations. Among the objections to it, the weightiest is, that I have long been preparing for a general history of English literature &#38; manners,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This project did not result in a book. Southey’s surviving notes for it were posthumously published as ‘Collections for the History of Manners and Literature in England’, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 439–578.</note> But this I think need not prevent me from treating a portion of our poetical history, upon a larger scale than can be allowed to it in my projected work. Loving Warton as I do, and owing him much as having studied in his school from my youth up, I am certainly as far disposed for the undertaking, as to be willing to hear from the Principals.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Tegg (1766–1845; <title>DNB</title>), publisher of popular works and abridgements of literary standards. Southey did not undertake any work for him.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  To say any thing farther upon the subject would be premature at present</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2"> Believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4">yours faithfully</salute>
           <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
