<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3945" type="letter"><head>3945. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#DibdinThomasFrognall">Thomas Frognall Dibdin</ref>], <date when="1823-01-03">3 January 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Tipped into a graingerised copy of <title>The English Bards and Scotch Reviewers, by Lord Byron. Illustrated with Portraits and Views, the First and Fourth Editions, with the alterations from the Fifth Edition</title> (London: n.p., 1811), pp. [141–2], Hornby Library, Liverpool City Libraries. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Note on correspondent: The correspondent is identified by the letter’s content; see Southey to [Thomas Frognall Dibdin], 9 December 1822, Letter 3929.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-01-03">3 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823.</date></dateline>
   
   <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Your first letter led me into a temptation, from which your second sets me free. – The sum which the publishers offer for two quarto volumes, is just one half of what I should require for one.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">On 9 December 1822 (Letter 3929), Dibdin had proposed that Southey should undertake a continuation of Thomas Warton (1728–1790; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of English Poetry from the Close of the Eleventh to the Commencement of the Eighteenth Century</title> (1774–1781). Southey did not take up the offer and a new edition appeared in 1824, edited by Richard Price (1790–1833; <title>DNB</title>), no. 2986 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. The proposed publisher of Southey’s continuation of Warton’s work was Thomas Tegg (1766–1845; <title>DNB</title>), well known for producing popular works and abridgements of literary standards. Southey did not undertake any work for him.</note> Of course therefore there is an end of the matter.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I guessed that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HaslewoodJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Haslewood</ref> was the person to whom you alluded. I called upon him one &#38; twenty years ago in consequence of his Chatterton collections,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Joseph Haslewood, 12 July 1802, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 694. Southey’s call was to receive assistance with his <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803), an edition of the writings of Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – &#38; by what I then saw of him, &#38; have since seen of his labours, <del>xxxxx</del> know how justly you have appreciated him.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Can you inform me where there exists a copy of the Comedies of Gil Vicente,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Gil Vicente (c. 1465–1536) wrote over forty plays. A posthumous edition of his works, <title>Compilação de Toda as Obras de Gil Vicente</title> (1562), appeared in five volumes, with the comedies occupying volume two and the farces volume four.</note> whom the Portugueze assert to be the father of the Spanish drama? You, who know every thing about books, are more likely to direct <del>xxxx</del> me in my search for this, than any other person. I should be glad to know also if the Cancioneiro of Resende is to be found in England.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), compiled by Garcia de Resende (1470–1536), contains nearly 1,000 lyrics in Portuguese and Castilian.</note> I made considerable extracts from it at Lisbon in the year 1801. But these are not sufficient for my purpose, &#38; whenever it is in my power, I must peruse the book.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">If chance should ever lead you this way, it would give me great pleasure to show you my Portugueze collection, – which in manuscripts I dare say is richer than any other in England.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Farewell my Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">&#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">Your obliged &#38; obedient</salute>
	   <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
