<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3954" type="letter"><head>3954. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1823-01-20">20 January 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. twenty four 1823/ To The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ CWWilliamsWynn<lb/>
Postmark: FREE/ 24 JA 24/ 1823<lb/>
Seal: black wax; design illegible<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-01-20">20 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823</date></dateline>
   
   <salute>My Dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">By the time this reaches you your holydays will be over, &#38; you will have settled once more to your routine of labour; which with all its discomforts, has some advantages over many, or most other employments. You are unequivocally doing good. You are not called, like the physician to prescribe for maladies which no human skill can remedy, &#38; witness sufferings of body &#38; of mind to which you can administer no alleviation, nor have you like the lawyer important interests of others dependent <del>xxxx</del> upon the success or failure of your management. You are neither in danger of losing a good cause, nor bound by your profession to do your utmost in favour of a bad one. It is better to deal with young blockheads (an illustrious trio for example) than with full grown knaves. And tho you are obliged to read the same books again &#38; again, they are some of the best books in the world. On the whole you may well be deemed a happy man, &#38; so I know you think &#38; feel yourself, – even tho the holydays are over.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> was to send you my first volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> as soon as it was ready for delivery. I have not heard from him since its publication. From other quarters I hear that the Whigs are up in arms at it,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 3–61, contained a great deal of criticism of the Whigs for opposing war with France, especially at pp. 55–58.</note> &#38; that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> in particular is very sore. It is his own fault if he as an individual chuses be offended; but I think he will not, for he is a very good natured man, &#38; I hope he will not, because personally I like him much, tho we have scarcely a single opinion in common. The presentation copy was acknowledged by <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Knighton</ref> officially, in the most flattering terms, &#38; what was more flattering <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> signified his approbation of the letter by writing upon it with his own hand “entirely approved. G.R.” – a special favour this. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has sent me a letter of <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Lord Colchesters</ref> in which he says “it is a Thucydidean History<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thucydides (c. 460–400 BC), Athenian historian, famous for his <title>History of the Peloponnesian War</title>, describing the war between Athens and Sparta.</note>, &#38; will last as long as our country &#38; our language.” – – I should not repeat this, if I did not think it would give you as much pleasure as it can possibly do me. Of any other likeness to Thucydides than what the title may support, I certainly never dreamt. But in composing the history of Brazil I certainly was not without a hope that my work would be hereafter to that wide portion of the new world, what Herodotuss history is now to the old.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) was the first English language history of that country; it might therefore be compared to Herodotus (c. 484–c. 425 BC), <title>The Histories</title> (c. 440 BC), widely recognised as the first work of history written in Europe. </note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> are now in London. – before they return to Cumberland they are to visit Ottery, – so you may possibly see them before you do me, as my movements may perhaps be in some degree influenced by theirs: that is, <del>x</del> if they return in any reasonable time, I may delay my departure, for the sake of taking <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> with me, who cannot well be spared during their absence.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not leave Keswick until 3 November 1823 and was accompanied by Edith May Southey.</note> You saw us in our grasshopper season:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lightfoot had visited Southey in July–August 1822, when grasshoppers were abundant. But this is also a reference to Aesop’s (c. 620–c. 560 BC), <title>Fables</title> and the story of the ‘Ant and the Grasshopper’, used to illustrate the value of hard work – the grasshopper sings all summer, while the ant stores up food for the winter. Southey implies that while he enjoyed himself in the summer months, like the grasshopper, he also worked hard in the winter.</note> – we are now as busy as bees in spring. But that holyday time was of signal service to me, no physician could have done for me what you did by leading me into a course of good exercise. I have kept it up till the last week when the snow detained me within doors: as soon as it disappears I shall be out again, &#38; endeavor up the tone of health which I have recovered.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My present pursuits are according to the humour of the day – or of the hour. The Book of the Church<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> chiefly occupies me, because that must be compleated before I can leave home. My second volume<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> waits for books from Spain<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has been more than twelvemonths in procuring, &#38; which are necessary for the first chapter. However I do not know that this will occasion any eventual delay, inasmuch as I get on with the other parts, &#38; may make the printers travel faster when it is in the press. The annual Ode<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Scotland, an Ode, Written after the King’s Visit to that Country. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureat’, <title>The Bijou: Or Annual of Literature and the Arts</title> (London, 1828), pp. 81–88. This poem was Southey’s annual New Year’s ode for 1823 in his role as Poet Laureate.</note> cost me some days, – it was to the praise &#38; glory of Scotland, &#38; will do me no discredit whenever it sees the light.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I meant to have seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#SetonBarbara">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bannister</ref> when I visited you. Perhaps the death of her husband<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">James Bannister (d. 1822), the Rector of Iddelsleigh in Devon, 1800–1822.</note> may make her remove from Devonshire. If she be in London I shall hear of her there.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> has refused to be made Bishop of Calcutta. So has <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Heber</ref>. Davison<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Davison (1777–1834; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman and occasional contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. His writings on the Poor Law had led to his receiving a number of preferments and he ended his career as a Prebendary of Worcester Cathedral 1826–1834. Southey’s information was correct, but eventually Reginald Heber was persuaded to become Bishop of Calcutta.</note> has the offer at this time, – &#38; I think he also will refuse it. The appointment I believe rests with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was President of the Board of Control, with ultimate authority over the East India Company’s possessions in India.</note> &#38; he will not find it easy to fill it. Whoever accepts it must consider himself as transported for life; there is no patronage annexed to it, &#38; the income is not <del>such as</del> one from whom any provision for a family can be made.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bishop of Calcutta’s salary was £5,000 p.a., but the expenses of the role were potentially huge.</note> Then there is the risque of climate, which is considerable for a man of middle age. No person therefore will go who has good prospects of preferment at home, – zeal must be the motive which induces any man to accept it, – &#38; it is extremely difficult to find this united with other qualifications.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">At present thank God we are all well. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> says he likes play so very much that he would rather not do his lessons, – he does them nevertheless as a necessary step towards becoming an Archbishop, which is the destination he has chosen. You would be amused to hear with what gravity he talks of Lambeth, &#38; Canterbury, – looking upon them as his in entail. The young ones speak of you &#38; enumerate you among their favourite visitors. The elders will be right glad to see you here again; – &#38; we talk of the places which you have not seen &#38; are to see on your next visit.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref> how young May<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802–1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August–2 September 1822, overlapping with Lightfoot’s visit. The younger John May was a student at Exeter College, Oxford.</note> is going on at Exeter. If I hear well of him I shall be glad to report it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">his father</ref>, – if not I shall say nothing. He is good-natured &#38; well meaning – but carries a light head &#38; no ballast. What a blessing it is to have a son upon whose good conduct you can rely with well-placed confidence! And this I trust is your case. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> desire their kind remembrances – present my kind regards to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot, – my goddaughter, &#38; my other unseen friends of you fireside<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806–1882), Southey’s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808–1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810–1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811–1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846–1855, Rector of Islip 1855–1881.</note> – &#38; believe me</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">My dear Lightfoot</salute>
	   <salute rend="indent2">Yours affectionately</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0">I drink your cyder in anticipation.</p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
