<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3959" type="letter"><head>3959. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-01-27">27 January 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 2xx<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 3x JA 30/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsements: 27 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823; 27. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 132–134 [in part].</note></head>
            
          <opener>  <salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very glad to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries’s</ref> appointment. By all that I have heard for many years past, a more unfit person than Arbuthnot<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Arbuthnot (1767–1850; <title>DNB</title>), Joint Secretary to the Treasury 1809–1823.</note> could not possibly have been in that situation: to get him out, &#38; have so efficient a man in his stead is indeed a great point. It is the very place in which I have wished to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>. – I hope &#38; trust now that such means as the existing laws afford will be steadily employed for checking the license of the press. The radical country papers continually lay themselves open to prosecution; &#38; I am certain that repeated prosecutions would go far toward stopping the mischief which they are doing at present, &#38; have so long been doing with impunity. A strict watch over these, &#38; over <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> would soon <del>surprize</del> &#60;suppress&#62;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The crossing out and the word ‘suppress’ inserted above are written in a different hand. ‘Suppress’ is also written in pencil, in the same unidentified hand, below the line.</note> them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I know nothing of the sale of my book.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has not written to me since it appeared. Only two opinions of it have reached me, except those of my friends, one in a complimentary letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littleton</ref> the member for Staffordshire, the other in a letter of <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbbotCharles">the ci-devant Grand Parleur</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘the former Great Speaker’.</note> which <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> sent me &#38; certainly nothing could be more flattering than what he said of it, that it was a Thucydidean history<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thucydides (c. 460–c. 400 BC), <title>History of the Pelopennesian War</title> (c. 431 BC).</note> which would last as long as our country &#38; our language! – I must confess however that I am not aware of any other resemblance than what the title suggests. Tho I have always flattered myself that my other historical work<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> might in more points than one <del>bear</del> &#60;be&#62; compared with Herodotus<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Herodotus (c. 484–c. 425 BC), <title>Histories</title> (c. 440 BC), usually seen as the first work of history.</note> &#38; will hereafter stand in the same relation to the history of that large portion of the new world, <del>xxx xx</del> as his work does to that of the old.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">We had an adventure this morning, which if poor Snivel<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The dog owned by Grosvenor Charles Bedford when he and Southey were boys.</note> had been living would have set up her bristles in great style. A foumart was caught in the back kitchen, – you may perhaps know it better by the name of polecat. It <del>was</del> &#60;is&#62; the first I ever saw or smelt, &#38; certainly it was in high odour. Poor Snivel! I &#60;still&#62; have <del>xx</del> the hairs which we cut from her tail thirty years ago; – &#38; if it were the fashion for men to wear lockets, in a locket they should be worn, for I never had a greater respect for any creature upon four legs than for poor Sni. – See how naturally men fall into relic-worship; – when I have preserved the memorials of that momentary whim so many years, – &#38; thro so many removals!</p>
	<p rend="indent1">To give you some notion of my heterogeneous reading, I am at this time regularly going thro Shakespere,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey possessed an undated eight-volume ‘Plays and Life’ of William Shakespeare (1564–1616; <title>DNB</title>), no. 2538 in the sale catalogue of his library (possibly Samuel Johnson’s (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) edition of 1765, though the title page was missing); and James Boswell (1778–1822; <title>DNB</title>) and Edmond Malone (1741–1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Plays and Poems of William Shakespeare, with the Corrections and Illustrations of Various Commentators: Comprehending a Life of the Poet, and an Enlarged History of the Stage</title> (1821), no. 2539 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Mosheims Ecc. History,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Lorenz von Mosheim (1693–1755), <title>An Ecclesiastical History, Antient and Modern, from the Birth of Christ, to the Beginning of the Present Century</title> (1758), translated by Archibald Maclaine (1722–1804; <title>DNB</title>), no. 2004 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Rabelais,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Le Rabelais Moderne, ou, Les Oeuvres de Maître François Rabelais</title> (1752), edited by Jean Frédéric Bernard (1680–1744), no. 2316 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Barrow,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Barrow (1630–1677; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Theological Works of Isaac Barrow</title> (1818), no. 118 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &#38; Aitzema,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieuwe van Aitzema (1600–1669) <title>Sakem van Staet en Oorlogh in ende Omtrent de Vereenigde Nederlanden</title> (1655–1671). Southey possessed a later edition and continuation of 1669–1699 in 11 vols, no. 214 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> a Dutch Historian of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century – in eleven huge full folios. The Dutchman I take after supper with my punch. You are not to suppose that I read his work verbatim, – I look at every page, &#38; peruse those parts which relate to my own subjects, – or which excite curiosity: &#38; a great deal I have found there</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I see <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">T. Courtenays</ref> letter in the Courier today,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">On 24 January 1823, Courtney had written to the Editor of the <title>Morning Post</title>. His letter was published there on 27 January and widely reprinted, including in the <title>Courier</title>, where Southey read it. Courtney’s letter confirmed a report in the <title>Courier</title>, 23 January 1823, that he was not the author of the anonymous pamphlet <title>Administration of the Affairs of Great Britain, Ireland, and their Dependencies, 1823</title> (1823).</note> &#38; wish he had given as the reason which induced him to write a desire of showing the public with what impudence the demagogues of the day make positive assertions at mere hap-hazard</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have not heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Anubis</ref> since he was mounted upon wheels, &#38; has employed eight legs to save the work of two.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey had bought a carriage, so the eight legs of the two horses that drew his carriage were saving the work previously done by his two legs.</note> They will save mine sometimes &#38; facilitate some of my visits in town.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">We have not seen the face of the earth here for fifteen days – a longer time than it has ever been covered with snow since I came into the country. I growl at it every day. – It seems a long while since I have heard from you</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
	  <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
 <lb/>           
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1823-01-27">27 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
