<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3962" type="letter"><head>3962. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-02-10">9–[10] February 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/>
Endorsement: 9. Feb. 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-02-09">Sunday 9 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
	<p rend="indent1">The blockade having been broken up, three mails have arrived to day, – that of the day being still due. They bring me your letter by which I am glad to perceive that this hard winter has not frozen up all the ink at the Exchequer, as I began to apprehend.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> thanks you for her pocket book &#38; so would <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> if she were here, instead of being in London at this time, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">her mother</ref>, visiting <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">So the Whigs are clamorous for war in behalf of the Spaniards!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In Spain the liberal Constitution of 1812 had been restored by a military revolt in 1820. France was preparing to invade Spain to restore royal absolutism and the Whigs were urging the government to pressurise France not to intervene.</note> I hope some person will remind them of their sympathy for the Spaniards during the last contest. Oh that my second volume<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> were ready at this time, for their sake. It stirs my gall to hear <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> speak about them as he does now,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In a widely publicised speech in the House of Commons on 4 February 1823, Brougham had stated that if France invaded Spain ‘our intervention in some shape would become unavoidable’.</note> he having used all his powers to vilify &#38; traduce them formerly, &#38; make this country abandon them to their fate.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham had often been critical of the British intervention in the Peninsular War 1808–1813.</note> – I will dress up his own words for him, which will prove as comfortable a dressing as the garment which Deianira sent to Hercules.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek myth, Deianira was the wife of the hero Hercules. She unwittingly killed Hercules by giving him a shirt smeared with the toxic blood of the centaur Nessus.</note></p>
	<p rend="indent1">The weather has confined me to the house, a full month, with the intervention of two or three days. I am not the better for this. It is now thawing fast, &#38; I hope to get abroad again, &#38; recover my good condition.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Will you send <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>, under favour of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right Honour</ref>, a cake of ultra-marine,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A dried bloc of pigment for use in watercolour painting. Ultramarine is a deep blue colour.</note> which she stands greatly in need of for certain drawings now in hand. When you come to us next summer – as I trust it is written in the Book of Fate<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destoyer</title> (1801), Book 11, line 7.</note> that you will do, – you will be pleased with her dexterity of hand.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If ears were transferable, I would lend you one excellent one, – &#38; sleep from that time forward with the deaf side upwards. However it will be far better if <ref type="m" target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Sir Antony</ref> can set you up with two of your own. I am glad to see his name in your letter, for the sake of old times.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	<date when="1823-02-10">Monday</date></p>
	<p rend="indent1">I thought to have filled my paper this evening but a sick headache disables me, – &#38; I will not detain it, because of the receipt, the delay of the QR<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), was not until published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> will render its account very accep<del>x</del>table.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
	 <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
