<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3991" type="letter"><head>3991. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-03-28">28 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham,/ Surrey<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmarks: E/ 31 MR 31/18xx; 10 F. NOON xx/ MR. 31/ 1823<lb/>
Seal: red wax; design illegible <lb/>
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 229. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished. </note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1823-03-28">28 March. 1823</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent1">I have been writing to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> to procure <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom’s</ref> credentials for Canada, without delay. A vessel sails from Maryport, on the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of April, in which he talks of embarking, to reconnoitre the land, &#38; prepare the way for his family.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In fact, Tom Southey sailed from Whitehaven on 20 April 1823 on the brig <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and reached Quebec on 27 May. He investigated emigrating to Canada but decided against this option. </note> That there was no other possible course for him to pursue, I have long perceived, without overlooking the difficulties in this. But it is a course, which in his circumstances I should certainly long ago have pursued. This however does not lighten the weight <del>which such</del> with which it lies upon my spirits.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Yesterday I heard from Knox,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John William Knox (1784–1862), clergyman, scholar and usher at Westminster School 1806–1821.</note> on his arrival in London. Perhaps you will have seen him ere this reaches you; as he announced his intention of walking to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> as soon as he should have settled himself in town quarters. From him I hear that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> was fifth in the challenge; – if so, there is little doubt of his getting in.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill had taken ‘The Challenge’, a gruelling examination at Westminster School to select the school’s King’s Scholars. This position had considerable advantages, including the right to proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Trinity College, Cambridge, or Christ Church, Oxford. Usually, ten boys were chosen each year, so Edward Hill was guaranteed a place.</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">I cannot yet see the time of my departure,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was planning a journey to London but did not leave until 3 November 1823.</note> but am working strenuously towards that end. As usual my book<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> grows under my hands, &#38; what was intended for a small duodecimo, will be a full sized octavo volume; – - a good &#38; useful one, I really hope.
                  Probably I shall bring some work with me to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. So many persons have asked me about Spanish affairs, that I have asked <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> whether he wishes me to take up the subject; if he replies in the affirmative, I shall begin the paper here, &#38; finish it under your roof, – which will be no trifling advantage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">When I am in town, it is my intention to talk with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about printing a selection of my papers from the Q.R.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">This project became <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title> (1832).</note> If they were duly arranged, with restorations, &#38; some corrections &#38; additions, they might bring me both credit &#38; profit. In this forthcoming number there is an account of the Theophilanthropists in France, introductory to a sketch of the rise &#38; progress of Infidelity.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Upon reading it consecutively in the proofs, I was glad that I had written it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> has just compleated his historical labours<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sharon Turner, <title>History of England</title> (1814–1823), no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – &#38; in consequence I shall begin a series of papers upon English history, which after they have served their main purpose in the QR may form a correspondent volume to the B. of the Church.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write these articles for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, or ‘The Book of the State’, which he planned as a companion to his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref> looks upon the affairs of Spain as I do, without a wish to throw into either scale, – &#38; without hope. Wishes, &#38; strong ones I should have, were the French a nation who could be trusted: but who can expect honour or principle from them! – One of the new Sp. Ministers Flores Estrada<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Alvaro Florez Estrada (1765–1853), Spanish lawyer, politician and journalist. He played a prominent role in politics in 1808–1814, before going into exile, only returning after the revolution of 1820. At this time he was not a Minister, but he was a member of the Cortes. He was from the mountainous area of Asturias.</note> I met once at <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Goodens</ref>, – a tremendous fellow he is, hard as the iron of his own mountains. I see nothing but utter ruin for that poor country, – in the total destruction of all property that can be destroyed, – a war of banditti over the whole land; a government supported by a foreign force, &#38; wholly without resources.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">As for any danger of our being involved in the war, I do not dream of it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#38; the children -</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>

	<postscript><p rend="indent1">The R. Irish Academy have sent me another tail to my name.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been elected an Honorary Member of the Royal Irish Academy (founded 1785), a body to promote Irish scientific and cultural activities and studies.</note></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
