<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4001" type="letter"><head>4001. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1823-04-18">18 April 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 385–386.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1823-04-18">April 18. 1823.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Neville,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I did hope that I should have been on my travels at this time; but it is with me in most of my writings<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was writing his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824). It was still uncompleted when he left Keswick for London in November 1823.</note> as with one who builds a house, and finds when he is in the middle of it that the cost thereof will exceed the estimate twofold. My work grows under my hands; and whether it be the natural effect of increasing years, or arises from any cause to which it might be more agreeable to impute it, certain it is that I compose much more slowly than I was wont to when younger. I shall not be able to leave home in less than a month from this time; and if it be equally convenient to you, it will, I think, be rather more so to me, if I take Norwich on my way home, in the middle of July.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">This has been a severe season, and you are in the coldest part of England. Next winter let me recommend to you what I have used myself for many years – a sleeved waistcoat of washing–leather.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">An old term for chamois leather.</note> I believe no other mode of clothing will protect the chest so well. As soon as the cold weather sets in I take to it; and I laid it aside for this year only last week.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother, the Captain</ref>, is on his way to Canada, to form a judgment upon the spot, upon the expediency of transplanting his family thither, in the spring of next year, to a grant of lands. He departed on Wednesday last.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey sailed from Whitehaven on 20 April 1823 on the brig <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and reached Quebec on 27 May. He was considering emigrating to Canada but decided not to do so after visiting the country.</note> This business has occupied much of my time, and will long continue to occupy too much of my thoughts.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Our climate is, in some respects, better than yours. We have had three weeks of delightful weather, though with easterly winds. The last two days there have been slight rains, and to–day there is snow on the mountains. From London I hear complaints of the cold, and the want of sunshine.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You will see a paper of mine upon the Rise and Progress of Infidelity, in the next “Q.R.”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> When the new edition of “Baxter” is completed,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Puritan clergyman, Richard Baxter (1615–1691; <title>DNB</title>). Southey may have heard of the forthcoming <title>The Practical Works of the Rev. Richard Baxter with a Life of the Author and a Critical Examination of his Writings</title> (1830), edited by William Orme (1787–1830; <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write on the subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I mean to take that opportunity of drawing up an account of his life. At present I am busy with “Cranmer” and his fellow worthies.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Strype (1643–1737; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memorials of the Most Reverend Father in God Thomas Cranmer, Sometime Lord Archbishop of Canterbury: Wherein the History of the Church, and the Reformation of it during the Primacy of the said Archbishop are Greatly Illustrated; and Many Singular Matters Relating Thereunto, now first Published</title> (1694). The book was reprinted by Oxford University Press in 1812 and was no. 2754 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. It focused on Thomas Cranmer (1489–1556; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1533–1555.</note> The Roman Catholics will not like my book; nor will it be more agreeable to the Dissenters. The chapter which is likely to produce most impression will be that relating to the destruction of the Church establishment during the great rebellion.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 347–467, which covered the Civil War of 1642–1651 and the parliamentary regime up to 1660.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you, my dear Neville,</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Yours affectionately,</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
