<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4013" type="letter"><head>4013. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1823-05-08">8 May 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re_</hi>/ Florence/ Italy<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE; CHAMBERY; CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTERA DA GENOA<lb/>
Postmarks: [partial] F/ 23; 28/ MAGGIA<lb/>
MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 40. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 388–390.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-05-08">8 May. 1823</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent1">Your letter arrived this day, &#38; yesterday I received &#38; answered one from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare</ref> concerning your Dialogues.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> The purport of his was to say that <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">Taylor</ref> (a man I believe very superior to most of his trade) demurred upon grounds of principle to certain passages, &#38; had, after some previous correspondence with him proposed that either I or <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> should see the proofs, &#38; if we approved of what he condemnd he would be bound by our decision. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is gone to the Netherlands, &#38; I replied without hesitation that I would most willingly take upon myself this responsibility, &#38; <del>expunge whatever</del> act for you in this matter as you would act by me, – taking care that wherever there was an omission the place should be marked.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was desired in December to send you my own<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821); <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832); <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821), originally intended to be part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> and first printed in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i–l; and a combined second edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) and <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814), published as <title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen Aulica, Written in 1814, on the Arrival of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821).</note> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> books,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth, <title>Ecclesiastical Sketches</title> (1822) and <title>Memorials of a Tour on the Continent, 1820</title> (1822).</note> &#38; Humboldts Travels,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander von Humboldt (1769–1859), <title>Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent During the Years 1799–1804</title> (1814–1826), no. 1463 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; and <title>Researches Concerning the Institutions and Monuments of the Ancient Inhabitants of America, with Descriptions and Views of Some of the Most Striking Scenes in the Cordilleras</title> (1814).</note> – he has never told me by what vessel they are sent, which he ought to have done, – but they should have reached you long ere this.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I long to see these Dialogues. Upon the question of Catholicism we shall entirely agree. There is a chapter upon the subject in my forth coming view of our Ecclesiastical History,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 10 of <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 292–330.</note> – &#38; whatever effect we may produce upon those who are more than moderately inclined to this base &#38; grovelling superstition (as you say <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hare</ref> is) I think we shall produce some upon those who at present are less than moderately acquainted with its real character. Yet I regret some of its parts.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your specimen is delightful. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare</ref> indeed speaks of the whole just in such terms as I should expect it to deserve. Upon one great question, that of the improvement of nations thro their governments, I <del>believe</del> think that were I in Italy I should approach nearer to you, &#38; were you in England, or in America you would draw nearer to me. The struggle at present <del>if</del> is between two extremes, both so bad, that if a wish of mine could incline the beam, I should not know in which scale to <del>x</del> cast it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My first volume is wormwood to the Foxites, &#38; not more palatable to the worshippers of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitt.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). It contained much criticism of the Whigs, whose leader had been Charles James Fox (1749–1806; <title>DNB</title>), for opposing British intervention to help repel the Spanish invaders; but it also did not support every decision made by the government, whose supporters had been led by William Pitt (1759–1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783–1801, 1804–1806.</note> I think there is not one feeling expressed in it with which you will not concur. The <del>op</del> single opinion in which you are likely to dissent from me is one which is derived from observation, – in opposition to my wishes, – that old despotisms can better be modified by a single will than by a popular assembly; &#38; that in such countries as Spain &#38; Portugal, a despotic minister (like Pombal)<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquis of Pombal (1699–1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750–1777.</note> acting in conformity to the spirit of the age, is the reformer to be wished for. I would have governments reformed, as Cranmer<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Cranmer (1489–1556; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1533–1555 and architect of the English Reformation.</note> would in all points, &#38; did in most, reform the Church of England. But let individuals &#38; communities err as they may, it is apparent that upon the great scale mankind are improving. But this too may appear differently in Italy from what it does in England.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am glad to hear of your <del>England</del> children.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnold Savage Landor (1818–1871); Julia Elisabeth Savage Landor (1820–1884); and Walter Savage Landor (1822–1899). They were followed by Charles Savage Landor (1825–1917).</note> Till we become parents we know not the treasures of our own nature, – &#38; what we then discover may make us believe that there yet latent affections &#38; faculties which another state of existence may develope. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My boy</ref> is now beginning his fifth year, &#38; is thank God, flourishing &#38; promising as I could wish. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My eldest daughter</ref> is a young woman, taller than <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her mother</ref>. Time has set his mark upon me, but lays his hand gently, – as yet he has taken nothing from me but the inclination for writing poetry, &#38; threatens nothing at present but my grinders, which he is attacking by regular [MS torn]proaches, sapping &#38; mining. Last summer I was severely shaken by an annual catarrh which for many years has taken up its quarters with me for the whole summer, &#38; last year effected a lodgement in my chest. Since it departed I have used more exercise &#38; a more generous diet, &#38; have kept in better condition during the winter than for the last seven years.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My Colloquies<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> have long been stationary. Yours will give them a fillip, – as far as they have proceeded I am well pleased with them. My Book of the Church will be published in about ten weeks, – perhaps in time to be forwarded to you with your own book.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
					<signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
