<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4027" type="letter"><head>4027. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-06-04">4 June 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmarks: E/ 7 JU 7/ 1823; [partial] F.NOON10/ JU.7/ 1823<lb/>
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 232. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-06-04">4 June. 1823.</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent0">My movements would be as regular as the habits of my life, if I had a regular income, &#38; not a contingent one. My ways &#38; means for the next six months depend upon this Book,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> &#38; tho it is by no means likely that doubling its size will increase its profits in the same proportion, it was nevertheless quite necessary to extend it. You will not think my time ill employed when you see it. Ten sheets of the second volume are printed, &#38; the printer has about five more in his hands. I am now in Elizabeths reign,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 252–312, covering the reign of Elizabeth I (1533–1603; Queen of England 1558–1603; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#38; nearly at the end of it, – there is about the third part of a volume to write, – but I will not pretend to say when I shall have compleated it.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">This work has lead me thro the whole of Strypes voluminous collections,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Anglican clergyman and historian, John Strype (1643–1737; <title>DNB</title>), whose lives of sixteenth-century divines were important sources for Church history. Southey acquired the twenty-three volume Clarendon Press edition of Strype’s <title>Works</title> (1816–1824), no. 2753 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#38; there, of course, I have noted many things which bear upon other subjects. I find there that Osorius, when he replied to Haddon’s answer to his attack upon the English Church, inserted in his book some caricatures of Haddon: – the earliest mention of such things which has fallen in my way, – &#38; therefore I should like to see the book.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Jerónimo Osório da Fonseca (1506–1580) in <title>Epistola Hieronymi Osorii ad Serenissimam Elisabetem Angliae Reginam</title> (1562) had urged Elizabeth I (1533–1603; Queen of England, 1558–1603; <title>DNB</title>) to return England to Catholicism. Walter Haddon (1515–1572; <title>DNB</title>) had replied with <title>Against Ierome Osorius Bishopp of Siluane in Portugall and against his Slaunderous Inuectiues: An Aunswere Apoligeticall: for the Necessary Defence of the Euangelicall Doctine and Veritie</title> (1563) and Osório responded with <title>Amplissimi atque Doctissimi Viri D. Hieronymi Osorii, Espiscopi Sylvensis, in Gualterum Haddonum Magistrum Libellorum Supplicum apud Clarissimam Principem Helisabetham Angliae, Franciae, &#38; Hiberniae Reginam</title> (1567). However, Strype, <title>Works</title>, 23 vols (Oxford, 1816–1824), XV, Part I, p. 96 (<title>Annals of the Reformation</title>, Vol. III, Part I), asserted it was one Emanuel d’Almada who wrote a book attacking Haddon, which included ‘certain ugly pictures’ of Haddon.</note> Very possibly it may be found at Lambeth,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Library of the Archbishops of Canterbury at Lambeth Palace, London.</note> &#38; there I will look for it.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">The Marquis</ref> has written to me with a large request for autographs I will answer his demand shortly. – We will talk about <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Erroll</ref> when we meet. I reckon very little upon my interest anywhere, except with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, – &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, I am sorry to say, has done me no good, by presuming upon it, without my knowledge. But it is possible that if the same persons should be in power a few years hence, a situation might be found for him in one of the public offices, if it were thought desirable. I think I can reckon, thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries’s</ref> good offices. If this destination should be thought of, Westminster would be better than Winchester, were it only as being nearer home, &#38; nothing would be gained by his going into College.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Errol Hill went to Winchester College and became a clergyman, rather than Westminster School, followed by a Civil Service career.</note></p>
                  <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, who makes excellent use of her fingers in all ways, has painted a pair of hand-screens for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>, which I am to bring with me. She is an excellent example of how little school-education is worth for girls, inasmuch as she can do every thing which is taught at schools without ever having been at one.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">I have heard nothing concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref><note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Gifford was ill and there was considerable speculation about the future of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> except what you tell me. It can never do for <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to let his review be kept in this state of abeyance. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">The great man</ref> himself is gracious toward me, – which implies that he is satisfied with the success of the history,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> &#38; in good hopes from the next adventure. He manifests this graciousness by sending some of his new publications, as the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> manifest a different temper by not doing so. They are out of humour at finding the history has proved a good concern after (if <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> account be accurate) they had shuffled out of it, thinking it was a day after the fair. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me Batty’s Campaign in the Pyrenees, of some use as a book, &#38; much interest for the prints.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Batty (1789–1848), <title>Campaign of the Left Wing of the Allied Army, in the Western Pyrenees and South of France, in the Years 1813–1814: under Field-Marshal the Marquess of Wellington</title> (1823), no. 181 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> I have received <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> at last.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey’s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &#38;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> The view of Cintra I think must have been taken from the road below your house.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill’s summer home at Sintra, where Southey had lived June–October 1800.</note></p>
                  <p rend="indent1">My annual cold has made its appearance, &#38; I am resisting it, according to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi></ref> directions. To day I am on the tonic system, fortifying with bark<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Willow bark, a common cure for colds and headaches.</note> in hope of keeping it off tomorrow.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">We are busy with work-people. The strangers have not yet begun to show themselves, &#38; in consequence of my own protracted movements we expect no guests. The only arrival I have had has been the welcome one of two hogsheads of cider, from my old fellow collegian <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref>. They stand beside a barrel of <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref> strong beer: &#38; both are the very best of their kind.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> – to the boys &#38; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillGeorgiana">Georgiana</ref></p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
