<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4028" type="letter"><head>4028. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">John Taylor</ref>], <date when="1823-06-07">7 June 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14176. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-06-07">7 June 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">According to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Julius Hares</ref> desire I forward to you the Dialogue which I this day received from him. – <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A section of Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> I do not believe that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> himself would argue seriously against prayer. He has only made Middleton speak in character,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue XVIII in Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 345–362, between Conyers Middleton (1683–1750; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman widely suspected of unorthodox views, and Antonio di Marco Magliabechi (1633–1714), bibliophile and librarian to the Grand Dukes of Tuscany, 1673–1714. At his death, Conyers left a manuscript on the ‘inefficacy of prayer’, which Landor used as the starting point for a discussion on the subject between his characters.</note> &#38; chosen the topic for the sake of introducing what he has heard in Italy. – I have drawn a pencil thro two passages which might give offence.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear which passages Southey deleted.</note> The rest will provoke a smile at Italian superstition, – but it will shake the reasonable faith of no man.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very glad these Dialogues have found a publisher who appreciates their worth. It is not to the credit of this generation that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> who will hereafter be regarded as one of its brightest ornaments should be so little known &#38; honoured among his contemporaries.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">I remain Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Yrs obediently</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
