<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4051" type="letter"><head>4051. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-08-08">8 August 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ xxx<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 11 AU 11/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsement: 8. Aug<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-08-08">8 Aug 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I pray you, pay my Tailors bill for me, poor Hydes<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Hyde (d. 1820) had been Southey’s tailor in London.</note> successor, M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Callan<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">J. McCallan &#38; Co., tailors of Leicester Square, London.</note> at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 28 Leicester Square. The amount is £10.1.0. When you hear that it bears date in June 1821 &#38; that the only new clothes I have had since that time consist of two pairs of Cockbaine<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cockbaine (1786–1873), a Keswick draper and tailor.</note> built pantaloons, you will not think that I am beggaring myself by any wasteful expenditure in dress. It is true that my wardrobe stands now in need of replenishing. But you told me some time ago you could introduce me to a <hi rend="ital">Hider</hi> who charges less that £4 8 for “a coat sup extra black cloth”, &#38; therefore I will rather wait till this Modere<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘moderate’ – a term used of a Spaniard whose politics were centrist, but here for a tailor whose charges were moderate.</note> can take my measure, than send an order to M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Callan who charges thus highly, &#38; puts me in a dandy cut.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">You will not be sorry to hear that I have at length pretty well got rid of my cold, &#38; of its consequences. Nothing I believe is wanting to bring me again into good condition, but the company of some charitable friend who would be willing to take me as his guide among the mountains. We have had the coldest summer, &#38; one of the wettest that I ever remember: yet in spite of the weather if you could give yourself a holyday we would enjoy ourselves heartily both out of doors &#38; within. You know that the journey from this place to London has been shortened so that the traveller arrives in town to supper on the second night.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Rumpelstilzchen<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">One of the Greta Hall cats.</note> has been poorly, but is now in better health, &#38; was yesterday created a Baron for good service against the rats. Since I wrote to you concerning this worthy Cat, a patronymic has been added to his name: for upon discovering that he was born in the house of a certain humble minister of the law, I immediately named him Macbum.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the son (‘mac’ in Gaelic) of a bum bailiff (a bailiff who was empowered to collect debts). </note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> is delighted with my description of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref><note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Cataract of Lodore, Described in Rhymes for the Nursery, By One of the Lake Poets’, published in Joanna Baillie (ed.), <title>A Collection of Poems, Chiefly Manuscript, And From Living Authors</title> (London, 1823), pp. 280–283. The poem describes the Lodore Falls, formed by the beck from Watendlath Tarn, as it descends towards the southern end of Derwentwater.</note> he says “it is a fierce poem &#38; makes a noise like the forge-hammer.”</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Grosvenor</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">yrs as ever</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
