<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4095" type="letter"><head>4095. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">Mary Ann Watts Hughes</ref>], <date when="1823-11-27">[27 November 1823]</date> 
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc MS 3826. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished. <lb/>
Dating note: Dating from content. The letter was written on Thursday 27 November 1823, the week before Southey went to hear Rowland Hill preach at Blackfriars Road on 30 November 1823.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><date when="1823-11-27">Thursday Afternoon.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Madam</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I thank you for your call, – for your enquiry, &#38; for all your kindness. And I shall have great pleasure in waiting on you at 5 on Wednesday next, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>, who (I must not forget the charge,) desires me to send her <hi rend="ital">love</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has intreated me to make explanations &#38; excuses &#38; apologies &#38;c for him to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes. By some mismanagement the paper<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), Mary Anne Watts Hughes’s son, had reviewed ‘Washington Irving’s Tales’. His article finally appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 473–487, published 11 March 1825. </note> was made to give place in the number where it ought to have appeared, – &#38; he could not <del>insist upon it</del> require its insertion afterwards, because it praised so highly a work of his publishing, just when the freshness of that work had past away,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray was the English publisher of Washington Irving (1783–1859), <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.</title> (1820).</note> that it would have looked as if the review were made subservient to his interests as a tradesman. He introduced the subject upon my mentioning M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes’s name, &#38; requested me very earnestly to say – how much the matter vexed him, &#38; how truly glad he should be to receive any other communications from the same hand. – I am sure he spoke sincerely, <del>xxx</del> I think the apology as far as he is concerned, a valid one, – &#38; I shall be glad to think M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> H. is one of my coadjutors.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In other words, both John Hughes and Southey were writers for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">On Sunday I shall certainly try my fortune in Blackfriars road,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was planning to hear Rowland Hill (1744–1833; <title>DNB</title>), a popular evangelical preacher who was not formally attached to any denomination. He built Surrey Chapel in Blackfriars Road, Southwark, in 1782–1783 and preached there when he was in London.</note> if the weather will permit. </p>
            <p rend="indent1">With best respects to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref>,</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">I remain</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">Dear Madam</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">very truly &#38; thankfully yours</salute>
				<signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
