<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4096" type="letter"><head>4096. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1823-11-28">28 November 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ Post Office/ Bath<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 7 OC 7/ 1823<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


   <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-11-28">28 Nov. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
   <p rend="indent1">Were I to delay answering your letter till I could do it in comfortable leisure, Heaven only knows when it would be answered. I must therefore <del>xxxxxx</del> rely upon your goodness for excusing a brief &#38; hurried reply, – &#38; proceed at once to state all I know upon the points concerning which you inquire.</p>
   <p rend="indent1">When I wrote to you concerning a monument for <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to William Peachy, 4 October 1823, Letter 4066, discussing a proposed memorial tablet in St Kentigern’s church, Crosthwaite, for John Edmondson.</note> it was in consequence of a conversation with <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref>, to whom I started the subject, at a time when he was thinking of proposing it to me. We did not know that the same feeling had been expressed on the day of the funeral, by the persons who had been invited to it, &#38; that <del>each of</del> some twenty of them had immediately subscribed half a guinea each, the intention being that the subscription should be limited to that sum. I have heard since my arrival in town that that intention is given up, that <ref type="m" target="people.html#StangerJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stanger</ref> has put down his name for 2 £, &#38; his sons<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Stanger (1796–1866) and Joshua Stanger (1801–1854), both of whom had gone into their father’s old business in London.</note> there for 1 £ each. &#38; this is all I know. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dentons<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758–1820), Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1786–1820.</note> monument cost something about forty pounds. I do not suppose that the persons who manage the affair (whoever they are) will think of incurring any unnecessary expence, a public testimony to the worth of a man most exemplary in his station is what is wanted &#38; intended; – a matter of gratitude &#38; feeling, – not of ostentation, – something which may hold up an example to the living, by recording the merits of the dead.</p>
         <p rend="indent1">I know something of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnold who was a fellow of Oriel,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Arnold (1795–1842; <title>DNB</title>), the educational reformer and Headmaster of Rugby School 1828–1842. He was a Fellow of Oriel College, Oxford 1815–1819, and had visited Southey in Keswick in 1818; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 2 October 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3199.</note> &#38; is associated with a brother of Professor Bucklands (your friend) in an institution at Laleham, nearly opposite Staines.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Arnold’s sister, Frances Arnold (1790–1863), had married in 1816 the clergyman John Buckland (1785–1859), officiating Minister at St Mary’s, Hampton, Middlesex. The brothers-in-law set up a school in Laleham, Middlesex 1819–1828. John Buckland was the brother of William Buckland (1784–1856; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman, Reader in Mineralogy 1813–1856 and Geology 1818–1856 at the University of Oxford, and Britain’s foremost geologist.</note> Buckland attends to the younger pupils in one house, &#38; Arnold to the elder in his own. What his terms are I do not know, except that they are high, – as may be expected from a man is a scholar of the very first order. Should you think seriously of placing Charles Edward<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807–1833), the younger of Peachy’s two stepsons.</note> there, it will be necessary to ascertain whether there be a vacancy for him, &#38; whether M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnold would take him for so short a term.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I know nothing of the three clergymen<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> whom you mention.</p>
   <p rend="indent1">You will easily imagine in what a giddy whirl of occupations &#38; engagement I am involved. I shall not feel at rest till I get into the mail coach for my return, – I am now writing before breakfast &#38; expect Lady Malet &#38; the Miss Charters<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, a prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters.</note> to call at half past ten that we go together to the Central School,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Central School in Baldwin’s Gardens, off Gray’s Inn Road, London, was a showpiece for Andrew Bell’s monitorial system of teaching.</note> where <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> expects us. My table is covered with notes, – which must be answered, – my cloak-bag is full of papers tost in higgledy-piggledy by <ref type="m" target="people.html#DoyleCharlesWilliam">Sir Charles Doyle</ref>, which I must take out &#38; bundle up, – the said cloak bag being in requisition because <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> &#38; I shift our quarters this afternoon from hence to Palace Yard, where we shall pass a week with <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi></ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>. I am to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Sir Humphry Davy</ref> &#38; Davies Gilbert<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Davies Gilbert (1767–1839; <title>DNB</title>), the Cornish engineer, author, antiquarian, early patron of Humphry Davy and MP for Helston 1804–1806, and Bodmin 1806–1832. Southey may have met him before, at Bristol in 1799–1802, in connection with Davy and the Pneumatic Institution. </note> there at dinner, while <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> goes to the play with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Charles Wynn</ref> &#38; her daughters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Williams Wynn had five daughters: Charlotte (1807–1869); Mary (1808–1869); Harriet (1812–1878); Emma (1814–1824) and Sidney (1818–1867). She also had two sons, Watkin (1816–1832) and Charles (1822–1896).</note></p>
   <p rend="indent1">Our kindest remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> &#38; Charles Edward. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> would desire his; did he know how I am employed –</p>
   <closer><salute rend="indent2">farewell my dear Sir</salute>
      <salute rend="indent3">&#38; believe me</salute>
      <salute rend="indent4">always most truly yours</salute>
				<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
