<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4115" type="letter"><head>4115. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>], <date when="1824-01-02">2 January 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 2. Anne St/ Mr Southey/ January 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1824/ ansd Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ Reqs work from Spain<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 89143/1/1/143/5. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">15. Queen Anne Street</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-01-02">Jany. 2. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> A man of letters may ask a favour of you in aid of his pursuits, without danger of being thought impertinent &#38; obtrusive. For two years I have vainly been endeavouring to obtain two Spanish works, which I am led to believe contain very interesting particulars relating to the <del>Spanish</del> &#60;Peninsular&#62; War. The one is a history of the war in Catalonia, the other anecdotes of the chief Catalan officers, – supplementary to it, both by Francisco da Oliveira.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help.</note> I have sought for them every where, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has been equally unsuccesful in his endeavours, – owing in great part to the late troubled state of Spain, the books having been published at Seville, &#38; therefore for some time not obtainable at Madrid. – May I request that you would procure them for me thro the Foreign Office, – the channel thro which I used to obtain documents from Spain, before <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">my poor correspondent in that country</ref>, fell into disgrace with that miserable Ferdinand,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833). He had restored royal absolutism in 1814, banishing or imprisoning many Spanish liberals.</note> was banished from the court, &#38; died.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I should have waited on you, <del>&#38;</del> asked this request in person, if I had not understood that you were confined by indisposition since the day on which I was disappointed in the hope of meeting you at <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn’s</ref>.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">I have the honour to remain Sir</salute>
           <salute rend="indent3"> with sincere respect</salute>
           <salute rend="indent4"> Your obliged &#38; obedient servant</salute>
           <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
