<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4141" type="letter"><head>4141. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-02-22">22 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: [partial] E/ 22 FE 2x/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: 22. Feb<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1824.<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 167–170 [misdated 23 February 1824].</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-02-22">22 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date>
            
            <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  Here then I am, nothing the worse for having been wheeled over fifteen hundred miles in the course of fifteen weeks. I no longer feel the effect of motion in my head, nor of jolting in my tail. I have taken again to my old coat &#38; old shoes: <del>xxxxga &#60;enjoy&#62; as I used to do the wholesome indulgence of xxxxxxx xxx after dinner</del> – dine at the reasonable hour of four, &#60;enjoy as I used to do, the wholesome indulgence of a nap after dinner,&#62; drink tea at six, sup at half-past nine, – <del>xx</del> spend half an hour over a sober folio &#38; a glass of black-currant rum with warm water &#38; sugar, &#38; then to bed. Days seemed like weeks while I was away, so many &#38; so various were my engagements: &#38; now that I am settling to my wonted round of occupations the week <del>seems</del> &#60;passes&#62; like a day. If my life is not like that of the <hi rend="ital">prisca gens mortalium</hi>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘the ancient race of man’: Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65–27 BC), <title>Epode</title> 2, line 2.</note> it is quite as happy <del>xxx</del>, – &#38; when you hear <hi rend="ital">Qui fit Mecaenas</hi><note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘How does it happen Maecenas’: Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65–27 BC), <title>Satire</title> 1.1 is titled, ‘Qui fit, Maecenas’. Its subject is the nature of human contentment.</note> quoted you may reply that you know one man at least, &#60;who is&#62; perfectly contented with his lot.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I was charged by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> particularly to describe to her how <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref> looked when the fatal horn should first be exhibited to her astonished eyes.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A kind of bugle that Southey had bought as a joke, as his sister-in-law Sara Coleridge had a horror of loud noises.</note> The task which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> imposed upon me, my powers of language are not sufficient to discharge. The horn, I must tell you was made useful, as a case for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> lithographic print of Warwick Castle.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Westall, ‘A View of Warwick Castle’ (1823).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Dogstar</ref> packed <del>up</del> it carefully up with my umbrella in brown paper, so that no person could possibly discover what the mysterious package contained; &#38; great curiosity was excited when it was first observed at home. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> stood by (I sent for her) while the unpacking was deliberately performed. The string was untied, – not cut: I unbound it round after round; – &#38; then methodically took off the paper. The first emotion was an expression of contemptuous disappointment at sight of – the umbrella, which I was careful should be first discovered. But when the horn appeared, the fatal horn,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A well-used phrase in British poetry; for example, William Somervile (1675–1742; <title>DNB</title>), Fable 14, ‘The Fortune Hunter’, Canto 5, line 295.</note> then oh then – </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Grosvenor it was an expression of dolorous dismay which Richter or Wilkie<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Richter (1772–1847; <title>DNB</title>) and David Wilkie (1785–1841; <title>DNB</title>), painters who were well known for portraying domestic scenes.</note> could hardly represent unless they had witnessed it, – it was at once so piteous &#38; so comical. Up went the brows, down went the chin, &#38; yet the face appeared to widen as much as it was elongated, by an undefinable drawing of the lips which seemed to flatten all the features I know not whether sorrow or resentment predominated in the eyes, – sorrow, as, in the Dutch manner, she pitied herself; – or anger when she thought of me, &#38; of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">your brother</ref> from whom I received the precious gift – &#38; whose benevolence I loudly lauded. She wished him at MO-KO, – (where that <del>x</del> is I know not) – &#38; me she wished to a worse place, if any worse there be. In the midst of her emotion, I called upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> to observe her well, saying that I was strictly charged by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> to <del>xxxxx the effect</del> &#60;make a faithful &#38; full report&#62; <del>xhxx</del> The comical wrath which this excited added in no slight degree to the rich effect. Then I blew a blast which tho not worthy of King Ramiro<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s poem, ‘King Ramiro’, lines 146–151, <title>Morning Post</title>, 9 September 1803.</note> was nevertheless a good blast, but she ran – &#38; yet finally, which I hold to be the greatest triumph of my act, I reconciled her to the horn, – yes, reconciled her to it, – by reminding her that rats might be driven away by it, according as it is written in the story of Jeffery.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, p. 442. John Wesley’s (1703–1791; <title>DNB</title>) sister, Emelia (1693–1779), recounted how the Wesley family’s home was haunted by a ghost, ‘Jeffrey’, but her mother, Susanna Wesley (1669–1742), was convinced the noises in the house were caused by rats. She used a horn to try and drive the rats out of the house.</note></p>
            <lb/>
         <p rend="indent0">   <date when="1824-02-22">Monday evening -</date></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> God bless you Grosvenor. I should probably have prattled thro the remainder of the sheet, but a parcel from <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">the Row</ref> has arrived, – &#38; that always occasions an evening of dissipation.</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent1">Yrs affectionately</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript> <p rend="indent0"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> compleats his fifth year tomorrow.</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
