<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4147" type="letter"><head>4147. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Samuel Tillbrook</ref>], <date when="1824-03">[c. March 1824] </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 1p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on correspondent and dating: as this letter asks for help in placing a student at the University of Cambridge and assumes knowledge of James Dusautoy, it was very probably written to Samuel Tillbrook, a Fellow of Peterhouse College, Cambridge, who had aided Dusautoy. Writing to Peter Elmsley on 3 April 1824 (Letter 4166), Southey stated he had ‘lately’ attempted to help James Dusautoy’s brother, so his letter to Tillbrook probably dates from c. March 1824.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">The letter which accompanies this tells its own tale. If it came from any other quarter I should feel as if I were acting importunately in sending it to you. But I think &#38; hope there will be a disposition to befriend this youth<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick Dusautoy (c. 1802–1891), younger brother of James Dusautoy. He was admitted as a sizar (i.e. a student receiving financial assistance in return for set duties) at Queen’s College, Cambridge, on 5 July 1824. He graduated BA 1828 and MA 1831, was a Fellow of his College 1830–1835 and became a clergyman. After a long series of curacies, he was Vicar of Mark, near Bridgwater 1860–1891. Dusautoy also published on a wide range of subjects, including geology.</note> in the College where <ref type="m" target="people.html#DusautoyJames">his poor brother</ref> was cut off,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Emmanuel College, Cambridge, where James Dusautoy was briefly an undergraduate 1813–1815.</note> &#38; you will know where to apply in his behalf.</p>
           <closer><salute rend="indent2">Yrs very truly</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">R Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
