<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4152" type="letter"><head>4152. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> [fragment], <date when="1824-03-07">[begun before and continued on] 7 [March 1824] </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ 4. Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 10 MR 10/ 1824<lb/>
               Watermark: HS &#38; S<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 236 1824/ Robert Southey/ – 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June<lb/>
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 205–206; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 170–172 [in part].<lb/>
               Dating note: Dating from endorsement and postmark; the top section of fol. 1 is missing; the contents of the letter suggest this may have contained an advertisement for Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title>; see, for example, Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 March 1824 (Letter 4151).</note></head>
            
            
          <p rend="indent0">  [MS missing]</p>
          <p rend="indent0">  My dear friend</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> What success this proposal*<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘* Of the Publication of a History of the West Indies by subscription’ [Editors note: This is added in another hand at the foot of fol. 1r.] </note> of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> may meet with remains to be seen.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827), which he was encouraged to write by Southey.</note> If he can obtain two hundred subscribers, <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will take the risk of printing 750 copies. The book will be respectable &#38; useful, comprizing a regular view of all that has occurred in those Islands – from their discovery to the present time. – Take it for all in all it is perhaps as disgraceful a portion of history as the whole course of time can afford; – for I know not that there is any thing generous, any thing ennobling, – any thing <del>xxx xx</del> honourable <del>to human</del> or consolatory to human nature – to relieve it – except what may relate to the missionaries. Still it is a useful task to show what those islands have been &#38; what they are: &#38; the book will do this much more fully, clearly &#38; satisfactorily than has ever yet been done.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> [MS missing] Three weeks have now nearly elapsed since my return, &#38; they seem like so many days, so swiftly &#38; imperceptibly the days pass by when they are past in regular employment &#38; uniform contentment. My old course of life has become as habitual as if it had never been interrupted. The clock is not more punctual than I am in the division of the day. Little by little I get on with many things, the Peninsular War<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> is my employment in the forenoon, the Tale of Paraguay<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> after tea, – before breakfast &#38; at chance times, as inclination <del>xxx</del> leads, I turn to other subjects, &#38; so make progress in all. The only thing at present wanting to my enjoyment is to have something in the press, – that I might have proof sheets to look for: &#38; I shall not long be without this. For tho M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Chinnery<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Robert Chinnery (1791–1825), a Treasury civil servant and secretary to George Canning’s embassy to Portugal in 1815. On 3 February 1824 he was appointed Resident Commissioner in Madrid for the Liquidation of British Claims on the Spanish Government, under the terms of a British-Spanish Convention (1823).</note> has failed to get the book I wanted<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Finally, Southey had sought the assistance of George Canning.</note> at Madrid, he has taken measures for seeking it at Barcelona &#38; at Seville; &#38; as it was published in the latter city, there can I think be little doubt of obtaining it; &#38; it cannot be long in reaching me. Meantime I go on with other parts of the history. It is one great advantage of such subjects, that I can have several parts in progress at the same time, &#38; lay any one aside for awhile till I perceive how to proceed with it satisfactorily to myself.</p>
            <lb/>
          <p rend="indent1">  <date when="1824-03-07">Sunday. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</date> </p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Today I have received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Locker</ref>, who delivers me a message from the Bishop of Durham<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Shute Barrington (1734–1826; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Durham 1791–1826.</note> thanking me for what I have done in the B. of the Church.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bp of London</ref> wrote to express his “high satisfaction.” Both regret that I have not referred to my authors an omission which appears to be generally thought injudicious. The truth is that when I began the book it was with an expectation that it would not exceed a single duodecimo volume, – &#38; that even when enlarged it is still a mere epitome for the most part, – in which I should feel that a display of authorities was out of place. After the proofs of research &#38; accuracy which I have given, I have a right to expect credit: – &#38; in fact the more my credit is examined, the higher it will stand. Whoever may examine my Collections for this, &#38; for my other historical works (&#38; doubtless they will one day be inspected) will find that I have always prepared many more materials than I have used.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> has had a mournful house since I left him.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey’s daughter, Louisa Mary Southey (1821–1824), had just died.</note> – I hope he may have no cause to be anxious concerning Roberts<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey’s oldest son, Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817).</note> strange attack of fever which came on with so much violence, &#38; went off as suddenly &#38; unaccountably as it went. The life of that child would be felt more deeply &#38; abidingly than that of the poor little girl, not only because he has longer been an object of solicitude &#38; affection, – but because he is old enough to discover a very sweet &#38; hopeful disposition.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">   My family thank God are well, – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> not less engaging than when you saw him. He reads fluently now, &#38; is at this time learning, as matter of amusement rather than business, the Greek alphabet. Of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your goddaughter</ref> you perhaps may know more at this time than I do. Remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &#38; your daughters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805–1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> &#38; believe me my dear friend</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">Yours most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
