<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4172" type="letter"><head>4172. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-04-12">12 April 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman<lb/>
               Endorsement: R Southey to SR/ 24 <lb/>
               MS: The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Wilson Library, James Saxon Childers Papers. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Madam</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> Your note arrived just as <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> was setting out, &#38; in time for us to alter her destination from York Place<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mary Gonne</ref> at 16 York Place, Baker Street, London.</note> to Palace Yard. There, if no delay occur upon the road, this letter I trust will find her. She is to sleep at Kendal to night, at Manchester tomorrow; &#38; on Thursday morning the Lady<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Tolson (dates unknown). She was from a Cumberland family and had set up business in High Holborn, London, as a ‘linen-draper, dealer and chapwoman’. Declared bankrupt on 8 July 1826, she started a new business in Regent Street as a ‘milliner and dress maker’ only to go bankrupt again on 16 May 1828.</note> under whose care she goes, has promised to carry or send her under safe convoy from Holborn Bridge to your door.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You will find her a timid, shy creature, just at the awkwardest age. It will, I doubt not be of use to her, to be a while from home, &#38; nowhere could she be sooner reconciled to this, her first absence, than with you</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You will soon receive another portion of my Waterloo Journal,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was sending the Rickmans fair copies of the journal he kept on his trip to the Low Countries in 1815, later published as <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902). This included a description of Southey’s visit to the battlefield of Waterloo (1815).</note> – &#38; I hope to proceed steadily with it, to the end.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> is a little out of spirits, &#38; out of health. The coming season I hope will improve her in both. She joins with me in kindest remembrances -</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Madam</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Yrs very truly</salute>
         <signed rend="indent3">   Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
          
             <postscript>
			 <lb/>
           <p rend="indent0"> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-04-12">12 Apr. 1824</date></p>
             </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
