<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4225" type="letter"><head>4225. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Peter Elmsley</ref>, <date when="1824-08-05">5 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Westminster School. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Nicholas Horsfall, ‘Four Unpublished Letters of Robert Southey’, <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 22.9 (September 1975), 403–405.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-08-05"> 5 Aug. 1824</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear Elmsley</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Among all the persons who have rejoiced in your recovery, there is probably no one who has felt the kind of pleasure which has fallen to my lot. I received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> telling me you were dead. I thought of you &#38; dreamt of you as of the dead, – &#38; continued in that belief till there came news from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> that <del>thxx xxxxx</del> he was going to visit you, &#38; witness the progress of your amendment. Never before did any letter give me so much delight, – &#38; most <del>likely xx</del> unlikely it is that any one ever will hereafter.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  A severe illness is middle life sometimes leaves the constitution in a better state than it found it. The <hi rend="ital">vis medicatrix</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A contraction of ‘vis medicatrix naturae’: literally ‘the healing power of nature’. This is the Latin version of a phrase attributed to Hippocrates (c. 460–c. 370 BC), Greek physician.</note> in such cases goes to work like a landlord, who having neglected his house till it threatens to fall down, sets about a thorough repair.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> On <del>Thursd</del> the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month I shall compleat the fiftieth year of my age. My tenement has some ugly flaws in it, tho it has stood pretty well, all circumstances considered. For more than twenty years I have been subject to a severe &#38; obstinate catarrh, beginning with the summer, &#38; lasting ten or twelve weeks: nor have I ever escaped it except the year when I went into Switzerland at the time of its usual visitation.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s visit to the Continent in May–August 1817.</note> Latterly it has always ended in a cough, &#38; this year that cough has for the first time given me a hint of its hereditary right to fix upon me. – I am getting rid of it for the present, &#38; have nearly recovered the strength which I had lost. But so surely as the seasons come round, so surely will the affection return, unless I can arm the system against it by a course of exercise &#38; constant change of air at that time. If therefore it be possible, I will pass the <del>months</del> latter end of May, &#38; the six following weeks next year in <del>travelling</del> Holland &#38; the North of Germany.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did indeed make this journey in 1825 and 1826.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am printing the second vol. of the Peninsular War,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> &#38; <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi><note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘as is my custom’.</note> writing it &#60;one chapter&#62; while the press is going on with another. Tho this may not be a good method, there are some good reasons for it, – the best being that it enables me to <del>use</del> &#60;employ&#62; the latest materials which fall in my way, more advantageously than <del>xx</del> &#60;if&#62; they came only in time to be used for correcting a narrative drawn from <del>documents</del> less satisfactory documents. This is a very sufficient reason. My materials are as authentic as I could desire, &#38; as ample as would be desired by any person except myself. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">The D. of Wellington</ref> would not supply me with any papers, for a reason which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has probably told you,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey believed that Wellington was reserving his help for Sir William Napier (1785–1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the War in the Peninsula and the South of France from the Year 1807 to 1814</title> (1828–1840). Napier did indeed receive much assistance from Wellington, but was not given use of his papers.</note> but thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> he will give me any information I may have occasion to ask that can be communicated <del>in x</del> <hi rend="ital">viva voce</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘by word of mouth’.</note> He would have done better in committing his papers to my hands, than in reserving them for a mere military history, – to which purpose they would have been equally applicable afterwards. But I have from others had so much both of his official &#38; confidential correspondence during those years while he <del>hxx</del> was fighting up hill, – that perhaps he would be very much surprized to know how well I am acquainted with his views, feelings &#38; opinions. So well indeed am I provided with documents, &#38; with that previous knowledge which is necessary for turning them to account, that I proceed with full confidence &#38; a firm step every where, – except upon a field of battle: – there <del>indeed</del> I am as sensible as I ought to be of my own ignorance; &#38; when I have done my best to understand what to my non-military &#38; non-mathematical head <del>xx xxxx</del> &#60;is&#62; unintelligible. I stick to the letter of my authorities &#38; make the reader as wise as myself. When I come to these parts of the story, <del>xx</del> my own situation puts me in mind of a Cat upon a tea table, – if you ever saw one picking her way among the cups &#38; saucers.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Should it please Gods, Men &#38; Booksellers I am thinking of a Book of the State<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write ‘The Book of the State’ as a companion to <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> – to be brought down to the death of Q Anne,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne (1665–1714; Queen of Great Britain 1701–1714; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – &#38; connected by an introductory view of the reigns of George 1 &#38; 2, with <del>a xxx</del> the Age of George 3,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">George I (1660–1727; King of Great Britain 1701–1727; <title>DNB</title>); George II (1683–1760; King of Great Britain 1727–1760; <title>DNB</title>); and George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – making thus a summary of our English history upon a scale &#38; in a form likely to be read &#38; remembered. Want of books is the chief obstacle, &#38; there need be no greater. I have lately read three works which would have made one part of my Eccl. Sketch<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> much less imperfect than it is, if I had perused them in time. Cardinal D’Ossat’s Letters,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnaud D’Ossat (1537–1604), <title>Lettres du Cardinal d’Ossat, avec des Notes Historiques et Politiques de M. Amelot De La Houssaie</title> (1708), no. 851 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Isaac Casaubons Epistles,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Casaubon (1559–1614), <title>Epistolae</title> (1656), no. 453 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &#38; Peter Heylyns View of Guernsey &#38; Jersey.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Heylyn (1600–1662; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Survey of the Estate of France and Some of the Adjoyning Ilands</title> (1656), no. 1187 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> One motive with me for undertaking a sketch of our Civil History would be for the opportunity it would afford of introducing there whatever of importance had been omitted in the former work.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> These are speculations, which with many others of a wider scope &#38; perhaps a worthier purpose, – time &#38; chance may easily frustrate. Meantime – sufficient for the day is the occupation thereof. How glad should I be to talk with you over the past – the present – &#38; the future, – here at leisure &#38; at rest! – <del>&#38; I hope this will</del> Whatever enjoyment there may be in meeting in London society (&#38; I am far from undervaluing it,) there is nothing of this kind to be had in crowds. One day I hope to have you again under this roof.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Elmsley had visited Southey at Keswick in September 1805.</note> Pleasure &#38; profit are not always united, but in that case I should find them so; – for mine is a mind upon which good seed is not wasted – tho it is sometimes long in springing up &#38; bringing forth fruit.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you Elmsley –</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  yrs affectionately</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> RS. </signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
