<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4233" type="letter"><head>4233. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#KnoxWilliam">William Knox</ref>], <date when="1824-08-19">19 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from William Knox, <title>The Lonely Hearth, The Songs of Israel, Harp of Zion, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1847)<lb/>
               Previously published: William Knox, <title>The Lonely Hearth, The Songs of Israel, Harp of Zion, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1847), p. xii.</note></head>
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1824-08-19">19<hi rend="ital">th August</hi> 1824</date>.</dateline></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1">Dear Sir, – Your little volume has been safely delivered to me by your friend Mr G. Macdonald, and I thank you for it. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Knox’s <title>Songs of Israel; Consisting of Lyrics, Founded upon the History and Poetry of the Hebrew Scriptures</title> (1824). Presentation copies of this and other works by Knox were no. 1496 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Macdonald is unidentified.</note> It has given me great pleasure. To paraphrase sacred poetry is the most difficult of all tasks, and it appears to me that you have been more successful in the attempt than any of your predecessors. You may probably have heard that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberReginald">the Bishop of Calcutta</ref> (before he was appointed to that see) was engaged in forming a collection of hymns and sacred pieces, with the hope of having them introduced into our English churches. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heber’s collection of ninety-nine hymns, including twenty-seven written by himself, was published posthumously as <title>Hymns Written and Adapted to the Weekly Church Service of the Year</title> (1827). This did not include anything by Knox.</note> Some of yours are so well adapted to that object that I will send out a copy of your book to him.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Deprivations such as you speak of are our portion here. I hope what have fallen to my lot have had their natural and proper effect in loosening the ties that bind us to this world. That effect affliction has produced upon you also; and I cannot but wish that talents and feelings such as yours were employed in the ministry of the gospel, where you would find your happiness in the performance of your duty – you are young enough to think of this.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">Farewell, dear sir, and believe me yours with sincere respect,</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer> 
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
