<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4241" type="letter"><head>4241. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WattsAlaric">Alaric Watts</ref>, <date when="1824-08-29">29 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Alaric A. Watts Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 3 Park Square/ Leeds <lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Endorsement: Original letter – Signature cut off/ for the purpose of being Engraved in Fac Simile in/ the Literary Souvenir)/ of Robert Southey. Poet Laureate<lb/>
               MS: Cornell University Library. AL; 3p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Alaric Watts, <title>Narrative of His Life</title>, 2 vols (London, 1884), I, pp. 197–198.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-08-29"> 29 Aug. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have this evening received your letter of July 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#38; the little volume which accompanied it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Alaric Watts, <title>Poetical Sketches: The Profession; The Broken Heart etc. With Stanzas for Music, and Other Poems</title> (1824), no. 2993 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The copy of the first edition of this book,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Alaric Watts, <title>Poetical Sketches: with Stanzas for Music, and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> which you had the goodness to intend for me, never reached my hands, – I should otherwise most certainly have written without delay to thank you for it, &#38; also have sought an opportunity of expressing my thanks in person when I past thro Leeds in November last.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">With your name I have long been acquainted, – tho not with your poems. But one piece which I saw in a provincial newspaper<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Ten Years Ago’, <title>Poetical Sketches: The Profession; The Broken Heart etc. With Stanzas for Music, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1824), pp. 23–27. Southey had probably seen this poem, and an account of Watts’s volume, in the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 14 August 1824.</note> – (<hi rend="ital">Ten years ago</hi>) convinced me that you had not been praise [MS missing]ing it, – &#38; in merely cutting open the leaves of this little volume, I see much to admire.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The Memoirs of my private history which have been published in Magazines &#38;c<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (January–July 1814), 566–571; <title>European Magazine</title>, 66 (July 1814), [3]–5.</note> – are as incorrect &#38; fallacious as they might be expected to be by all who know <del>nothin</del> any thing of such publications. I was born in Wine Street Bristol, Aug 12 1774. In 1788 I was placed at Westminster school, &#38; in 1792 entered as a Commoner at Balliol College, Oxford. I left the University in 1794 without taking a degree, married in 1795, came to this place in 1803 to visit my brother-in-law <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, – &#38; have remained here ever since.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Should you visit this beautiful part of England at any time, it would give me much pleasure to have an opportunity of shaking you by the hand.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Your obliged &#38; obed<hi rend="sup">t</hi> sev<hi rend="sup">t</hi></salute></closer>
           <postscript> <p rend="indent4">[MS missing]</p> </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
