<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4253" type="letter"><head>4253. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-09-22">22 September 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 25 SE 25/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: 22. Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824; 22 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">If you &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> can make holiday for a month, let it be at the beginning of October instead of the latter end, &#38; come here, where mountain air will prove the best restoration for both, &#38; where you will do me good by engaging me in a more determined course of exercise than it is possible to take alone. You know that the mail in returning to London arrives between 9 &#38; 10 – thus saving the second night: which is an advantage to look to when you turn your faces homeward.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I would not have you say anything to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> farther than to let him know that the article<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. It was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311. Southey had hoped that it might appear in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> has not be sent to me for alteration, &#38; that what he has communicated thro you is all that I have heard concerning it. I have no objection to insert some qualifying sentences, tho if the tenour of the paper be understood as it ought, it will appear less to eulogize Hayley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley (1745–1820; <title>DNB</title>), the poet and biographer.</note> (which as an author I have nowhere done) than to expose the miserable state of national taste in an age when he could flourish as first poet. The real sin of the article is this Grosvenor, – that it is written in a humane &#38; gentlemanly spirit altogether at variance with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> own tone of criticism, &#38; with that <del>of his</del> which he has suffered to characterize &#38; disgrace his Review.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have a suspicion that <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> apprehends I may withdraw from the Q. when it changes hands (as it is very likely I may do) &#38; therefore has an eye to saving the expence of the last paper, the place of which he has plenty of merrymen to supply at half price. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">The Megistonos</ref> is quite penny-wise &#38; pound-foolish enough for this. If there is an intentional incivility (&#38; of this there is certainly every appearance at this time) it is because he has played the tradesman with me in the most barefaced manner &#38; knows that I am perfectly well aware of it. <hi rend="ital">N’importe</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the half-bills, – &#38; for the Shrewsbury commission.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had passed on £10 to Edward Southey, Southey’s youngest brother, who was working in the theatre at Shrewsbury.</note> When you write next pray tell me if you paid the 2 £ to the subscription for poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfields</ref> family. Having said that this would be done, I should like to know that my word has been performed.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I wish very much you could come down – for the sake of a certain medical practitioner,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Daniel Dove, the central character in Southey’s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847).</note> with whom you ought to be better acquainted, &#38; to whom I think you would feel disposed to be of use -</p>
       <closer>    <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
		  <lb/></closer>
		 
           <postscript><p rend="indent1"> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-09-22">22 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1824</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
