<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4261" type="letter"><head>4261. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-10-10">10 October 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: 10 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 453. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 188–189 [in part].</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><date when="1824-10-10">Oct. 10. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> The Peninsular War is going on well. 20 sheets of the second vol. are printed.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> The printer<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766–1831).</note> does not hurry me, neither do I hurry the printer; having found by long experience that after letting a narration rest awhile, it is renewed with fresh spirit. It is proceeding well, the best proof of which is that I am well satisfied with it myself.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  My literary employments have never in the slightest degree injured my health. For in truth I neither am, nor ever have been a close student. If I do not take sufficient exercise, it is not from any love of the desk, but for the want of a companion or an object to draw me out when the season is uninviting; – &#38; yet I overcame this <del>xx</del> dislike of solitary walking, &#38; every day unless it be a settled rain, walk long enough &#38; far &#38; fast enough, to require the wholesome process of rubbing down on my return. At no time of my life have I ever applied half so closely to my employments, as you always do to yours. They impose upon me no restrictions, there is nothing irksome in them, – no anxiety connected with them. – they leave me master<del>s</del> of my time &#38; of myself. Nor do I doubt but that they would prove conducive to longevity, if my constitution were disposed for it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> With regard to the prudence of working up ready materials rather than laying in more, upon whatever I employ myself I must of necessity be doing both. The work which I am most desirous of compleating is the Hist. of Portugal, as being that for which most preparations have been made, &#38; most time bestowed on it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had begun research for his ‘History of Portugal’ on his visit to the country in 1800–1801, but it was never finished or published.</note> And when the Peninsular War shall be completed – by Gods blessing, – a week will not elapse before it goes to the press, – for it has been long in much greater forwardness than any work which I ever before began to print.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am however conscious <del>of</del> now of a disposition the reverse of Montaigne’s who loved he said rather to forge his mind than to furnish it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Michel de Montaigne (1533–1592), <title>Essais</title> (1580), Book 3, chapter 3, ‘Des Trois Commerces’: ‘Meditation is a large and powerful study to such as vigorously can taste and employ themselves therein. I had rather forge than furnish my mind.’ Southey returned to this quotation from Montaigne in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834–1847), IV, p. 225.</note> Avarice you know is the passion of declining life, &#38; avaricious I confess myself to be of the only treasure I have ever coveted, or ever shall possess. My temper or turn of mind, inclines also to form new projects, – but it is one thing to perceive what might be done, &#38; another to dream of doing it. – No doubt wherever <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Telford</ref> is travelling he cannot help seeing a line of road ought to be carried, <del>or</del> a harbour improved, or a pier carried out – In like manner I see possibilities &#38; capabilities &#38; desirablities, – &#38; think no more of them</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to hear of Mitchells<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Mitchell (1779–1824), Principal Inspector of Roads and Bridges in the Highlands 1810–1824. Southey and Rickman had met him on their tour of Scotland in August–September 1819. John Mitchell was a protégée of Thomas Telford, and Telford ensured that Mitchell’s eldest son, Joseph Mitchell (1803–1883), succeeded his father as Principal Inspector of Roads and Bridges in the Highlands 1824–1867.</note> death, an upright, useful, &#38; happy man, &#38; therefore on all accounts worthy of regret. You have been a true friend to his family, – but to whom are you not a true friend?</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your Chichester travellers<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> have not yet shown themselves – They will find me, as any visitor will who comes in a wedding garment, always at leisure.</p>
          <closer><salute rend="salute1">  God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
