<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4264" type="letter"><head>4264. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">Mary Ann Watts Hughes</ref>, <date when="1824-10-15">15 October 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes/ Amen Corner/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 18 OC 18/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc 3799. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 444–446.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-10-15">15 Oct. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Madam</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  My employments, thank Heaven, are such that they allow me to be always at leisure; &#38; this is a blessing which would compensate for more untoward circumstances than have fallen to my lot: – so great a one indeed, that if I had sold my time for any official situation, I verily believe I should have been as uncomfortable as poor Peter Schlemil when he had parted with his shadow.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Schlemihl, the main character in Adelbert von Chamisso (1781–1838), <title>Peter Schlemihls Wundersame Geschichte</title> (1814). He sold his shadow to the Devil for a bottomless wallet, only to find himself shunned by society.</note> But if I were busier than I am, or ever shall be, it would always give me pleasure to receive a letter from you. I believe we can all of us find time for what we like.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes’s</ref> kind present<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Woolnoth (1780–1837), <title>A Graphical Illustration of the Metropolitan Cathedral Church of Canterbury</title> (1816), no. 2916 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> (for which I thank him truly) will probably find a speedy conveyance from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">your neighbours in the Row</ref>. The book will not be the less welcome for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert’s</ref> sake, who having some three years ago when <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> asked him whether he would chuse to be an Archbishop or a Carpenter, preferred the Archbishoprick, verily looked upon Canterbury afterwards as his allotted portion in this world, &#38; used to talk with great complacency of what he should do when he came to live at Lambeth, where he was to have more books than his father. – He was ill enough to make us very anxious about a fortnight ago, – with a bilious fever, – but thank God he has perfectly recovered from it; – &#38; at present we are all well. I have been somewhat seriously an invalid during the summer: the cough however has fairly departed, &#38; being once more in tolerable condition, I am taking all dutiful pains to keep myself so.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I had neither seen nor heard of the foolish apology for <ref type="m" target="people.html#OpieAmelia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Opie</ref>, which is enough to shame her out of Quakerism.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified. At this time, rumours were beginning to circulate that Amelia Opie had become a Quaker, for example, in the <title>York Herald</title>, 19 June 1824. In fact, she had only begun to investigate this possibility and did not join the Quakers until August 1825.</note> Without the aid of Cupid<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Roman god of love. Mary Anne Watts Hughes had suggested that Amelia Opie’s conversion to Quakerism was inspired by her love for a Quaker.</note> (who however has worked many conversions in both sexes) I can account very satisfactorily for her becoming a Quaker. She was bred <del>up</del> nominally in Unitarianism, &#38; that too of the laxest kind; – &#38; it was but nominally, – for her father<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">James Alderson (1742–1825), a Norwich surgeon and physician.</note> belonged to that sect only because it was necessary <del>for</del> &#60;that&#62; a man in his profession should remain to be of some religion. She grew up when revolutionary opinions were taking their freest course, &#38; in a city where I believe they prevailed more than in any other part of England. Some of her warmest admirers (<del>few</del> &#60;&#38;&#62; no woman had more) were far gone in unbelief, they were men of splendid talents &#38; in other respects of great real worth.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Amelia Opie’s early admirers included the radical writers William Godwin and Thomas Holcroft (1745–1809; <title>DNB</title>).</note> In fact she has always lived among persons whose speculations were under no restraint, &#38; who however much they differed among themselves, agreed in that rooted dislike to the Establishment, which is a bond of union between the darkest bigots of Popery, the wildest fanatics, &#38; the most thorough infidels. In the state of mind which such circumstances could hardly fail of producing upon a woman who had always been flattered for her talents, &#60;but with a lively fancy &#38; a good heart&#62; <ref type="m" target="people.html#OpieAmelia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Opie</ref> from <del>her</del> a life of gayety in London, went at the age of about forty five to nurse her father,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Amelia Opie devoted herself to nursing her father from the time of his illness in December 1820. She was then fifty-one years old.</note> whom in his old age, severe bodily infirmity had awakened to some sense of the <hi rend="ital">profligacy</hi> of his past life. The only persons in her circle at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> who had any warmth of religious feeling were Quakers; – &#38; were you to <del>see</del> &#60;know&#62; her Quaker Abelard you would see that <del>Elo</del> few Eloisa’s<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Abelard (1079–1142), a celebrated scholar and monk who conducted a clandestine affair with Heloise (d. 1164). The ‘Quaker Abelard’ was probably <ref type="m" target="people.html#GurneyJosephJohn">Joseph John Gurney</ref>, the Norwich banker and leading Quaker, who was a close friend of Amelia Opie and instrumental in her conversion.</note> were to be trusted with him. But whatever her feelings toward him may be, she wanted something more for her imagination &#38; her heart than the cold forms &#38; colder creed of Unitarianism can supply, – &#38; Quakerism has a great deal for both. – I believe she is sincere, – &#38; I like her well enough even to excuse the verses which she has written in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Ediths</ref> – Album.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Amelia Opie had written a verse in Edith May’s album, when she and her father had left Norwich on 30 January 1824, which had likened Southey to a swan and Edith May to a cygnet: ‘and see thee, fam’d Swan of the Derwent’s fair tide/ With that elegant cygnet that floats by thy side’ (John Wood Warter, <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, p. 435).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>, will <hi rend="ital">tell</hi> you, (for she must not write), – the ungracious return which they called forth.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is probably here recalling the jokey references he had made to Opie’s poem in the opening of his letter to Edith May Southey, 24 July 1824, Letter 4223.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Your friendly message to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Edith</ref> shall not be forgotten. I believe she will leave Taunton for London on the 25th of this month; but &#60;whether&#62; Lady Malet<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> whom she there rejoins, means to make any tarriance upon the road, I do not yet know.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The Peninsular War<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> is going on well in the press, – &#38; I am prosing &#38; versing<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was finishing <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> in as good heart &#38; with as much good will, as if all the world liked my verse &#38; prose as well as you are pleased to do.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I would fain do the State some service.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had decided not to write a ‘Book of the State’ to accompany <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> But I am beginning to act upon the resolution of finishing what I have begun &#38; working up the materials which so <del>many years h</del> large a part of my life has been spent in accumulating, – before I open any new foundations. Now that I am half an hundred years old it is time to wind up my accounts.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Our kindest remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref>, mine also to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> H.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), son of Mary Anne Watts Hughes and miscellaneous writer.</note> &#38; </p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="salute2">believe me Dear Madam</salute>
          <salute rend="salute3">  Yrs very sincerely</salute>
           <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
