<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4286" type="letter"><head>4286. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1824-12-03">3 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major General Peachy/ at the Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wooll’s/ Rugby/ Warwickshire<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-12-03">3. Dec. 1824</date></dateline>
            
         <salute>   My dear Sir</salute></opener>
         <p rend="indent1">   I am glad to hear that you have disposed of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charles Henry<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807–1833), the younger of Peachy’s two stepsons. He had a serious accident on 2 August 1822 that was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming Henry): ‘A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull’ (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy’s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta. </note> so well, &#38; so much to your satisfaction. If any disposition to over-task himself in study should appear, his tutor no doubt will be aware that it ought rather to be repressed than encouraged; for tho all danger is long since past, yet a few more years should elapse before the brain be exerted as if it had never sustained an injury.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">The Bishop of Barbadoes</ref> has had a lucky escape in not having embarked before the late tremendous gale.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Great Storm of 22–23 November 1824 – a hurricane-force wind and storm surge that particularly affected the south coast of England.</note> His baggage was not so fortunate, – the vessel in which that was stowed is among the wrecks, – tho it has not gone to pieces. The storm was felt here, but I suppose we were only in the skirts of it, for it was by no means the worst that we have experienced since the end of September, till which time we <del>had</del> &#60;have&#62; had the finest, &#38; since, the worst season I remember in this country. At present we are in a white world, &#38; nothing could be more glorious than the silvery splendour of the mountains this day.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe’s</ref> observations on <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowless</ref> Life of Pope;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Roscoe, <title>The Works of Alexander Pope, Esq. with Notes and Illustrations by Himself and Others. To Which are Added, a New Life of the Author, an Estimate of his Poetical Character and Writings, and Occasional Remarks</title>, 10 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. xvi–xix, severely criticised William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Works of Alexander Pope, Esq., in Verse and Prose, Containing the Principal Notes of Drs Warburton and Warton</title> (1806) for ‘imputations on the moral character of Pope … accompanied by an apparent disposition of Mr. Bowles to detract also from his estimation as a poet’.</note> but I should suppose that whatever difference of opinion he may entertain, he will have expressed it courteously. With no great respect for <ref type="m" target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> as an author I have great respect for his personal character, as an accomplished kind hearted &#38; generous man. As for the matter of controversy,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A huge controversy had been ignited by Bowles’s <title>The Invariable Principles of Poetry</title> (1819), which claimed that poetic images should be drawn from nature, not art; and that the finest poetry did not deal with the transient manners of society, but with general and enduring themes. Bowles had been very critical of Alexander Pope (1688–1744; <title>DNB</title>) in this context.</note> it lies in a nutshell; &#38; if the parties were but agreed upon the meaning of the terms which they use, there would be an end of it. – It would be very gratifying to me to pass a few days under <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles’s</ref> roof, but I can seldom move from home, inclination &#38; prudence combining to keep me there. <del>if</del> Even if I considered travelling as a luxury, it is one in which I am not rich enough to indulge without especial cause; <del>x</del> inasmuch as that all the while I am absent from home, my only estate (which is time) is lying unproductive. – I have no intention of seeing the south next year; if I go from home at all (which &#60;for&#62; the hope of escaping my annual attack in the chest it is probable I shall do) – it will most likely be to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bishop of Limerick</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey actually visited the Low Countries in 1825.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">My daughters<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>.</note> will, I hope, return in February. We heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> to day. She sends good accounts of Lady Malet &#38; the Charters.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), maternal uncle of the Charter sisters, <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref> and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). The Charters were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Some extracts from Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Medwins book<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824).</note> have been transmitted to me, which, little inclined as I am to controversy, require notice on my part; &#38; you will probably see in the course of some ten days an exposure in the Courier of as much of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> impudent &#38; malignant falsehood as it behoves me to notice.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s Letter to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 8 December 1824, Letter 4289, published 13 December 1824.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The only news of this place is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> has let his estates, &#38; is about to remove to London; – &#38; as the Fryers<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777–1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. He had been renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick. He married Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799–1874), who had been Tom Southey’s lodger, in June 1822.</note> are already removed to the vicinity of Cockermouth, we lose in him – literally the last of our neighbours, – &#38; the only &#60;one with&#62; whom a constant intercourse has been kept up. The young women I am afraid will feel the loss, which I shall not, – living always in the society best suited to my habits &#38; inclinations.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The Ladies desire their best remembrances – mine accompany them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>, when you may write to, or rejoin her. I beg my compliments also to Dr Wooll.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wooll (1767–1833; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman and Headmaster of Rugby School 1807–1828. Peachy’s two stepsons, James Henry (1803–1884) and Charles Edward Henry (1807–1833) were educated at Rugby School.</note> Rugby I hope is proud of having sent forth <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Landor</ref>, – who notwithstanding some errors of opinion, will undoubtedly be <del>reme</del> regarded hereafter as one of the brightest ornaments both of his age &#38; of his country.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">farewell my dear Sir, &#38; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
