<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4305" type="letter"><head>4305. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-12-24">24 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 27 DE 27/ 1824<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.337a. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener> <salute> My dear Harry</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">  A letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Episcope</ref> goes by this post.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to William Howley, 24 December 1824, Letter 4304, which sought the Bishop’s support for Henry Herbert Southey’s application to become a Fellow of the Royal Society.</note> I wish you would bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> together, &#38; I have told <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">J.C.</ref> so.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 24 December 1824, Letter 4303.</note> They ought to know each other, on the score of the Q.R, &#38; will do it better thro you than by a dry introduction at <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref>, or one of his crowded dinners. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref> is at present a writer who has a great deal of power &#38; all good materials in him; &#38; his official situation is such that he is in a fair – I may say a <hi rend="ital">sure</hi> way, of becoming a very considerable person. I have a great liking for him, &#38; great hopes of him. – There was an article in the Courier<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘To the Editor of the Courier’, <title>Courier</title>, 18 December 1824, and signed ‘H.T.’</note> by him (which I have not seen) in reply to that atrocious &#38; beastly libel in the M Chronicle.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey versus Lord Byron’, <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824. Southey considered taking action against the newspaper but did not do so.</note> That libel I have referred to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, to deal with, or leave alone as he may deem expedient; but if our laws are good for anything, I think he will notice it, in the only way which it ought to be noticed by prosecuting a paper villainous enough to publish it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My letter has been inserted in Blackwoods Magazine with an introduction in the true Blackwood style, bepraising both <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Byron</ref> &#38; me, talking nonsense about both, &#38; praising the composition of the letter as a masterpiece in its kind.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Southey and Byron’, <title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title>, 16 (December 1824), 711–715.</note> The remarkable thing in this, is the forwardness with which that Magazine is got ready, &#38; the promptude with which it is carried. My letter was published on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi><note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 8 December 1824, Letter 4289, published 13 December 1824.</note> it could not reach Edinburgh till the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, – it is not the last article in the Magazine which is not to be published till New Years day, yet the Magazine is printed, sent to London for <ref type="m" target="people.html#FreelingFrancis">Francis Freelings</ref> frank, &#38; reaches me by that account on the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. The Scotch manage these things better than their neighbours.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  The transfer of the QR to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> is to me a matter of great satisfaction on all accounts. My papers will not be mutilated nor will they be postponed from one number to another, – so that I shall know what I have to depend on.</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent1">Love to all – &#38; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
             <postscript>
			 <lb/>
			 <p><date when="1824-12-24"> Dec 24. 1824</date></p>
            <lb/>
            <p>A merry Xmas to you all, &#38; many of them</p></postscript> 
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
