<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3794" type="letter"><head>3794. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Hew Dalrymple</ref>, <date when="1822-01-06">6 February 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Sir Hew Dalrymple/ &#38;c &#38;c &#38;c / Upper Wimpole Street/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 9 FE 9/ 1822<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, Acc 10698/3. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-02-06">6 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> The box containing your books &#38; papers is safely arrived, &#38; I shall immediately begin to peruse them.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Dalrymple had loaned Southey his papers to help with the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> The use which I shall make of them will, I hope, express my sense of this favour better than I feel myself able here to do. They will enable me to rewrite that portion of my history in which I was most in want of satisfactory documents. Their bulk is by no means alarming. It has often been my duty to go thro more bulky materials, in investigating subjects in themselves less interesting, &#38; much less momentous. If there be any point which may seem to require farther explanation, I will avail myself of your permission, as conveyed to me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B. Frere</ref>, &#38; apply for it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am at this time preparing for the press that chapter which relates to the campaign in Portugal.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 526–610.</note> On this subject I hope it will be found that I shall have written in a manner which you Sir, will think satisfactory, &#38; which will not be discreditable to myself. No man who has lived to any purpose can reach the verge of fifty without reconsidering some of his opinions, &#38; modifying or changing them, as the same things appear to him in new &#38; different lights. Were I to begin life again, &#38; with a proper knowledge of myself, the fault which I should be most desirous to correct would be that of <del>taking</del> expressing <del>up</del> with too much warmth &#38; vehemence opinions which had been taken up with too little consideration.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent">I have the honour to remain</salute>
              <salute rend="indent2">   Sir Hew</salute>
              <salute rend="indent3"> with much respect</salute>
              <salute rend="indent2"> Your obliged &#38; obedient humble servant</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
