<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3805" type="letter"><head>3805. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-02-25">25 February [1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: RS to JR 25 Feby<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 429. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: This letter shortly pre-dates that of 27 February [1822], and refers to the government’s proposal of 15 February 1822 to repeal the malt tax.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> It is by <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> desire that I return these proofs under your cover.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs for the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> I conclude of course that you understand this, &#38; that he knows the favour is done to him. – They will not carry back with them the ill-luck which they brought, – for they came with the black post office mark ‘not put in till the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>,” – <del>whereby the revenue</del>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the Pop. Abstract.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">1821 Census, ‘Abstracts of the Answers and Returns: Enumeration Abstract’, <title>Parliamentary Papers</title> (1822), XV.</note> How much better would it have been to have appropriated a million a year for transporting emigrants, than to have repealed a tax, which the public did not feel, &#38; for which ministry will get nothing but insults from their opponents, – well deserved by such weakness.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">On 15 February 1822 the government had announced its proposal to repeal the malt tax, thus reducing its income by between £1 million and £1.5 million p.a.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> So Willy is gone to Laleham.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Rickman (1812–1886), Rickman’s son, was a pupil at Thomas Arnold’s (1795–1842; <title>DNB</title>) school at Laleham, near Staines.</note> You could not have placed him at a better school of that kind.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The population gives one much to think of – I cannot account for the great difference in the rate of increase in different countries, where there is no difference of circumstances sufficient to explain it.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
              <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
            
           <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-02-25"> 25 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi></date>.</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
