<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3806" type="letter"><head>3806. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#WranghamFrancis">Francis Wrangham</ref>], <date when="1822-02-25">25 February 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS, vol. 96, 1 and 2, tipped into a graingerised copy of Revd T. F. Dibdin, <title>The Library Companion; or, the Young Man’s Guide, and the Old Man’s Comfort, in the Choice of a Library</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, between pp. 102–103. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on correspondent: Identified by content.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-02-25">25. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Dear Sir</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  I can now thank you for your Lyrics of Horace,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Wrangham, <title>The Lyrics of Horace; Being the First Four Books of his Odes, Translated by F. Wrangham</title> (1821), no. 1371 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which reached me a few days since, – just long enough ago for me to have looked at them, – not cursorily, or hastily.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You have succeeded, I think, as well as you could expect in a task wherein compleat success is impossible. Poems the merit of which consists so much in their language, are in fact untranslatable, – they are like <del>xxxxx</del> &#60;trinkets&#62; in filagree, where the material, tho sterling, bears no proportion in value to the cost of the work. – You might have composed a volume of better English poems in less time, &#38; with much less labour than you have bestowed upon this version.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I could find much to praise, &#38; nothing seriously to object to, except those inversions, which, common as they have become in the poetry of this age, are not accordant with the nature of our language. The effect which they would have in their proper place is very much weakened by the too frequent use of them. In my judgement, they should never be used without a special reason.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> You have probably seen it announced that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> has in the press a series of sonnets upon the course of our religious history.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth, <title>Ecclesiastical Sketches</title> (1822).</note> They are some of the noblest compositions in this, or in any other language. He has employed the highest powers to the best &#38; most useful purpose.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2"> I remain Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">  with much respect</salute>
               <salute rend="indent">    Yours faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
