<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3815" type="letter"><head>3815. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-03-23">23 March 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsements: 23. March 1822; 23 March 1822<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear G</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> Pray send me the rest of the clean sheets<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> as soon as you can, for I really want to refer them, &#38; cannot begin my next chapter till I see how the narrative broke off in one of the preceding ones.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I will send you in my next a fair piece of handwriting for your friend Hawker,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Samuel Hawker (1763–1838), who had served in the Peninsular War 1808–1811 as commander of the 14th Light Dragoons and made a number of sketches in Spain. Westall wished to use Hawker’s sketches for <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey’s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &#38;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These pictures could be inserted into the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> to whom I feel myself very much obliged, &#38; with it I will return his Sp mss.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Last week I was at Rydal, – while you were at Hastings. But remember you that mountain-air is of approved efficacy for you. I have strong beer for you, – &#38; toasted cheese, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> must taste <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith Mays</ref> wines, &#38; instruct her how to mend them in the next brewing.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  I have been working hard upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymples</ref> papers. – It is only the last Chapter<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 15, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 756–806. This concerned the retreat to Corunna in 1808–1809, in which Courtenay had participated.</note> which is to go to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">Courtenay</ref>; – &#38; I apprehend that this chapter will not vary in any material point from the narrative as it now stands in the Ed. Ann. Register<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 431–459.</note> subsequent materials have given me little to add &#38; I do not know that there is any thing to alter</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> All well thank God –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
          <postscript> <p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-03-23"> 23 March 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
