<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3821" type="letter"><head>3821. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>, <date when="1822-04-09">9 April 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898)<lb/>
               Previously published: Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898), pp. 31–33.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">KESWICK</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1822-04-09">9<hi rend="ital">th April</hi> 1822.</date></dateline></opener>
            
           <p rend="indent0"> My dear Heraud, – Your ‘Nero’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud had sent Southey his tragedy ‘Nero’, centred on Nero Claudius Caesar Drusus Germanicus (AD 37–68; Roman Emperor AD 54–68). Heraud did not publish this work.</note> was a long while before it reached me. I have now perused it, and find – what I expected – an exuberance of power which you do not know how to direct. Writers who have the mere talent of imitation (which is all that ninety-nine out of the hundred possess) soon attain to all the perfection of which they are capable, and write as well at sixteen as they would do at threescore. Like ginger-beer, they are soon ripe; but where the liquor is generous, it must have time for ripening.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I advise you not to publish ‘Nero,’ because there is little likelihood that it would pay the expense of publication, and because all it could do for you would be no more than what your ‘Legend’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud’s <title>The Legend of St Loy, with Other Poems</title> (1820).</note> has done; that is, it would convey sure evidence of genius to those persons who are capable of discovering it – a much smaller number than is generally supposed.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Only have patience, and you will surely rise to your natural station.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You had better let the subject of the Deluge<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud was planning an epic poem, eventually published as <title>The Judgement of the Flood</title> (1834).</note> ripen in your mind than begin upon it, till you are better able to construct the plan of a poem. Your easiest way to distinguish yourself is by the drama, and not by aiming at its highest branches at first. Choose some graceful subject with a romantic interest, one which requires more poetry than passion; form your plan first, and if you construct that well, there will be no fear of your failing in the execution.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> One thing more I would say: you may be a great poet without being a classical scholar. Do not suppose that I undervalue the advantages of a regular education; but the attempt to supply by severe application that want of one and to make yourself a scholar, must be deeply injurious to your health, and could not be successful. Remember how many poets have excelled without <hi rend="ital">this</hi> kind of learning, for after all this is <hi rend="ital">only one kind</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Shall I keep your manuscript till I have an opportunity of returning it by a private hand, which will surely occur in the course of the summer? You have given a wrong pronunciation to two of the names: the accent in Natalis should be on the middle syllable; in Tigellinus on the last but one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Two characters in Heraud’s tragedy ‘Nero’ both drew on historical figures. Antonius Natalis (fl. AD 65) took part in a plot against Nero in AD 65 and betrayed his co-conspirators. Ofonius Tigellinus (c. AD 10–69) was Prefect of the Praetorian Guard AD 62–68. He turned against Nero in AD 68.</note> Farewell, and believe me, yours very truly,</p>
            
           <closer> <signed rend="right">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
