<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3822" type="letter"><head>3822. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1822-04-10">10 April 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ 4. Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 13 AP 13/ 1822<lb/>
               Watermark: W D &#38; Co/ 1819<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 225 1822/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April/<lb/>
               rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi><lb/>
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 192–194.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-04-10">10 Apr. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear friend</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> It is long since I have heard from you, &#38; I am afraid one cause of this silence may have been that you have had no favourable intelligence to communicate. I look at the news from Brazil always with apprehension because of the manner in which it may affect you.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in Porto in August 1820 led to the election of a Cortes in Portugal in December 1820 and demands that the monarchy return from Brazil, where it had fled in 1807–1808 following the French invasion. John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826) arrived back in Lisbon on 3 July 1821 and eventually agreed to a new liberal Constitution in October 1822. John VI appointed his son Pedro (1798–1834; Emperor of Brazil 1822–1831) as Regent in Brazil, and Pedro summoned an elected advisory council to represent the different Brazilian provinces. These events eventually led to the separation of Portugal and Brazil on 7 September 1822. John May’s business affairs in Brazil had long been in financial difficulties and finally collapsed in early 1822.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> writes to me but seldom, &#38; his letters when they come are not longer than so many prescriptions; so that I learn nothing from him. On Saturday however I heard something concerning you which gave me sincere pleasure. Dining at a neighbours with a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thompson<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> he gave an excellent report of your son, from Arnold,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John May (1802–1879), after his expulsion from Eton in 1818, was being educated at a school in Laleham, near Staines, run by Thomas Arnold (1795–1842; <title>DNB</title>).</note> who spoke of him in the highest terms, &#38; said how glad he was to have had him under his care. This must be a great satisfaction to you, &#38; one motive for my writing is to repeat it to you because coming in this circuitous manner more weight may be given to a commendation of this kind, than if it had been said directly by Arnold to yourself.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Another motive is to remind you <del>that</del> of something like an engagement to visit <del>xxx</del> me this year, &#38; to say that the <del>xxxx after the leaves xxx not the better</del> nearer Midsummer you can come the better, <hi rend="ital">before</hi> rather than after. You should come at the end of May, &#38; be here when the days are at the longest, &#38; the country in its best dress. I cannot express how much I wish to see you under this roof.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son visited Southey for four weeks in August–September 1822.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your goddaughter</ref> has not been in good health, we have counted &#38; still count<del>xx</del> upon an opportunity of sending her to Harrogate with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref> (<ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthMary">Mrs Wordsworths</ref> sister) – such waters &#38; such baths being plainly what she stands in need of. If they go <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss H.</ref> must return by the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of May; – so that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> will be returned in time for your arrival. You will be pleased with her manners which are thoroughly unaffected, – diffident &#38; at the same time frank; – None of the others have you ever seen; thank God they are all in tolerable health &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> in particular thriving as we could wish.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I sent you the reprinted volume of Brazil, thinking that you were interested enough in that work to like to have it in its amended <del>form</del> state.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The second (1822) edition of the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> The additions amount to nearly 100 pages; &#38; the expence of time &#38; labour was much greater than this sum might seem to imply, good part having been gathered from Dutch materials &#38; from manuscripts which were not easily perused. If at any time you feel disposed to look at the additional matter, the paging will direct you to it, that of the former edition being <del>xxx</del> retained in the margin.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">In this last QR. I have reviewed <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridges</ref> translation of Dobrizhoffer,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Sara Coleridge’s <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (January 1822), 277–323, published 30 March 1823. The book was a translation of Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784).</note> – &#38; in the next there will be a life of Camoens, including one of Faria e Sousa.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Adamson, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820), no. 10 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1–39, published 4 July 1822. Southey included in his review (14–19) a life of Manuel de Faria e Sousa (1590–1649), an editor of the poetry of Luis Vaz de Camões (1524–1580), who Southey felt was ‘entitled to a fuller account in a life of Camoens than Mr. Adamson has assigned him’ (14).</note> The proofs of it were returned last week.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The biographical letter which I have begun<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John May, 28 December 1821–21 April 1822, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey, 1819–1821. Part Six</title>, Letter 3772.</note> has lain unfinished from a feeling that such communications would be ill timed while you have such pressing anxieties to occupy your mind. – My first volume of the War is advanced to 600 pages, – about 750 will be the extent, &#38; I am now travelling fast toward the conclusion.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). It ran to 806 pages.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Today I had a chearful letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>; his boys seem to be going on well, &#38; his old age happier than that of most men. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref> was here last week, &#38; from him I heard of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sealys<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Sealy (c. 1752–1821), Lisbon merchant and father of Henry Herbert Southey’s first wife, had died in Lisbon on 11 July 1821. His first wife, Elizabeth Baldwin, had died in 1811; his second marriage is unrecorded.</note> secret marriage, &#38; the manner in which it was disclosed after his death. The old Lisbonians are almost all past away, – your Uncle<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Coppendale (d. 1833), John May’s uncle and business partner.</note> &#38; mine are nearly all that now remain: – &#38; you &#38; I are taking <del>xxx</del> our place among the elder part of <del>xxxxx</del> society. Johnny however will make you old M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> May before I shall be old M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John May’s son had been born in 1802, while Southey’s only living son, Charles Cuthbert Southey, had been born in 1819. John May would therefore have had to be referred to as ‘old Mr May’ to distinguish him from his son long before Southey needed to be referred to as ‘old Mr Southey’.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">Mrs May</ref> &#38; your daughters,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805–1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> not forgetting Charlotte who I hope still remembers the Lamb &#38; the Lark.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">This may refer to a children’s book, possibly Lindley Murray (1745–1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Introduction to the English Reader: or, A Selection of Pieces, in Prose and Poetry; calculated to Improve the Younger Classes of Learners in Reading; and to Imbue their Minds with a Love of Virtue</title> (1811).</note> Write, – &#38; tell me that I may expect you by the first of June –</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4">   yours most affectionately</salute>
            <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
