<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3829" type="letter"><head>3829. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Edward Hawke Locker</ref>], <date when="1822-04-22">22 April 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Huntington Library, LR 324. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Previously published: W. A. Speck, ‘Robert Southey’s Letters to Edward Hawke Locker’, <title>Huntington Library Quarterly</title>, 62.1–2 (1999), 157 [in part].</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-04-22">22 Apr. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I heard lately, upon your authority, a very singular story of the horses belonging to Romanas troops, which were left behind when the men were brought off by the British ships.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of La Romana (1761–1811), a Spanish general. He commanded the Army of the North and ensured its evacuation to Spain in 1808, where he was one of the more successful Spanish commanders. <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 663–664, related that the horses belonging to the Spanish troops were set free on the Danish shore and most of them killed each other in a ‘dreadful work of mutual destruction’.</note> Will you oblige me with the facts? I am just coming to the escape of that army, &#38; being richly provided with accounts both Spanish &#38; English from persons concerned in the adventure, shall be very glad to add an anecdote so curious as a fact in natural history.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I want <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilberforce</ref> to bring the question of Duelling before Parliament,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to William Wilberforce, 3 April 1822, Letter 3818.</note> seeing, as he does, that the detestable license of the press, of which both parties avail themselves without scruple, must make the practise more frequent than it already is. It is my opinion that it might easily be put a stop to, if it were seriously regarded as a breach of the laws, &#38; rendered liable to such a punishment as Juries would not shrink from inflicting; – fine, for example, imprisonment &#38; banishment for the parties &#38; seconds, – according to circumstances. If such a law was past, &#38; it were made known at the same that any Officer in army or navy should be dismissed the service, if he engaged in an affair of this kind, I am persuaded that the object would be at once effected. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilberforce</ref> sees greater difficulty, tho entirely agreeing in the wish: – but he is thinking about it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Will Government let this opportunity pass, for prosecuting the M Chronicle, which is now actually publishing French verses, to excite the French armies to rebellion?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Conservative newspapers, such as the <title>British Neptune</title>, 22 April 1822, had reported that copies of the Whig newspaper, the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, had been seized in Paris for publishing revolutionary verses.</note> Chateaubriand<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">François-René, Vicomte de Chateaubriand (1768–1848), the French writer and diplomat. He was at this time Ambassador to Prussia (1821–1822), before becoming Minister of Foreign Affairs 1822–1824.</note> ought to present a formal complaint, – &#38; the paper ought to be punished as severely as John Bull.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>John Bull</title> (1820–1892) was a popular conservative Sunday newspaper; it had faced a number of legal actions. On 22 April 1822, Robert Waithman (1764–1833; <title>DNB</title>), a Whig MP for the City of London 1818–1820 and 1826–1833, was awarded £500 damages against the paper for libel.</note> <del>xxxx xxxxx only be</del> Otherwise it will appear still more plainly that the liberty of the press is always to be what the Enemies of good order chuse, &#38; never what its friends desire.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2"> farewell my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">  &#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4"> yrs with much respect</salute>
           <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
