<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3833" type="letter"><head>3833. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-05-07">7 May 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 305–306.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address>, <date when="1822-05-07">May 7. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear E. May,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Fortune, I think, has fitted you with a physician<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Jacques (d. 1832), a doctor based in Harrogate.</note> to your taste. He has <hi rend="ital">tabooed</hi> ham, vinegar, red–herrings, and all fruits. But if the melancholy Jaques<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Melancholy Jaques’, a character in <title>As You Like It</title> (1599).</note> were not a heretic, he would never have put you to a trial so far beyond the strength of women. If Eve, when she had the choice of the whole garden besides (a garden, too, as rich in fruits as William Herbert’s,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Herbert (1778–1847; <title>DNB</title>). He abandoned a career in politics and the law for the Church of England, serving as Rector of Spofforth, near Wetherby, 1814–1840, and Dean of Manchester 1840–1847. Herbert was also a poet and a noted writer on botany. His garden at the Old Rectory, Spofforth, was well known and the site of Herbert’s development of the Spofforth crocus.</note> which you have been visiting, is in flowers), could not refrain from the forbidden apple,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title> 3, Eve, the first woman, was tempted to eat the forbidden fruit of the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil. The fruit was usually identified as an apple.</note> how does he suppose that a daughter of Eve can resist strawberries, cherries, and currants, to say nothing of green gooseberries and hard pears?</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Your second letter arrived to–day, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> has it at Mrs. Calvert’s,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (c. 1775–1834), née Mitchinson, the wife of William Calvert.</note> whither she is gone for the remainder of the week. I have not much to tell you. The boat is in the water, and looks very well; the pew<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southey family’s pew at St Kentigern’s church, Crosthwaite.</note> was painted yesterday; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">your uncle Tom</ref> has lost a cow, in calf–bed; sundry rats have been taken; I expect a parcel by the next carrier, and your plant is as well as can be expected; whereby you will understand that there is an addition to its leaves. But this new leaf has been produced in a curious manner, the stem proceeding from the base of the youngest and largest of its three ancestors, and all the folded part from the mother, or middle one; so that its genealogy is more puzzling than the relationship between Dick and John.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Dick and John’ were commonly used for fictional characters, including by Southey himself in his Botany Bay Eclogue, ‘John, Samuel, &#38; Richard’, <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 92–98.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am glad you take so kindly to the waters, and that they seem to agree with you so well. What a happy quarter of an hour you must pass between the two draughts! I had forgotten to tell you, as part of the domestic news, that I have laid hands, since your departure, upon a larger and richer picture of Mukkens<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Cuthbert Southey’s pronunciation of ‘monkeys’.</note> than any which <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> had ever seen before. Having told you all that has happened, I believe I must now tell you what has not. <hi rend="ital">Pone</hi><note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> is not gone; Mr. Midgeley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Midgeley (first name and dates unknown) was renting Greta Lodge, next door to Greta Hall.</note> is not come; Miss W****<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799–1874), Tom Southey’s lodger.</note> is not married: Mr. F***<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777–1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. A surveyor, geologist and mining engineer, Fryer spent part of each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick. He married Mary Laetitia Wilbraham in June 1822.</note> is not false, and a she–Friar will not be the same thing as a Nun; Mr. P***<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> has made no proposals to ****** (by–the–by, if he has ever any children they will all be pipkins)<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A ‘pipkin’ is a small cooking pot, but also a diminutive of the name ‘Philip’, so it is possible that ‘Mr P’ was a Mr Philip.</note>; Sara has had no letter from W***;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> I have not yet heard from Mr. B.;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Grosvenor Charles Bedford.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your mother</ref>, notwithstanding her persevering search, has not found anything under the bed at night; I am neither younger, nor fatter, nor quieter, nor graver, than when you departed for Harrogate. O ye immortal Powers!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Addison (1672–1719; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Cato, a Tragedy</title> (1712), Act 5, scene 3, line 9.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I would send you a noise, but I cannot tell how to enclose it; but you may imagine one at breakfast–time.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My movements will be determined by yours. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Mr. Wordsworth</ref> goes with us, we shall travel in a jaunting–car, which will bring us all back. If I go alone, I shall follow your course to Skipton, and chaise it, solo, from thence, which will be better than taking the Penrith road, and sleeping the second night at Borough Bridge. I do not wish to be more than three days at Harrogate, at the most.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss H.</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonJoanna">her sister</ref>,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Joanna Hutchinson (1780–1841).</note> and so</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you,</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3"> Very magnificent daughter,</salute>
            <signed rend="indent4">YO EL PA.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
