<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3839" type="letter"><head>3839. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-05-17">17 May 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Southey/ Hattersleys Hotel/ Harrogate<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-05-17">17 May. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Edith</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I purpose setting off for Kendal on Wednesday next, &#38; taking the stage to Skipton next day. With regard to your meeting me, you must bear in mind that there is no certainty of my finding room in the coach on either day. On the supposition however that you will go to Bolton<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bolton Abbey, a ruined twelfth-century Augustinian monastery in North Yorkshire.</note> on the Thursday, I must whether you can take me from thence, or not, that I may know how to engage the chaise from Skipton. If I do not meet you, I shall of course stop to see the place, that we may shape our return <del>either</del> by Wensley Dale, or any other course that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref> may think best.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I shall bring with me my summer cold, which is in great perfection. It is very likely that I may leave it at Harrogate, or lose it on the way.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Our weather here is delicious. I was in the river this morning, enjoying myself like a river-God. The Laburnum is just coming into full blossom &#38; its beauty will be over before you see it, – which I am sorry for, for it will be a beautiful sight</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your mother</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs C.</ref> are gone to Barrow,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Barrow House on the shores of Derwentwater, owned by Joseph Pocklington (1804–1874).</note> &#38; as I have had other letters to write, I have only time to scrawl this much, before I set forth to meet them on their way back.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
