<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3843" type="letter"><head>3843. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-05-21">21 May [1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Southey/ Hattersley’s Hotel/ Harrogate<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: Dating from content. This letter was clearly written shortly after that to Edith May Southey, 17 May 1822 (Letter 3839).</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-05-21">Tuesday 21 May.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Edith</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am afraid you will be vexed at seeing a letter instead of your father in person: &#38; this thought vexes me. Last night we heard from Rydal that Miss Joanna Hutchinson<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Joanna Hutchinson (1780–1841), sister-in-law of William Wordsworth.</note> was coming there with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">her sister</ref>; &#38; that Miss H. on account of the Clarksons<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Thomas</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonCatherine">Catherine Clarkson</ref>.</note> arrival, would probably wish <del>to</del> not to linger upon the road. Therefore as the motions for my intended journey were that we might fill a chaise, &#38; return leisurely, seeing all that is to be seen upon the way, the first of these was rendered needless, &#38; the second set aside: so upon due deliberation I came, not very willingly because of your disappointment, (otherwise willingly enough) to the resolution of staying quietly at home.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Inclosed is half a ten pound bill: the other half will come in a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> tomorrow or next day. You will remember not to bring home with you any country bills<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Banknotes issued by banks in Yorkshire, but which would not be readily accepted in Cumberland.</note> that are not current in these parts</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> We shall all rejoice to see you home again. – Yet if you &#38; your friends think the waters seem to be producing such an effect upon you, that it is a pity you should not try them a little longer, – tell me so by return of post, &#38; I will set off to join you before <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss H.s</ref> departure, &#38; remain with you a week or ten days, – as long indeed as I can so that we may be home in time to receive <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">your godfather</ref>. You will not suppose that I have any desire to do this; – but if there be reason to think it would be advantageous to you, I will come.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> sends a kiss, &#38; when I asked how I was to send it, he replied you must <hi rend="ital">wite</hi> it. You will therefore please to understand that one of his kisses is written here. –</p> <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> has been calomelld &#38; jalappd this day, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bel</ref> has been salted.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Calomel (mercury chloride), jalap (derived from the root of a Mexican plant) and various ‘salts’ (for instance, Epsom Salts) were all routinely used as purgatives.</note> – I must tell you that I have advised <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">your Aunt Lovell</ref> to <del>takx</del> take salt-petre instead of salt, for the purpose of <del>making herself of a good</del> colouring her cheeks.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Salt-petre (potassium nitrate) is used as a preservative in the curing of bacon, to which it imparts a pink colour. Salt-petre was also sometimes used as a purgative.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Our weather here is delicious. I bathe every day, but have not been able to wash away my cold. – There is no other news except that I have taken to my straw-hat, &#38; that my poor jacket is fairly worn out at last, after seven years service in different shapes.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Our love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss H.</ref> God bless you my dear child so prays your dutiful father</p>
           <closer> <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
