<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3853" type="letter"><head>3853. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-06-14">14 June 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: x/ 17 JU 17/ 1822<lb/>
               Endorsements: 14 June 1822.; 14 June 1822<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I must beg you to put 10 £ into <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctors</ref> hands for the use of poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>, – who is just in the same condition that he was last year. Poor cast-away that he is, nothing can be done for him to better his state. I dare say he has a tendency to consumption; &#38; every attack will leave him weaker that the last.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have been very unwell myself ever since my last letter was written. My cold which was then perhaps as bad as you can suppose cold to be, got into the chest &#38; I have had cough &#38; fever ever since. Both are abating now, &#38; last night I slept, which I had not done for several nights, because I could not breathe thro my nostrils. I shall be very glad to return to meat &#38; wine, for I feel myself without them as weak as De Wiggle – &#38; am grown thinner that De Higgle.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">These phrases may be part of one of Southey and Bedford’s many elaborate jokes.</note> However I am recovering &#38; promised change of weather (for the glass is falling rapidly) will be of use to me, &#38; the attack has not been such as to leave any uneasiness behind it. Only that in future I must try every means to cut these annual catarrhs short when they make their appearance.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
              <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript><p><date when="1822-06-14">June 14. 1822.</date> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
