<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3855" type="letter"><head>3855. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#JacksonThomas">Thomas Jackson</ref>, <date when="1822-06-15">15 June 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Revd Thomas Jackson/ New Chapel/ City Road<lb/>
               Stamped: [illegible]<lb/>
               Postmark: 2 o’Clock/ 18 JU/ 1822 AN<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Special Collections, Wellesley College. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName>><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1822-06-15">15 June. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I thank you heartily for your Life of John Goodwin,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Jackson, <title>The Life of John Goodwin: Comprising an Account of his Opinions and Writings, and of the Controversies in which he was Engaged in the Defence of Religious Liberty and of General Redemption: with a Review of Several Public Transactions in Great Britain, during the Civil Wars and the Inter-Regnum</title> (1822). This was a study of the clergyman and theologian, John Goodwin (1594–1665; <title>DNB</title>).</note> (which reached me two days ago) &#38; for the gratifying letter that accompanied it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Your book is written in a fair &#38; manly spirit, &#38; is a valuable addition to the history of those times. You have done justice to the merits of a good man, while at the same time you have not dissembled his errors. If history were always written in this spirit, the world might be better than it is. I endeavoured so to write concerning M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wesley,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley: and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> – believing that those readers who might not approve my views, would do justice to my motives. You have done so, &#38; I thank you for it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I shall consult your book with advantage when I arrange my materials for the Life of Cromwell;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey planned, but never wrote, a full-scale biography of Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>).</note> it will give me pleasure to acknowledge my obligations to it, &#38; to express my sense of your civility by sending you the volume. But a considerable time must elapse before this can be ready for the press. Meantime if any circumstances should bring you into this part of the North, I hope you will give me an opportunity of shaking you by the hand.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">I remain Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2"> with sincere respect</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3"> Your obliged &#38; obedient servant</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
