<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3864" type="letter"><head>3864. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1822-06">[late June 1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: Dating from content. The letter must have been written in late June 1822 as Southey refers to expecting a visit from Nicholas Lightfoot ‘next week’ and Lightfoot arrived on 4 or 5 July 1822.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> You will have seen that I wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> on the very day when your note was dispatched. Her sons book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Itinerary of Provence and the Rhone made During the Year 1819</title> (1822).</note> reached me only the day before. Bracebridge Hall<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Washington Irving (1783–1859), <title>Bracebridge Hall, or The Humorists. A Medley</title> (1822). A copy was sent to Southey by John Murray.</note> came with it. I agree with you in your opinion of Irving; only I should not select Westminster Abbey as the best specimen of his talents.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Washington Irving, ‘Westminster Abbey’ in <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.,</title> 2 vols (London, 1820), II, pp. 3–26.</note> I thought it over laboured for the sake of effect, even when I made allowance for the feelings of an American.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Have you read Leucadio Doblado (i.e. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco Whites</ref>) Letters from Spain?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from Spain by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822).</note> They give, as might be expected, a better account of manners &#38; the state of society in that country than can be found in any other work.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I expect my old fellow collegian <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> to visit me next week – whom I have not seen for eight &#38; twenty years.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
