<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3866" type="letter"><head>3866. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1822-07-07">7 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 25 To Miss Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 7 July 1822<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 26–28.</note></head>
            
            
            <p rend="indent1">I have just received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>, in which he says – “you mention my namesake Caroline. If you write, do make my warmest congratulations known to her. – Have I read Ellen Fitzarthur?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820).</note> – There was only one copy in Bath, – no one read a word of it, no one thought of buying it, no one spoke of it. I was the first in this neighbourhood to bring it into notice. I spoke to every one with the utmost warmth of it, as deeply affecting in story, &#38; beautiful in genuine language of poetry. I trumpeted it to Lord &#38; Lady Lansdowne,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess of Lansdowne (1780–1863; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician and great landowner; and his wife, Lady Louisa, née Fox-Strangways (1785–1851). Their country seat was Bowood, Wiltshire.</note> Miss Fox,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Caroline Fox (1767–1845), sister of Lord Holland.</note> &#38; all the literati of Bowood, &#38; <hi rend="ital">without knowing the name</hi>, I flatter myself I contributed in some degree to its more general notice among some distinguished ornaments of taste &#38; literature. I should be happy to know Caroline, &#38; more to think her a relation. I think a poem so remote from the golden – silvery – diamond –alabaster – Pontypool-style <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Pontypool’ was a form of decorated domestic tinplate.</note>of the present Cockney race of Dandy Poetasters<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Cockney school’ was a dismissive term for London-based poets, especially those associated with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunt</ref>.</note> cannot be too much noticed; &#38; I am rejoiced the real touches of nature &#38; passion have awakened attention.”</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Thus for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>, &#38; in a postscript he adds ‘I think I shall write a note to Caroline, with my poem.’</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If authorship in its notoriety brings with it some evils, they are overpaid, where there is desert, by a large portion of good. I owe to it not merely many pleasant acquaintance, but some valuable friends &#38; you will reap the same fruits. My question to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> was concerning your last volume,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> as well as Ellen Fitzarthur: – if he has not seen it, he will look for it now, &#38; he will find there all that he found in the former publication &#38; more. I have shown it to many persons &#38; in no one instance have I been disappointed of seeing it produce the effect which I expected.
               I have <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">a friend</ref> with me now whom I had not seen since we parted at College, eight &#38; twenty years ago – <del>xxx</del> &#60;tho&#62; our occasional communication by letter had never been interrupted. We parted <del>xxx</del> just as mere commencing men, <del>in youth &#38; xxx</del> with the world before us, – &#38; we meet just at that time of life when age &#38; decay are beginning to make themselves felt. You can better feel what the feelings of such a meeting are, than I could express them. I should not have recognized him so much is he changed: he says he should have known me any where. We have been comparing notes, &#38; find our hearts &#38; views just as much in unison as they were when we, literally, lived together at college, – for we breakfasted together every morning, read together, &#38; past every evening together. In this respect I have been peculiarly fortunate, that most of my friendships have been formed for eternity, &#38; grown stronger as they have grown older.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> There is a very bad translation of Herman &#38; Dorothea by Holcroft,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Holcroft (1745–1809; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Herman and Dorothea. A Poem, from the German</title> (1801), a translation of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749–1832), <title>Hermann und Dorothea</title> (1797).</note> but it would show you the plan of the poem. The original I am told is a piece of finished versification: the translation is meant for blank verse by a man who was no poet &#38; did not even understand the common rules of metre.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> You mention <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley.</ref> – I should like to show you some letters which past between that wretched man &#38; me about two years ago.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">At this point is added in another hand: ‘Note. These letters are in possession of Southey’s family – &#38; very remarkable ones they are.’ [Editors note: In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358–359. Southey responded with his letter to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517. Shelley replied in a letter to Southey, 17 August 1820, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 361–363. Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538, closed the correspondence.]</note> He came to this place with his wife immediately after his marriage.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley had stayed in Keswick November 1811–February 1812, shortly after his marriage to Harriet Westbrook. He met Southey a number of times.</note> I saw a great deal of him then, &#38; hoped that he would outgrow the insane opinions which had <del>held</del> &#60;their root&#62;, as I then thought, in mere ignorance not in a corrupted heart &#38; will. And I know a great deal of his accursed history since.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  How are you? &#38; what are you doing? – I have been very much out of order. A cold which comes regularly every year with the summer &#38; continues ten or twelve weeks, has this year attacked my chest; &#38; tho materially better I cannot yet say that it is fairly dislodged. I shall soon have a volume of the Peninsular War<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> abroad; a noble story, which will set foul tongues railing, while it makes sound hearts throb with generous emotions. My Book of the Church<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will speedily follow it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">God bless you – sister-poetess. I have a right to call you so, tho I cannot look for a relationship like <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">yrs truly</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
               
            <postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1822-07-07">7 July. 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
