<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3867" type="letter"><head>3867. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-07-07">7 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS to JR 7 July/ 1822<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 424. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on MS: The letter originally contained an enclosure, Southey to Caroline Bowles, 7 July 1822, Letter 3866.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener><dateline> <date when="1822-07-07">7 July. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I see one ground of hope that the mischief which is going on may be arrested in time.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 2 July 1822, Rickman had told Southey at length about his concerns that the government was unable to transact any business in the face of criticism from the opposition and the press.</note> So long as the people – that is to say the mob, look on with unconcern, the Government has it in its power to recover what it has lost in the H. C. if there were in its service any man of commanding intellect &#38; courage. But where such a man is to be found among the sons of the feeble – I confess I know not. Whether any good can be done by stating the danger plainly, &#38; showing it in <del>its</del> all its bearings – Heaven only knows: the trial at least shall be made.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Surely the water theory cannot be true – the manner in which the roads touch the ravines disproves it, as we observed upon the spot. I do not believe that water would make such shelves, familiar as I am with the margins of lakes, nothing that I have ever seen bears any resemblance to this sort of levelling<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been sending Rickman the fair copy of the journal he kept during their tour of Scotland in August–September 1819. This had provoked both men to further speculation on the origins of the Parallel Roads of Glen Roy that they had seen on 20 September 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp. 212–216. The ‘Roads’ are, in fact, lake terraces formed along the shoreline of an ancient ice-dammed lake.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> – But I am truly gratified that you like the Journal. And heartily wish you may like the foreign ones as well.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902); and his journals recording his visit to the continent in May–August 1817.</note> you will find them as full &#38; as perfectly faithful, but I had not the same opportunities of acquiring information. – I shall soon send you the first packet.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> perhaps, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, may like to look over the Journal. Shall we ever take another journey together? I should like to think so.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman and Southey travelled to the Low Countries in 1826.</note> There is in travelling a sort of true fellowship such as is hardly <del>allowed</del> &#60;attainable&#62; at any other time <del>by the habits of society</del>. While it lasts <del>the</del> <del>xx</del> it is ‘for better for worse’<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A quotation from the ‘Form of Solemnization of Matrimony’ in the Church of England’s <title>Book of Common Prayer</title> (1662).</note> –</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R. </ref> has not read Ellen Fitzarthur &#38; the Widows Tale,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> I recommend them strongly to her. They are written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">the Lady</ref> for whom the inclosed is addressed, – a little timid creature full of all good feelings.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
