<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="1822-07-20" type="letter"><head>3873. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-07-20">20 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham<lb/>
               Stamped: [illegible]<lb/>
               Postmark: 2 o’Clock/ 24 JY/ 1822 AN<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 219. ALS; 2p. This does not include the three draft dedications for the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), which originally accompanied this letter. The text of the dedications reproduced here is taken from that published in John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 318–331.</note></head>
            
            
            <p rend="indent1">Utrum horum?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘which of these’.</note> – You need not return the paper.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Enclosed were draft dedications for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref>; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">George IV</ref>; and Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844; Prime Minister 1801–1804 and Home Secretary 1812–1822; <title>DNB</title>). The second was used, on Herbert Hill’s advice.</note> But let me know your opinion without delay.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I prefer the last.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The second would cost me about nine guineas in court binding, – which is <del>xxx</del> &#60;a&#62; heavy <del>xx</del> tax upon dedications. If however you prefer it, that to Lord S. with a little alteration would be transferable to another work.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#38; the young ones – I have quite got rid of my cold.</p>
           <closer> <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
            <lb/>
            <dateline><date when="1822-07-20">20 July. 1822.</date></dateline>
             <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address>
  <lb/></closer>          
           <postscript> 
              <lg type="stanza"><l rend="center">To the Memory</l>
                 <l rend="center"> of</l>
                 <l rend="center"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref>,</l>
                 <l rend="center">  A Statesman,</l>
                 <l rend="center"> Who, in the most arduous of times,</l>
                 <l rend="center"> With a right English spirit,</l>
                 <l rend="center"> Defended the institutions and upheld the honour of his</l>
                 <l rend="center"> country,</l>
                 <l rend="center">  This work is inscribed</l>
                 <l rend="center"> by</l>
                 <l rend="center">R.S.</l></lg>
            <lb/>
              <lg type="stanza"><l rend="center"><hi rend="ital">To the King</hi>.</l></lg>
            
           <p rend="indent0"> SIR,</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It is with peculiar fitness, as well as pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a history of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">When the Regency devolved into your hands,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George IV became Prince Regent on 5 February 1811.</note> the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor effort were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis everything, under Providence, depended upon your single determination, and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">To you, therefore, this faithful history is offered, as a portion of the tribute which will always be paid to the merits of a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from,</p>
         <p rend="indent1">   Your Majesty’s most dutiful subject and servant,</p>
         <p rend="right">   R.S.</p>
            
            <lb/>
           <p rend="center"> <hi rend="ital">To Lord Sidmouth</hi>.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> In inscribing to your lordship this “History of the Peninsular War,” I am actuated not less by private than by public considerations.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am one of many persons who, at the beginning of the French revolution, were deceived by its specious promises. The error is not one upon which I look back either with compunction or shame. It was connected with generous feelings, and pursued with an utter disregard of worldly interests. Youth, ignorance, and an ardent mind, rendered me easy to be so deluded. I believed that the war in which this country was engaged against France was unjust in its commencement, and iniquitous in its object; and I was ill-informed enough to suppose that popular governments must needs be free, and that whenever such governments could be established, there, in the natural course of things, the people would become virtuous and happy. Thus prejudiced, I suffered myself to be persuaded that the crimes of the revolution were caused by the resistance which was opposed to it; and when the character of that revolution had so developed itself as to make it evident that worse danger was to be apprehended from republican France than that from which Europe had been delivered by the efforts of Great Britain, and the consummate abilities of Marlborough,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650–1722; <title>DNB</title>), main British commander in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–1713), which prevented France dominating continental Europe.</note> still I thought a war which in its origin had been injurious, carried with it a sin from which no change of circumstances in its progress could purify it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">This was my temper when the Peace of Amiens<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Sidmouth was Prime Minister (1801–1804) at the time when the Treaty of Amiens was concluded between the United Kingdom and France on 27 March 1802. This temporarily ended hostilities between the two countries, though war resumed on 18 May 1803.</note> was concluded, and there were many who partook in the same erroneous feeling. No act of amnesty ever produced such conciliatory consequences as that Peace. It restored in me the English feeling which had been deadened; it placed me in sympathy with my country, bringing me thus into that natural and healthy state of mind upon, which time, and knowledge, and reflection, was sure to produce their proper and salutary effect. Now that your lordship has retired from administration, it may not be unpleasing to you, at the close of a long and honourable career, to receive this public and grateful acknowledgement.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The occasion which I have taken is a fitting one. The work records the glorious termination of a war commenced under your ministry with the full accord of the nation, and in just reliance upon God and a good cause. Throughout all the vicissitudes of that long and eventful struggle, whether you were in or out of power, there was no change in your conduct – your heart and voice were always with your country. No factious motives stand upon the record against you; no malevolent opposition; no opinion or sentiment which you could wish to recall. Pursuing the same straightforward course at all times, you supported the honour of Great Britain when you no longer directed its counsels, and finally bore a part in those counsels when the most arduous contest in which Great Britain ever was engaged was brought to a triumphant close.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">That your Lordship may long live to enjoy the approbation of your own heart, and the esteem of all who value as they ought the institutions of their country, is the wish of him who subscribes himself, with sincere respect, 	</p>	
           <p rend="indent3"> Your Lordship’s humble servant,</p>
            <p rend="indent4">R.S.</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
