<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3876" type="letter"><head>3876. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-07-27">27 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 30 JY 30/ 1822<lb/>
               Endorsements: 27 July 1822; 27 July 1822; [in pencil] Fair Sheet of Pen: War/ wanting p. 617 to p. 624/ 4.I./If proofs can be had from/ p. 1 to p 168. <lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">It seems an age since I have seen your handwriting. You see mine for this reason; the printer has now commenced upon my concluding chapter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 15, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 756–806. Thomas Davison (1766–1831) was the book’s printer. The chapter concerned the British army’s retreat to Corunna in 1808–1809 under the command of Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), in which Courtenay had participated.</note> which contains Sir J Moores Campaign, &#38; I have desired that proof may be sent to you – which you will send to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">Courtenay</ref>. If he has any remarks to make upon them, I will weigh them well, – &#38; shall for the chance of receiving them, keep my proofs 48 hours instead of 24. I do not anticipate any corrections of importance but shall be glad to correct even the smallest error or inaccuracy. Time &#38; reflection have only confirmed my first views of that miserable campaign; – &#38; I have had very little to alter in the narrative as it was given in the Ed. An. Register<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 431–459.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Title, Preface &#38; Dedication go by this post, the Ded. is to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> It is very short, but says a great deal &#38; I expect that you will like it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, p. [iii]: ‘It is with peculiar fitness, as well as with pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a History of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals./When the Regency devolved into your hands, the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor efforts were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis every thing depended, under Providence, upon your single determination; and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance./To your Majesty, therefore, this faithful History is offered, as a portion of the tribute due to a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from/Your Majesty’s/Most dutiful subject and servant,/ROBERT SOUTHEY.’ The Preface was on pp. [v]–vi.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Send me as soon as you can the remaining clean sheets.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> departs tomorrow, &#38; I go with him as far as <ref type="m" target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>. He desires me to say that if any chance takes you into Devonshire he should be heartily glad to see you at Crediton, &#38; talk over the events at the Duke of Portlands Installation<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The installation, on 1 July 1793, of William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738–1809; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783, 1807–1809, as Chancellor of the University of Oxford.</note></p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
              <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-07-27">27 July 1822.</date> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
