<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3885" type="letter"><head>3885. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1822-08-17">17 August 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 323–324.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-08-17">17 Aug. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Wynn</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am setting off, not very willingly, to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bolton (1756–1837; <title>DNB</title>), Liverpool merchant, originally from Ulverston. He was a leading figure in the Tory party in Liverpool and one of Canning’s chief supporters as the city’s MP. His home at Storrs Hall was on the east side of Lake Windermere, two miles south of Bowness.</note> where he is expected tomorrow, – if his plans are not changed by Ld Londonderrys unhappy death.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary and Leader of the House of Commons 1812–1822. He had succeeded as 2nd Marquess of Londonderry in 1821. On 12 August 1822 he committed suicide after increasing signs of derangement. His successor as Foreign Secretary and Leader of the Commons was Canning.</note> – It has often appeared wonderful to me that any mind or body can endure the perpetual wear &#38; tear of ministerial business in England. That business would be sufficient for any human capacity, even without the House of Commons: &#38; I am less surprized at an instance like his, of over-excitement, than that instances of insanity so produced, are not more frequent, – especially in minds which have little or no religious principle to regulate them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">What a blessing is tranquillity! I am so accustomed &#60;to&#62; it, that any thing which interrupts my ordinary course of life seems a change for the worse, &#38; I do not even leave home for a couple of days on an occasion like this, without reluctance. During the last month I have taken a great deal of exercise, to the material improvement of my health; – first with my old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref>, &#38; lately with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. We have been mountaineering in all directions; &#38; I shall have another weeks work of the same kind on my return. The sensible strength which I have gained must compensate for a loss of time, which otherwise I could not afford.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My first volume of the war is finished, – the last proof sheet is now on the table before me. I have dedicated it to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">King</ref>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, p. [iii]: ‘It is with peculiar fitness, as well as with pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a History of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals./When the Regency devolved into your hands, the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor efforts were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis every thing depended, under Providence, upon your single determination; and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance./To your Majesty, therefore, this faithful History is offered, as a portion of the tribute due to a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from/Your Majesty’s/Most dutiful subject and servant,/ROBERT SOUTHEY.’</note> Whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> means to delay the publication till the winter I know not; – this is his concern, &#38; I am perfectly indifferent about it. – One of the first things which I shall do will be to resume the Tale of Paraguay,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &#38; go on with it, resolutely &#38; doggedly, till it is compleated. This I must do, because my Ways &#38; Means require it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> But I am interrupted &#38; must close my dispatches</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
