<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3886" type="letter"><head>3886. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>, <date when="1822-08-26">26 August 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898)<lb/>
               Previously published: Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898), pp. 33–34.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">KESWICK</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1822-08-26">26<hi rend="ital">th Aug</hi>. 1822.</date></dateline></opener>
            
           <p rend="indent0"> My dear Heraud, – I have now an opportunity of sending back your tragedy;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud’s unpublished tragedy ‘Nero’.</note> but time will only allow me to say with it, that in the course of the winter I expect to visit London, and that one of the first things which I shall do there will be to look for you. For the present it will be of more advantage to you to store your mind by reading than to exercise it much in composition. Command of language you already possess, and every other requisite for a poet which nature can bestow: arrangement is what you have to learn. Your last letter with the account of your brother’s death<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Merzeau Bird Heraud (c. 1811–1822), Heraud’s younger brother, died on 16 April 1822.</note> affected me greatly. Take care of your own health, which is best done by keeping your mind tranquil. Be not intemperate in your studies, and be not too eager for that reputation which, sooner or later, you will surely obtain. Farewell, and believe me, yours affectionately,</p>
           <closer> <signed rend="right">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
