<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3905" type="letter"><head>3905. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#LaingDavid">David Laing</ref>], <date when="1822-10-11">11 October 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections, The Laing Collection. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note>
            </head>
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-10-11">11 Oct. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I return you your books<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">David Laing had loaned Southey books to help with his projected, but unrealised, life of George Fox (1624–1690; <title>DNB</title>), founder of Quakerism.</note> with many thanks for their use. Forgive me for not sending them sooner. But from the time I saw you till last week, I have &#60;been&#62; almost wholly engaged with guests &#38; visitors, – &#38; in the necessary task of recruiting my health by continued exercise.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have retained Croeses Latin History<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Gerard Croese (1642–1710), <title>Historia Quakeriana</title> (1695), no. 767 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> because I ought to have it at hand during the whole of my progress. Will you spare it to me? And have the goodness to send me the following books from your Catalogue</p>
            <lb/>
           <p rend="indent1"> 1681 – Martyres (Petre) de Rebus &#38;c<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Martyr d’Anghiera (1457–1526), <title>De Rebus Oceanicis et Novo Orbe</title> (1574), no. 1811 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">/<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The forward slash (/) is added in another hand for this entry and the subsequent one; this mark probably indicates the works that were sent to Southey.</note> 1722 – Pinto (Mich) de Sousa &#38;c –<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaspar Pinto Correia (1596–1664), <title>Musa Panegyrica in Theodosium</title> (1624), no. 2253 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey noted in his copy: ‘This singularly rare book I obtained from Laing’s Catalogue.’</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> / 2865 – Finestres, Hist: de el real Monasterio de Poblet.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jaime Finestres y de Monsalvo (1691–1769), <title>Historia de el Real Monasterio de Poblet</title> (1753–1765), no. 3300 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  5334 Vie du Madame Guion<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey possessed Jeanne Marie Bouvier de la Motte Guyon (1648–1717), <title>The Life of Lady Guion</title> (1772), no. 1722 in the sale catalogue of his library. He did not own a French edition of this work.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> 2941. Isla. Cartas Familiares.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">José Francisco de Isla (1703–1781), <title>Cartas Familiares</title> (1786).</note></p>
            <lb/>
            <p rend="indent1">The easiest mode of paying for them, will be in London, if you will tell me where I shall direct the payment to be made.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> You were in too great a hurry when you past thro <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. When next you come you must allow yourself more time. There are many things both within doors &#38; without which I should have pleasure in showing you.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Present my remembrances to your father.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Laing (1761–1832; <title>DNB</title>), Edinburgh bookseller and publisher.</note> &#38; believe me</p>
            <closer>   <salute rend="indent2">my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">   yrs very truly</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent1">I inclose a letter for <ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">Mr Feldborg</ref>, containing payment for some books.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">This letter is untraced but probably contained payment for the ‘materials’ Feldborg had supplied to assist Southey’s study of works in Danish, including those gifted to him in 1822 by Adam Oehlenschläger (1779–1850), Danish poet and playwright, and Bernhard Severin Ingemann (1789–1862), Danish novelist and poet; see Robert Southey to Andreas Andersen Feldborg, 26 June 1822, Letter 3858. Three volumes of Oehlenschläger’s works and ten volumes of Ingemann’s works were nos. 786 and 1480, respectively, in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
