<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3912" type="letter"><head>3912. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1822-11-02">2 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J.T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 2. Pump Court / Temple / London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 5 NO 5/ 1822<lb/>
               Endorsement: 1822. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ RS. Keswick<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Previously published: W. Braekman, ‘Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge’, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 125–127.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">It is quite necessary that the Editor of the QR. should be a person in whom Government can confide; but I have no notion that any member of the Government would be consulted in the choice, or that any pledge can be required. The truth is that Government &#60;interferes&#62; in such things less than for its own interest, &#38; the interests of the country it ought to do. Upon the course to be pursued by such a Journal, you &#38; I are perfectly agreed. – The only member of Government with whom I have any direct communication (except by accident) is <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Wynn</ref>, – &#38; I will without delay let him know my wishes upon the subject.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 2 November 1822, Letter 3913. Gifford was considering whether to retire as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>; Southey wished John Taylor Coleridge to succeed Gifford (as he briefly did in 1824–1825).</note> I have written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to [John Murray], 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> with whom the choice must rest.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> What you said concerning the payment of a printers bill may perhaps rather imply need in the printer than in the bookseller. There is much competition for a great publisher’s employ; &#38; the booksellers (who as far as I know them, have the true trading spirit, in the worst meaning of the words) – take advantage of it, so as to pay the lowest possible price, &#38; take eighteen months credit, while they collect their own debts half-yearly. – The QR is the foundation of <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> fortune. When he moved from Fleet Street, it was an adventure hazarded in consequence of the success of the review, &#38; without the capital required.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray had launched the <title>Quarterly Review</title> in 1809; he moved his publishing firm from 32 Fleet Street to grander premises at 50 Albermarle Street in 1812, when he bought the business belonging to William Miller (1769–1844; <title>DNB</title>).</note> And I know that a year or two afterwards he was so much in arrears with the Courier<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title> (1792–1842) was a London evening newspaper. Southey received a free copy through his long friendship with Daniel Stuart, its co-owner 1796–1822.</note> for advertising, that they would advertise for him no longer without prompt payment. At present I rather doubt his judgement as a publisher, than his prosperity. He must have lost a great deal by large prices given for bad books: &#38; latterly the bookselling trade has suffered more by the pressure upon the gentry,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Corn prices had been falling since 1819 and reached their lowest point in 1822; this situation produced political controversy and calls from some landowners for action to help agriculture.</note> than any other. But the Quarterly is not affected by this in any material degree; – it is likely to gain quite as many purchasers as it may lose; &#38; it alone, is a fortune.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Had there been any Gods in Albermarle Street, an earthquake must surely have been felt &#60;there&#62; or some other portentous signal – at what passed with Mawman.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Mawman (1759–1827), bookseller and author from York, who became a well-known London publisher. His firm was based in the City of London. Mawman had proposed to set up a rival journal to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, edited by Southey, though this project did not materialise. Southey was, instead, campaigning for John Taylor Coleridge to take over the <title>Quarterly Review</title> after Gifford’s retirement.</note> But tho I am arrived at that age when the necessity of laying by money is felt, &#38; tends strongly to create the love of it, I do not think any offers however advantageous, ought to withdraw me from a course of life so congenial to me in all respects, as that which I now enjoy: nor that I ought to give up more time to temporary subjects, than is necessary for supplying my ways &#38; means. The offer may be for your consideration, if our present object fails; – but I hope it will not fail.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> You ask me respecting Lingard I had sent for <del>it</del> &#60;his history&#62; with an intention of reviewing <del>x xxx x</del> it &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref> <del>xx</del> together,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lingard (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A History of England: from the First Invasion by the Romans to the Accession of Henry VIII</title> (1819), no. 1634 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; and Sharon Turner, <title>History of England</title> (1814–1823), no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Neither book was reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> – a task which may very well be transferred to you, without any inconvenience <del>xx</del> on my part. The book arrived only two or three days ago. I read the reign of William Rufus, which is not nearly so good as <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref>, – &#38; the Roman period, which is very well done, infinitely better than I have ever seen it done before.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lingard, <title>A History of England: from the First Invasion by the Romans to the Accession of Henry VIII</title>, 3 vols (London, 1819), I, pp. 457–487, 1–63, on the reign of William II (c. 1056–1100; King of England 1087–1100; <title>DNB</title>) and the Roman involvement in Britain from 55 BC to the fifth century. Southey compares the first of these treatments with that in Sharon Turner, <title>History of England</title>, 3 vols (London, 1814–1823), I, pp. 108–130.</note> Farther I have not &#60;yet&#62; seen. But I have read his former publication – a history of the A-Saxon Church,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lingard, <title>The Antiquities of the Anglo-Saxon Church</title> (1806). An edition from 1810 was no. 1728 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which is full of sophistry, &#38; that worst kind of falsehood which is produced by the suppression of truths. – The question of suppression in Beckets history is the subject of an Appendix to Beringtons Hist. of Henry 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> a book of great ability,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Berington (1743–1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Reign of Henry the Second, and of Richard and John, his Sons; With the Events of the Period, from 1154 to 1216. In which the Character of Thomas a Becket is vindicated from the Attacks of George Lord Lyttelton</title>, 2 vols (Birmingham, 1790), II, Appendix II, pp. 379–413. Appendix II defended the conduct of St Thomas Becket (c. 1119–1170; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1162–1170.</note> which you should peruse when you set about Lingard &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>. The course of reading is one, in which increase of appetite grows by what it feeds on. As soon as I have gone thro Lingard I will return it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> for your use.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> We have not heard of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartleys</ref> arrival at Ambleside.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge did not arrive in Ambleside to take up a position as a teacher until 1823.</note> He may probably be staying at Birmingham upon his way, – or possibly he may have got out of sight in London. I think if he had <del>xxx</del> known that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his Mother</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sister</ref> set out on Wednesday next for the south, he would have deferred his journey to the north, for the sake of seeing them. They make visits at Derby<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge took her daughter to visit Elizabeth Evans (1758–1836), of Darley, near Derby. Sara and Samuel Taylor Coleridge had stayed with Mrs Evans in 1796, when there was a possibility that Coleridge would tutor her children.</note> &#38; at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson’s</ref> (near Ipswich) before they reach London, or rather Highgate. The cause of the journey is <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara’s</ref> strong desire to see her father</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I re[MS missing]ice to hear that you are going on well in your nearest &#38; dear[MS missing]ons, – &#38; that your late alarm has past way. Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">My old friend Lightfoot</ref> has <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">a son</ref> at Exeter whose character is such that I should be glad to hear young John<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John May (1802–1879) did not enter Exeter College, Oxford, until 1823.</note> had formed an acquaintance with him. By the fathers account he is a youth of thorough good principles &#38; good sense.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs &#38;c</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-11-02">2 Nov. 1822.</date></p></postscript>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
