<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3920" type="letter"><head>3920. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bartholomew Frere</ref>], <date when="1822-11-17">17 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 43. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on identity of correspondent: Southey had received a box of papers from Frere in early October 1822, Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 11 October 1822, Letter 3906. These papers were to aid Southey in writing the second volume of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-11-17">17 Nov. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My Dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Had I known you were returned from France, I should have written to acknowledge the receit of the papers, &#38; to thank you for them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I feel confident that the use which I shall make of these letters, can in no possible manner compromise any person, nor hurt the feelings of any one of the writers. You will indeed perceive by the first volume,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> that where the narrative is drawn from original materials, no reference either general or particular, is made to the authorities; neither have I any where specified the sources to which I have had access. My reason for this was twofold, – first because some of the communications were confidential, – &#38; secondly because it behoved me, where I was <del>not</del> writing from unpublished documents, to take upon myself the sole responsibility.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The only person likely to have any uncomfortable feeling in the perusal, is Sir Robert Wilson,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilson (1777–1849; <title>DNB</title>), the radical MP for Southwark 1818–1831, had commanded the Loyal Lusitanian Legion of Portuguese troops in the Peninsular War. In December 1808 he advanced to Ciudad Rodrigo in Spain and maintained his position, despite the retreat of the main British army to Corunna. Southey believed that Wilson’s actions helped prevent the French advancing on Lisbon, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), II, pp. 77–83, 241–245.</note> &#38; that discomfort will arise not from any thing which is said of him, but from the comparison which he himself will make between what he then was, &#38; what he is now. It is not my business to hint at this. I shall do him full justice for the good service which he performed; &#38; do it the more willingly, because it was neither generally understood nor sufficiently rewarded.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am very cautious with regard to others, however little I may be thought so as concerning myself. But do me the favour to look at the proof sheets in their progress, &#38; I will alter any passage in which you may think I have made an indiscrete use of these materials. – I shall go to press, as soon as <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> obtains for me Olivarez’s History of the War in Catalonia.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. This had mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877.</note></p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">farewell my Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent1"> &#38; believe me thankfully &#38; truly yours</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
