<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3921" type="letter"><head>3921. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>], <date when="1822-11-22">22 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">There are some Ecclesiastical Lives published by Todd (Bryan Waltons is one)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Todd (1763–1845; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, literary editor and author of <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of the Right Rev. Brian Walton, D.D. Lord Bishop of Chester, Editor of the London Polyglot Bible</title> (1821), no. 2187 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Todd’s account of Brian Walton (1600–1661; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Chester 1660–1661, was his only ecclesiastical biography.</note> which might be useful to the Book of the Church<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> And I think <ref type="m" target="people.html#NicholsJohn">Nichols</ref> also published a collection of the same kind, including Bp Newtons Life.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Newton (1704–1782; <title>DNB</title>), the Bishop of Bristol 1761–1782. His biography was included in <title>The Lives of Dr. Edward Pocock, the Celebrated Orientalist, by Dr. Twells; of Dr. Zachary Pearce, Bishop of Rochester, and of Dr. Thomas Newton, Bishop of Bristol by themselves; and of the Rev. Philip Skelton, by Mr. Burdy</title> (1816), no. 1737 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. It was published by C. and J. Rivington, not John Nichols.</note> These may come in to my assistance for the last period, – which is where I need it most. The Acta Sanctorum<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1794), the huge compendium of hagiographies that Southey bought in Brussels in 1817; no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> have been of special use for early times. Please to send with them the last Q.R but one,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), published 4 July 1822.</note> – which I have not received.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> In my presentation list I forgot</p>
            <p rend="indent2"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Revd. Neville White</ref> – Norwich –</p>
            <p rend="indent2"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi></ref> – Norwich</p>
            <p rend="indent2">&#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">George Ticknor</ref> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boston. New England to the care of Samuel Williams Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> 13. Finsbury Square.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Williams (c. 1761–1842) was an expatriate American merchant, who had founded the banking house of Welles &#38; Williams in London. The bank’s office at 13 Finsbury Square was used as a forwarding address by many well-connected American travellers.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknor</ref>, whom you probably recollect, is now Professor of Modern Languages at Harvard College. It is from him that I have received my supplies of American books, &#38; I am sure his efforts will be used in aid of mine to bring about a proper &#38; friendly feeling between that part of America at least, &#38; England.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent3">yrs very truly</salute>
               <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript> <p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1822-11-22"> 22 Nov. 1822.</date></p></postscript>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
