<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3935" type="letter"><head>3935. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref>] [fragment], <date when="1822-12">[c. mid-December 1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 1p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: This dates from Sara Coleridge and her daughter’s visit to the south of England, 1822–1823. They had left Keswick by 8 November; see Robert Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 8–12 November 1822 (Letter 3915). They spent about a month staying with Elizabeth Evans near Derby. This letter probably dates from mid-December 1822, when they were in transit between Derby and the Clarksons’ home, Playford Hall, Suffolk; see Southey to John May, 5 December 1822 (Letter 3927). On their way to the latter, they paid a brief visit to Cambridge, where Derwent Coleridge was a student.<lb/>
               Note on MS: This fragmentary letter (or at least the surviving version of it) was possibly not sent to Sara Coleridge but instead dispatched at an unknown date to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, a connoisseur of Mrs Coleridge’s linguistic practice, as an example of her lingo grande. This is suggested by the fact that the manuscript survives as part of a short run of letters to Bedford and – unusually – opens (top of fol. 1r) with an address to him: ‘And so-oh-oh/ Dar Miscumber Bedfordiddlededford/ I sub&#60;cum&#62;scribe myself – your sincumcere friendiddledend/ Robcumbert Southeydiddledouthey/ Student of the Lingo Grande, Graduate in Butlerology, Professor of/ the Science of Noncumsensediddledence, of sneezing, &#38; of vocal music –/ P.L. &#38; LLD.’ This nearly duplicates the closing salutation of Southey to Bedford, 24 December 1822 (Letter 3940), perhaps indicating that this fragment was sent to Bedford shortly after this date.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>Dear Venerable</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> Odiddledowloo, why is it that neither you nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">that poor lassitudinarian thing</ref> will write to the &#60;Umaining&#62; porkaboarobumbels of this family? <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Scampalum</ref> <del>xxxxxxxx</del> looks every day for a letter, &#38; every day it gives her a pange to be disappointed. We thought you would not stay more than a jiffump among the Chappets &#60;at Cambridge&#62; giddytonians as they are, &#38; shall think you can hardly be indiscrukt enough to be dumdawdling, among them, for you are not as improvidentipur. Yet had you reached Playford,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Playford Hall, home of Thomas Clarkson.</note> we think you would shartainly have written. This we have conclucted.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I write in your own lingo-grande, <del>because</del> &#60;because then&#62; if you should happen to leave <del>the</del> your &#60;portfolio&#62; <del>xxxx</del> about &#38; any improprieter or indelicardium should be roken &#38; dabdobbering among your papers, the signifumpification of this will not be undercamestood, at least not in a momper.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Scampalum</ref> will have told you most of what has happened, since you &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">the lassitudinarian</ref> left your two holes at the table here. The journey we hope will have given both your constitutions a jerk. You must stulch when the weather is not going to ramp &#38; tear so as to make slatching disagreeavobus, – &#38; when the rampasity of the day prevents any other exercise then I advise you to be horsemangandered, which is better than stroming or meandering up &#38; down the room <del>I practice what I preach</del> It will never do for you to be a slouwdowdlecum, a slowdonothinger. For you to keep in health the nocksen must vork as well as the towsalowset the foottells-tottels &#38; legrums as well as in <del>chaprat</del> under futoarum</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Dont cody me now for this good advice – nor detest me, nor play the very dunder, forshammenum if you do. Dont tear goarum (why should poor gravum suffer such toru?) – dont go tarradiddle.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
