<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3983" type="letter"><head>3983. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1823-03-19">19 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 22 MR 22/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsement: Mar 19 – 1823/ R Southey<lb/>
MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note>
         </head>
            
<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-03-19">19 March. 1823</date></dateline>
   
  <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have discovered to my vexation, that in returning Strypes Life of Cranmer<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Strype (1643–1737; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memorials of the Most Reverend Father in God Thomas Cranmer, Sometime Lord Archbishop of Canterbury: Wherein the History of the Church, and the Reformation of it during the Primacy of the said Archbishop are Greatly Illustrated; and Many Singular Matters Relating Thereunto, now first Published</title> (1694). The book was reprinted by Oxford University Press in 1812 and was no. 2754 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. It focused on Thomas Cranmer (1489–1556; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1533–1555.</note> to you some time ago I was mistaken in supposing the extracts which I had made would be sufficient for my purpose; – for upon looking to them I find references to several parts of importance which were too long for transcription. May I request you therefore to send me the book again, – that what will be perhaps the most impressive chapter in the Book of the Church may not be weakened by this oversight.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">One of chapters 12–14 of Southey’s <title>Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 1–242.</note> – I feel in some degree ashamed at troubling you thus in consequence of a mistake; but if you saw my notes I am sure you would at once forgive me, &#38; wonder at the cost of labour expended upon them, – not at the economy of time which these references were designed to effect.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">Yrs very truly</salute>
		 <signed rend="indent3">  R Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
