<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3987" type="letter"><head>3987. Robert Southey to [Unknown Correspondent], <date when="1823-03-23">23 March 1823 </date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Morgan Library, MA 63. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished. <lb/>
Note on correspondent: The person seeking Southey’s assistance in securing a position is unidentified.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-03-23">23 March. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
	<p rend="indent1">The situations in the British Museum are in the joint appointment of the Archbishop of Canterbury, the Chancellor, &#38; the Speaker;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Manners-Sutton (1755–1828; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1805–1828; John Scott, 1st Baron Eldon (1751–1838; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801–1806, 1807–1827; Sir Charles Manners-Sutton (1780–1845; <title>DNB</title>), the Speaker 1817–1835. The holders of these offices were the three Principal Trustees of the British Museum and were ultimately responsible for appointments to its staff.</note> of course those of the Kings Library will be so, when it is removed &#38; placed under their direction.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The King’s Library was formed by George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>) and given to the nation by George IV in 1823. A new wing had to be built at the British Museum (1823–1827) to accommodate the books.</note> </p>
	<p rend="indent1">But the Kings Library has already a proper establishment of librarians, &#38; these persons, beyond all doubt, will accompany it, unless for other reasons than for the removal, any of them may vacate their offices. – I have no interest with either of the three Trustees, nor any knowledge of them. The duties of a librarian are neither difficult nor arduous; – literary habits would, undoubtedly, be a recommendation to the office, &#38; some classical knowledge, should suppose a requisite.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Where I can assist you my good word shall never be wanting: – where I cannot you must be content with my good will. I am sorry that the latter is the case at present.</p>
            <closer>	<salute rend="indent1">Farewell &#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Yours sincerely</salute>
   <signed rend="indent3">	Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
