<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3988" type="letter"><head>3988. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William Gifford</ref>, <date when="1823-03-23">[c. 23 March 1823] </date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Gifford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> <lb/>
Endorsement: April 1823/ R. Southey Esq<lb/>
MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: Dating from content and other correspondence. This letter was written before 28 March 1823 when Southey informed Herbert Hill that he had asked Gifford about writing on Spanish affairs for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> (Letter 3991). On 6 April 1823 Southey told Rickman that he had written to Gifford ‘a fortnight ago’, i.e. 23 March or thereabouts (Letter 3995). </note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
	<p rend="indent1">I have inserted in these proofs a few lines in honour of our friend Jeremy Bentham.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey added a note (p. 502) to his mention of Bentham: ‘Long may it [Bentham’s head] continue to adorn those shoulders! For were the egregious Jeremy to be deprived of it (as the Orator of the Human Race [Anacharsis Cloots (1755–1794)] was before him) by an unlucky effect of his own doctrines, let us not be suspected of flattery when we say, that – “The best of workmen, and the best of wood,/Could <title>scarce</title> supply him with a head so good.” [<title>Criticisms on the Rolliad. Part the First</title> (London, 1785), p. 134].</note> He loves the Quarterly Review &#38; he calls me S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeremy Bentham (1748–1832; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Church-of-Englandism and its Catechism Examined</title> (London, 1818), p. 26.</note> I hope therefore you will not think the compliment ill-bestowed.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The praise which is bestowed upon Elia (my poor old acquaintance <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref>) I trust you will let stand.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had commended Lamb’s <title>Essays of Elia</title> (1823) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 524, published 8 July 1823, but commented that the book ‘wants only a sounder religious feeling, to be as delightful as it is original’. Lamb took offence and responded with ‘Letter of Elia to Robert Southey, Esquire’ (<title>London Magazine</title>, 8 (October 1823), 400–407).</note> It is written in kindness, &#38; carries with it a monition, which may be felt as it is intended. The passage quoted from his Essays, relates to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunts</ref> child; you will perceive therefore how well my comment upon it was deserved.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thornton Leigh Hunt (1810–1873; <title>DNB</title>), eldest son of Leigh Hunt and later editor of the <title>Daily Telegraph</title> 1855–1873. Southey had quoted (524–525) from <title>Essays of Elia</title> (London, 1823), pp. 154–155, which described how the young Thornton was still subject to night terrors, despite being brought up without religion or knowledge of popular superstitions.</note></p>
	<p rend="indent1">How you may like the paper I know not, as to its execution. Its intent I know you will approve. And after reading it consecutively &#38; carefully, I am glad that I have written it.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Will you have an article upon Spain &#38; Portugal?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> If so, let me know it without delay, &#38; ill as I can afford the time, I will take it in hand, – &#38; finish it in London, for the number after this which is in the press. – Some persons who are going wrong upon that subject I can certainly set right; – &#38; chastise, as they deserve, those who are misleading them.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">I hope you are recovering strength as the spring advances. – I would fain be in town at this time that I might return when the leaves are opening, – for that fortnight is worth the whole remainder of the year. But I am fixed to my desk for the next six weeks.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not leave Keswick for London until 3 November 1823.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Farewell my Dear Sir</salute>
	   <salute rend="indent1">&#38; believe me</salute>
	   <salute rend="indent2">Yours very truly</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
