<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3997" type="letter"><head>3997. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-04-11">11 April 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer,/ Westminster<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 14 AP 14/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsement: 11 April 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1823-04-11">11 April. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I have sent under <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right Honours</ref> frank, a packet to you, which I will beg you to send to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref>, its shape making it unfit for the twopenny post, &#38; its palpable contents somewhat too temptatious (if there be such a word) for that conveyance.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The packet was a gift from Edith May Southey to her cousin, Henry Herbert Southey, Jnr (1822–1829).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Tom</ref> sails on Monday next for Quebec, – to look out a place for his family in Upper Canada. He has a letter from the Colonial Office for Sir Peregrine Maitland,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Peregrine Maitland (1777–1854; <title>DNB</title>), a soldier and Lieutenant-Governor of Upper Canada 1818–1828 and Governor of Novia Scotia 1828–1834.</note> &#38; by mere accident obtains one in this place to the person who is employed under Sir P. in allotting the grants of land there.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Marshall (b. 1779), Colonel of the Lanark Militia and Captain in the Canadian Fencibles. He was Secretary and Superintendent of the new Lanark settlement on the Clyde river in Eastern Ontario from its foundation in 1820 until 1830.</note> His purpose is to return in the autumn, &#38; remove his household thither this time next year. As you may well suppose this presses heavily upon my spirits, as any event must needs do which can only be reconciled to us by necessity, – &#38; absolutely necessary this is. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">His wife</ref> has a friend &#38; relation at Quebec<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew Bell (1769–1849), a wealthy merchant, iron manufacturer and land speculator in Quebec, originally from Berwick-upon-Tweed. He was a relative of Sarah Southey.</note>, who is likely to be very useful to them.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I do not recollect whether I thanked you for the French blue<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bleu de France, a blue pigment used in painting. Bedford was supplying this for Edith May Southey’s use.</note> – upon the merits of which I will report when <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> instructs me. Send me, I pray you, some money <hi rend="ital">pro necessitatibus meis</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘for my necessities’.</note> I have workmen employed in building outhouses, the cost of which is to be deducted from my rent, but the outlay for which I must advance. The next Q.R. will cover this &#38; my domestic expences for some time.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> And I count upon the B of the Church<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> – at which I am working doggedly, – for my travelling expences, &#38; other calls. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> I suppose continues as ill as your last notice of him stated; – he would otherwise have replied to my question whether he chose to have a paper upon the state of Spain.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write an article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> on Spain at this time.</note></p>
                  <p rend="indent1">Our weather here is delightful, &#38; has long been so. – Pray send me some vegetable marrow-seeds, – it is time they were in the ground. If you were here I would feed you with that food which mortals call <hi rend="ital">laver</hi>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">An edible seaweed. The barrel was a present from John Kenyon; see Southey to John Kenyon, 3 April 1823, Letter 3994.</note> – its Olympian name I know not. A barrel arrived last week, which I can find no one to partake with me. Even <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> declares vehemently against it, &#38; says “he hates it, it is so dirty.”</p>
                    <p> There is a report in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brougham</ref> has taken my house, – &#38; that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> has sent for me to London. – You see we have our politicians, – &#38; wise ones too!</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">- I wish I were London, – because there I should the sooner escape from it, &#38; its exhausting round of engagements. But my book <hi rend="ital">must</hi> be finished first, – &#38; like every thing else it grows under my hands. Alas, my labours are like the widows cruise,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">1 <title>Kings</title> 17: 4 ‘For thus saith the LORD God of Israel, The barrel of meal shall not waste, neither shall the cruise of oil fail, until the day <hi rend="ital">that</hi> the LORD send rain on the face of the earth.’</note> &#38; not my resources. And two months absence from home, will <del>xxx</del> cost not only their expences but the loss of what I might have earned during that time. However I am still able &#38; willing, – tho too evidently less alert than I was in former days. That is – I compose much more slowly: not for lack of matter, – but because I proceed with more consideration. – You must come down this year, were it for no other reason but to mercurialize<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">To treat with mercury. As mercury was a common treatment for constipation, Southey may mean that a visit from Bedford would unblock his writing process. </note> me.</p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
