<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4000" type="letter"><head>4000. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-04-18">18 April 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Ap<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 18. 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the half notes, &#38; thank you also for your solicitude concerning an evil which is not to be averted.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey was considering emigrating to Canada and Southey had mobilised his friends to help.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has done all that I asked him, &#38; I believe also all that could be done at this time, by facilitating matters at the Colonial Office, &#38; obtaining <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">him</ref> thro that channel good letters of introduction. The time when he might have been served in his profession was when <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleThomas ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Grenville</ref> was at the Admiralty, – &#38; perhaps this would have been done if that Administration had not built a wall that they might run their heads against it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The government of 1806–1807 had fallen because of its insistence on pressing George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>) to agree to Catholic Emancipation.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">There prevails an opinion that I have made a large fortune by my writings that I enjoy large pensions, &#38; moreover am a person of the greatest influence with government. Upon this latter point, even <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> who ought to have been wiser, has presumed far too much. The ship<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey never commanded a Royal Navy ship; it is not clear which posting he received due to Herries’s intervention.</note> which he did gain thro my means would never have been obtained <del>by</del> had it not been for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>. No other course was left for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">him</ref>, but that which he is now taking. – My death, – or disablement – (even the latter a possible event at any moment) would leave him without any assistance; – his, or that of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wife</ref>, – would throw a family of eight children<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813–1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815–1864); Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816–1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818–1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820–1834); and Sophia Jane Southey (1822–1859). Thomas Castle Southey (1824–1896) completed the family.</note> – almost wholly upon my hands. He will secure a provision for them by emigration, at the cost of some privations &#38; some difficulties at first – It has long been a burthen upon my mind, – which has but too many cares of its own</p>
<p rend="centre">———</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have behaved ill to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CunninghamAllan">Cunningham</ref> in not thanking him for the tales which he sent me.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Allan Cunningham, <title>Sir Marmaduke Maxwell, a Dramatic Poem; The Mermaid of Galloway; The Legend of Richard Faulder; and Twenty Scottish Songs</title> (1822), no. 745 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The real cause has been that I meant to write more than a mere letter of thanks, &#38; have never found time to do it. The older I grow, the slower I proceed with my compositions, – &#38; the less leisure I have.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Has <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">the Mag: Rot.</ref> tried acupunctuation for his rheumatism? I see a treatise upon it advertised.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">James Morss Churchill (1796–1863), <title>A Treatise on Acupuncturation; Being a Description of a Surgical Operation Originally Peculiar to the Japanese and Chinese, and by Them Denominated Zin-King. Now Introduced into European Practice, with Directions for its Performance and Cases Illustrating its Success</title> (1821).</note>
	Do not delay the Vegetable Marrow Seeds – because the seasons will tarry for no man, &#38; it is time they were in the hot-bed.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A nineteenth-century method of growing salad crops up to a month earlier than usual, by planting them on top of a layer of manure that provided heat as it broke down.</note></p>
   <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1823-04-18">Apr. 18. 1823.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
