<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
        <head></head> <div n="4004" type="letter"><head>4004. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1823-04-19">19 April 1823 </date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener>
   <p rend="indent1">The account which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> gave me was that three pounds per head were paid by the parishes for the passage of the emigrants<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey sailed from Whitehaven on 20 April 1823 on the brig <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and reached Quebec on 27 May. He investigated emigrating to Canada but decided against this option. The <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> carried 53 settlers. Some of those from Cumberland had received assistance from their parishes to emigrate.</note> that sum including the food upon the voyage which is calculated at four weeks. I do not know whether the adventurers received any money to support them on their first arrival. They were certainly persons either chargeable to the parish at the time or as sure to become so, that this has been deemed the cheapest method of providing <del>xxxx</del> &#60;for&#62; them – for it is a parochial business. I cannot answer M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilmots<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilmot-Horton (1784–1841; <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1821–1828, and an indefatigable promoter of emigration schemes. </note> questions more precisely at present, – but I will endeavour to obtain such information. My brother has sailed – &#38; by good fortune for the human cargo onboard there goes a navy surgeon in the same vessel, who is appointed to a ship on the Lakes.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">There was a ‘Forrester’ on the passenger list for the <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and James Forrester (d. 1833) was a Surgeon in the Royal Navy, so he may have been the person to whom Southey refers.</note> But it is evident that when they reach Canada they will find themselves in a worse state than a set of redemptioners in Yankee land.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Emigrants who paid for their passage by agreeing to become indentured servants on arrival in America.</note></p>
      <p rend="indent1">I will lose no time in making inquiry &#38; communicate the result to you as soon as possible. </p>
   <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
		<signed rend="indent3">RS</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-04-19">19 Apr. 1823</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
