<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4009" type="letter"><head>4009. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1823-04-27">27 April 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS to JR 27 April/ 1823<lb/>
MS: Huntington Library, RS 434. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is well pleased with the success of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">his son</ref> at Westminster.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill had passed the examination known as ‘The Challenge’ and become one of the 40 King’s Scholars at Westminster School. They had their own house, known as ‘College’, and a range of special privileges, from taking part in coronations to proceeding to Closed Scholarships at Christ Church, Oxford, or Trinity College, Cambridge.</note> It is a tremendous examination, – &#38; yet so mere a matter of cramming, that it affords not the slightest test of a boys abilities or real proficiency. The object gained is of considerable importance, – for we must act as if the institutions of this country were secure, – whatever we may think of their danger.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I am sorry for your sake that this Irish squabble is to be heard in the H. of Commons.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">On 21 April 1823 the House of Commons had voted to set up a committee of the whole house to examine the convoluted legal proceedings against some members of the Orange Order, who had led a riot in the New Theatre Royal in Dublin on 14 December 1822. Local officials were accused of colluding to prevent prosecution of the rioters, while William Plunket (1764–1864; <title>DNB</title>), the Irish attorney-general 1822–1827, was alleged to have abused due legal process to bring charges against the rioters. The matter was debated on ten separate days in the House of Commons in May 1823.</note> For the parties I care nothing, but heartily wish you a good deliverance. How much of the session will be consumed in this manner, for the mere purpose of vexation, &#38; to no other possible effect than that of increasing the ferment in Ireland! – a country which can be brought into order by no other possible process than half a century of military government.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">I wonder the French do not proceed at once upon Madrid.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">French forces had invaded Spain on 7 April 1823 in order to overthrow the liberal government.</note> They seem to be acting very injudiciously, &#38; will soon that they have got themselves into a scrape. There is nothing tangible for them to overthrow or to overcome.</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">My Book of the Church<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> is growing into a second volume, &#38; this keeps me at my desk when I would fain be in town. I am however well satisfied with it, as it proceeds –</p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1823-04-27">27 Apr. 1823.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
