<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4016" type="letter"><head>4016. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1823-05-11">11 May 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
Endorsement: R Southey Esq/ May 11/23 –<lb/>
MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1823-05-11">11 May. 1823.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Thank you for sending to Madrid,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had now written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> – if <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">my poor Spanish friend</ref> had been living, I should regularly have received the books which would be useful to me, thro the Ambassador.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William à Court, 1st Baron Heytesbury (1779–1860; <title>DNB</title>), Ambassador to Spain 1822–1824, Portugal 1824–1827, Russia 1828–1832.</note> They used to come in the dispatches, – I have lately obtained some valuable documents from Sir Nicholas Trant.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Nicholas Trant (1769–1839; <title>DNB</title>), an Irish soldier and commander of Portuguese troops 1809–1813.</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">If you can get the old edition of Strypes Annals,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Strype (1643–1737; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Annals of the Reformation and Establishment of Religion</title> (1709). Oxford University Press published a new edition in 1824, no. 2753 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey wanted this for his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824). </note> pray let me have them, – They may be returned in a week, – for by the time they can arrive, I shall be ready to make immediate use of them. And it would be mortifying if there should appear any deficiency of information in any part of a book for which I have been so long preparing, &#38; with which I have taken so much pains. – We are now getting on rapidly, – &#38; if I do not deceive myself, the book <del>will</del> bids fair to attract readers, &#38; to impress them. More interesting materials no subject could afford.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">With regard to Lingard my intention is to review his history &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref> together in a series of papers,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lingard (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of England, from the First Invasion of the Romans</title>, 5 vols (1819–1823). Southey only possessed the first three volumes of this, published in 1819, no. 1634 in the sale catalogue of his library; and Sharon Turner, <title>History of England</title> (1814–1823), no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Neither book was reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> – adding as they occur other titles in the headings, – &#38; perhaps this series of essays on English history – with proper alterations may form <del>other</del> such another work as this Book of the Church.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this projected work.</note></p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me</salute>
                     <salute rend="indent2">yours very truly</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
