<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4061" type="letter"><head>4061. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Samuel Rogers</ref>, <date when="1823-09-21">21 September 1823 </date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: University College, London, Special Collections, Sharpe Papers. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Previously published: P. W. Clayden (ed.), <title>Rogers and His Contemporaries</title>, 2 vols (London, 1889), I, p. 362.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1823-09-21">21 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Having been asked for a letter of introduction to you, I somewhat hastily promised it, presuming upon your kindness to excuse a liberty which at this moment I feel that I have no right to take. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Carne<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Carne (1789–1844; <title>DNB</title>), a traveller and author, who had just returned from an extended visit to the Near East.</note> came to me with a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam
               ">Wordsworth</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref> having found him at <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">Professor Wilson’s</ref> &#38; taken him to <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydal</ref>. He has travelled in the East, has visited Lady Hester Stanhope,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Hester Stanhope (1776–1839; <title>DNB</title>), a traveller and archaeologist, who had settled in Lebanon.</note> <del>xxx</del> past ten days in captivity with the Arabs in the desert, &#38; seen something of the horrors which are going on in Greece;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek War of Independence (1821–1829), from the Ottoman Empire. </note> &#38; as he likes better to tell his adventures than to set them forth in a book, his conversation is very interesting. It will remind you perhaps of poor Kemble, by making you ready to exclaim O my <hi rend="ital">aches</hi>!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Philip Kemble (1757–1823; <title>DNB</title>), actor and manager. He had famously insisted on pronouncing ‘aches’ as ‘aitches’ in Shakespearean roles. Southey is here referring to Carne’s inability to pronounce the letter ‘h’ at the beginning of words.</note> – but his stories are not the worse for the want of aspirates, – nor his pronunciation the better for being Ionic as well as Stafford or Lancashire.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The initial letter ‘h’ was not pronounced in Ionic dialects of Ancient Greek. This was the most prestigious version of the language as it was associated with leading figures of Greek literature, including Homer. The initial ‘h’ was also often dropped from spoken English in the West Midlands and Lancashire.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Should you be in town during the winter, I hope to have the pleasure of seeing you, &#38; receiving your forgiveness for this intrusion</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my Dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Yours with sincere respect</salute>
				<signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
