<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4076" type="letter"><head>4076. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-10-27">27 October 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmarks: E/ 30 OC 30/ 1823; OF. NOON/ OC. 30/ 1823<lb/>
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 237. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName></address><date when="1823-10-27">27. Oct. 1823</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent1">It is my intention to make <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> my head quarters, but I cannot proceed thither in the first instance for sundry reasons. It is very possible that we may arrive in London at night, this being a matter in which we shall have no choice, but must take the chance of the road. As the time is thus uncertain, so is the day, depending upon the weather. Rain may prevent us from seeing some of the objects which we hope to visit. If all things prove favourable we may sleep at Matlock on Saturday the 8<del>xx</del><hi rend="sup">th</hi> pass the Sunday morning there, &#38; proceed <del>after</del> in the afternoon to Derby. There we shall part with our fellow travellers,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, a prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), maternal uncle of the Charter sisters. Their other companion was one of Sir Charles Malet’s three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793–1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied Malet to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785–1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810–1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833–1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843–1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet.</note> make some calls, &#38; reach Cole Orton to dinner on the Monday. There I think of staying either two or three days, as we may feel disposed. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> will send us to Loughborough, &#38; then we must trust to fortune. The most likely thing is that we shall have to travel from thence by night. But whether we shall reach London on Saturday the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> – or one two or three days sooner depends (setting other chances aside) upon so uncertain a thing as the weather. Of course I shall let <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> hear of me from Cole Orton.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I shall be glad to reach <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> as soon as I can, &#38; settle to work there, – for I shall have my last chapter to write,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 468–528.</note> &#38; also a paper to finish for the QR.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752–1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821–1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1–40, published 17 April 1824.</note> But if we arrive on the Saturday I shall hardly be able to get out of town till Tuesday.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The very thought of moving, now it is so near, gives me a sort of <hi rend="ital">bowelquake</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#38; the children -</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
