<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4079" type="letter"><head>4079. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>, <date when="1823-11-02">2 November 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text taken from William Knight, <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 1887)<lb/>
Previously published: William Knight, <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 1887), II, p. 216.</note></head>


            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick"><hi rend="ital">Keswick</hi></ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1823-11-02">2<hi rend="ital">d Nov</hi>. 1823.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">We are on the eve of our departure, and if the weather should allow us to look at the Yorkshire caves, Gordale Scar, Bolton Abbey,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A ruined twelfth-century Augustinian monastery in Yorkshire.</note> and the Peak Cavern,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A cave near Castleton, Derbyshire, popularly known as the Devil’s Arse.</note> we shall reach Matlock on Saturday night, pass the better part of the Sunday there, see our fellow-travellers<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), maternal uncle of the Charter sisters. Their other companion was one of Sir Charles Malet’s three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793–1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied him to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785–1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810–1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833–1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843–1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet.</note> off from Derby on the Monday, and present ourselves at Coleorton on the afternoon of that day. Should our plans be curtailed by the rain, we may arrive on the Saturday.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">It is no small effort for me to leave home, rooted to it as I am by so many habits. But among the pleasures to which I look on as a recompence, that of halting under your roof is not the least.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mrs. S.</ref>, her sisters,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> join in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>. If the season be as prematurely severe with you as it is with us, we shall see her winter garden<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The garden in a former quarry in the grounds at Coleorton, co-designed by Lady Beaumont and William Wordsworth in 1806.</note> to advantage. – Believe me, dear Sir George, with sincere respect and regard, yours faithfully,</p>
<closer><signed rend="right">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
