<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4080" type="letter"><head>4080. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1823-11-02">2 November 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London Fifth Nov 1823/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hants/ Fm Rickman<lb/>
Postmark: FREE/ 5 NO 5/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 35 To Miss Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 2 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1823<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 3p. <lb/>
Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 40–41 [in part].</note></head>


            <p rend="indent1">I once declared in a poem that I never put out the eye of a Cyclops;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unpublished ‘Ode’, line 15; see Southey to Daniel Stuart, 19 December 1799, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 464. In Greek mythology the Cyclops were a race of one-eyed giants.</note> &#38; I now declare with equal sincerity that I never offered any outrage to the nose of Sir Cloudesly Shovel.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In the south aisle of Westminster Abbey there is a huge marble monument to Admiral Sir Cloudesley Shovell (1650–1707; <title>DNB</title>). Its nose is intact. However, in ‘Letter of Elia to Robert Southey, Esquire’, <title>London Magazine</title>, 8 (October 1823), 406–407, Lamb had mischievously asked Southey whether he knew anything about the mutilation of the monument, in the nave of Westminster Abbey, of Major John André (1751–1780; <title>DNB</title>), a British officer hanged as a spy by the American revolutionaries. Lamb alleged that the nose was broken off a figure on the monument at the time that Southey was at Westminster School (1788–1792).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">You have a good heart, &#38; it stands you in good stead. Would that some of my family had a portion of your courage. But the truth is that your Job’s comforters<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">From the <title>Book of Job</title>, where Job is afflicted by God, but the comfort provided by his friends only makes him feel worse.</note> are as unwise in entertaining their fears as they are in communicating them.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s outhouses had been robbed and she was worried about the prospect of prosecuting the offenders at Winchester Assizes.</note> There is danger in acting against smugglers &#38; poachers, because smugglers &#38; poachers think they have natural justice on their side, &#38; have some show of reason for thinking so: they therefore think themselves aggrieved when they are prosecuted for their illicit practises, &#38; feel as if they had a right to revenge themselves upon any one who has taken part against them. But this is not the case with those who have committed a breach of the moral law: they are self-convicted of a known sin, &#38; here in England not even a Bow Street Officer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Professional police officers based at Bow Street magistrates court since 1753.</note> has ever suffered the slightest injury from after-revenge, – tho some times very serious ones in the discharge of their duty. – You may therefore sleep in peace. – Perhaps it <del>may</del> &#60;would&#62; lessen in some little degree the unpleasantness of your appearance at Winchester, if you had any acquaintance there; – &#38; I can very well introduce you to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill’s</ref> sisters<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Heathcote (1773–1855) and Alethea Bigg (1777–1847), two sisters of Catherine Hill, who shared a house at 12 Cathedral Close, Winchester.</note> who reside in that city. But I shall see you before that time; &#38; persuade you, I hope, not only <hi rend="ital">almost</hi>, but wholly, that there are yet hopes &#38; enjoyments in store for you in this world.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Before this reaches you I shall be far on my journey. I am now in all the disquiet &#38; discomfort of preparing for it. We depart on Monday, &#38; if the weather permit us to see all we purpose seeing on the way, it will be just a week before we arrive at Cole Orton. Direct to me at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref> in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref>, &#38; remember that a letter from you will always be a pleasure to me. Tell me what stages pass thro Lymington by which I can find my way from the West: I shall be coming from Exeter, most likely just after Xmas, – but of course you shall be acquainted with my movements. My time <hi rend="ital">must</hi> be short, – &#38; yet I am sure you will believe me when I say that were inclination alone to be consulted I know not how long it might prove. The work which I carry with me in an unfinished state,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> – or rather which I have to do must be done at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> before my departure <del>xxx</del> for the West, because it will be wanted for the press. And if this were not the case what inclination should I have to spend <del>my</del> &#60;that&#62; time in composition, which is to be past with you? To be put in the call of silence then would be to endure penance indeed.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">This has remained unfinished till the last minute. It is now Sunday night, – my table sadly disfurnished, every thing packed, &#38; my last dispatches on the wing. God bless you</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">yrs affectionately</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1823-11-02">2 Nov. 1823</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
