<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4086" type="letter"><head>4086. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-11-15">[15 November 1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Robert Southey<lb/>
MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. AL; 1p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: Dating from content. This letter was written on a Sunday after Southey and Edith May arrived in London in November 1823 but before Sunday 22 November, which they spent with Mary Anne Hughes; see Southey to Bertha Southey, 26 November 1823, Letter 4094. The only possible Sunday is 15 November. </note></head>


<opener><dateline><date when="1823-11-15">Sunday morning</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Edith</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Will you say to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> that I will reply to her kind note in person the first morning on which I can feel myself fairly free from the desk. Say also that I send Yamoyden<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Yamoyden, A Tale of the Wars of King Philip, in Six Cantos</title> (1820). The authors were James Wallis Eastburn (1797–1819) and Robert Charles Sands (1799–1832). Southey’s copy was no. 886 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes’s<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), whom Southey was encouraging to write an article for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> on American literature. His review of ‘Washington Irving’s Tales’ finally appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 473–487, published 11 March 1825.</note> use, &#38; that when I reach home I will send him what little information I can collect there from my American books &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknors</ref> letters, concerning American literature.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your best way to Amen Corner,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Hughes was a Canon of St Paul’s Cathedral, and he and Mary Anne Hughes lived in a house at Amen Corner, just west of St Paul’s.</note> is by Warwick Lane, which you enter from Newgate Street. The great gates are on a line with <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref>.</p>
            <closer><signed rend="indent2">Yo el Pa.</signed><note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘I the Pa’. </note></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
