<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4098" type="letter"><head>4098. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>], <date when="1823-12-03">Wednesday evening [probably 3 December 1823] </date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: [illegible]<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: This letter was written on a ‘Wednesday evening’ in December 1823; as Southey had procured a frank for Caroline Bowles, he must have been in London, rather than Streatham, making 3 December the most likely date.</note></head>


            <p rend="indent1">I have procured a frank for you, but alas it is not so easy to find time for filling it, in this abominable city. Would I that were out of it, – I had almost said never to return to it again.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">My present plans are to start for Exeter on the third of January, &#38; in about a fortnight afterwards set out from Taunton to Salisbury as the nearest way to you, consistent with my movements. If I find no ready conveyance from Salisbury, I will take chaise rather than lose time. How glad I shall be to set out upon that journey!</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I asked your question of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>, but he is not acquainted with Naylor Burrard<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Naylor Burrard (d. 1834), Lieutenant in the 1st Madras European Regiment, and first cousin of Caroline Bowles.</note> &#38; did not know the name.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It was <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> into whose hands I put your two volumes that he might take care of them in the QR.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822) were not reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> This he will do, &#38; meantime he has done them a good office in the Christian Remembrancer,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) was reviewed in the <title>Christian Remembrancer</title>, 5 (December 1823), 747–749, and <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822) in <title>Christian Remembrancer</title>, 6 (February 1824), 110–112.</note> &#38; will do the like in the British Critic,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822) were reviewed in the <title>British Critic</title>, 20 (December 1823), 623–635.</note> – for he is as much taken with them, as I expected &#38; wished him to be.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The resemblance to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> Ivanhoe<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sent Bowles an outline for a poem on the legendary figure of Robin Hood; see Southey to Caroline Bowles, 19 November 1823, Letter 4087. This was never completed and was published as ‘Robin Hood’ in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]–36. Walter Scott, <title>Ivanhoe</title> (1819) also dealt with Robin Hood, but Southey’s outline was based on his notes, now catalogued as ‘Robin Hood’, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. These are dated ‘Oct 28. 1808’, ‘July 19. 1814’ and there is an undated, earlier, ‘Original Sketch’. These all predate Scott’s first novel, <title>Waverley</title> (1814).</note> – or rather the resemblance there to a plan which was dreamt of ten years at least before <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> wrote any of his tales, may easily be avoided &#38; we may make the restoration of his estates depend upon the Barons war against King John.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John (1166–1216; King of England 1199–1216; <title>DNB</title>). The last part of his reign in 1215–1216 was spent in conflict with his leading nobles.</note> I could also as the poem begins with the infancy of its chief personage – carry it on to his death. You will feel at once what may be done by describing the autumn &#38; winter of an irregular life, – even in its most favourable form. But I have no time to say more – lest the postman with his bell should surprize me before I can fold up &#38; seal</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you dear friend – </salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">Yrs faithfully RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1823-12-03">Wednesday evening.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
