<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4102" type="letter"><head>4102. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert Southey</ref> [fragment], <date when="1823-12-18">[18 December 1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Cuthbert Southey/ Keswick<lb/>
Endorsement: About 1823 or 1824/ R Southey to C C Southey<lb/>
MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14159. AL; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: Southey here says he is leaving London for Streatham that day; in Southey to Edith Southey, 24 December[–26 December] 1823 (Letter 4106), he states he left London for Streatham on 18 December 1823.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear good boy</salute></opener>
   <p rend="indent1">Your cousin Robert<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817), eldest son of Henry Herbert Southey.</note> was very much pleased with your letter, &#38; so we all were. He would like very much to come to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &#38; go in the boat<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southey family kept a boat, the <hi rend="ital">Royal Noah</hi>, for expeditions on Derwentwater.</note> with you.</p>
      <p rend="indent1">I saw your god-brother little Charles Herries<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles John Herries (1815–1883; <title>DNB</title>), eldest son of J. C. Herries, and in later life a financier.</note> at Montreal Park.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Montreal Park, near Sevenoaks, Kent, a large Palladian mansion commissioned by Jeffrey Amherst, 1st Baron Amherst (1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>), and rented by J. C. Herries.</note> Some time ago he fell down &#38; knocked two of his front teeth almost out. His mouth was so hurt that they sent for a surgeon, &#38; the poor little boy had to wait some hours before he could be found, &#38; then the teeth were taken out, but he was such a good brave little boy that he never once cried nor made any [MS missing]</p>
   <p rend="indent1">Your cousin Henry<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey, Jnr (1822–1829), son of Henry Herbert Southey.</note> is just able to walk by himself. To day I shall see my cousins <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Marquis Bruin</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Earl Bruin</ref> as I used to call them.</p>
   <p rend="indent1">Now I have no time for writing more, because I am going to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, &#38; have a great deal to do first. So God bless you my good child. Give my love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bell</ref>. I hope that good cat Rumpelstilzchen is well, &#38; Hurliburlibuss, &#38; all my other friends. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hansard<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Luke Hansard (1752–1828; <title>DNB</title>), owner of the firms which printed the <title>Journals of the House of Commons</title> and the <title>Parliamentary Debates</title>. He was the employer of Robert Lovell, Jnr.</note> has a finer cat than any in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
   <p rend="indent1">I hope you will write me another letter soon, &#38; you may send me one for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary</ref> if you like, for I shall soon go to [MS missing]</p>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
