<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4107" type="letter"><head>4107. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-12-24">[24 December 1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Southey/ with Lady Malet/ 100 Gloucester Place<lb/>
Postmark: T.P./ Tooting; [partial] NIGHT / xE. 24<lb/>
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 2p. <lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: The postmark indicates this was posted on the 24th of a month. In his letter to Edith Southey of 24 December[–26 December] 1823 (Letter 4106), Southey, as in this letter, mentions that he will see Edith May Southey the next day and give her a brooch. </note></head>


<opener><dateline><date when="1823-12-24">Wednesday Morning</date></dateline>

<salute>My Dear EMay</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">As there is often more enjoyment in expectation, than in the expected pleasure itself, I send you three-pennyworth of that enjoyment, in the news that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has charged me with a broche for your Ladyship, an <hi rend="ital">agoa-marina</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese term for aquamarine, a precious stone of a bluish-green colour.</note> very prettily set, which I shall deliver into your hands tomorrow.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I hope Lady Malet<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>). Edith May Southey was staying with her in London.</note> will let me <hi rend="ital">borrow</hi> you for Friday. Perhaps we shall have no other opportunity of dining together at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref>, &#38; it would be a great disappointment to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref>, – who is now my oldest friend of her sex, – not to see you. You may pledge yourself to pay the day that is borrowed, whenever Lady Malet may please to require it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very busy &#38; very quiet here, having seen no creature except <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">your Uncle</ref>, who came out yesterday on a summons to see poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Errol</ref>. Of course I have got thro good part of my work. Yesterday I finished &#38; sent off the review,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752–1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821–1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1–40, published 17 April 1824.</note> &#38; now I am getting forward with the BC.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> which I shall compleat in about three mornings in a cog at <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">QAnne Street</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My kindest remembrances to you kind hostess, <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Miss Charter</ref>, Dame Elizabeth,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), sister of Louisa Charter, and friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#38; Miss Malet<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Malet had three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793–1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied him to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785–1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810–1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833–1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843–1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet. Miss Malet, the Charter sisters and Lady Malet had all travelled south with Southey from Keswick to London in November 1823.</note> if she be with you –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear child</salute>
	   <salute rend="indent2">Yr affectionate</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
