<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4109" type="letter"><head>4109. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>], <date when="1823-12-26">26 December 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898)<lb/>
Previously published: Edith Heraud, <title>Memoirs of John A. Heraud</title> (London, 1898), pp. 36–37.</note></head>


   <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">LITANE STREET</ref></placeName></address>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘LITANE’ probably a mistranscription of ‘Queen Anne’ Street, London.</note> <date when="1823-12-26">26<hi rend="ital">th Dec</hi>. 1823.</date></dateline></opener>

   <p rend="indent1">Little leisure as I have during my incessant movements, when every day brings with it its enjoyment, and every hour its business, I should, perhaps, have replied sooner to your letter, could I have done it more satisfactorily. There are few things more unpleasant than to abate the hopes of another person.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your scheme is altogether visionary and impracticable.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud was planning an epic poem, eventually published as <title>The Judgement of the Flood</title> (1834). Southey discouraged him from publishing hastily or by subscription.</note> I do not believe you could obtain ten subscribers; I am sure that I could not obtain one for you; and as for my influence with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref>!! it is about as much as yours with the Lord Chancellor,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Scott, 1st Earl of Eldon (1751–1838; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801–1806, 1807–1827. The Lord Chancellor is often considered to be the head of the legal profession, of which Heraud was an associate, as he worked in his father’s legal stationery business.</note> and not a jot more. You are too hasty, and will spoil a fair harvest if you cut it while green. Whatever power he might possess, no man ever attained to greatness unless he worked his way patiently. There is no way of getting up the hill but by climbing it.</p>
         <p rend="indent1">Were the poem of yours finished, I should <hi rend="ital">not</hi> advise you to publish it till some years had passed over your head. The proper course for you is to increase your means by writing (if you can obtain employment there) in the periodical publications, – offer a ticket now and then to the lottery of the theatre, – and work up a great poem at leisure. “The Deluge,” if now completed and published, could do no more than your existing volume<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud’s <title>The Legend of St Loy, with Other Poems</title> (1820).</note> has done – it could only prove your power, and hold out a promise of better days, when your mind shall be fully matured. Was my mind even so at your years?</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Whatever you may think of my advice now, there will come a time when you perceive that it is the best which could be given you. God bless you. – With sincere good wishes,</p>
<closer><signed rend="right">R. SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
