<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4117" type="letter"><head>4117. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">John Taylor</ref>], <date when="1824-01-02">[2 January 1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Robert H. Taylor Collection, Princeton University Library. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished. <lb/>
               Dating note: This letter was written on the last Friday that Southey spent in London, before leaving for the West Country that evening, and visiting Nicholas Lightfoot in Crediton the following Wednesday, 7 January 1824.</note></head>
            
           <opener> 
              <address> <placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q. Anne Street</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-01-02">Friday Morning</date>
            
          <salute>  My dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> These are combustible sheets, &#38; yet I do not see any thing which it is necessary to strike out.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was helping to censor Walter Savage Landor’s <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824) for publication. This section dealt with Dialogue V, I, pp. 55–65, between Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>) and ‘Walter Noble’, Landor’s misnaming of his own ancestor, Michael Noble (1591–1649), MP for Lichfield 1640–1649. Their debate centred on whether Charles I (1600–1649; King of Great Britain 1625–1649; <title>DNB</title>) should be executed.</note> It does not strike me that any stroke is intended against the Old Testament:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Cromwell’s arguments made use of Old Testament allusions, including ‘if Moses and his prophets commanded me to this villainy, I would draw back and mount my horse’ (Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 59–60).</note> allusions in the same spirit might be made by very religious men, &#38; are in fact often found in such writers as Fuller, South &#38; Warburton.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fuller (1608–1661; <title>DNB</title>), Robert South (1634–1716; <title>DNB</title>) and William Warburton (1698–1779; <title>DNB</title>), Anglican controversialists, historians and theologians.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The argument in favour of tyrannicide may pass without danger. It is a question which in former times was regularly mooted in schools &#38; Colleges; – &#38; were I to declaim upon it, I should take <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> side of the question, – tho altogether opposed to his &#60;intended&#62; application of it. – But as he speaks only in generalities I would not expunge so fine a passage.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> That speech of Cromwells he instanced in a letter to me, as a specimen of the manner in which (where it was possible) he endeavoured to make his characters think &#38; express themselves, as they would have thought &#38; spoken. – Will it not be sufficient to print it thus – In the name of the Lord, I will —— upon these firebrands.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">This line was printed as: ‘In the name of the Lord, I must piss upon these firebrands before I can make them tractable’ (Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, p. 60).</note> &#38; then no one will be surprized into reading the word aloud. I do not object to the manner in which the sentence begins because it is thoroughly characteristic, &#38; every reader will perceive that it is so.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> From Wednesday till Monday next I shall be at the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> N. Lightfoot’s</ref>, Crediton, Devonshire. <del>Thex</del> After that day not stationary any where till the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> when I hope to return to London for 48 hours.</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent2">Yrs very truly</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
