<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4118" type="letter"><head>4118. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1824-01-02">2 January 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have been applied to by Lady Malet,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), an artist and the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had travelled south from Keswick to London with her in November 1823, and Edith May Southey was staying at Lady Malet’s London house.</note> whom I should most gladly serve if I could, – to ask if you can assist an arrangement which she has in view</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Her fourth son George Grenville Malet<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Grenville Malet (1805–1856) became a Lieutenant in the 3rd Bombay Light Cavalry on 21 February 1825. He rose to be Lieutenant-Colonel of this regiment and was killed in action in the Anglo-Persian War 1856–1857.</note> went to Bombay in January last as an Infantry Cadet. She has been trying ever since to get him exchanged into the cavalry at the same Presidency &#38; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morris<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant Thomas D’Arcy Morris (1792–1835) of the 12th Native Infantry, Bombay. He was a cadet of the 2nd class of season 1808 and received a captaincy in the 24th Native Infantry on 1 May 1824. Morris was also a poet, whose ‘The Griffin’ (1821) achieved some fame in India.</note> has assured her that if she can prevail on any one to give him a Cavalry appointment, that person will get his present Infantry Cadetcy. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morris will return to him the first Cavalry appointment which falls to his lot after his re election in April, in exchange for an Infantry one. – If I understand the case, what is requested is the loan of a Cavalry appointment – subject to the chances of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morris’s life &#38; re election. What those chances may be you must know better than I can do, &#38; whether you can render this service to a very estimable family.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am on the point of leaving town for Devonshire, where a letter directed to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> N Lightfoot’s</ref> Crediton will find me from Wednesday next till the Sunday following. I return to town on the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> leave it the 23, &#38; return again on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> or 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of February, when I shall not remain more than two or three days in these parts. Heartily glad shall I be to find myself once more at home &#38; at rest, – for I have scarcely had a sound nights sleep since I left <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Will you when you see <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> give him the inclosed note, which asks to procure for me the desiderated books from Spain.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to George Canning, 2 January 1824, Letter 4115.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I looked for you on Monday last, – &#38; will look for you on the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> if no accident should prevent me from keeping the course of my arrangements. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> is left in town with Lady Malet.</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
            <signed rend="indent2">RS</signed></closer>
     <lb/>       
         <postscript>  <p> <date when="1824-01-02">Friday 2 o clock. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 2. 1824.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
