<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4120. Robert Southey to Edith May Southey, 11 January 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4120Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4120. Robert Southey to Edith May Southey, 11 January 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="/editions/southey_letters/4120Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4120" type="letter">
        <head>4120. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-01-11">11 January 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Southey/ at Lady Malet&#8217;s/ 100 Gloucester Place/ London<lb />
               Stamped: CREDITON<lb />
               Postmark: [partial] 13 JA 13/1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 261&#8211;263.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Crediton.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-01-11">Sunday. 11 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Very magnificent &amp; most dissipated Daughter,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I the Pa received your letter yesterday morning, &amp; as you may like to know the course of my proceedings I take the hour between our return from Oldridge Chapel,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Oldridge Chapel was a chapel of ease of St Thomas, Exeter. Nicholas Lightfoot was the Curate.</note> &amp; our going to Crediton Church, to send you a bulletin.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> After a journey with no discomfort &amp; only one misadventure, I was landed at the Kennaways<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836), who made a fortune in the East India Company and became a landowner in Devonshire. Southey knew him through his son, Charles Edward Kennaway, who had visited Southey in the Lake District in 1819&#8211;1820.</note> door at one o clock. The misadventure consisted in overturning a market cart, with a woman &amp; two men in it. The tilt saved them from any harm, but I suppose the butter &amp; eggs suffered, &amp; they were in such a rage that they would not suffer us to give them any assistance, so we left them in the road, vowing vengeance. It afterwards appeared that their anger was increased by an unlucky mistake of the Guards, who in the half morning twilight thinking to help the woman out from under the tilt by her arm, took hold of her knee. It is supposed there will be a law suit about it; but I believe they were to blame for keeping directly in the middle of the road, &amp; not drawing on one side when they saw us coming.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Sir John Kennaway doses his guests &amp; his servants with family worship, of which too much is worse than none. He edified <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Copplestone</ref> as well as myself on the Sunday evening by reading a sermon &amp; a long prayer after it; &amp; with equal want of judgement he made his two little girls<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Sir John Kennaway&#8217;s two youngest (of five) daughters: Augusta Kennaway (1810&#8211;1895) and Susan Kennaway (1812&#8211;1890), who married, in 1841, Gerard Thomas Noel (1782&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman and hymn writer.</note> (nice creatures they are,) &#8211; show off by repeating verses &amp; extracts from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Irving.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Washington Irving (1783&#8211;1859), <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.</title> (1820).</note> They are about the size of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bel</ref>, &amp; waltzed together very prettily. Only think of their calling one Gussy!! whose name is Augusta. Lady K.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Kennaway, n&#233;e Amyatt (c. 1774&#8211;1845). Southey means that Lady Kennaway used cosmetics.</note> paints &#8211; her husband ought to chuse the chapter about Jezabel<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">2 <title>Kings</title> 9: 30: &#8216;Now when Jehu came to Jezreel, Jezebel heard <hi rend="ital">of it</hi>; and she painted her face, and tired her head, and looked out at a window.&#8217; Jezebel (d. c. 850 BC) was a queen consort of Israel who supported the worship of Baal. In later Christian tradition she was often associated with false prophecy and female immodesty.</note> for his reading &amp; commenting. They were very obliging &amp; hospitable to me. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KennawayCharlesE">Charles</ref> as good humoured as ever. He appears to remember with great pleasure every little circumstance that occurred at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. The most interesting person in the family is a brother of Sir Johns<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably one of Sir John Kennaway&#8217;s two younger brothers: Richard Kennaway (d. 1832) or Robert Kennaway (d. 1829). Both had also served in the East India Company.</note> who is almost blind; a well informed, mild, patient man, whom it is impossible not to like &amp; compassionate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  On Monday I removed to Ottery. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeHenryNelson">Henry Coleridge</ref> (the <hi rend="ital">Amans amantis</hi> of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara&#8217;s</ref> book)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge had become secretly engaged to her cousin, Henry Nelson Coleridge on 21 March 1823. &#8216;Amans amantis&#8217; are different forms of the Latin word for &#8216;lover&#8217;.</note> speaks &amp; laughs so like Edward,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A comparison with either <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward Hill</ref>, or Edward Coleridge (1800&#8211;1883), brother of Henry Nelson Coleridge. Edward Coleridge was a Master at Eton College 1825&#8211;1857, Fellow of Eton College 1857&#8211;1883 and Vicar of Mapledurham 1862&#8211;1883.</note> that I could have <del>xxx</del> supposed he had been Edward if my eyes had been shut. But he is neither so tall nor so handsome. I liked him well &amp; his brother Frank<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis George Coleridge (1794&#8211;1854), a solicitor in Ottery St Mary.</note> also. &#8211; The Colonel<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">James Coleridge (1759&#8211;1836), father of Henry Nelson Coleridge and Lieutenant-Colonel in the East Devon Militia.</note> seems the only fortunate one of the family in his sons. George,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">George May Coleridge (1798&#8211;1847), son of George Coleridge; BA Christ Church, Oxford 1820, Prebendary Wells Cathedral 1823&#8211;1847, Vicar of St Marychurch 1827&#8211;1847.</note> tho very well disposed, appears to be much inferior to them in understanding, &amp; Edwin<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Ellis (Edwin) Coleridge (1803&#8211;1870), son of Edward Coleridge (1760&#8211;1843), Vicar of Buckerell, Devon 1804&#8211;1829; BA Trinity College, Oxford 1825, Vicar of Buckerell 1829&#8211;1870.</note> is a sort of Tony Lumpkin<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A character from Oliver Goldsmith (1728&#8211;1774; <title>DNB</title>), <title>She Stoops to Conquer</title> (1773), fond of practical jokes, horses and drinking.</note> upon whom education has been thrown away. The Colonel is suffering from a spasmodic affection of the stomach, which has I fear a serious appearance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tuesday to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Marriotts.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Marriott (1780&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. The patron of the latter church was Sir Thomas Acland, who was also a friend of Marriott.</note> There I met M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Barker,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">William Barker (1772&#8211;1838), Vicar of Broadclyst 1819&#8211;1838 and Rector of Silverton 1806&#8211;1838. Sir Thomas Acland&#8217;s seat, Killerton Park, was in the parish of Broadclyst.</note> &#8211; almost heart-broken by his sons<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Philip Barker (dates unknown), a student at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge (1817&#8211;1822) and later a barrister. Southey had met him in Keswick in 1821; see Southey to William Peachy, 23 August 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3718. It is not clear what he had done to cause distress to his father.</note> conduct, &amp; D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Miller of Exeter,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Patrick Miller (1782&#8211;1871), Physician to the Devon and Exeter Hospital and to St Thomas&#8217;s Lunatic Asylum, Exeter. He married Anne Hewett (dates unknown), an elder sister of Philip Hewett, in 1818.</note> who married one of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hewitts<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Hewett (1799&#8211;1879), fifth son of Sir George Hewett, 1st Baronet (1750&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), an eminent soldier and Commander-in-Chief in Ireland 1813&#8211;1816. Hewett was also a student at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge (1817&#8211;1822), and met Southey in Keswick in 1821; see Southey to William Peachy, 23 August 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3718. Hewett was ordained 21 December 1823 and his first post was as Curate at Downton, Wiltshire 1822&#8211;1825. He was later Rector of Binstead 1833&#8211;1879.</note> sisters. Hewitt is in orders, &amp; serves the curacy of Downton, about four miles from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mays house at Hale.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Hale Park in Hampshire, home of John May&#8217;s mother, Mary May (1745&#8211;1824).</note> Wednesday to Exeter. There to my great disappointment I found that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> was living fifteen miles to the westward, quite out of my tract, where it would have cost me two days to visit her. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> met me &amp; brought me to Crediton &#8211; to a house where wife husband &amp; children<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768&#8211;1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882), Southey&#8217;s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808&#8211;1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889); and Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811&#8211;1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846&#8211;1855, Rector of Islip 1855&#8211;1881.</note> seem to think they cannot show me kindness enough. Thursday we were to ourselves. Friday the World &amp; his Wife dined here, &amp; yesterday I met another World &amp; his Wife &amp; all their family at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bullers.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">James Buller (1766&#8211;1827) of Downes House, Crediton. Buller was MP for Exeter 1790&#8211;1796, East Looe 1802, Exeter 1802&#8211;1818.</note> This was the Great World there was Lady Duckworth<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Susannah Catherine Duckworth, n&#233;e Buller (1769&#8211;1840), of Wear House, Exeter, widow of Sir John Duckworth, 1st Baronet (1748&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>), Commander-in-Chief at Plymouth 1815&#8211;1817, and cousin of James Buller.</note> who is &lt;herself&gt; as big as the World, &amp; as round; &amp; as good-natured as possible. And there was Lady somebody else &amp; all the grandees of the neighbourhood, the Whatsisnames, the Whatdyecallums, &amp; the Thingambobs. Young M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Buller<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">James Wentworth Buller (1798&#8211;1865), MP for Exeter 1830&#8211;1834 and North Devon 1857&#8211;1865. He was a good classicist, gaining a First from Oriel College, Oxford, in 1819 and  elected a Fellow of All Souls in 1820. Duppa recounted their travels in <title>Travels in Italy, Sicily and the Lipari Islands</title> (1828).</note> who promises like his father to be a very mild, gentlemanly &amp; estimable man has been travelling with <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> in Sicily; &amp; he is well acquainted with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeathcoteWm">William Heathcote</ref>.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">James Wentworth Buller and William Heathcote had studied together at Oriel College, Oxford.</note> &#8211; Great enquiries were made for you, &amp; many wishes expressed that I had brought, &amp; that I would bring or send you into Devonshire.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But time passes &amp; I must conclude. Tomorrow <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> &amp; I go to <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T Aclands</ref>. Tuesday I proceed to Taunton &#8211; Thursday to my old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref>. And by Gods blessing I hope to be in town again on Wednesday the 21.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not told you that my god daughter &amp; your god sister is a very sweet girl, &amp; so are her sisters Kate &amp; Bridget. &amp; Nico is a fine honest boy. &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot a thoroughly friendly open hearted woman, very much to my liking.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I send you love, &amp; kind remembrances, &amp; simple remembrances, to be distributed according to your discretion, trusting that you will not misbestow my love &#8211; any more than your own. &amp; so farewell &#8211; very magnificent &amp; most dissipated Daughter</p>
        <p>
          Yo el Pa.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;I the father&#8217;.</note>
          
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot has given me something for you in a little box &#8211; a ring or brooch I suppose it to be.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>