<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4132" type="letter"><head>4132. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-02-09">9 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Cuthbert Southey<lb/>
               Endorsement: Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1824/ R Southey to C C Southey<lb/>
               MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14160. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished. </note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName>Richmond.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-02-09">Monday 9 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear son</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am coming home very soon. There are three things which keep their appointed course, Time, Tide, &#38; your father. My place is taken in the mail coach for Friday next. At a quarter after seven that evening I am to be at the Inn called the <ref type="m" target="places.html#BullandMouth">Bull &#38; Mouth</ref>. That is a very foolish name. The sign of that Inn almost three hundred years ago was a picture of the mouth, that is the entrance of Boulogne harbour: this was called Boulogne Mouth; &#38; foolish people when the sign was worn out, not knowing what it had been painted a great Bull, &#38; a great Mouth. What silly people!</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  There is a plan of London in your great book, &#38; you may find out in it where this Inn is: it is behind Newgate Street about two miles from your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Uncles</ref> House</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  You may look in the maps too, &#38; see which way I am coming, thro S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Albans S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Neots. Stilton. Grantham, Newark, Worksop, Doncaster; Wetherby, Bowes Brough &#38; Appleby to Penrith. And on Sunday morning, if it please God, I shall reach home; &#38; very happy I shall be if I find you all well.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> If you are a good boy &#38; go on well with your lessons, as I dare say you will, I shall soon begin to teach you Greek; that you may be a good scholar, &#38; so become a wise man. The wiser people are the better they ought to be; &#38; the better they are, the happier they must be.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I shall bring you each a book. On Wednesday I shall begin to pack up, about the time you receive this letter.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Give <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your dear Mamma</ref> a kiss to keep for me. And tell Betty<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Thompson (c. 1777–1862), the Southey family’s longstanding servant. She was buried in the Southey family grave.</note> I shall be glad to see her again. My love to your Aunts<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> &#38; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref>. I hope the Cats are well. The finest cats which I saw in my travels were at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Clarksons</ref>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Clarkson’s house at Playford Hall, Suffolk.</note> Their names are M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Burrell, Blucher, &#38; Fanny, all beautiful dark tabbies, of the very best kind. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Burrell is the mother of the other two, &#38; Blucher is such a good cat that he slew a weasel lately in single combat.</p>
         <closer>  <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my good little boy</salute>
           <salute rend="indent2"> your dutiful father</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
