<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4134" type="letter"><head>4134. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-02-15">15 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Southey/ with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne/ 16. York Place/ Baker Street/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 18 FE 18/ 1824<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 3p. <lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-02-15">15 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear EMay</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I arrived here this morning about 12 o clock, without mishap, &#38; God be thanked, found all well. I have had my after dinner nap, spoken to Rumpelstilzchen, &#38; seen Hurlyburlybuss<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Two feline members of the Southey household.</note> from the window. The children are delighted with their presents; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your mother</ref> is not pleased that I should have looked so ill after being shorn to the quick at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>: &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> has yet to witness the unpacking of the horn.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A kind of bugle that Southey had bought as a joke, as his sister-in-law Sara Coleridge had a horror of loud noises.</note> My ancles were swoln with the journey, already the swelling has begun to subside, – &#38; the last fifteen weeks seem to me now like a dream, from which I am hardly yet awakened.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  The ring fits well: not so <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupns</ref> cap, which must be let out (if that be possible) before he can wear it. He has become an expert angler, &#38; you need not wish to see any creature happier than he is at this moment. This being Sunday evening, he is just come up stairs to see Moses.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The reference is obscure. As it was Sunday, Southey may have been using a picture of the prophet Moses to introduce his son to the Bible.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> My companions were a young man by name Bowman<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Bowman (c. 1799–1824) settled as a surgeon at Seaton, Cumberland. He was originally from the nearby village of Aspatria. His death was announced in <title>The Lancet</title>, 19 June 1824, p. 384. </note> or Beaumont, who having just <del>qualif</del> passed at Surgeons Hall<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The headquarters of the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh.</note> is about to settle as a practitioner between Whitehaven &#38; Maryport, &#38; a Miss Donald,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> evidently his intended bride, a pleasing young woman. I dare say they had a pleasant journey: &#38; it was not inconvenient to them that he was obliged to whisper having lost his voice by a cold. The first night was said by the Coachman to be the very worst which he had ever endured, for wind, rain &#38; sleet. His great coat was literally encrusted with ice. We however were well protected within. This morning it snowed while we were crossing Stainmoor, <del>It xx</del> The weather cleared at sunrise, &#38; was beautifully fine when I arrived, as if to welcome me.</p>
         <closer>   <salute rend="indent1">And now appointing you my Embassadress extraordinary to deliver kind remembrances when due, I remain</salute>
          <salute rend="indent1">  Your dutiful father to command</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
