<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4144" type="letter"><head>4144. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-02-28">28 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 446. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <dateline><date when="1824-02-28">28 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am both sorry &#38; provoked that any person should have been thoughtless enough to direct to me under your cover from Boulogne – The letter was from Gen- Hawker,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Samuel Hawker (1763–1838), who had served in the Peninsular War 1808–1811 as commander of the 14th Light Dragoons.</note> whom I never saw, – to thank me for the first vol. of the Peninsular War,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> which I had sent him, because in civility to me, he had allowed <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> to engrave some of his sketches.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Westall, <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey’s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &#38;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823).</note> How he picked up the address I know not, – <del>but</del> he had just learnt it he says by “good fortunes.”</p>
            <p rend="indent1">   An inclosed paper will show you what <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother Tom</ref> has been about.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Longman had agreed to publish Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> offers to take the risk of printing 750 copies, provided he can procure 200 subscribers: but should he succeed in getting that number, he will be entitled I think to ask for something more certain than half the eventual profits. – He has however a very limited circle of friends, time having carried off many of the old, &#38; his place of abode for the last ten years affording him little opportunity of making new ones. His chance of success therefore depends mainly upon me, – &#38; I wish it were a matter of less importance to him, than in sad reality it is.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  You will see that such a subject can only be treated chronologically, – continuous narrative being no ways adapted to a broken subject. I suggested subject &#38; plan many years ago, – my stores have supplied the materials, – what notices fell in my way have regularly been marked for his use, – &#38; I shall have to revise, &#38; intersperse general views &#38; occasional remarks. The book will be useful &#38; respectable; – rather for reference than regular perusal, – &#38; yet I believe that they who open it will read farther than they had anticipated before they lay it down. For of necessity it must contain much curious matter.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Our kindest regards to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref></p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
