<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4155" type="letter"><head>4155. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-03-12">12 March 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Southey/ at M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne’s/ 16. York Place/ Baker Street<lb/>
               Postmark: EVEN/ 15 MR/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Frellsen Fletcher Smith Collection, Special Collections, Manuscripts, and Archives, Prescott Memorial Library, Louisiana Tech University, Ruston, Louisiana. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 412–414 [in part].</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1824-03-12">12 March. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear E May</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> <hi rend="ital">I am to give notice</hi>,</p>
            <p rend="indent1">that the packages arrived on Tuesday last, &#38; that the tunic &#38; trowsers produced a most extraordinary metamorphosis in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>. He declared that he must now leave off all his childish ways, he kept his hands in his pockets, as if that were the main purpose for which hands were <del>xx</del> intended: &#38; having unawares given me a kiss after tea, he recollected himself, reddened to think of the impropriety into which he had been betrayed, &#38; exclaimed in a quick tone, half anger, half mortification, – Oh, but I’ve left off kissing! For your comfort however I may assure you that the tunic &#38; trowsers are quietly put away for high days &#38; holydays, &#38; that he no longer insists upon the decorums belonging to the degree which he has taken in apparel.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The Beaumonts<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>.</note> move for London in the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month. I would have you call there soon.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomerys</ref> two volumes of <title>Prose; by a Poet</title>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Montgomery, <title>Prose, by a Poet</title> (1824).</note> were left behind. They had been lent to somebody I suppose. When they turn up, let them be sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> to come in one of his parcels. I have succeeded in stowing away the whole of this recent cargo, &#38; of the books from Italy, without having any new shelves; – by converting four duodecimo shelves in the Organ room,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A room at Greta Hall that had contained an organ when it was used by William Jackson and had once served as Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s study.</note> into three octavo ones; &#38; removing the duodecimo books into the passage, where some of the shelves have been pieced to make them hold a double row, – octavos behind, <hi rend="ital">shorticums</hi> in front. Another change has been to fill the bookcase on the lower landing place with bound books, – which has very greatly improved its appearance</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I wrote an account of the effect produced upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> by the unpacking of the horn, – in a letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, which you ought to see.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Grosvenor Bedford, 22 February 1824, Letter 4141. The horn was a kind of bugle that Southey had bought as a joke, as his sister-in-law Sara Coleridge had a horror of loud noises.</note> You will let us know when you are low in purse, &#38; I will desire him to supply you. I will supply you also with another pack of autographs. By the by if you were &#60;to&#62; get yourself a little book, &#38; transcribe into it these brief extracts from time to time as they pass thro your hands; – you would find yourself possessed <del>of xxxx</del> one of these days of a choice collection of sentences &#38; maxims, – &#38; I should have an additional reason for supplying you.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May Southey bought the notebook but made little progress in filling it up.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Your drawing books are likely to prove as useful as you wished them to be. All three girls<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> are getting on well, – &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> has made a hopeful attempt at colouring a butterfly. – What shall I do for my wine–brewer this year?? – I am at this time drinking your currant wine, – &#38; I assure you that some bottle marked with the ignominious name of puddle, might have very well past muster for Champagne. One third of the bottle was puddle; but the clear part was as good as any Champagne I ever tasted; the main difference – almost the only distinction – being, that it left no unpleasant tang behind it</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your mother</ref> I suppose has told you all the business &#38; news of the family. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> is Secretary for triangular affairs.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Aiding Southey with <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847). The title pages of the individual volumes bore a triangle.</note> The department of nonsense is all that is left for me; &#38; in that you shall hear from me officially sometimes. – My love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">your Aunt</ref>, – &#38; my kind remembrances to Lady Malet –<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Miss C.</ref> &#38; Dame Elizabeth.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>) and a sister of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy. Elizabeth and her sister Louisa Charter had travelled from Keswick to London with Southey, Edith May Southey and Lady Malet in November 1823.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear child!!</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
