<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4159" type="letter"><head>4159. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>, <date when="1824-03-18">18 March 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Pri Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey/ with a Keswick petition/ &#38; subscribg to his Brothers/ Book chronoll Hist<hi rend="sup">y</hi> of/ x W Indies<lb/>
               MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished. <lb/>
               Note on MS: The verso is printed at the head with the following: TO BE/ PUBLISHED/ BY/ SUBSCRIPTION, IN THREE VOLS. OCTAVO,/ PRICE, £2. S2./ (The money to be paid on delivery,)/ A CHRONOLOGICAL HISTORY OF THE/ WEST INDIES,/ BY CAPTAIN THOMAS SOUTHEY, COMMANDER/ ROYAL NAVY. [Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827) was finally published by Longmans.]</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-03-18">18 March. 1824.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> To you, as the fittest person on such an occasion, I forward a petition from this little town for the gradual abolition of slavery.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Acland presented various petitions against slavery in the West Indies to the House of Commons on 14 April 1824; ‘Similar Petitions were presented from Keswick and Aberystwyth’, <title>Morning Post</title>, 15 April 1824.</note> The tenour of it is in conformity to our friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> suggestions.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I send also on the next leaf the Prospectus of a work which will represent <del>West Inde</del> colonial slavery in its proper colours. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> has been long employed upon it. The plan was suggested by me, &#38; my assistance will not be wanting in it. It will be conferring a kindness upon me if you can assist the subscription.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  I was sorry not to find you in London during my late visit to that place. After an absence of fifteen weeks, &#38; a circuit of as many hundred miles, you may imagine with what delight I returned home, to my wonted way of life, &#38; the quiet enjoyment of my wonted occupations. I miss however <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my eldest daughter</ref>, who was left in town.</p>
           <closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Yours with the sincerest respect &#38; regard</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
