<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4171" type="letter"><head>4171. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MitfordJohn">John Mitford</ref>, <date when="1824-04-12">12 April 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in two hands] To/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. John Mitford [end of Southey’s hand]/ [in another hand, probably Bernard Barton’s] Benhall/ Saxmundham <lb/>
               Stamped: [partial] WOODBRIDGE<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn C18th Bound MSS, Osborn fc 76, vol 2, item 153. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1824-04-12">12 April. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  Dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">   In the New Monthly Magazine for October 1818 is an account of the Life &#38; writings of Francisco de Olivarez written, as I suppose, by you for it is signed in your name.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see  Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey’s most recent attempt to find the books was through George Canning. </note> He is there said to have published a history of the war in Catalonia &#38; likewise Anecdotes of the Chiefs employed in that War. You will probably be surprized to hear that from the time when that Magazine was published I have been endeavouring in vain to obtain these works. The second volume of my History of the War<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> has been withheld from the press more than a year &#38; half, in expectation of them. And having now been again informed from Madrid that they are not to be procured in that city, &#38; indeed not known there, I have bethought myself as the last forlorn hope, of writing to you to enquire if they are in your possession, &#38; if so, to request the loan of them. Should it be in your power thus to oblige &#38; assist me, the readiest mode of conveyance will be to send them thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</ref> the bookseller, apprizing him what the parcel contains, that no time may be lost.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Not knowing whither to direct to you, I send this under cover to our friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard Barton</ref>, who I believe is acquainted with your address. Many years have elapsed since we had some communication by letter.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Their surviving correspondence suggests they had last communicated by letter in 1811; see Southey to John Mitford, 20 March 1811, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 1886.</note> That communication however would render an apology for the present application unnecessary, if apologies on such occasions were required from one man of letters to another.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent2"> I remain Dear Sir</salute>
            <salute rend="indent3">Yours with respect</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
