<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4189" type="letter"><head>4189. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-05-24">24 May 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 27 MY 27/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: 24. May 1824.<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 424–425.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-05-24">24 May. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">  What should I do without the Exchequer, or rather without the <hi rend="ital">Auditurus</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford was Chief Clerk in the Auditor’s Office 1822–1834, part of the Exchequer.</note> thereof, who of all personages whether in <hi rend="ital">rus</hi> or <hi rend="ital">in <del>uxx</del> urbe</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘country’ or ‘town’.</note> is the one to whom I most naturally write nonsense, talk nonsense, &#38; look for friendly offices? – I pray you send <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> 25 £. She has consignments to send home, &#38; some outlay to make for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, besides her own expences, which (excellent manager &#38; economist as she is) are of necessity much greater than they would be here. At present she seems to be heartily enjoying London, which is made as agreable to her as midnight parties &#38; dancing can make it. A little of this is very well, but I shall not be sorry when she takes leave of it, &#38; sets off for the Devonshire coast to enjoy better air, keep better hours, &#38; employ herself in quieter &#38; wholesomer pleasures. I wish she were coming home instead of travelling westward, for she is very much missed here at all times, &#38; will be still more so when the marooning<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the season for outdoor expeditions in the Lake District, though this term was usually applied to expeditions to the sea shore.</note> season begins – as it would do now were she with us. But it is better that she should take this opportunity of going wherever inclination &#38; occasion lead her, when she is already so far on the way.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I wrote her a letter the other day concerning a favourite simily of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridges</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Edith May Southey, 17 May 1824, Letter 4188.</note> – which would amuse you who know the parties. It lead me heartily to wish that you &#38; I could spend a few weeks in absolute idleness together, that we might write the Butlers Travels.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The mythical hero about whom Bedford and Southey had made up stories since their school days.</note> What a noble chapter might be made concerning the country in which all the creatures of Heraldry are found. Alas I am at this time brimfull of good – genuine, glorious nonsense, worth all the stupid sense in the world, &#38; worthy of living for ever, &#38; behold the <del>dogge</del> &#60;dull&#62; employment with which I must drudgingly &#38; doggedly go on, in – a reviewal of the Life of Hayley,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311.</note> in which however I have the satisfaction of treating a gentleman – a scholar, &#38; a generous-hearted man as he ought to be treated.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
