<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4194" type="letter"><head>4194. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1824-05-28">28 May 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>./ Richmond/ Surry<lb/>
               Stamped: [partial] T.P./ Bridge St West<lb/>
               Postmarks: 2. A.NOON. 2/ 1. JU/ 1824; 2. A.NOON. 2/ JU. 1/ 1824<lb/>
               Watermark: Kingsford/ 1814<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 237. 1824/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May/ recd. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> June/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb/>
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 206–207.<lb/>
               Note on MS: This contained an enclosure, Southey’s autobiographical letter to John May of 27 May 1824, Letter 4191.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-05-28">28 May. 1824</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear friend</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">The inclosed biographical letter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John May, 27 May–26 June 1824, Letter 4191.</note> may serve to remind you that I am in the land of the living, which I am sorry to say, some of my correspondents seem to have forgotten. That you are so, I happen to know from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughter</ref>. – I know very little of what is going on in London; three lines from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> telling me about three weeks ago that he had sent a second edition of the B. of the Church<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824). It went into three editions in 1824.</note> to press are all that I have heard from him since my return. There is I suspect a little intentional slight in this to make me understand that booksellers are greater personages than authors. – </p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have been busy upon a review of Hayleys Memoirs which I expect to finish tomorrow.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311.</note> that done my second volume<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> goes forthwith to press, all hope of obtaining the book from Spain<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning. Finally, Southey had written to John Mitford, 12 April 1824, Letter 4171. </note> being at an end.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> My annual catarrh announced itself on Wednesday last. I have suspended it by keeping in a darkened room, – for while it is upon me no photometer can be more sensible of light. The evil is that by keeping house I bring on a general relaxation, <del>which</del> &#38; this frame of mine is not easily braced again. – I miss the two girls<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>.</note> – &#38; shall miss them more as the season advances – With best remembrances to your fireside believe me my dear friend your most affectionately RS.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
