<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4195" type="letter"><head>4195. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-06-01">[1 June 1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 4 JU 4/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> <del>6</del> June 1824; 1 June 1824.; June 1./ 1824.<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> The cast with its accompaniments is safely arrived.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had commissioned a plaster copy of a glass cup he possessed, to present to Southey. Bedford believed the cup to be the work of Benvenuto Cellini (1500–1571), Italian goldsmith and sculptor.</note> Nothing could have been more carefully packed. I observed your directions how to handle the glass, &#38; it now ornaments my workshop, which I dare say is furnished with more curious things than any other wherein the manufactory of verse &#38; prose is so diligently carried on.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Have you seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor’s</ref> Imaginary Conversations?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824), no. 1600 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> My copy arrived yesterday, &#38; such sheets only having been sent me during its passage thro the press as were <hi rend="ital">thought</hi> by the publisher<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The firm of John Taylor (1781–1864; <title>DNB</title>) and James Augustus Hessey (1785–1870), of 93 Fleet Street, London.</note> to require castration about a third part of it was new to me. Some things have passed in that part which I should have struck out, especially where <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref> is aimed at, &#38; grossly slandered.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue XIV of Landor’s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824) I, pp. [229]–248, between the Greek orator Demosthenes (384–322 BC), and the philosopher Eubulides (4th century BC). On pp. 245–248, Canning was portrayed as ‘Anaedestatus’.</note> If you have not read the book, you have a rich treat to come: so much error, so much intemperance you will rarely meet with, where there is any thing to compensate for such faults, but such manliness of thought &#38; expression, such life &#38; vigour, such thunder &#38; lightening – are I verily believe nowhere else to be found. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> would have winced had he lived to read it, – &#38; yet what is said of him<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue XII of Landor’s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824) I, pp. [154]–165, between Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Salisbury 1689–1715 and ‘Humphrey Hardcastle’. On pp. 160–164, Byron was satirised as ‘Mr. George Nelly’, whose recent death was noted.</note> is now the more impressive because it speaks of him as dead.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I am interrupted –</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
