<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4197" type="letter"><head>4197. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#AtherstoneEdwin">Edwin Atherstone</ref>, <date when="1824-06-07">7 June 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London Eleventh June 1824/ Edwin Atherstone Esq/ Taunton/ Fm/ J Rickman<lb/>
               Postmark: FREE/ 1 JU 1/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Somerset Record Office. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-06-07">7 June 1824</date>
            
            <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am much obliged to you for your little volume,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edwin Atherstone, <title>A Midsummer Day’s Dream. A Poem</title> (1824), no. 13 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which not having such locomotive powers as you possessed in your dream, had to wait a month in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref>, &#38; then travel patiently in the Waggon.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">There is as much power in the poem as I had expected to find in it, – &#38; this is saying much. I do not enter upon any task of verbal criticism because highly useful as it is to a youth who is making his first essay, &#38; serving as it were his apprenticeship in the art, – it must be superfluous to those who know the proper use of language &#38; have obtained a command of it. – The only remark which seems worth making is that there appears to be some confusion of time in the prelude: p. 26. The sun an hour ago, Went down – &#38; p. 31. it is again noon.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Edwin Atherstone, <title>A Midsummer Day’s Dream. A Poem</title> (London, 1824), p. 26, ‘The sun an hour ago/ Went down without a cloud;’ compared to p. 31: ‘It was the hour of noon’.</note> You I believe mean first to describe the whole day, &#38; then return to speak of your noon day dream: but this produces an apparent confusion.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I can say nothing of your design, because it is in its very nature lawless as well as boundless. A dream it is, &#38; the effect upon the reader is like that of a dream, before the impression is shaken off. But a more durable impression is made by what more resembles reality, &#38; a poet I should think is more likely to be popular by keeping to this low earth, than by taking flight thro the Universe. But I heartily wish you success both in your mundane &#38; extra-mundane flights, &#38; remain with much respect</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent2">Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  Yrs faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
