<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4207" type="letter"><head>4207. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-06-27">27 June 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: June 27. – 24<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 451. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener> <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of your holidays. You have had a pacific session, &#38; a comical incident at its close in the affair of Gourlay.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Fleming Gourlay (1778–1863) had attacked Brougham in the lobby of the House of Commons on 11 June 1824. Gourlay was imprisoned in the Palace of Westminster, but the Commons were at a loss what to do with him after two doctors reported he was of unsound mind. He was eventually committed to Cold Bath Fields prison as a ‘dangerous person’, where he remained until 1828. Gourlay was an eccentric farmer, statistician, reformer and writer whose life was dominated by his attempt to vindicate himself over his expulsion from Upper Canada in 1819.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I thank you for all your kindness to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>. She is a good girl, timid by constitution &#38; inheritance, but with a right mind, &#38; as much discretion as can be looked for at her <hi rend="ital">ea</hi>rs. That she will be much improved by this visit I do not doubt, – tho she is not at an awkward age. – I am very much pleased with her letters; they are just such as a girl ought to write.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The summer has brought with it my usual ailment at this season; – it has laid deep hold on me, &#38; is enfeebling me very much. Certainly if I live till next May I will set out from home at that time &#38; try whether I can escape it by a long journey. I will either visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bp. of Limerick</ref>, – or if I can meet with a companion, make a tour in Holland<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey visited the Low Countries in 1825. He was accompanied by Henry Taylor, Neville White and Arthur Malet (1806–1888; <title>DNB</title>), later a civil servant in India.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">My second volume of the War is in the Press.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> I know nothing of what is going on with the Q R. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> I suppose cannot write, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will not. I should otherwise propose for it a paper on the state of Portugal – which is a subject upon which I could set some well-meaning people right.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> I am <del>now</del> very well satisfied with what is going on there now.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A liberal constitution, based on the Spanish constitution of 1812, had been adopted in Portugal in October 1822. A military counter-revolution in May 1823 led to the abolition of the constitution, but another revolt in April 1824, which aimed to restore royal absolutism, was defeated with diplomatic support from Britain and France.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> There are four ways of governing a nation – by reason, by delusion, – by money, or by the sword. The King of Portugal must pension his Humes<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hume (1777–1855; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish radical MP, who was particularly disliked by Rickman because of his campaign to reduce government expenditure.</note> &#38; his <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Broughams</ref>, – banish his <ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Burdetts</ref> &#38; his Hobhouses,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cam Hobhouse (1786–1869; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Westminster 1820–1833, Nottingham 1834–1847, Harwich 1848–1851.</note> &#38; hang his <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref> &#38; his <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hones</ref>. He may then govern by reason, – with the help of gold, iron &#38; hemp.</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <closer><lb/>
          <date when="1824-06-27">  June 27. 1824</date></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
