<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4209" type="letter"><head>4209. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-07-04">4 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881)<lb/>
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 65–66.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">KESWICK</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1824-07-04"><hi rend="ital">July</hi> 4<hi rend="ital">th</hi>, 1824.</date></dateline></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1"> Hayley’s book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was reviewing John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. His article appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311, published 11 March 1825.</note> is as bad as you describe it, and there is truth enough in your view of his character to justify its severity. Yet he has his better points, and I verily believe the worst thing he ever did was writing those Memoirs; for, as they stand, they have the deadly sin of dulness, and as he left them they were much more sinful. By way of explaining his domestic history, he intended to publish details which ought not have been whispered even in a confessional.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Hayley made it clear that he had separated from his first wife and that she suffered from mental illness, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823), I, pp. 382–385, 481–484.</note> Yet you will see that Mrs H. must have made no secret of the matter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823), I, pp. 385–386.</note> Perhaps I am the more inclined to excuse him, because his wife has made a very disagreeable impression upon me by a silly, or worse than silly, essay called “The Triumph of Acquaintance over Friendship.”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Eliza Hayley, née Ball (1750–1797), <title>The Triumph of Acquaintance over Friendship: an Essay for the Times, by a Lady</title> (1797).</note> I like him, not for his writings as you may well suppose, but for his love of literature. It is so rare a thing to find a man in Hayley’s rank who prefers it to dogs, or horses, or guns, the common dissipations, or the common business of the world (which is not much better), that I could forgive him even if his epitaphs had been more numerous and worse than they are. You are right about the nature of his feeling; it was of a kind that easily worked itself off. As far as my observation extends, those persons recover soonest from their sorrow who let it take its full course at first.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Whether I have done as well with Hayley as you are pleased to say I should have done with a broomstick you will probably soon see. But for your sake I certainly will try what I can do with the latter subject;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on the subject of broomsticks, as he had promised.</note> it does me as much good to indulge sometimes in nonsense as it did Hayley to draw off his sensibility in a sonnet.</p>
         <closer>  <salute rend="indent4"> Dear Caroline, God bless you.</salute>
           <signed rend="indent6"> R. SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
