<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4210" type="letter"><head>4210. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">Mary Ann Watts Hughes</ref>, <date when="1824-07-04">4 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London July seven 1824/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes/ Uffington/ Faringdon/ CW Williams Wynn <lb/>
               Postmark: FREE/ 7 JY 7/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc 3797. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 430–432.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-07-04"> 4 July. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear Madam</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  Your letter brought me the first, &#38; only intelligence that I have received of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> death.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Watts Hughes was misinformed. Elmsley was very ill, but he did not die until 8 March 1825.</note> His place will not easily be filled at Oxford, &#38; in that walk of letters which he had chosen,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Elmsley was a leading classicist. Since 1823 he had been Principal of St Alban Hall, Oxford, and Camden Professor of Ancient History.</note> – but to his friends it never can be supplied. For myself, it is a loss which will be perceived whether I look backward or forward. Many recollections which used to be chearful ones, must now change their character, – &#38; I feel myself left with one friend less in the world, at an age when we rarely <del>make ne</del> form new friendships, even if a new friend could ever supply the place of an old one.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have been very much confined to the house since your departure by that annual visitation of catarrh<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suffered very badly from hay fever.</note> which was then upon me. It has now taken the form of cough, which is usually its last stage, but this year, the cough seems to lie deeper &#38; take stronger hold than it was wont. Next year, if it be possible for me to break away from my employments, I will leave home at the end of April, &#38; try as the only probable means of escaping it, to make a journey of six or eight weeks, – into Holland &#38; the North of Germany if I can find a companion</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> You were fortunate while you were here in the weather, – but had you been a month later, you would have seen our wonder of wonders, which tho there is nothing beautiful in it, <del>it</del> is still very well worth seeing, for I believe nothing of the kind has ever been observed else where. What is called the Floating Island has made its appearance.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Floating Island of Derwentwater is a mass of vegetation that rises to the surface every few years. It appeared from 21 June 1824 to the end of September, its first siting since 1819.</note> By good fortune Sedgewick, the Cambridge Professor of Geology<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Sedgwick (1785–1873; <title>DNB</title>), Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, and Woodwardian Professor of Geology 1818–1873.</note> is here. I went with him to reconnoitre it on Monday last, – &#38; yesterday he investigated it thoroughly.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The bottom of the lake in that part (near <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref>) is covered with aquatic plants, growing in a soft vegetable mould which is <del>about xxxx</del> hardly a foot thick, &#38; lies upon a bed of peat, – that bed is six feet in thickness &#38; rests upon a stratum of fine white clay. From time to time a quantity of <del>xxx</del> &#60;gas&#62; is generated (whether in the peat, or below it remains to be discovered) which fills this peat, till it becomes so buoyant that it is seperated from the clay, &#38; then that part of the bottom of the lake floats &#38; rises to the surface. But so great was the accumulation when this took place that it has made a rent in the bottom some fifty yards long, &#38; some six feet deep. Upon probing the gas comes out freely but not so plentifully, on the sides of this chasm, – as in another portion at some little distance, where instead of forcing for itself a vent, the gas has puffed up the bottom in a convex form. Then when a pole is thrust down, the air rushes out like a jet.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">We have had rain enough in the course of the lake to raise the lake full four feet. The convex part is therefore now under water, – &#38; probably the two other pieces, or the sides of the chasm will soon subside.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> My young ones, thank God, are well, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel’s</ref> face which has been frightfully swoln, from an inflammation of the ear, is recovering its usual dimensions. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> is still complaining of her eyes, &#38; talking of going to the South to have them cured, – but in this family every thing is talked of a long while before it is done. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My eldest daughter</ref> has deferred all account of her visit to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls till she returns, – as <del>certain</del> having <del>too</del> &#60;so&#62; much to say that she dared not begin to write it. She is now on her way to Devonshire. Last week she met <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> W Wynn</ref> at the Caledonian Ball,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Caledonian Ball is a major event in the London Season. In 1824 it was held on 25 June at Almack’s Assembly Rooms.</note> &#38; thought her looking very ill. She gives a good account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, who spent the last week with her, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> gives good accounts of herself.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">And now my dear Madam present our united regards to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref> not forgetting mine to your son,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), a miscellaneous author, most recently of <title>An Itinerary of Provence and the Rhone made During the Year 1819</title> (1822), which Southey admired.</note> &#38; believe me</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent3">Yrs very truly</salute>
            <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
