<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4211" type="letter"><head>4211. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-07-07">7 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 10 JY 10/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsement: 7 July 1824<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-07-07">7 July. 1824</date></dateline>
            
        <salute>    My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Your letter gave me as much surprize as hope, for I had heard that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> was dead,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been misinformed on this subject by Mary Ann Watts Hughes.</note> – &#38; you may very well suppose had been thinking of him by day &#38; by night. – I shall look for your next letter with great <del>anxiet</del> anxiety.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Since I wrote last I have been &#38; indeed continue to be on the sick list. My annual catarrh has settled into a cough, which tho in itself not very troublesome, lies deep, &#38; is accompanied with a feverish pulse. In this state it has been for some six weeks, &#38; what with starving, want of exercise when the catarrh made me incapable of bearing the light, &#38; physicking, it will I fear be more than tonics are able to do (when I can venture to take them), to bring me into condition again this season. – Your appearance would do me more good than any thing else. What I told you respecting as the French would say, <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswicks</ref> being brought one night nearer to London, relates to the journey up: The mail which used to arrive in town about six in the morning arriving now between nine &#38; ten at night. If you wish to escape a night on the road in coming down you should take the day coach to Grantham, or Stamford: but then there is the chance of not finding a place next morning in the Carlisle Mail. – When you reach Penrith, you will find a Mail Coach starting from thence for Whitehaven; which will give you time to wash, shave &#38; breakfast, &#38; deposit you here a little before twelve o clock.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> has taken flight for Seaton on the Devonshire coast with Lady Malet,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> goes with the Rickmans<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> and his family.</note> into Hampshire. We miss them very much.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  <del>There has been</del> &#60;We have had&#62; a forgery here also,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford reported to Southey in a letter of 4 July 1824 that he had uncovered an instance of fraud in his work at the Audit Office.</note> – &#38; in one of my departments, – which tho it gives me none of the sort of anxiety that you have suffered, will deprive me of a very useful person. There was a bookbinder here,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Crampton (c. 1785–1843), a Keswick bookseller, had obtained a copper plate to forge one-guinea banknotes of the Whitehaven Bank of Johnston, Adamson, Hope &#38; Co. He was condemned to death at Carlisle Assizes on 26 August 1824 but recommended to mercy and sentenced to three years’ imprisonment.</note> whom I was employing to mend &#38; letter old books &#38; – so by little &#38; little to bring my ragged regiments into a state of discipline &#38; equipment. The fellow fancied it would be a better trade to make Whitehaven Bills than to vamp old books, – accordingly he procured a plate from <del>Bxxx</del> Birmingham, set to work, was detected before he <del>xx</del> could set half a dozen notes in circulation, &#38; is now upon the stool of repentance in Carlisle jail, waiting for the Assizes to know whether he shall be hanged or transported for life. “I could have better spared a better man”<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The First Part of Henry the Fourth</title>, Act 5, scene 4, line 103.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Call at <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> <del>for</del> when you go that way next &#38; pay two pounds for me to the subscription for poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfields</ref> family. It is money very well bestowed. Will there ever come a time when the Public as that many headed beast is called, will show their regard for a good &#38; meritorious man while he can profit by it, – instead of letting him die half 
            -starved &#38; half-heart broken, – &#38; then subscribing for his family – or perhaps for his monument!</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear G.</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
           <postscript> <lb/>
              <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your Godson</ref> is, where his father is very often, – &#38; where you &#38; I were once on <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, – <hi rend="ital">in nubes</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘In the clouds’.</note></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
