<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4219" type="letter"><head>4219. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-07-21">21 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ [illegible] 4/ 1824; [partial] 10.F.NOON.10/ J<lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 246. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-07-21">21 July. 1824</date></dateline></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1"> Since I heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> that the hooping cough had appeared at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, I have neither heard of, nor from you. Hoping however that all may be going on well, I write now concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> journey, that you may determine upon his plan of operations.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> The surest, shortest &#38; easiest mode of conveyance, is to take the mail, which will bring him in six &#38; thirty hours from <ref type="m" target="places.html#BullandMouth">the Bull &#38; Mouth</ref> to Penrith; where he will find another mail ready to start for <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> when he has breakfasted. In that case it is at <ref type="m" target="places.html#BullandMouth">the Bull &#38; Mouth</ref> that the place must be taken, &#38; in the Carlisle Mail. There is another Carlisle mail at some other Inn which would carry him round by Manchester &#38; Kendal &#38; delay him two or three hours at the former place.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If the fatigue of travelling two nights successively is thought too much, there day coaches from London to Birmingham thence to Manchester, &#38; thence again to Kendal, – from whence there is a morning coach to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> every day except Sunday. In this he would arrive here at 11 o clock on the fourth morning, after travelling three whole days. The former plan brings him to his journeys end on the second morning at 12, after travelling two nights &#38; a day: – &#38; it must be remembered that the three whole days begin early, – &#38; are indeed days &#38; quarters. – If he can sleep, or even doze in a coach, it will save as much fatigue as time to come by the mail.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> are looking for him with some impatience, &#38; I can assure him that he will not despise them as companions upon the mountains.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> My cold I hope has nearly run its career. There are very little remains of the cough, &#38; I am about to begin upon a tonic course this day. The attack this year has been so serious, that if it be possible, I will endeavour to escape it by flying next season before the time of its usual return.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  We have heard of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref> arrival on the Devonshire coast, – where <del>xx</del> it is to be hoped she will wear out more shoes upon the shore than in ball-rooms.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I should like you to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bp of Limericks</ref> speech upon the state of the Irish Church, – which he sent me last week. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CadellThomas">Cadell</ref> is the publisher.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Speech Delivered in the House of Peers, Thursday, June 10 1824: on the Occasion of the Third Reading of the Irish Tithe Composition Amendment Bill. By John, Lord Bishop of Limerick</title> (1824). This was a prolonged defence of the Anglican Church of Ireland.</note> A more temperate &#38; convincing refutation of misrepresentations &#38; calumnies could not be desired. It is quite worthy of the man. I am told he is to have the first Irish Archbishoprick, I heartily wish it were Canterbury instead.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Jebb did not become an archbishop, in Ireland or England.</note> But the Ministry however well they may wish to act in the disposal of church preferment, are not yet ashamed of making undeserved promotions. That to Chichester has been such: <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Carr (1774–1841; <title>DNB</title>), a close friend of George IV, whom Carr came to know when he was Vicar of Brighton 1804–1824. The King ensured that Carr was showered with ecclesiastical preferments, including the posts of Bishop of Chichester 1824–1831 and Bishop of Worcester 1831–1841.</note> – that of the D of Ch. Ch to Durham absolutely a scandalous one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Henry Hall (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>), Dean of Christ Church, Oxford 1809–1824, was installed as Dean of Durham on 26 February 1824.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> is – almost miraculously recovering, having been it was thought <hi rend="ital">in articulo mortis</hi>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘at the point of death’.</note> his legs the size of mill posts, &#38; his respiration choked by water in the chest. Just at that point he fell into a long &#38; profound sleep, awoke refreshed, &#38; continued from that time to amend. The last news I heard of him was that he was going that day to dine with his physician, <ref type="m" target="people.html#KiddJohn">Kidd</ref> however takes no credit for the cure, which seems to have been wholly Natures. He is going this week to the house of his sister in law<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Elmsley (c. 1775–1831), née Hallowell, widow of John Elmsley (1762–1805), Chief Justice of Upper Canada 1796–1802 and of Lower Canada 1802–1805.</note> – at Waddon – in your neighbourhood – near Croydon.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#38; the children – Let me hear of you -</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
