<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4227" type="letter"><head>4227. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">[Susannah] Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-08-08">8 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ [MS missing] Rickman<lb/>
               Endorsement: R Southey to SR/ 24 <lb/>
               MS: The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Wilson Library, James Saxon Childers Papers. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <salute>My dear Madam</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I inclose these few lines with a portion of my Journal,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A fair copy of the journal Southey kept on his trip to the Low Countries in 1815, later published as <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note> thinking that tho they tell you n[MS missing] but what you knew before, you will [MS missing]rtheless have some pleasure in hearing it.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arnold<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Arnold (1795–1842; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman and later the Headmaster of Rugby School 1828–1841. At this time he jointly ran a school at Laleham, Middlesex (1819–1828).</note> was here the other day. I asked him how my friend Willy<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Charles Rickman (1812–1886), son of John and Susannah Rickman.</note> went on, &#38; his answer was that he was one of the best boys he ever knew. These were his very words. He added that those boys who did best in their respective classes took their turns to dine at certain times at his house, – &#38; that at those times he never failed to see William Rickman.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> This was what I <hi rend="ital">expected</hi> as well as hoped to hear; – for if your son were not all you could wish him to be, I should never again place any trust in voice, manner[MS missing] countenance – all the outward &#38; visible [MS missing]s of inward goodness.</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent2">Yrs very faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
           <postscript> <lb/>
           <p rend="indent0"> <date when="1824-08-08">Keswick. 8 Aug. 1824.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
