<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4236" type="letter"><head>4236. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BoundenJoseph">Joseph Bounden</ref>, <date when="1824-08-22">22 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Joseph Bounden Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 65 Newman Street/ Oxford Street<lb/>
               Stamped: [partial] Bge West <lb/>
               Postmark: 2/ A/ NOON/ 2/ 25 AU/ 1824<lb/>
               Seal: [partial] red wax<lb/>
               MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 5. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1824-08-22">22 Aug. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am obliged to you for a volume of Poems which lately reached me in a parcel from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Longmans</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Bounden, <title>The Deserted City; Eva, a Tale in Two Cantos; and Other Poems</title> (1824), no. 278 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> You have been happier in the execution than in the choice of your subjects, – which is generally the case with young poets. Such stories as that of Eva are not calculated for poetry, which should avoid whatever is shocking &#38; gives <hi rend="ital">un</hi>mingled pain. We do not willingly read a second time any thing that draws tears, or excites shuddering. Your Ruined City had better, I think, have been an existing scene, – you might have found many such in Greece – Egypt – Asia – &#38; on the African shores of the Mediterranean, &#38; any of these would have given you the advantage of historic truth &#38; venerable associations. You would however not have had an opportunity of touching upon modern manners &#38; institutions, – which makes so prominent a part of your plan</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Heraud</ref> when you see him &#38; believe me</p>
           <closer><salute rend="indent3"> Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4">  yrs obediently</salute>
         <signed rend="indent5">   Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
