<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4237" type="letter"><head>4237. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-08-22">22 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hampshire<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 62 To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 3p. <lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><del>Sunday</del> &#60;<address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address>&#62;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><del>Sunday</del> &#60;Keswick&#62;: Deletion and insertion in another hand.</note> <date when="1824-08-22">22 Aug. 1824.</date></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1">Tho there is a letter for you inclosed to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> care lying on the chimney piece for this nights post, – I must not let that post depart without replying to yours which I have just received &#38; which dark as its tidings are<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s old nurse (name and dates unknown), her last link with her childhood, had just died.</note> – has in truth relieved me from a growing anxiety, – for I was very uneasy at your silence. – The loss which has befallen you, you know how to bear: &#38; you have no longer to bear the prospect of it. An evil which you knew to be inevitable, &#38; near, is past. – For such sorrows time is the sure cure, &#38; tho the <del>eld</del> generation of your earliest friends is now past away, you are not &#38; cannot be alone in the world. How sincerely do I wish that you were always as near me as you were this time twelvemonth.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">One word about myself. It is not change of climate that I want, – my annual catarrh coming on always with the fine weather. It is constant exercise &#38; change of air at the time when that relaxation of the system would otherwise come on, – the North therefore would do as well as the south, &#38; six or eight weeks suffice. – Of that complaint I am pretty well recovered, – but my tenement is out of repair, &#38; has some ugly flaws in it. I will take all the care of it that can be taken, &#38; that a tranquil mind enables me to take. See that you do the same with yours, – &#38; take you hope also. We shall meet again, – often I trust in this world, – &#38; surely &#38; lastingly in another: – but in this also. – Write to me &#38; tell me that you <del>xxx</del> are recovering from the shock &#38; the exhaustion which you have undergone.</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">God bless you dear friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  R</signed></closer>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
