<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4259" type="letter"><head>4259. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-10-06">6 October 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Portsmouth Tenth Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824/ Miss Southey/ with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wade Browne/ Exeter/ Free/ JRickman<lb/>
               Stamped: PORTSMOUTH/ OC 10/ 1824/ 73<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p. <lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
        <opener>  <salute>  My dear EMay</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> The stinking stone was the first thing for which I enquired in Crediton Church.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Southey’s Common-Place Books</title>, 4 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 252, ‘In Crediton Church is one stone remarkable, because it has the smell of a corpse.’</note> I believe there is nothing wonderful in it: strike a flint, &#38; you will produce a strong smell. The size of the stone may possibly make it remarkable, &#38; at any rate no one should be allowed to indulge that vile English humour of breaking it to carry away a fragment. Our nation is infamous for this – <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobert">Robert Lovell</ref> has just been groaning over an example of it in Bedes chair, – certainly the most venerable relic in these kingdoms, which is utterly defaced &#38; half destroyed by those who have cut their names in it, &#38; carried pieces away.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A wooden chair, reputedly that of St Bede (673–735; <title>DNB</title>), used to be on display in the chancel at St Paul’s Church, Jarrow. The chair was not only a tourist attraction but also believed to have the property of improving the chance of bearing many children. It is now thought to date to the fourteenth century.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am not certain whether or not I have said to &#60;you&#62; in any former letter, that if your invitation to pass a <del>xxx</del> day or two with the Longmans should be repeated, I wish you to accept it. This I should not do, if you were not disposed to like the female part of the family.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Longman had married Mary Slater (1781–1842), of Horsham, Sussex, in 1799. Their daughters included: Mary Longman (1801–1870), who married the publisher Andrew Spottiswoode (1787–1866) in 1819; and Frances Longman (1807–1888), who married Reginald Bray (1797–1879), a solicitor of Shere, Surrey, in 1836.</note> But they appear very likeable persons, &#38; I should like you to be better acquainted with them, because I believe their father has a sort of feeling towards me which is not entirely dependent upon the state of my accounts. Bookseller usually consider author as a goose whom he has to pluck; – &#38; in that light the <hi rend="ital">firm</hi> in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref> consider me &#38; deal with me accordingly; but I believe that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> individually regards me with respect &#38; good will.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  You will not wonder that you are wished for at home now that the winter is approaching, &#38; we are left to ourselves, – <hi rend="ital">totally</hi> to ourselves it will soon be. Without intending to hurry you, or prevent any visits which you may purpose to make, I suppose, you will think of returning with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> about February, – that is as soon as the weather becomes mild enough for travelling. There is a bare possibility, (which must neither be built upon, nor mentioned to any one except <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">your Uncle Henry</ref>,) – that I may go to London at that time, under pretext of bringing you home, – but in reality to see a favourite book of yours carried thro the press xx with all imaginable secresy &#38; dispatch.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847), which was published anonymously.</note> I have done so much to it within the last three weeks, as to render this possible, – &#38; in fact easy, if that abominable Tale of Paraguay<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> were not hanging about my neck like a millstone. I get on with it <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘with love’.</note> &#38; yet should proceed with more pleasure if you were here to witness its progress. – You would have had some nonsense from me ere this, if all my nonsense had not of late been directed into this channel.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your character of John L.[Lightfoot,JohnP] is not a pleasant one, &#38; I am sorry for it, – the fault not being <del>one</del> &#60;of that kind&#62; which time is likely to correct. No man can either be happy himself thro life, or make those so who are connected with him, unless he has good principles, good temper, &#38; good health. A woman may be deceived concerning the first, &#38; must take her chance for the last: but if she marries a man of uncomfortable temper it must be her own fault. You have not mentioned Bridget<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810–1889), daughter of Nicholas Lightfoot.</note> in your letters, – a wild-eyed girl who took my fancy much. Indeed I liked the whole family. There was a warmth &#38; heartiness in their whole behavior towards me, which one does not always find in the family of an old friend, however close the ties of friendship may be with the master of the house.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  But I must conclude that I may pass the rest of the evening with your friend the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. –<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847).</note> There is a prospect of seeing <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir WScott</ref> here for a day, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, so <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> writes to tell me. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> sends his love &#38; a kiss, &#38; the promise of a letter. He was <del>xxxx</del> very unwell last week with one of his bilious attacks, but thank God is perfectly recovered. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your mother</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">the Venerable</ref> are drinking tea with the Miss Dentons.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758–1820), Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1786–1820, had three daughters, two of whom, Elizabeth and Sarah (dates unknown), were renting Greta Lodge at this time and were therefore Southey’s near neighbours.</note> Our kindest remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> &#38; Mary<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Browne (1810–1892), daughter of Elizabeth Browne. She later married William Farwell (1806–1876), Rector of St Martin’s, Liskeard 1830–1876.</note></p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript><lb/>
           <p rend="indent1"> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-10-06">6 Oct. 1824</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
