<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4269" type="letter"><head>4269. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-10-27">27 October [1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 1p. <lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: Year is derived from the content.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-10-27">27 Oct.</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear EMay</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  Tho’ we have nothing to say, I do not like to let these half-bills go without a line to accompany them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">A frightful circumstance has happened at the Island.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Island, home of William Peachy.</note> One of the servant was taken ill on Saturday &#38; died the next morning. – A very fine young woman, Stoddard by name,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> who once lived with the Townshends.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the family of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncey Hare Townshend</ref>.</note> I do not remember her.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> A great shock to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the poor General</ref>. – He has shown great feeling for us at this time; – &#38; if I had had no regard for him before, I should now love him as long as I live. – But I already knew his real worth. – You are likely to see him in the course of the winter.</p>
            <p rend="center">————</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Have they told you that Haec is no longer <hi rend="ital">declined</hi>, but actually <hi rend="ital">conjugated</hi>?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Hic’ is a Latin word meaning ‘this’, which declines (i.e. has its endings altered depending on its place in a sentence) as ‘Hic, Haec, Hoc’. Conjugation refers to the differing forms taken by Latin verbs. Southey’s joke here is obscure but may refer to the fact that a person known to him and Edith May Southey had ceased to ‘decline’ an offer of marriage, and decided to ‘conjugate’, i.e. to marry.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
            <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
