<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4281" type="letter"><head>4281. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#NashWilliam">William Nash</ref>, <date when="1824-11-19">19 November 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W. W. Nash Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Peckham/ near/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmarks: E/ 22 NO 22/ 1824; 10 F NOON 10/ NO 22/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsement: Rob Southey/ 19 Nov 1824<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Rare Book and Manuscript Library. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1824-11-19">19 Nov. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I shall be very glad if my application to my brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey</ref> should be of any avail in promoting your wishes, &#38; the success of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Waring in his present pursuit.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Mere Latham (1789–1875; <title>DNB</title>) resigned as senior physician at the Middlesex Hospital on 16 November 1824. He was a friend and colleague of Henry Herbert Southey. Eight candidates put their names forward for the post, including Richard Waring (d. 1868), a native of Kent, who had qualified from Edinburgh University in 1823 and became a Licentiate of the Royal College of Physicians in 1824. The result was declared on 18 December 1824 and Francis Hawkins (1794–1877; <title>DNB</title>) was successful, holding his post until 1858. Hawkins was the Registrar of the Royal College of Physicians 1829–1858 and held various appointments to the royal family.</note> But I am not without apprehension that as this vacancy must have been known in the Hospital before it was announced to the public, &#38; there are always persons looking with expectations for such an opening, his influence may have been preengaged.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">On this &#38; any other occasion, I shall always desire to testify the respect I bear to <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">your brothers</ref> memory. There were few persons whose friends were more sincerely attached to them, or whose loss can have been more sincerely lamented</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">I remain Sir</salute>
         <salute rend="indent2">   yr obedient servant</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed> </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
