<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4294" type="letter"><head>4294. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-12-14">14 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 14. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
        <opener>  <salute>  My dear G.</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  It will be less trouble for you to transfer these papers to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dog Star</ref>, than to Richard Westall,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Westall (1765–1836; <title>DNB</title>), painter and illustrator.</note> – who lives so near the M Hospital<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall lived at 6 South Crescent, Bedford Square 1816–1828; Henry Herbert Southey was a physician at the Middlesex Hospital on Mortimer Street, 1815–1827.</note> that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dog Star</ref> may without any inconvenience see him.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I want two prints for the poem,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> – for the very laudable purpose of making the volume sell for half a guinea,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was priced at half a guinea (10 shillings and 6 <hi rend="ital">d.</hi>).</note> which would not otherwise be more than 7–6. For the one subject I chuse the single figure of Mooma singing beside the bower – Canto 3. St. 37–45. – for the other I recommend the single figure of the Missionary in the wood st. 21 of the same canto.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall did not take this advice. His first illustration was for Canto I, stanza 44, and showed Mooma and her family; the second was for Canto III, stanza 42, but showed Mooma and the Jesuit.</note> The poem affords no theatrical situations – &#38; these are sufficiently picturesque.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The fourth &#38; last Canto is begun, &#38; will be finished without delay.</p>
         <p rend="indent1">   The character of the poem is wholly meditative, &#38; they who look for any interest of incident or passion will not find it. It is intended less for what is called effect, than for impression. You can have no conception of the difficulty which the stanza<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was written in stanzas of nine lines – eight in iambic pentameter, followed by a final alexandrine line. The rhyme scheme was ‘ababbcbbc’.</note> has occasioned. And yet it is so certainly the measure best adapted to the nature &#38; movement of the story, that I do not repent having chosen it.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  When Westall has satisfied himself with the mss he may return it to you, – if you wish to have it, till it be wanted for the press, which will not be till the engravers are in forwardness with their task. Do not therefore delay it now longer that to glance at it.</p>
           <closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript><lb/>
           <p rend="indent0"> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-12-14">14 Dec. 1824.</date></p>
            <lb/>
          <p rend="indent1">  I have had a somewhat formal &#38; respectful letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about the Q.R. to say that very little remains to be settled with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> &#38; to request as “a kind &#38; serviceable act” that I will of <hi rend="ital">my own accord</hi> write my opinion &#38; recommendation of him to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, whose confidence it is of great importance (he says) to obtain.</p>
               <p rend="indent1"> My answer will be that I can have no objection to write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> – with whom I am upon terms of sufficient acquaintance. But that I will not intrude upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref>. – I will tell you two reasons for this, – first, I will never give myself airs, &#38; affect any importance with a man of power upon the strength of the interest (or no interest) that I have in the Q.R. Secondly – there is something like an intrigue going on on <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Cannings</ref> part for bringing in some of the Whigs, &#38; ousting some of the Tories to make room for them. In that case there will be as strong a reaction as there was in 1806<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1806 the ‘Ministry of All the Talents’, led by Wynn’s uncle, Lord Grenville, had failed to make significant gains in the general election that it called. It had been unable to secure peace with France and broke up in 1807 over the issue of Catholic Emancipation.</note> &#38; I shall put on my <hi rend="ital">clogs</hi> to assist in kicking out a set of men who would destroy the Church &#38; betray the state. – The Religious War which we may look for speedily in Ireland may either ripen or blast this notable scheme, – the latter is most likely</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
