<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">frank27.chars</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-04-01">May 1, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">STUDY AIDS : CHARACTERS</title>
						<author>
							<persName>Curran, Stuart</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<editor>Curran, Stuart</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date>2009-05-01</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="3" when="2009-05-01" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-05-01" who="#DR">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-05-01" who="#MQ">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<head>STUDY AIDS : CHARACTERS</head>
			<div type="appCharsA">
				<list>
					<item>
						<ref target="beaufort">M. Beaufort</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="clerval">Henry Clerval</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="creature">The Creature</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="agatha">Agatha de Lacey</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="felix">Felix de Lacey</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="delacey">M. de Lacey</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="alphonse">Alphonse Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="caroline">Caroline Beaufort Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="eliz">Elizabeth Lavenza Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="ernest">Ernest Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="felix">Victor Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="william">William Frankenstein</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="kirwin">Mr. Kirwin</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="krempe">Herr Krempe</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="justine">Justine Moritz</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="nugent">Daniel Nugent</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="safie">Safie</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="saville">Margaret Saville</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="waldman">Professor Waldman</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="walton">Robert Walton</ref>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
			<div type="appCharsB">
				<list>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="agatha" target="#agatha">Agatha De Lacey</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Daughter of M. De Lacey and sister of Felix.</p>
						<p>Agatha first appears anonymously (described only as "a young creature") in the Creature's narration (II:3:14): </p>
						<p/>
						<p> I ate my breakfast with pleasure, and was about to remove a plank to procure myself a little water, when I heard a step,
							and, looking through a small chink, I beheld a young creature, with a pail on her head, passing before my hovel. The girl
							was young and of gentle demeanour, unlike what I have since found cottagers and farm-house servants to be. Yet she was
							meanly dressed, a coarse blue petticoat and a linen jacket being her only garb; her fair hair was plaited, but not
							adorned; she looked patient, yet sad. </p>
						<p> She provides the Creature with his first experience of beauty (II:3:15): </p>
						<p> The young girl was occupied in arranging the cottage; but presently she took something out of a drawer, which employed her
							hands, and she sat down beside the old man, who, taking up an instrument, began to play, and to produce sounds, sweeter
							than the voice of the thrush or the nightingale. It was a lovely sight, even to me, poor wretch! who had never beheld
							aught beautiful before. </p>
						<p> The Creature first learns her name in II:4:9, as he learns the rudiments of language. Over time he comes to know her
							history: she once "had ranked with ladies of the highest distinction" (II:6:2), but after De Lacey's fall, she was
							imprisoned with her father (II:6:13). After five months in prison, the family was condemned to exile and found "a
							miserable asylum in the cottage in Germany," where the Creature first encounters her.</p>
						<p> In her last appearance in the novel, she faints from terror upon beholding the Creature (II:7:38): </p>
						<p>At that instant the cottage door was opened, and Felix, Safie, and Agatha entered. Who can describe their horror and
							consternation on beholding me? Agatha fainted; and Safie, unable to attend to her friend, rushed out of the cottage.</p>
						<p> When the Creature returns to the cottage, the De Laceys have deserted it (II:8:7).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="william" target="#william">William Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Youngest son of Alphonse and Caroline Frankenstein; brother to Victor and Ernest.</p>
						<p> Victor Frankenstein describes William in the novel's first chapter: </p>
						<p>William, the youngest of our family, was yet an infant, and the most beautiful little fellow in the world; his lively blue
							eyes, dimpled cheeks, and endearing manners, inspired the tenderest affection. (I:1:27)</p>
						<p>WhileFrankenstein is at Ingolstadt, Elizabeth provides this account of "darling William":</p>
						<p>he is very tall of his age, with sweet laughing blue eyes, dark eye-lashes, and curling hair. When he smiles, two little
							dimples appear on each cheek, which are rosy with health. He has already had one or two little wives, but Louisa Biron is
							his favourite, a pretty little girl of five years of age" (I:5:7).</p>
						<p> William is murdered by the Creature, who discovers that he is a relation of Frankenstein (II:8:29), and Justine Moritz is
							framed for the murder (I:6:31).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="alphonse" target="#alphonse">Alphonse Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Father of Victor, Ernest, and William Frankenstein; husband of Caroline; uncle and adoptive father of Elizabeth.</p>
						<p> Alphonse Frankenstein is a syndic (magistrate) of Geneva and comes from a long line of syndics. Victor describes his
							character and his devotion to public duty: </p>
						<p> My father had filled several public situations with honour and reputation. He was respected by all who knew him for his
							integrity and indefatigable attention to public business. He passed his younger days perpetually occupied by the affairs
							of his country; and it was not until the decline of life that he thought of marrying, and bestowing on the state sons who
							might carry his virtues and his name down to posterity. (I:1:1)</p>
						<p>The emphasis on duty is clear in all of his dealings with his son.</p>
						<p> Alphonse dies of an apoplectic fit after hearing of the death of Elizabeth.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="beaufort" target="#beaufort">M. Beaufort </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>"Intimate friend" of Alphonse Frankenstein (I:1:2); father of Caroline, who becomes his wife.</p>
						<p> Victor Frankenstein relates that Beaufort, </p>
						<p> from a flourishing state, fell, through numerous mischances, into poverty. This man, whose name was Beaufort, was of a
							proud and unbending disposition, and could not bear to live in poverty and oblivion in the same country where he had
							formerly been distinguished for his rank and magnificence. Having paid his debts, therefore, in the most honourable
							manner, he retreated with his daughter to the town of Lucerne, where he lived unknown and in wretchedness. (I:1:2) </p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="caroline" target="#caroline">Caroline Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Daughter of M. Beaufort; mother of Victor, Ernest, and William Frankenstein; wife of Alphonse; aunt and adoptive mother of
							Elizabeth; mother surrogate to Justine Moritz.</p>
						<p> Beaufort, in his decline into poverty and wretchedness, brings Caroline with him, and during his final illness, she
							ministers to him for ten months. Finally, </p>
						<p> Her father died in her arms, leaving her an orphan and a beggar. This last blow overcame her; and she knelt by Beaufort's
							coffin, weeping bitterly, when my father entered the chamber. He came like a protecting spirit to the poor girl, who
							committed herself to his care, and after the interment of his friend he conducted her to Geneva, and placed her under the
							protection of a relation. Two years after this event Caroline became his wife. (I:1:5) </p>
						<p> She joined the hands of Elizabeth and myself: "My children," she said, "my firmest hopes of future happiness were placed
							on the prospect of your union. This expectation will now be the consolation of your father. Elizabeth, my love, you must
							supply my place to your younger cousins. Alas! I regret that I am taken from you; and, happy and beloved as I have been,
							is it not hard to quit you all? But these are not thoughts befitting me; I will endeavour to resign myself cheerfully to
							death, and will indulge a hope of meeting you in another world." (I:2:2)</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="clerval" target="#clerval">Henry Clerval </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Friend and schoolfellow of Victor and Elizabeth from childhood; murdered by the Creature.</p>
						<p> Victor describes him as an only child, "the son of a merchant of Geneva, an intimate friend of my father. He was a boy of
							singular talent and fancy" (I:1:11). Clerval is almost a family member in the Frankensten household: when Victor complains
							that "My brothers were considerably younger than myself," he notes, "but I had a friend in one of my schoolfellows, who
							compensated for this deficiency" (I:1:11), and Victor includes Clerval in his account of his "domestic circle" because "he
							was constantly with us" (I:1:13). The two are united by "the closest friendship" (1831:I:2:2).</p>
						<p> After parting from Clerval on his departure for Ingolstadt, Victor does not see his friend until after the creation of the
							Creature: he arrives just in time to care for Victor in his first insane fever (I:4:17).</p>
						<p> After Frankenstein's recovery, Clerval convinces his father to allow him to join Frankenstein at the university, studying
							classical and Eastern languages: </p>
						<p> Clerval was no natural philosopher. His imagination was too vivid for the minutiae of science. Languages were his
							principal study; and he sought, but acquiring their elements, to open a field for self-instruction on his return to
							Geneva. Persian, Arabic, and Hebrew, gained his attention, after he had made himself perfectly master of Greek and Latin.
							(I:5:14)</p>
						<p> He came to the university with the design of making himself complete master of the oriental languages, as thus he should
							open a field for the plan of life he had marked out for himself. Resolved to pursue no inglorious career, he turned his
							eyes toward the East, as affording scope for his spirit of enterprise. (1831:I:6:14) </p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="creature" target="#creature">The Creature</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Frankenstein describes the Creature's creation: </p>
						<p> I doubted at first whether I should attempt the creation of a being like myself or one of simpler organization; but my
							imagination was too much exalted by my first success to permit me to doubt of my ability to give life to an animal as
							complex and wonderful as man. The materials at present within my command hardly appeared adequate to so arduous an
							undertaking; but I doubted not that I should ultimately succeed. . . . As the minuteness of the parts formed a great
							hindrance to my speed, I resolved, contrary to my first intention, to make the being of a gigantic stature; that is to
							say, about eight feet in height, and proportionably large. (I:3:7) </p>
						<p> How can I describe my emotions at this catastrophe, or how delineate the wretch whom with such infinite pains and care I
							had endeavoured to form? His limbs were in proportion, and I had selected his features as beautiful. Beautiful! Great God!
							His yellow skin scarcely covered the work of muscles and arteries beneath; his hair was of a lustrous black, and flowing;
							his teeth of a pearly whiteness; but these luxuriances only formed a more horrid contrast with his watery eyes, that
							seemed almost of the same colour as the dun white sockets in which they were set, his shrivelled complexion, and straight
							black lips. (I:4:2)</p>
						<p> After unintentionally driving the De Laceys from him, he vows vengeance on humanity, and especially on his creator: "I,
							like the arch fiend, bore a hell within me; and, finding myself unsympathized with, wished to tear up the trees, spread
							havoc and destruction around me, and then to have sat down and enjoyed the ruin. . . . I declared everlasting war against
							the species, and, more than all, against him who had formed me, and sent me forth to this insupportable misery" (II:8:3).
							He goes to seek Frankenstein, and on the way encounters and murders William (1818:II:31).</p>
						<p> At the end of his long narrative, the Creature demands that Frankestein create for him a mate (II:8:36), a task
							Frankenstein at first refuses. But the Creature's eloquence prevails: </p>
						<p> If I have no ties and no affections, hatred and vice must be my portion; the love of another will destroy the cause of my
							crimes, and I shall become a thing, of whose existence every one will be ignorant. My vices are the children of a forced
							solitude that I abhor; and my virtues will necessarily arise when I live in communion with an equal. I shall feel the
							affections of a sensitive being, and become linked to the chain of existence and events, from which I am now excluded.
							(II:9:14)</p>
						<p> But Frankenstein, fearing the propagation of "a race of devils" (III:3:2), reneges on his promise, and destroys his
							half-finished creation (III:3:4). The furious Creature declares,</p>
						<p> Slave, I before reasoned with you, but you have proved yourself unworthy of my condescension. Remember that I have power;
							you believe yourself miserable, but I can make you so wretched that the light of day will be hateful to you. You are my
							creator, but I am your master; obey! (III:3:11)</p>
						<p> Finally Frankenstein is picked up by Walton, who is uncertain about his story until, after Frankenstein's death from
							exhaustion, the Creature appears aboard ship and laments over his body (III:WC:35). He justifies his actions to Walton—"I
							pitied Frankenstein; my pity amounted to horror: I abhorred myself. . . . I knew that I was preparing for myself a deadly
							torture; but I was the slave, not the master of an impulse, which I detested, yet could not disobey"—and declares his
							intention to "seek the most northern extremity of the globe," there to immolate himself and find rest in death.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="delacey" target="#delacey">M. De Lacey </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Father of Agatha and Felix.</p>
						<p> The Creature first observes De Lacey from the inside of his sty: "In one corner, near a small fire, sat an old man,
							leaning his head on his hands in a disconsolate attitude" (II:3:15). He further describes the </p>
						<p> old man, who, taking up an instrument [a guitar], began to play, and to produce sounds, sweeter than the voice of the
							thrush or the nightingale. . . . The silver hair and benevolent countenance of the aged cottager, won my reverence.
							(II:3:15)</p>
						<p> The Creature soon discovers De Lacey is blind (II:4:3), and as he learns language, he learns about the family. He learns
							first their names and familial relations: "I learned also the names of the cottagers themselves. The youth and his
							companion had each of them several names, but the old man had only one, which was father. The girl was called sister, or
							Agatha; and the youth Felix, brother, or son" (II:4:9). Later he learns their story: </p>
						<p> The name of the old man was De Lacey. He was descended from a good family in France, where he had lived for many years in
							affluence, respected by his superiors, and beloved by his equals. His son was bred in the service of his country; and
							Agatha had ranked with ladies of the highest distinction. A few months before my arrival, they had lived in a large and
							luxurious city, called Paris, surrounded by friends, and possessed of every enjoyment which virtue, refinement of
							intellect, or taste, accompanied by a moderate fortune, could afford. (II:6:2)</p>
						<p> The Creature, hoping to make his presence known to the family, decides to begin with old De Lacey, whose blindness will
							prevent him from being horrified by him (II:7:13). The Creature begins to relate his story and his hopes of finding a
							friend, when Felix returns to the cottage, and drives the Creature from it. When he returns later, the family has
							abandoned the cottage.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="eliz" target="#eliz">Elizabeth Lavenza Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Cousin, adopted sister, and eventually wife of Victor Frankenstein (in the first edition of 1818; in the third edition of
							1831, she is a foundling).</p>
						<p> The Frankenstein family adopted Elizabeth, and Caroline Frankenstein early planned that Elizabeth should be Victor's
							future wife. Frankenstein describes her character at length: </p>
						<p> She was docile and good tempered, yet gay and playful as a summer insect. Although she was lively and animated, her
							feelings were strong and deep, and her disposition uncommonly affectionate. No one could better enjoy liberty, yet no one
							could submit with more grace than she did to constraint and caprice. Her imagination was luxuriant, yet her capability of
							application was great. Her person was the image of her mind; her hazel eyes, although as lively as a bird's, possessed an
							attractive softness. Her figure was light and airy; and, though capable of enduring great fatigue, she appeared the most
							fragile creature in the world. While I admired her understanding and fancy, I loved to tend on her, as I should on a
							favourite animal; and I never saw so much grace both of person and mind united to so little pretension. (I:1:9).</p>
						<p> On Victor's return to Geneva, Alphonse Frankenstein returns to his late wife's plan, that Victor and Elizabeth should
							marry. Victor agrees, but postpones the wedding until after he has completed his task. When he destroys the half-finished
							female creature (III:3:4), the Creature vows, "I will be with you on your wedding-night!"(III:3:15)—a threat Frankenstein
							imagines is directed against himself ("I carried pistols and a dagger constantly about me," (III:5:30).</p>
						<p> The two are married after the death of Clerval and Frankenstein's imprisonment and long illness. On their wedding night,
							however, Frankenstein leaves the room, and hears a scream above. He returns to find Elizabeth "lifeless and inanimate,
							thrown across the bed, her head hanging down, and her pale and distorted features half covered by her hair" (III:6:8).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ernest" target="#ernest">Ernest Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Younger son of Alphonse and Caroline Frankenstein; brother to Victor and William.</p>
						<p> Victor Frankenstein describes his younger brother: </p>
						<p> Ernest was six years younger than myself, and was my principal pupil. He had been afflicted with ill health from his
							infancy, through which Elizabeth and I had been his constant nurses: his disposition was gentle, but he was incapable of
							any severe application. (I:1:27). </p>
						<p> Ernest is the only Frankenstein to survive the novel.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="felix" target="#felix">Felix De Lacey</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Son of the blind M. De Lacey and brother of Agatha.</p>
						<p> It is through Felix's conversation and language tutoring to Safie that the Creature learns to speak and read. As he
							becomes more proficient in the language, he learns Felix's story: he had fallen in love with Safie and arranged her
							father's escape from prison (II:6:9), but, betrayed by her father (II:6:13), he finds his family imprisoned and Safie
							taken out of his reach. The De Laceys flee to "a miserable asylum in the cottage in Germany" (II:6:15). </p>
						<p> Felix is never aware of the Creature until he returns to the cottage to find his father in the Creature's presence.
							Fearing for his father's safety, he "darted forward, and with supernatural force tore me from his father, to whose knees I
							clung: in a transport of fury, he dashed me to the ground and struck me violently with a stick" (II:7:38). The Creature
							flees; on his return, he discovers that the De Laceys have abandoned the cottage.</p>
						<p> Felix seems to have served as a role model for the Creature, who reverts to his betrayal by him in speaking to Walton: "Am
							I to be thought the only criminal, when all human kind sinned against me? Why do you not hate Felix, who drove his friend
							from his door with contumely?" (III:WC:43).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="frank" target="#frank">Victor Frankenstein </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Son of Alphonse and Caroline Frankenstein; brother to Ernest and William; cousin, adoptive brother, and later husband to
							Elizabeth; childhood playfriend of Henry Clerval; student of Krempe and Waldman.</p>
						<p> Rescued from an icefloe in the Arctic Ocean (I:L4:6), Frankenstein narrates the complete novel to Robert Walton. Born in
							Geneva, Victor is educated at the University of Ingolstadt in chemistry. There his researches bring him to discover the
							secret of life, and he constructs and animates a giant being (I:3 and I:4). Appalled by his ugliness, Victor flees, and
							upon returning to his lodgings finds the Creature gone. He suffers a nervous collapse and is nursed back to health over
							several months by Clerval, who has also come to the university to study.</p>
						<p> A year-and-a-half pass, then Victor receives a letter from his father announcing the death of his youngest sibling,
							William, and summoning him home. On the way he encounters his Creature on the outskirts of Geneva (I:6:22) and realizes
							that the Creature has been agent of William's death. Upon his arrival, however, he is greeted with news of the arrest of
							Justine Moritz for the deed. Justine is tried and, convicted on circumstantial evidence, is executed. Recognizing his
							responsibility, Victor sinks into a deep depression.</p>
						<p> Hoping to recover the family's former sense of well-being, Alphonse proposes a trip to the valley of Chamounix beneath Mt.
							Blanc. (In the 1831 edition Victor undertakes this tour by himself.) Upon the glacier known as the Mer de Glace, Victor
							suddenly encounters his Creature (II:2:5) and is forced to listen to the story of the Creatures' existence up to that
							point, a narration that takes up the central third of the novel. The Creature appeals to Victor to create a mate for him,
							and Victor reluctantly promises to do so.</p>
						<p> Returning to Geneva, Victor asks of his father that his nuptials with Elizabeth be postponed until he has had a chance to
							travel. His real purpose for his trip to England is to gain further knowledge before creating a second being. Clerval
							accompanies him on this trip, but they part in Scotland; Victor settles in the remote Orkney Islands and sets to work. He
							is racked with second thoughts and, upon discovering the Creature observing his efforts, destroys the being he was
							creating. The Creature vows revenge, telling Victor that he will be with him on his wedding night. Victor sets off for the
							Scottish mainland, but a strong wind carries his boat to the northern coast of Ireland, where he is arrested for a murder
							just committed, that of his friend Clerval. This event precipitates a second collapse of health; he is brought back to
							health after the arrival of his father.</p>
						<p> Acquitted on the grounds that he had arrived in Ireland after Clerval's death, Victor returns to Geneva to marry
							Elizabeth. On the night of their marriage the Creature's vow that he would be with Victor on this night translates into
							the murder of his bride. Alphonse suffers a fatal stroke, and Victor sets off to enact his own revenge on the Creature,
							travelling first to Marseilles, then across the Mediterranean Sea to Russia and across its vast expanse to the frozen
							Arctic Ocean. There, after a break-up of the ice, Victor finds himself stranded and incapable of further pursuit, but he
							is rescued by Walton. When Walton, under threat of a mutiny, determines to abandon his expedition and return to England,
							the exhausted and now purposeless Victor dies (III:WC:31). The Creature returns to the ship, where Walton encounters him
							lamenting his creator's death.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="justine" target="#justine">Justine Moritz </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Servant to the Frankenstein family and particular friend of Elizabeth.</p>
						<p> Elizabeth relates how Justine came to join the Frankenstein household: </p>
						<p> Madame Moritz, her mother, was a widow with four children, of whom Justine was the third. This girl had always been the
							favourite of her father; but, through a strange perversity, her mother could not endure her, and, after the death of M.
							Moritz, treated her very ill. My aunt observed this; and, when Justine was twelve years of age, prevailed on her mother to
							allow her to live at her house. (I:5:3)</p>
						<p> She is accused of the murder of William (I:6:31), is convicted on circumstantial evidence (I:7:12), and, although thought
							innocent by the entire Frankenstein family, is executed for the crime.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="kirwin" target="#kirwin">Kirwin</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Irish magistrate who charges Victor Frankenstein with the death of Clerval (III:4:1).</p>
						<p> When Frankenstein falls into another fever, this one lasting two months, Kirwin nurses him back to health until Victor's
							father arrives (III:4:36). Afterwards, Kirwin, convinced of Frankenstein's innocence, serves as his defense
							(III:4:44).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="krempe" target="#krempe">Krempe</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Professor of Natural Philosophy at the University of Ingolstadt whose instruction Victor Frankenstein resists.</p>
						<p> Krempe, discovering Frankenstein's fondness for alchemists in their first interview, bursts out contemptuously, "Have you
							really spent your time in studying such nonsense?" (I:2:9). Frankenstein relates his impression of his new teacher: </p>
						<p> M. Krempe was a little squat man, with a gruff voice and repulsive countenance; the teacher, therefore, did not prepossess
							me in favour of his doctrine. (I:2:12)</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="nugent" target="#nugent">Daniel Nugent </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>An Irish fisherman and witness against Victor Frankenstein for the murder of Clerval (III:4:2).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="safie" target="#safie">Safie</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Daughter of a Turkish merchant, adopted by the De Lacey family.</p>
						<p> The Creature watches Safie's arrival at the cottage, admiring her "countenance of angelic beauty" (II:5:4), and noting her
							cheering effect on Felix. He soon notices that as she "appeared to have a language of her own, she was neither understood
							by, or herself understood, the cottagers" (II:5:6); the Creature resolves to use this to his advantage, learning the
							French language by overhearing Safie's language lessons.</p>
						<p> As the Creature learns a language, he learns the shared story of Safie and the De Laceys. Safie was the daughter of a
							Turkish merchant resident in Paris and a Christian Arab, enslaved by the Turks, who had raised her as a Christian
							(II:6:8). Her father's arrest (on unspecified political grounds) leads Felix to vow to free him, and this attracts Safie
							to him. The night before his scheduled execution, he frees the Turk and conducts him to Leghorn with Safie. The Creature
							notes that "The Turk allowed this intimacy to take place," not wishing to lose Felix's help (II:6:12). But when the De
							Lacey family is imprisoned for assisting in his escape, "the treacherous Turk, for whom he and his family endured such
							unheard-of oppression, on discovering that his deliverer was thus reduced to poverty and impotence, became a traitor to
							good feeling and honour, and had quitted Italy with his daughter" (II:6:15).</p>
						<p> Safie, averse to the thought of living in Turkey, fled her father and traveled to Germany to stay with the De Laceys. As
							the Creature notes of their cottage, "The presence of Safie diffused happiness among its inhabitants" (II:7:10). The
							Creature's last sight of her is as she flees the cottage in horror upon discovering him with old De Lacey (II:7:38).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="savillewalton" target="#savillewalton">Margaret Walton Saville </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Sister of Robert Walton and the recipient of the letters that constitute the novel. Although her brother's confidante, she
							disapproves of his expedition (the first sentence of the novel, [I:L1:1]).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="waldman" target="#waldman">Waldman</term>
						<lb/>
						<p>Professor of Natural Philosophy at the University of Ingolstadt, with a specialty in chemistry, and instructor of Victor
							Frankenstein.</p>
						<p> Unlike Krempe, whom Frankenstein finds intellectually and physically repulsive, Waldman proves a kind and understanding
							teacher. Frankenstein describes him: </p>
						<p> This professor was very unlike his colleague. He appeared about fifty years of age, but with an aspect expressive of the
							greatest benevolence; a few grey hairs covered his temples, but those at the back of his head were nearly black. His
							person was short, but remarkably erect; and his voice the sweetest I had ever heard. (I:2:25)</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="walton" target="#walton">Robert Walton </term>
						<lb/>
						<p>English ship's captain on an arctic expedition in search of the Northeast Passage to the Pacific Ocean. Rescuing Victor
							Frankenstein at sea, he is the recipient of the narrative of Victor's life.</p>
						<p> Robert Walton writes the series of letters to his sister, Margaret Saville, that constitute the novel.</p>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
