<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Improvisational Accessibility and Romanticism </title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Giffen Mare Maupin</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-04-17</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.wellbeing.maupin</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">wellbeing</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">On Tending, Movement, and Making
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Giffen Mare</forename>
                                <surname>Maupin</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.maupin"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism, Teaching, and Wellbeing</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-04-10">April 17, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>04.17.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>On Tending, Movement, and Making</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Giffen Mare Maupin</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Hendrix College</affiliation>
                </byline>
            
            <p>To what extent can we as educators conceptualize teaching as a practice of care? In
                what ways can or should we tend to the embodied lives of our students? My teaching
                life is anchored in Hendrix College, located in Conway, AR; we enroll approximately
                1,200 students per year. I know many of my students and colleagues well, and I worry
                that we are forgetting how to live in our bodies. I fear that we are increasingly
                unable to keep ourselves well. I redesigned English 325: British Romanticism during
                the spring semester of 2018 because I wanted to explore alongside my students how
                walking can impact our approaches to writing and to being well. My own history as a
                learner informed my thinking about this course. For the first twenty-five years of
                my life, I set my body aside; I could barely admit I<hi rend="italic">had </hi>a
                body in the first place. When I discovered in my late twenties that my physical self
                could be a source of gladness and calm, I received a crucial, animating gift. “I
                want us to be well in the midst of each other,” I often thought as I planned this
                course. “I want students to exist vibrantly in their bodies, and to recognize how
                our bodies can help us learn.” How, I wondered, could I use British Romantic
                literature to anchor a capacious model of writing in which we both choose to move
                and choose to be still?</p>
                
            <p> Two ideas about care guided me as I reimagined this course. First, I wanted to care
                for my students indirectly, introducing texts and assignments that promote
                questioning, experimentation, and attentiveness. Yet I also wanted to care in a way
                that would make something happen,something I could recognize and name. I hoped that
                one of this course’s core assignments would impact students in legible ways. Towards
                the middle of the course, students selected a one-hour route and walked this route
                multiple times. They kept regular journals of their walks, guided by questions that
                linked these walks to those of the Romantic walkers we were studying. As they
                pondered connections between our readings and their own walking practices, I hoped
                that students would also develop a deeper sense of calm. I expected that they would
                become more patient and meditative, more aware of their bodies and the world through
                which they walked. I imagined, in brief, that students would recognize how walking
                regularly could keep them well. As is so often true of courses, this one ended
                untidily; in some sense, English 325 continues still. Throughout the semester, I
                remained aware of students’ energy and lethargy, their periods of focus and
                inattentiveness, and variations in their apparent physical and mental health. In the
                process of doing so, I became more humble in my approach to wellbeing and
                unwellness. Engaging ethically with the embodied lives of our students requires us
                to be gentle, even slightly distant, and to accept all we cannot know of them. We
                can practice this gentleness, in part, by understanding wellbeing as a temporary
                state, one that settles only to shift. English 325’s texts, conversations, and
                writing ultimately suggested to me how the bodies of learners who share the same
                room keep our own separate time.</p>
                
            <p>In this fourteen-week course, we read varied accounts of walking in British Romantic
                poetry and prose. Walking also functioned for us as a mode of reading, and, more
                specifically, a mode of listening. The early weeks of the course prepared students
                to complete a close reading of ten to fifteen lines of a poem, using the embodied
                reading techniques I describe below. Students walked in order to hear more deeply
                the poems they read. They also pursued connections between the course material and
                their own walking lives by completing five entries in a walking journal of their
                own. During our second month together, we studied longer works of poetry and prose,
                including <hi rend="italic">Home at Grasmere</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Grasmere
                    and Alfoxden Journals</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein. </hi>During this
                part of the semester, we concentrated on ethical questions, including how embodied
                differences shape the experiences of individual walkers, considering how a walk’s
                form, pace, and rhythm might shift for those who are living with disabilities. We
                also pondered the distinctions between walking for leisure and walking out of
                necessity, and the relationship between walking and home. Each of students’ five
                walking journals focused on a different aspect of the same one-hour walk to which
                they returned each week. In their final essay of the semester, students drew their
                walks into conversation with our course texts by choosing a single idea and
                describing the place that this idea occupied in their walks and in one or more of
                our readings.</p>
                
            <p> My approach to close reading, in this course and elsewhere, locates reading in the
                body. If poems require close listening, we can hear them withour ears as well as our
                feet. Particularly when we encounter the syntactic intricacies of poems like
                “Tintern Abbey” and “Mont Blanc” for the first time, they sound ponderously
                cerebral. It is easy for new readers of poetry to miss the dynamism of poetic
                sentences, the ways that thinking, perception, and feeling unfold across lines. Many
                students came to British Romanticism with a noun-based approach to reading poetry;
                they were used to locating and naming a poem’s sounds, images, meter, and line
                breaks. As we studied a small group of poems whose speakers contemplate domestic and
                natural scenes, I encouraged students to shift their focus from naming different
                aspects of poetic form to describing how poems move. We concentrated particularly on
                the charged relationship between sentences and lines. The following sentence from
                James Longenbach’s <hi rend="italic">The Art of the Poetic Line </hi>guided us in
                this work: “The line is no arbitrary unit, no ruler, but a dynamic force that works
                in conjunction with other elements of the poem: the syntax of the sentences, the
                rhythm of stressed and unstressed syllables, and the resonance of similar sounds”
                (43). </p>
                
            <p> I was curious about how walking with our course texts might help students to feel
                the line’s dynamic force.<hi rend="bold"> </hi>During the second and third weeks of
                the semester, we began to walk around the track near our classroom as we read aloud.
                The class by this point had some experience in voicing poems like “Tintern Abbey”
                and “Frost at Midnight.” The sounds of Romantic poems, however haltingly, were
                beginning to inhabit their ears. We walked with these poems in several different
                ways. One student began by reading a brief section of a poem unnaturally. The class
                followed with our feet, stopping at the end of every line. Doing so allowed students
                to feel the friction between a poem’s enjambments and their own steps, to experience
                how a sentence continued while they stopped. We then returned to the same section of
                the poem, this time letting the sentence’s movement guide us to its natural
                conclusion. Following these experiments, students began to describe what these
                sentences did to them as they walked. Four templates anchored their responses: “This
                sentence [verb + adverb] us to the next line”; “The speaker [verb + adverb] us to
                the next line”; “[Author’s last name] [verb + adverb] us to the next line,” and “We
                are [passive verb + adverb] to the next line.” At the end of this exercise, we had
                compiled a list of verbs to which students returned in their close reading essays.
                As they brainstormed for these essays, I asked them to translate the work we did in
                the classroom to the lines on which they chose to focus.</p>
                
            <p> Although students approached our first poem-walks with some skepticism, these
                exercises became more meaningful to them as we used them to sharpen the attention we
                gave to emotion in the poems at hand. As these thirteen students dipped their toes
                into Wordsworth, Coleridge, Shelley, and Keats, they were both puzzled and amused by
                the particular intensities of Romantic feeling, the sheer largeness of emotion they
                encountered on the page. Our walking exercises encouraged the class to trace the
                feelings they heard in a speaker’s voice to a poet’s choices about form, and, in
                particular, how a poet distributes sentences across lines. Our capacity to be moved
                in an emotional sense, in other words, is closely linked to our capacity to be moved
                in a physical sense. For example, a sentence might lead us gently from one line to
                the next, or set us down at the end of a line. As a result, we might detect
                hesitation or certainty in a speaker’s voice. By concentrating on a poem’s movement,
                students experience the close relationship between hearing a poem and being touched
                by it. They shift their focus from what texts <hi rend="italic">are</hi>to what
                texts <hi rend="italic">do</hi>: invite, engage, unsettle, propel, question, and
                more. As a result, students’syntaxshifts: verbs, rather than nouns, ground their
                sentences.</p>
                
            <p> The first essay in the course, then, asked students to understand close reading as a
                practice in which a writer attends to a text’s liveliness, its capacity to make
                something happen in the reader’s ear. By practicing this deep attentiveness in their
                first essay and throughout the semester, students prepared to render their own walks
                on the page. In upper-level courses like British Romanticism, I emphasize the close
                relationship between a detailed rendering of a text and a vivid articulation of
                one’s own perceptions or memories. Particularly because Hendrix English majors can
                choose from among three tracks—literary studies, film studies, and creative
                writing—I often design assignments that invite classes to understand both literary
                criticism and creative nonfiction writing as “[arts] of description,” a phrase I
                borrow from Mark Doty’s volume of the same title. As they built a small portfolio of
                five walking journals, students shifted their attention from printed texts to the
                natural and human world that they encountered during a one-hour walk. Each student
                returned to the same one-hour walk five times and composed 500 words in response to
                each walk. Following the same route resembles rereading; I hoped that the distinct
                paths students chose to follow would become continually new, would claim their
                attention in different ways. </p>
                
            <p> Students began their walking journals by describing how they chose where to walk.
                Their second journals, inspired by our discussionsabout <hi rend="italic">The
                    Grasmere and Alfoxden Journals</hi>, encouraged students to use the
                particularity of Dorothy Wordsworth’s observations as a guide. I asked them to
                record small details, and to incorporate impressions provided by each of the five
                senses. As we discussed <hi rend="italic">Home at Grasmere</hi>, students carried
                index cards with the word “home” on them during their walks. In these entries, they
                observed how this word informed the kinds of details they chose to record. A spring
                break journal prompt invited students to pursue a new route and to consider the
                differences between their familiar path and one they encountered for the first time.
                During their final walk, students selected one-third of a page of prose or ten to
                fifteen lines of poetry from one of our readings and carried this text with them as
                they walked. This last entry led into their final essay for the course, in which
                they traced a single topic or question through their walking path and through one or
                more of our course texts. </p>
                
            <p> The final essay in the course asked students to use their own walks as a framework
                for their textual engagement. They experimented with anessay form appropriate to the
                digressions and errancies of both walking and thinking. Rebecca Solnit, whose <hi
                    rend="italic">Wanderlust: A History of Walking</hi>, framed our early
                conversations in the course, describes how walking can inform thinking: “Moving on
                foot makes it easier to move in time; the mind wanders from plans to recollections
                to observations. The rhythm of walking generates a kind of rhythm of thinking, and
                the passage through a landscape echoes or stimulates the passage through a series of
                thoughts” (6). Solnit suggests how writers who pursue questions about walking can
                craft essays whose form acknowledges the surprises, uncertainties, and associations
                one experiences during a walk. Rather than constructing a formal argument about our
                readings, students pursued a more meandering path in which the details of their
                walks occasioned a brief meditation on a piece of poetry or prose, and vice-versa. I
                invited them to consider how a single concept or question could lend coherence to
                their pieces. In Maggie Nelson’s <hi rend="italic">Bluets</hi>, for example, the
                word “blue” anchors Nelson’s meditations about desire and loss. After students had
                completed their first three walking journals, I met with each member of the class
                individually to discuss the patterns I noticed in their work. My goal in these
                meetings was to suggest potential routes to pursue in their final essays, and to
                encourage class members to refine their topics as they continued to read, write, and
                walk. Final essays addressed topics that included home, a memorable peach orchard,
                disorientation, and holiness. </p>
                
            <p> As I read these final essays, I felt an acute sense of loss.“I want to keep us
                together,” I thought after the class met for the last time. My impulse to continue a
                course after its ending arises, in part, from an awareness of work left undone. New
                ideas about a course’s readings, in-class exercises, and writing assignments often
                occur to me only after a semester’s official completion. After fourteen weeks of
                English 325, I was more familiar with the learners who shaped the course; I knew
                more about their questions and goals. So too did I have a clearer sense of how we
                could use class time to refine our ideas and shape more rigorous pieces of writing.
                The first incarnation of English 325 reinforced how slowly intellectual and creative
                work proceed, as well as how the lived experiences of individual learners, including
                the varied capacities of distinct bodies, impact thinking, walking, and writing
                alike. The next version of English 325 will take both this necessary slowness and
                the possibilities created by students’ embodied differences as guiding principles.
                Students will have more opportunities to practice describing both our course texts
                and their walks, with feedback from one another and from me. Essay prompts and
                in-class exercises will more fully acknowledge the various ways in which learners
                inhabit their bodies and offer a range of approaches for those who are living with
                chronic illnesses and disabilities. For example, students will have the option to
                prepare to write their close reading essays by walking with course texts or moving
                with them from seated positions, using their eyes, voices, hands, and feet to
                indicate the endings of sentences and lines. So too can writers who feel unable to
                complete hour-long walks approach journal prompts by immersing themselves in single
                locations, exploring variations on stillness, recording in-depth perceptions
                generated by one or more of their senses, and, as their bodies allow, cataloguing
                how their thoughts and perceptions change when they shift physical positions. The
                course will incorporate more writing workshops in which we both discuss and refine
                our textual analyses and descriptions of our walks, drawing inspiration from models
                of both kinds of work.</p>
                
            <p> During the next iteration of this course, wewill also study more experimental essays
                on which students can rely as they compose their final essays. My commitment to
                assigning essays like the final essay in this course comes from two places. Because
                I am a critic by training and a poet by nature, my own thinking on the page often
                proceeds lyrically. My essays meditate, describe, and question more readily than
                they argue. I ask students to write in this mode because I have been educated by
                doing so. Students, too, have often expressed to me a discomfort with the voice they
                adopt in argumentative essays; they describe a sense of remoteness from their work
                and from any particular audience. In many of my upper-level courses, students spend
                the semester building towards capacious and intricate final essays that dwell on the
                thresholds between distinct modes of expression, essays that engage critically with
                the texts at hand while also imagining broadly what it might mean to respond to
                those texts. In spite of my commitment to this kind of writing, I continue to be
                challenged by the work of locating essays in which writers demonstrate a sustained
                engagement with a text before shifting to a new line of thinking. Many pieces of the
                type I am describing feel to me insufficient in their slowness; I want my students
                to encounter writing, in other words, whose mode of attending to texts is as
                particular as Dorothy Wordsworth’s prolonged involvement with a nest of swallows. </p>
                
            <p> Yet my wish to keep the class together was also anchored in my wish to care for
                them, to walk beside them in their writing lives, to keep watch over the
                vulnerabilities they shared with me when we spoke one-on-one. These thirteen
                students delighted and intrigued me, frustrated and saddened me. Rarely were all
                fourteen of us present in the same room, at the same time. Towards the middle of the
                semester, I expressed to the class my concerns about their sporadic attendance. Yet
                I did so with a lump in my throat. The particular focus of this course has prompted
                me to consider how our bodies both frame our access to classroom space, and
                influence how we inhabit that space. When chronic illness, depression, and anxiety
                prevented students from attending class, I struggled to balance compassion with
                fairness. The porousness of my role as an educator struck me once more. What does it
                mean to treat students with care when I am neither a diagnostician nor a therapist?
                How could I establish meaningful common expectations for class attendance while also
                acknowledging the wide variations in students’ day-to-day wellbeing, particularly
                given the close relationship between wellbeing and socioeconomic status? According
                to the Hendrix community contract, “all Hendrix students are expected to attend
                class in accordance with the catalog and individual course syllabi.” The contract
                also holds students responsible for their own mental and physical health: </p>
                
            <p>Hendrix students are expected to tend to their own mental and physical health. Campus
                resources are available for short-term conditions. Persistent or chronic health
                problems may require care beyond the campus resources. Students should discuss
                academic options with their advisor, professors, or Academic Success office if
                persistent health problems impact a student’s ability to complete educational
                tasks.</p>
                
            <p>These general guidelines offer little clarity for instructors about how to support
                students who are experiencing prolonged or chronic illnesses, and even less clarity
                about how to work alongside students whose depression, anxiety, or other mental
                health challenges impact class attendance. Students navigate health challenges with
                limited resources: one registered nurse and two full-time therapists work tirelessly
                to support our students. Such guidelines also fail to consider how access to
                off-campus physicians, therapists, emergency rooms, and urgent care centers depends
                on students’ ability to pay for these resources.</p>
                
            <p> To approach care in terms of ongoing vigilance, however, risks devaluing the
                necessary solitude, even loneliness, of both learning and embodied life. If I had
                semi-regular contact with students over the course of fourteen weeks, they remained,
                and remain, largely unknown to me. The exigencies of our bodies, our varied states
                of wellness and illness, kept us alone. So too did we read, write, and walk one by
                one. Even as I hoped formore consistent attendance, the writers I discussed with my
                students encouraged me to consider how fourteen individuals could be variously
                present to course texts, and to each other, in a common room. The present tense of
                our classroom differed for each of us, all of the time. On any given day, this
                present tense might include a lingering cough, several sentences of “The Old
                Cumberland Beggar,” harsh fluorescent lights, a description of Frankenstein
                wandering through the Alps, the repeated twisting of a piece of hair, a student’s
                meditations about trash in the Hendrix Creek Preserve, our audible and inaudible
                breaths. In other words, if it is true that conversations among a common group
                create a sense of safety and regularity, it is much more difficult to identify “what
                happens” to and for us, bodily, mentally, and emotionally during a single class and
                beyond it. A more generously exacting question might take this form: what happens,
                and for whom, and how, and with what consequences? Prompted by our course texts, I
                began to think of theword “course” as a verb rather than a noun, an experience
                shaped by individual and collaborative reading, perceiving, walking, thinking,
                conversing, and writing. In texts ranging from <hi rend="italic">Home at Grasmere
                </hi>to <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi>, the writers we studied contemplate
                being alone and being together, both while walking and while still. As students read
                our course texts and described their own walks, their descriptions of solitude and
                companionship became increasingly specific and strange. These singular conditions
                branched and multiplied, assumed different textures and qualities. A common
                classroom space makes room for shared learning and intellectual community, but
                community, too, emerges unrecognizably in time. Like the writers we studied, we were
                and are variously alone and together, new every minute. Our sentences emerged at
                different paces; our realizations and distractions occurred at different times. Our
                bodies shifted in crucial and imperceptible ways.</p>
                
            <p> When I imagined that I could care for my students by asking them to walk, I assumed
                that I would be able to read the effects that our walks would have on us. When I
                anticipated that walking would lead to wellbeing, I thought of wellbeing in terms
                inadequate to its complexity. Before I met the individual learners who created this
                course alongside me, I thought I could know when my students were well, that they
                would demonstrate wellbeing and illness in familiar, legible ways. Yet from the
                course’s beginning, my students took their walks seriously and carried their
                struggles into these walks. They demonstrated, perhaps without fully realizing it, a
                determination to be well on their own terms and in their own time. If we often
                describe wellness in terms of the habits and experiences that are inextricable from
                having both the money and the time to engage in these habits and experiences, it is
                more difficult to identify as well or unwell those bodyminds whose ways of engaging
                with the world differ from our own, particularly because the normative mythology of
                wellness suggests that we reveal wellness through our quietude, restraint, and
                self-composure. Georges Canguillhem, in fact, recalls Henri Michaux’s description of
                health in terms of “the silence of the organs”: 
                
            <quote>As Henri Michaux has put it, “the body (its organs and its functions) has become
                known not through the prowess of the strong, but through the troubles of the weak,
                the ill, the infirm, the wounded (for health is silent, the source of that
                enormously mistaken impression that <hi rend="italic">tout va de soi</hi>”). (20) </quote>
                
            Particularly if we adhere to a narrower sense of wellness that excludes more varied
                possibilities for wellbeing, as I admit that I did when I first envisioned this
                course, we sense that we and others are well when our bodyminds are as inconspicuous
                as possible, when they fail to attract notice, when they are appropriately
                self-contained. Identifying wellbeing in others becomes even more difficult when we
                consider the porous boundaries between our bodies, our minds, and our environments.
                In <hi rend="italic">Volatile Bodies</hi>, Elizabeth Grosz reminds us of the perils
                of separating the body from the mind. As Maurice Merleau-Ponty articulates in <hi
                    rend="italic">Phenomenology of Perception</hi>, to speak of “the body” is to
                speak of something other than an object, something unstill; the word “body” gestures
                towards “our means of communication with [the world]” (106). Rather than being
                separate from the world, Merleau-Ponty writes, the body is deeply involved with it,
                and vice-versa: “Insofar as it sees and touches the world, my body can therefore be
                neither seen nor touched…It is neither tangible nor visible insofar as it is that
                which sees and touches” (105). For all of its small revelations, my own body,
                however I mark its contours and its boundaries, remains a secret to me; it continues
                to educate me in its possibilities and its needs. How can I know, then, what any one
                of my students knows of his, her, or their physical self, or how best to go about
                caring for the bodyminds none of us can place?</p>
                
            <p> I began this essay with a question about care, a curiosity about how we as educators
                might tend to the embodied lives of our students. I continue to pose this question
                as a liberal arts college professor whose charged awareness of individual students
                often overwhelms me as I work to identify common learning goals. In what ways can we
                acknowledge and respond to the intellectual and embodied particularities of the
                students in our courses, both within and beyond the classroom? How can we tend to
                these particularities while also upholding the value of a single<hi rend="italic"
                    >group</hi>, a collection of individual lives juxtaposed for a given,
                unrepeatable period of time? The particular group of students with whom I worked
                during Spring 2018 often seemed to require thirteen different courses, and I found
                myself continually adjusting class plans and assignments in response to each of
                them. The course included three seniors, one majoring in creative writing, one
                majoring in chemistry, and a third majoring in international relations; four
                juniors, two majoring in creative writing, one majoring in literary studies, and one
                majoring in biology; two sophomores, one majoring in film studies and the other
                majoring in psychology; two first-year students, one majoring in chemistry and the
                other majoring in theater; and one student who was visiting Hendrix from a
                university in Austria. Throughout the semester, I wondered whether I had attempted
                to stretch the course beyond what it could reasonably contain, whether this
                walking-centered course was insufficiently still. English 325, in its spring 2018
                form, often shifted gears. Students encountered the challenging poetry and prose of
                early nineteenth-century Britain for the first time and approached close reading in
                an unfamiliar way. Class members walked regularly and sharpened their descriptions
                of the world they encountered as they walked. The course’s final essay invited
                students to write associatively, to allow their thinking to proceed slowly, and to
                achieve coherence through alternatives to traditional argumentation. Any one of
                these tasks could easily occupy a full fourteen weeks. </p>
                
            <p> As the spring 2018 semester concluded, I wondered whether the sheer multiplicity of
                English 325 had fragmented our common time. When I thought about the course, I felt
                disoriented and uncentered, aware of the divergent paths we had walked and
                described, the texts we had discussed, the essays we had crafted, the conversations
                we had held one-on-one and as a group. Given the amount of time we devoted to
                discussing our own walks and walking journals during class discussion, I wondered
                whether our walks had crowded out more“serious” reading and writing. When a course
                like this one asks students to walk more, both inside and outside of the classroom,
                it also allows them to read and to write in ways less recognizable as work. Rebecca
                Solnit reminds us how walking is “the something closest to doing nothing…Walking
                itself is the intentional act closest to the unwilled rhythms of the body, to
                breathing and the beating of the heart. It strikes a delicate balance between
                working and idling, being and doing. It is a bodily labor that produces nothing but
                thoughts, experiences, arrivals” (5). In a series of reflections that they completed
                throughout the semester, students shared with me that their walks calmed them, that
                they came to recognize their paths as homes, and that they learned to incorporate
                their bodies into their written work. At the same time, these walks, both in our
                class conversations and on the pages of students’ final essays, seemed to occupy
                their own time, adjacent to the course without being part of it. </p>
                
            <p> Yet the more time I spend in the classroom, the more I orient myself towards the
                writing lives students will shape beyond their college years. We as writers work in
                the charged space made by tending to our own bodyminds, and engaging with the
                bodyminds of those who surround us. In this space, it is often difficult to trace
                how our finished pieces come to be, to identify the texts and walks and other lives
                and breaths that have informed them. Dorothy Wordsworth’s <hi rend="italic">Grasmere
                    and Alfoxden Journals</hi>, one of the texts that centers this course, bears
                witness to the varied activities of an individual writing life; these activities sit
                breathlessly together on the page, shaping an ongoing present tense. Rachel Mayer
                Brownstein, Lucy Newlyn, Sarah Zimmerman, and other careful readers of Dorothy
                Wordsworth’s writing observe that these journals record domestic tasks completed
                alongside toothaches suffered alongside observations about the weather, that they
                are metonymic or associative in their organization, and that they refrain from
                sequencing the moments of a day according to the progression of hours. By gathering
                rather than chronicling a day’s moments, in other words, Dorothy disrupts the
                boundaries between discrete events and observations; her regular omission of the
                pronouns “I” and “we” also thwarts any attempt to classify her walks as definitively
                solitary or resolutely companionate. Because Dorothy Wordsworth often nests the word
                “walk” within descriptions of broccoli planted, laundry hung, beggars met, poems
                transcribed, and books read, it is difficult to mark when a walk begins and when it
                ends. The journals thus ask us to imagine how walks might linger in Dorothy
                Wordsworth’s rarely noted body, how one might write while walking, while quiet,
                while talking, while at rest. In the context of this course, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grasmere and Alfoxden Journals </hi>thus suggest the tender ephemerality of
                writing and walking alike. The journals allow us to imagine the ways in which both
                writing and walking are situated within the rhythms of our days, and introduce the
                possibility that both essays and walks might continue in our individual and
                collective bodyminds beyond the times in which they take place. </p>
                
            <p> For all the restlessness I feel in response to this fledgling course, one particular
                class period allowed me to feel temporarily still, convinced that we were continuing
                to make something, together. The fourteen of us facilitated a public conversation on
                walking and writing as part of the Literature and Language Over Lunch series, part
                of the Hendrix-Murphy programs in Literature and Language. Students’ voices threaded
                through one another as they read selections from our course texts alongside excerpts
                from their walking journals, and described to a gathering of peers, staff, and
                faculty the questions we were pursuing as a group. This hour reminded me of a
                co-authored ephemeral essay, a living document made by our shared and separate time.
                When my students and I bring our bodies with us into the classroom, when we work and
                walk with and in and through our physical selves, we become differently vulnerable
                to one another, in new, strange, and often unlocatable relationship to British
                Romantic writing, to our own work as readers and writers, walkers and makers. The
                embodied reading practices we apply to our course texts alter us, make us
                imperceptibly new. The accidents, discomforts, and surprises of the walking
                classroom, framed by Romanticism’s own vital inquiry into the purposes and
                possibilities of walking, left both my students and me with a repertoire of
                questions about, and approaches to, the practices of reading, writing, and walking,
                and a renewed commitment to keep those questions in mind as we pursue our work.
                Perhaps it is the restless and continuous engagement with these questions that will
                continue to make of English 325 a place at once palpable and precarious, a location
                made by solitary walks and collaborative conversations, a nexus of bodyminds in a
                room and in the world beyond the room, reading together, writing alone, walking on. </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="citation">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
            
            <bibl>Brownstein, Rachel Mayer. “The Private Life: Dorothy Wordsworth’s Journals.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>34 (1973): 48-63.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Canguillhem, Georges. “La sante: concept vulgar et question philosophique.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Ecrits sur la médecine. </hi>Paris: Editions du Seuill,
                2002. <hi rend="italic">The Body: A Reader</hi>. Eds. Mariam Fraser and Monica
                Greco, New York: Routledge, 2005.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Community Contract for Hendrix College Students.<ref target="https://www.hendrix.edu/studentlife/handbook.aspx?id=80379">Student Life Handbook</ref>. Web. 1
                Jan. 2019. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Doty, Mark. <hi rend="italic">The Art of Description: World into Word.
                </hi>Minneapolis: Graywolf, 2010. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Grosz, Elizabeth. <hi rend="italic">Volatile Bodies</hi>. Bloomington: Indiana
                University Press, 1994. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Longenbach, James. <hi rend="italic">The Art of the Poetic Line. </hi>Minneapolis:
                Graywolf, 2007.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Merleau-Ponty, Maurice. <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology of Perception</hi>. Trans.
                Colin Smith. New York: Routledge Classics, 2002.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Newlyn, Lucy. “Dorothy Wordsworth’s Experimental Style.” <hi rend="italic">Essays in
                    Criticism. </hi>57:4 (2007): 325-348. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Solnit, Rebecca. <hi rend="italic">Wanderlust: A History of Walking. </hi>New York:
                Penguin, 2001. Print. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Wordsworth, Dorothy. <hi rend="italic">The Grasmere and Alfoxden Journals.
                </hi>1798-1802. Ed. Pamela Woof. New </bibl>
                
            <bibl> York: Oxford World’s Classics, 2002.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Zimmerman, Sarah M. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Lyricism, and History.
                </hi>Albany: State University of New York Press, 1999. </bibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
