<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Untitled Document</title>
                <author>Rebecca May</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2024-04-17T18:27:00</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>no publication statement available</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><name>Anna Wingfield</name><date>2024-04-17T18:27:00</date></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="center">“When the dreadful steel was plunged into the breast”: Teaching
                Romantic Surgeons, Anatomists, and Bodysnatchers to Students in Health Sciences</p>
            <p rend="center">Rebecca E. Maatta</p>
            <div type="div1" rend="P12">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Context, Demographics, and Structure</hi></head>
                <p>At Duquesne University, I regularly teach a 300-level writing-intensive
                    “Healthcare and Literature” class populated almost exclusively by sophomores and
                    juniors enrolled in a Doctorate in Physical Therapy (DPT) program, which awards
                    them a bachelor’s degree after 4 years and a doctorate after 6. My primary goal
                    is for these students to articulate practical, professional takeaways from
                    studying literary representations of illness and medical intervention. Thus, I
                    prioritize relevance, foregrounding it on the first day of class and throughout
                    the semester, frequently asking students, “What does this mean for you as future
                    physical therapists?” I let them know that I have worked to align the class’s
                    goals and their needs by considering their program’s outcomes. And I require
                    them to reflect on how experiences of illness and expectations for healthcare
                    professionals have changed over time. We extend our discussion into how
                    wellbeing coexists with illness on separate yet parallel tracks. We read a
                    narrative of illness, and we ask, “Despite how sick the patient was, what made
                    that patient’s experience terrible? What made that patient’s experience
                    uplifting? How did the healthcare provider affect that experience? How can the
                    healthcare provider manage their own wellbeing to subsequently increase patient
                    wellbeing?” These things are interconnected. </p>
                <p>My “Healthcare and Literature” class is part of a trend in higher education:
                    students majoring in health sciences are increasingly offered liberal arts
                    courses designed to address humanistic issues that arise in their fields. Though
                    at times the gap between literary studies and my students’ study of physical
                    therapy has yawned wide, outcomes for the physical therapy program dovetail with
                    literary and cultural studies’ investments in social justice, intersectionality,
                    and careful reading. Indeed, this overlap is a hallmark of the medical
                    humanities, which uses an interdisciplinary framework to bridge that imagined
                    gap between medicine and literature. When we take a medical humanities approach,
                    we draw from literature and art as well the social sciences to critically
                    examine representations of medical education and medical practices. The
                    college’s vision for the physical therapy program is outlined in their
                    “Strategic Statements” document, which harmonizes with studies in the medical
                    humanities by asking students to be “compassionate, culturally competent, and
                    socially responsible reflective practitioners,” and “critical thinkers,
                    life-long learners, healthcare educators … critical consumers of pertinent
                    literature, and leaders in the profession” (“Strategic Statements”). In
                    addition, the program’s learning outcomes emphasize “practic[ing] … in a
                    competent, safe, ethical … reflective and professional manner,” “perform[ing]
                    effective patient examination [and] evaluation,” “provid[ing] healthcare
                    education to patients, clients, families, peers, and society, using culturally
                    appropriate teaching methods,” and “demonstrate[ing] social responsibility and
                    altruism” (“Outcomes”). </p>
                <p>Clearly, the program stresses empathy and reflection. It also links textual
                    literacy to interpersonal literacy. Professional acumen flows from the ability
                    to interpret patients’ individual needs. Students are expected to understand
                    that patients<hi rend="italic">and </hi>practitioners are influenced by
                    socio-cultural contexts and power-privilege dynamics; there is additionally an
                    investment in holistic patient-centered care. My pedagogy, drawn from the
                    medical humanities and narrative medicine, facilitates developing
                    professional-personal critical reflection, altruism, interpersonal communication
                    skills, and an awareness of the factors that affect hearing, telling, and
                    developing care plans. Under the umbrella of the medical humanities, narrative
                    medicine draws attention to the narratives that patients and practitioners
                    construct. It also teaches students to interpret those narratives by thinking
                    about things like word choice, mind-body relations, point of view, power, and
                    context. I emphasize that skills in textual analysis are a personal-professional
                    asset that will help students to hear patients and, by meeting them where they
                    are, ensure that they are administering effective care.</p>
                <p>In “Healthcare and Literature,” the classroom becomes a space of conceptualizing
                    wellbeing. Our medical humanities approach invites students to imagine
                    themselves as future practitioners, but more importantly, it requires students
                    to consider the relevance of their emotions in the present. We confront
                    difficult scenarios together as a class. We discuss and process those feelings
                    to create emotional resilience, a <hi rend="italic">preparedness</hi> that
                    equips them to lean into hard emotions now, which may prevent burnout later. The
                    class—capped at 18—is discussion driven and thematically organized, and
                    transhistorical. Focusing on North American and Western European medicine and
                    culture, students complete reading, in-class writing, and process-writing with
                    individual guidance.<note xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1"> Process writing
                        involves assisting students with planning, drafting, and revising. I
                        dedicate class time to each stage of the process, including workshopping
                        student drafts. During workshop we discuss how the student might revise
                        their paper to meet the assignment’s guidelines. It also allows me to
                        demonstrate to them what an “A” thesis looks like, for example. </note> I
                    explain to students that our discussions will facilitate their awareness of
                    humanistic issues in medical contexts past and present; improve literary
                    analysis and close reading skills across genres; enable them to articulate their
                    professional goals and values; and finally, set them up to write informal and
                    formal essays. </p>
                <p>Although I teach texts from many historical periods, there is good reason in
                    “Healthcare and Literature” to discuss Romantic texts as a foundation and
                    starting point because the Romantic era is an especially rich moment in medical
                    history. At the time, for example, surgery suffered from low status as manual
                    craft (i.e., the “sawbones”) compared to the more “cerebral” work of physicians.
                    Pairing Romantic texts with contemporary ones also shows how medical attitudes
                    change across time. Clusters of texts allow us to study how anatomy has been
                    taught and learned; shifting attitudes towards mental illness and disability;
                    different conceptualizationsof pain and attitudes towards pain management; and
                    individual articulations of how treatment can traumatize patients. In this vein,
                    our texts include long and short fiction and medical texts, poetry and visual
                    art. We end the semester with contemporary nonfiction written by medical
                    professionals and a visit to the campus cadaver lab where students will perform
                    a dissection during their fourth year.</p>
                <p>Romantic texts that address medical topics are diverse, but I have found two
                    texts especially useful for helping my students develop compassion and cultural
                    awareness: Frances Burney’s journal letter, “Account from Paris of a Terrible
                    Operation – 1812,” and an anonymous 1831 short story “The Victim” from <hi
                        rend="italic">The New Monthly Magazine, </hi>in which a medical student
                    finds his friend’s fiancée on his dissection table. These works enable us to
                    discuss aspects of healthcare that many students typically take for granted:
                    that surgeons embody the pinnacle of expertise and manual dexterity, and that
                    dissection and human anatomy are foundations for medical knowledge. As we engage
                    both of these texts, historical distance allows students to safely express shock
                    or anger and to openly criticize the practitioners as well as the “barbarism” of
                    medicine. Students begin to probe their assumptions about professionalism,
                    patients’ rights, and even the construction of the body in medical study. </p>
                <p>As I will demonstrate, when taught using principles of narrative medicine,
                    including the concepts of logotherapy and pathography, Burney’s letter and “The
                    Victim” provide an opportunity to connect literary study to the physical therapy
                    program’s goals. The texts present relatable healthcare situations, such as
                    receiving a cancer diagnosis or studying for an anatomy exam, with a striking
                    strangeness that engages students’ emotional and intellectual interest.
                    Ultimately, the texts often lead students to not only question the history of
                    the medical professions, but also to assess their own personal and professional
                    values and learn how to use emotions to facilitate care. As is characteristic of
                    Romantic texts, Burney’s letter and “The Victim” stage and elicit powerful
                    sentiment. The sexualized cadaver in “The Victim” disgusts students and opens a
                    conversation about clinical distance as the story’s own medical students fail to
                    balance clinical distance with empathy. Burney’s letter invites students to
                    explain how they might communicate with their own patients differently from
                    Burney’s surgical team in order to better support patient quality of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P12">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Narrative Medicine, Logotherapy, and Pathography</hi></head>
                <p>Narrative medicine emphasizes the transportability of close reading skills and
                    the importance of language to the medical practitioner (Charon et al, “Close
                    Reading” np). Narrative medicine also considers forms and effects through two
                    concepts, pathography and logotherapy, which are a key focus of my “Healthcare
                    and Literature” course.<note xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="2"> Anne Hunsaker
                        Hawkins coined the term “pathography” in <hi rend="italic">Reconstructing
                            Illness: Studies in Pathography. </hi>Purdue UP, 1993. </note>
                    Pathographies, or patient-produced narratives, provide audiences with the deeply
                    subjective “extra-clinical” details of illness that resonate poignantly and
                    build empathetic connections. As a philosophy, logotherapy affirms that
                    narratives have the power to validate experiences of illness and can promote
                    recovery.</p>
                <p>Narrative medicine uses literary texts to increase provider effectiveness by
                    fostering skills in listening, critical thinking, and interpretation. Together,
                    these skills are known as “narrative competence, that is, the competence that
                    human beings use to absorb, interpret, and respond to stories … it enables the
                    physician to practice medicine with empathy, reflection, professionalism, and
                        trustworthiness”<hi rend="bold"> </hi>(Charon, “Narrative Medicine” 1897).
                    Working with diverse kinds of texts ultimately equips the practitioner to avoid
                    any one-size-fits-all assumptions, because “[e]valuating patients requires the
                    skills that are exercised by the careful reader” (Charon et al ,“Literature and
                    Medicine” 601). Much like literary scholars, the healthcare provider listens,
                    collates, and interprets metaphors, point of view, and repetition. Narrative
                    medicine fundamentally values patients’ stories, whether filled with
                    overwhelming detail or loaded with meaningful silences, and views each story as
                    much more than an index of symptoms. Narrative competence ensures that the
                    practitioner meets the patient where they are (Charon, “Narrative Medicine”
                    1898). Patients can feel compelled to narrate their histories into coherence
                    (Torney 37), and they know when they are being heard. </p>
                <p>Broadly speaking, writing about traumatic illness or treatment can promote
                    wellbeing. Trauma-focused therapy frequently requires patients to write, read,
                    and re-read narratives of their trauma because repeated exposures decrease
                    episodes of physiological distress (Gurak et al). Pathographies prioritize the
                    patient’s point of view within their socio-cultural moment: “in the full, rich,
                    nuanced particularity seldom if ever available elsewhere, literary accounts of
                    illness widen physician-readers’ knowledge of the concrete realities of being
                    sick and enable these readers to appreciate their own patients’ stories of
                    sickness” (Charon et al, “Literature and Medicine” 600). Pathographies tap into
                    readers’ emotions. Healthcare providers who believe that clinical detachment
                    keeps them unbiased while emotions distract from caregiving can benefit from
                    using pathography to discuss how emotions can be appropriately leveraged into
                    caregiving. </p>
                <p>Clinical detachment, though at times necessary, can become dangerous when
                    practitioners are burned out. Yet suffering and illness cannot be ignored, nor
                    can narratives in which medical professionals fail to practice effective care.
                    Narrative medicine offers safeguards against the exhaustion deadly to careful
                    interactions, and against the weariness born of bearing constant witness to
                    suffering. The design of my “Healthcare and Literature” course follows a logical
                    chain. Students read pathographies to encounter difficult patient experiences.
                    Discussing these pathographies together as a class, we share our own strong
                    emotions. In sharing these emotions, the emotions are in turn validated. Through
                    such discussions, students can therefore begin to see emotions as a meaningful
                    guide to patient care and to self care. When students can trust their emotions
                    in this way, their wellbeing is preserved. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P12">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Burney’s Mastectomy Letter</hi></head>
                <p> I use Burney’s letter early in the semester to foreground the value of
                    transhistorical analysis and reading medicine “across history.” Students usually
                    expect that surgeons will explain to patients what kind of operation they need
                    and what will be done to them. It is difficult for students to imagine surgeons
                    lying – deliberately or through omission – because they believe that patients
                    are entitled to transparency. However, by reading Burney’s letter they realize
                    that their assumptions about surgical professionalism are historically
                    constructed. Ultimately, I want students to consider how and why Burney’s
                    surgeons fail to communicate honestly with her and what kinds of emotions drive
                    their interactions. Before reading Burney’s letter, I have students watch “Being
                    Mortal” (2015), an episode of<hi rend="italic">Frontline</hi> in which Atul
                    Gawande addresses how difficult it is for oncologists to discuss end-of-life
                    priorities with terminal patients, often because they fear hurting a patient’s
                    feelings or being perceived as a failure. After discussing Gawande, the class
                    reads Burney’s letter to study the ways in which Burney’s surgical team
                    compounds her suffering by avoiding hard conversations. Finally, we read Mary
                    Roberts Reinhart’s 1947 interview with Greta Palmer for <hi rend="italic">Ladies
                        Home Journal</hi>, “I Had Cancer,” about her experience with breast cancer.
                    We discuss these three texts over three class periods. I offer framing questions
                    or comments, but most of my time is spent reading passages aloud, moderating
                    discussion, and synthesizing students’ comments. They then submit a two-page
                    reflection in which they may respond to a single text or the triad overall. </p>
                <p>The thematic focus on cancer allows us to confront a troubling topic head-on
                    while also inviting us to consider what kinds of things are said about cancer at
                    different moments in history. What kinds of assumptions surround the symptoms,
                    diagnosis, and treatment plan? What must be communicated? What is at stake? Many
                    of these questions lead us to close examinations of language: the words used to
                    describe disease reflect social attitudes towards that disease. After watching
                    “Being Mortal,” we typically discuss the belief that patients need their doctors
                    to communicate openly, even if doctors are worried about arousing strong
                    emotions or coming across as failures. Only when doctors manage their own
                    negative emotions can they venture into conversations that, though painful, can
                    spare a patient long-term suffering.</p>
                <p>While students have not yet read secondary materials on logotherapy or
                    pathography, I introduce these terms to them during our discussion on Burney’s
                    writing. Given the letter’s vivid and sometimes gruesome details, it is perfect
                    for linking emotions to wellbeing via logotherapy. In addition, Burney’s
                    literary skill infuses her pathography, enabling students to emotionally connect
                    with her. I begin class by asking students how they felt about the reading: Was
                    the letter hard to understand? What feelings didthey have about Burney’s
                    experience? They usually confess that they had difficulty sustaining attention
                    up to the surgery. Student recall of the surgery is very high because of the
                    feelings it elicits, while the “build up” takes more work to unpack. I lean into
                    their discomfort with the earlier part of the text by having students recount
                    Burney’s experience before the surgery. What results is a discussion about the
                    meandering process of illness and treatment, and what students expect doctors
                    will do when a patient needs help. </p>
                <p>Students react especially strongly to the way that Burney’s surgical team treats
                    her, and they empathize with her. We linger over passages where Burney describes
                    her shock and terror. When I ask why Burney feels so terrified, students blame
                    the surgeons. The students believe that Burney’s doctors prioritize their own
                    fears and concerns over her wellbeing, and also that Burney’s male doctors treat
                    her with a destructive delicacy because she is a woman. Moreover, they perceive
                    the surgeons as inappropriately emoting. In their eyes, medical professionals
                    should inspire confidence in their patients instead of expressing fear and
                    anxiety. When Burney is told that a surgery is unavoidable, Dr. Larrey has tears
                    in his eyes: “All were silent, and Dr. Larrey, I saw, hid himself nearly behind
                    my Sofa… I saw all hope was over. I called upon them to speak. M. Dubois then,
                    after a long and unintelligible harangue, from his own disturbance, pronounced
                    my doom” (435-436). Students interpret Larrey’s hiding as childish, and Dubois’s
                    “long and unintelligible harangue” as an inadequate effort to communicate
                    clearly. In this respect, students see Burney’s doctors as incompetent because
                    they cannot balance appropriate empathy with confidence. The surgeons’ poor
                    communication compounds Burney’s helplessness and disempowerment. </p>
                <p>The disempowerment escalates as Burney must fully submit to the surgeons. While
                    Burney does not mention embarrassment at baring her breast to a male doctor, she
                    comes close to expressing humiliation: “I was compelled, however, to submit to
                    taking off my long robe de Chambre, which I had meant to retain – ah, then, how
                    did I think of My Sisters! – not one, at so dreadful an instant, at hand, to
                    protect – adjust—guard me” (440). Students interpret this passage as a
                    commentary on gender. Burney realizes that only a woman could understand what
                    she feels, yet her surgery is spearheaded by men who have demonstrated little
                    interest in her wellbeing. A particularly poignant endorsement once came from a
                    student who had experienced breast biopsy. She said that Burney’s account
                    collapsed historical distance and made a Romantic text accessible. She knew the
                    rawness. She knew the pull of modesty during disrobing and the helplessness in
                    relinquishing it. She felt affirmed in her connection to Burney. It was like a
                    shared triumph. This is an example of how the upsetting emotions elicited by
                    pathography can lead a student to an insight about caregiving. Burney’s
                    narrative allowed a student to think of herself as both patient and
                    practitioner. By powerfully empathizing with Burney she could ask herself what
                    responsibilities the surgeons abdicated andappreciate Burney’s fortitude.
                    Difficult emotions thus become a gateway to assessing patient care. </p>
                <p>Taken together, Burney’s letter and Gawande’s “Being Mortal” bring students to
                    recognize that communication issues have long plagued medical interactions and
                    that a fear of emotions is at the root of the problem. But while Gawande
                    emphasizes including patients in conversation, making sure they understand their
                    disease and asking about their goals and priorities, Burney’s doctors bowl her
                    over, and in the end they don’t protect her from any suffering. Patients expect
                    doctors to take the lead, but doctors may be unprepared for the emotional nature
                    of conversations about critical illnesses. What is the patient’s understanding
                    of their disease? What are their priorities? Gawande insists that medical
                    professionals should avoid instilling false hope. He advises allowing patients
                    to emote in whatever way they need to, since patient personalities differ. I ask
                    students, as future physical therapists, what kinds of difficult conversations
                    they may have to have with patients and how Gawande’s claims and Burney’s
                    experience help them to think about what they should take into consideration
                    when talking to patients. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P9">
                <head/>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P12">
                <head><hi rend="bold">“The Victim”</hi></head>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P9">
                <head/>
                <p>After discussing Burney and Gawande, I transition students into texts on anatomy
                    and surgical education during the Romantic period, focusing on Ruth Richardson’s
                    historical analysis of the 1832 Anatomy Act called <hi rend="italic">Death,
                        Dissection, and the Destitute</hi> and the short story “The Victim” (1831).
                    What were surgeons taught? How were they taught? Can we find in other texts
                    examples of emotions interfering with patient care? While Burney’s doctors
                    emoted in uncontrolled ways, Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">Death, Dissection
                        and the Destitute</hi> shows how clinical detachment, or emotionlessness,
                    could be taken to such an extreme that patients were treated as objects. She
                    argues that during the nineteenth century, the emotional distance that medical
                    professionals adopted in order to dissect human beings took on new stakes.<note
                        xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="3"> Britain’s 1832 Anatomy Act dictated that
                        “people too poor to pay for their own funerals” could be used for dissection
                        (Richardson 50). This abuse of the dependent poor showed how Romantic
                        surgeons’ clinical detachment could encourage a callous attitude towards
                        patients. </note>
                </p>
                <p>The dark fictional landscape of “The Victim” presents the dangers of clinical
                    detachment when medical study overshadows the main characters’ social awareness.
                    Dudley, the narrator, is a medical student. He and his roommate St. Clare order
                    a cadaver from a resurrectionist to study for an examination on the arteries of
                    the neck. Passing this exam has high stakes for St. Clare: once he receives his
                    certification, he will be able to marry his fiancée Emily and receive a
                    significant sum of money. Dudley receives the cadaver late one evening and
                    directs the resurrectionists to take it to the closet in his bedroom. Upon
                    unwrapping the body, he is astounded to see the most beautiful woman he’s ever
                    encountered. Rather than dissecting her, he kisses her, sketches her, and falls
                    asleep on her exposed “inanimate breast, which had been deprived too soon of
                    existence to know the pure joy of pillowing a fellow-heart it loved” (190). When
                    St. Clare arrives home, he is devastated to learn that the cadaver is Emily.
                    Time passes, St. Clare dies, and Dudley ends up treating a man who confesses to
                    the murder of Emily. The story’s somewhat heavy-handed moral comes with the
                    horrifying revelation that St. Clare’s love interest had been abducted and
                    murdered because resurrectionists found it more convenient than digging up a
                    dead body. Once Dudley realizes his complicity in the trafficking of the dead he
                    “renounc[es] the scalpel for ever” (193). </p>
                <p>Students invariably discuss the irreplaceable importance of hands-on dissection.
                    Students in the DPT program have the privilege of completing a yearlong cadaver
                    lab on campus during their undergraduate curriculum. They know that dissection
                    is a vital privilege. Some anticipate it with anxiety, while others look forward
                    to it for years, but most have not thought about it critically. “The Victim”
                    provides us with an opportunity to talk about students’ emotional experiences by
                    using the characters in the story as our case study. </p>
                <p>Before we begin discussing the story, we analyze images from John Bell’s and
                    Govard Bidloo’s Romantic-era anatomical atlases so that they can get a sense of
                    what anatomical study looked like before the historical development of the
                    clinical gaze. I ask them what they could learn from these images and what their
                    reactions are. They find them frightening and compelling, but not scientific.
                    When I show them these images, they even more deeply understand why Dudley and
                    St. Clare feel the <hi rend="italic">need </hi>to dissect to prepare.
                    Illustrations from John Bell’s 1810 <hi rend="italic">Engravings of the Bones,
                        Muscles, and Joints</hi>, for example, do not meet their criteria for a
                    didactic anatomy textbook. They marvel that students learned anything at all
                    when textbooks were so encumbered with emotional valences and chaotic
                        excesses.<note xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="4"> Janis McLarren Caldwell’s
                        essay “The Strange Death of the Animated Cadaver” could be taught in tandem
                        with J. Bell and “The Victim.” To extend discussion into the Victorian
                        period, Ruth Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">The Making of Mr. Gray’s
                            Anatomy</hi> provides an outstanding analysis of what made Gray <hi
                            rend="italic">the </hi>game-changer in anatomical textbook illustration
                        and design.</note> Through these images my students also speculate on how
                    anatomists felt when dissecting and sketching their cadavers. John Bell’s images
                    especially communicate a horror and sadness that students believe has no place
                    in the dissecting room, even if they anticipate feeling fear or sadness when it
                    is their turn in the lab. Even Dudley calls dissection a “necessary, but
                    revolting, part of the profession” (189). Most importantly, “The Victim” gives a
                    sexual torque to dissection’s insult. The sight of Emily’s cadaver stirs up
                    erotic feelings in Dudley. He feels dissection will dishonor her, but he cannot
                    resist her beauty. He experiences a warping of his ethical and erotic drives: </p>
                <p>never till that instant had I seen aught that came so near to my most ideal
                    picture of female loveliness; even though the last touches had been painted by
                    the hand of Death … I had almost brought myself to meet with indifference the
                    objects which are found on the dissecting table, [but] I could not gaze on one
                    so young, so very fair, without feeling the springs of pity dissolve within me.
                    (189) </p>
                <p>Dudley is stirred away from clinical distance toward more altruistic thinking.
                    But his activated emotions lead him to a series of activities that starkly
                    emphasizes his masculinity, agency, and dominance in contrast to her feminine
                    and unresisting vulnerability. Receiving Emily’s body, unwrapping it, examining
                    it, opening her eye, kissing her, sketching her, cutting off her hair, then
                    finally dissecting her: these acts show Emily’s sexual undoing as a drawn-out
                    process culminating in dissection. </p>
                <p>While students do not interpret this as a rape scene, I read out loud Dudley’s
                    description of Emily’s body and his behaviors to push them to see the eroticized
                    power dynamics at play in “The Victim.” I also show them anatomist Robert Knox’s
                    1828 nude sketch of Mary Paterson’s cadaver.<note xml:id="ftn6" place="foot"
                        n="5"><p> Richardson details Knox’s treatment of Paterson’s body: “men had
                            come to draw her body, comments had been made upon her physical
                            attributes and Knox had even had her body preserved in spirits so that
                            he could continue to indulge in necrophiliac voyeurism” (96).</p></note>
                    This allows them to imagine that Dudley’s sketch of Emily may have looked to
                    them more like an eroticized image of a nude, consenting, living woman than like
                    a dead body. I also remind them that in the early nineteenth century, anatomists
                    were viewed with disgust and distrust because they meddled in guts, and their
                    affiliation with surgeons linked them to manual craft and butchery—not
                    intellect. Excess of clinical distance, thinking of humans as inert material,
                    facilitates the cavalier ordering and receiving of Emily’s remains. The ensuing
                    objectification enables Dudley’s Robert Knox-esque abuse, even as it is masked
                    as a misdirection of socially appropriate chivalrous emotion. We take time to
                    identify the thoughts Dudley has, the emotions he feels, and the behaviors that
                    follow from these.</p>
                <p> While students cannot imagine admiring the beauty of a cadaver, they<hi
                        rend="italic">can</hi> imagine feeling exhilarated to see anatomical
                    structures. They can also imagine being unable to “turn off” their feelings to
                    achieve the clinical distance they need to dissect. None of them, I certainly
                    hope, are at risk of sexualizing their cadavers, but I ask them what kinds of
                    behaviors might be similar to Dudley’s behavior, such as making a joke about a
                    cadaver’s appearance or taking photos. Most students share that they are afraid
                    of what they will think and feel in the lab. They believe that to be studious,
                    they must be <hi rend="italic">somber</hi>. This is where we really hit on
                    appropriate emotions and coping. They can feel sad, frightened, excited,
                    nervous, and even silly. But there are ways to experience all of these feelings,
                    to accept them, and to use them as guides to engage their learning. If they are
                    sad, they can talk about it. If they are excited, they can express it. If they
                    are afraid, that’s okay, too. As narrative medicine can teach us, registering
                    and exploring these emotions can make my students more compassionate and more
                    effective medical professionals. I often share my own thoughts and feelings
                    about the cadaver lab and how I have coped.</p>
                <p>We come back to the dissecting experience twice more in the last three weeks of
                    class. First, we read Pauline Chen’s 2012 work of creative nonfiction,
                    “Resurrectionist,” in which Chen describes her first dissection as a med
                    student. The essay allows us to discuss what a current-day student thinks,
                    feels, and experiences before, during, and after dissecting. I again ask
                    students how they feel about their upcoming dissection – are they anxious,
                    excited, worried? This discussion is usually animated, and it’s clear that
                    students are relieved to hear their peers’ concerns. Then, I collaborate with
                    the Anatomy I lab professor who meets us in the cadaver lab where students will
                    eventually be doing their dissections. My students have the opportunity to meet
                    students who are currently dissecting. We give students time to experience their
                    sensations and talk about their feelings first. Then, we open the body bags and
                    let the students talk through their thoughts and feelings. Anatomy I students
                    share what they thought and felt about dissecting, and how they coped. They show
                    my students their cadavers and dissections. This has been an enormously fruitful
                    collaboration. The Anatomy I professor knew that his students at times had
                    struggled emotionally, and we both anticipate that the collaboration will equip
                    future anatomy students with more resources for addressing these struggles. My
                    students report great appreciation for the experience in written reflections, in
                    the class discussion following the lab, and in their course evaluations. They
                    feel that when it will be their turn to dissect, they will be able to fully
                    engage intellectually instead of worrying about getting sick or crying.
                    Organizing this collaboration has required emotional labor on my part, but
                    supporting students during a difficult confrontation with a cadaver has afforded
                    me another opportunity to validate their difficult emotions. It also has allowed
                    me to show students how we can work through sadness or fear. For example, one
                    semester I sat in the hallway with a sobbing student. I listened to her, and we
                    developed a plan to walk into the lab together. She asked me to walk ahead of
                    her, to keep up a steady stream of chatter, and to lead her to a table where a
                    few of her friends were. Students know that they need to work through the
                    discomfort of seeing cadavers but have few guided opportunities to do so.
                    Visiting the cadaver lab has also given me a chance to really communicate to
                    students that I care about their wellbeing, and I am able to welcome and
                    withstand their feelings. I am, in other words, modeling how I accept emotions
                    as part of my profession. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P12">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Student Reactions</hi></head>
                <p>The medical worlds of literary texts like Burney’s letter and “The Victim” are
                    unimaginable to students pursuing degrees in health science—a world in which a
                    mastectomy is performed on an inadequately informed, fully conscious woman by a
                    clutch of terrified and silent surgeons, and a world in which anatomy students
                    become sexual predators complicit in murder. My students’ world is one in which
                    cancer is openly discussed, where cadaver lab is part of their undergraduate
                    curriculum, and where surgeons are stereotypically the apotheosis of efficient
                    protocol. My students are not ready for the butchery, for the emotionally labile
                    surgical team, for the woman who holds her own breast on a pile of old
                    mattresses. Nor are they ready for the student falling weeping onto and kissing
                    his study-cadaver in his bedroom the night before an exam. The strength of these
                    texts, then, is their medical uncanniness. They are familiar enough to
                    comprehend and alien enough to shock students into engaged reflection. They
                    bring to the surface students’ assumptions about appropriate study and care and
                    thus embed them more mindfully in the present. Burney’s letter and “The Victim”
                    invite conversations about clinical detachment as both necessary to practice
                    surgery and dissection and also something that can be taken to a dangerous
                    extreme. By reading these nineteenth-century texts, students come to the
                    conclusion that empathy cannot be sacrificed in medical care. Even though
                    medical professionals face complicated emotional challenges that can make
                    effective care difficult, the patient’s experience must always be weighed and
                    appreciated. Narrative medicine makes it clear that this leads to better
                    outcomes for patients and can prevent other negative effects for medical
                    professionals.</p>
                <p>My “Healthcare and Literature” students connect to the texts in three significant
                    ways: as learners with professional aspirations, as erstwhile and future
                    patients, and as individuals who want to change lives. Official Student
                    Evaluation Surveys have confirmed that students find the texts relevant to their
                    future professions. They appreciate being introduced to communication
                    challenges, and they can express the importance of language when working with
                    patients. Students have stated that they appreciate discussing difficult medical
                    scenarios. They know that they will have hard conversations when they ask a
                    patient why they aren’t completing their prescribed exercises or when they
                    resist instilling false hope in a postoperative athlete who will likely not
                    comfortably play their sport again. Part of my joy in working with future
                    physical therapists is their belief in recovery and triumph. They are optimistic
                    and excited to help future patients. My ancillary joy is mediating their
                    journey, even if in a small way, to becoming comfortable with situations where
                    they may feel powerless, overwhelmed, angry, or frustrated—and being able to
                    persist in the midst of those feelings. By normalizing difficult conversations,
                    they can, I hope, take comfort, feel prepared, and know they are not alone. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="div1" rend="P11">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <p>Anonymous. “The Victim.” (1831) <hi rend="italic">Gothic Evolutions: Poetry,
                        Tales, Context, Theory</hi>. Ed. Corinna Wagner. Peterborough, Ontario:
                    Broadview, 2014. 186-193. </p>
                <p>Bell, John. <hi rend="italic">Engraving of the Bones, Muscles, and Joints,
                        Illustrating the first volume of the anatomy of the human body. </hi>3<hi
                        rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. London: Longman, Hurst, Reese, and Orme, 1810. <hi
                        rend="italic">HathiTrust. </hi>Accessed 28 July 2011.</p>
                <p>Burney, Frances. <hi rend="italic">Journals and Letters.</hi> Introduction by
                    Peter Sabor and Lars E. Troide. New York: Penguin, 2001. </p>
                <p>Caldwell, Janis McLarren. “The Strange Death of the Animated Cadaver: Changing
                    Conventions in Nineteenth-Century British Anatomical Illustration.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Literature and Medicine</hi> 25.2 (2006): 325-357. <hi
                        rend="italic">Project Muse</hi>. Accessed 30 November 2016.</p>
                <p>Charon, Rita. “Narrative Medicine: A Model for Empathy, Reflection, Profession,
                    and Trust.”<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Medical Association</hi> 286.15
                    (2001): 1897-1902. Web. 30 August 2016.</p>
                <p>Charon, Rita, Joanne Trautmann Banks, Julia E. Connelly, Anne Hunsaker Hawkins,
                    Kathryn Montgomery Hunter, Anne Hudson Jones, Martha Montello, Suzanne Poirer.
                    “Literature and Medicine: Contributions to Clinical Practice.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annals of Internal Medicine </hi>122 (1995): 599-606.</p>
                <p>Charon, Rita, Nellie Hermann, and Michael J. Devlin. “Close Reading and Creative
                    Writing in Clinical Education: Teaching Attention, Representation, and
                    Affiliation.” <hi rend="italic">Academic Medicine </hi>91.3 (2016): 345-350. <hi
                        rend="italic">Ovid</hi>. Web. 1 September 2016. </p>
                <p>Epstein, Julia L. “Writing the Unspeakable: Fanny Burney’s Mastectomy and the
                    Fictive Body.” <hi rend="italic">Representations </hi>16 (1986): 131-166. <hi
                        rend="italic">JSTOR. </hi>Accessed 1December 2016.</p>
                <p>Gurak, Kayla K., Blanche Freund, and Gail Ironson. “The Use of Both Prolonged
                    Exposure and Cognitive Processing Therapy in the Treatment of a Person With
                    PTSD, Multiple Traumas, Depression, and Suicidality.” <hi rend="italic">Clinical
                        Case Studies</hi> 15.4 (2016): 295-312. <hi rend="italic">SAGE</hi>.
                    Accessed 29 November 2016.</p>
                <p>“Outcomes.” <hi rend="italic">Physical Therapy</hi>. John G. Rangos, Sr. School
                    of Health Sciences. Duquesne U. </p>
                <p>duq.edu/academics/schools/health-sciences/academic-programs/physical-therapy/outcomes.
                    Accessed 29 November 2016.</p>
                <p>Richardson, Ruth. <hi rend="italic">Death, Dissection, and the Destitute</hi>.
                        2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. U Chicago P, 2000.</p>
                <p>---. <hi rend="italic">The Making of Mr. Gray’s Anatomy. </hi>Oxford UP,
                    2008.</p>
                <p>Roach, Joseph and Shelby Richardson. “Writing the Breast, Performing the Trace:
                    Madame d’Arblay’s Radical Prosthesis.” <hi rend="italic">Acting on the Past:
                        Historical Performances Across Disciplines</hi>. Ed. Mark Franko and Annette
                    Richards. Wesleyan UP, 2000. 52-66.</p>
                <p>Souter, Kay Torney. “Narrating the Body: Disease as Interpersonal Event.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Health and History</hi> 1.1 (1998): 35-42. <hi rend="italic"
                        >JSTOR</hi>. Accessed 29 November 2016.<hi rend="color(#1a1a1a)"> </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="color(#1a1a1a)">“Strategic Statements.” </hi><hi
                        rend="color(#1a1a1a)italic">Physical Therapy. </hi><hi rend="color(#1a1a1a)"
                        >John G. Rangos, Sr. School of Health Sciences. Duquesne U.
                        duq.edu/academics/schools/health-sciences/academic-programs/physical-therapy/strategic-statements.
                        Accessed 29 November 2016.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
