<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Romanticism Behind Bars: An Inside-Out Poetry Workshop</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Elizabeth Effinger</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-04-17</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.wellbeing.effinger</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">wellbeing</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Romanticism Behind Bars: An Inside-Out Poetry Workshop
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                                <surname>Effinger</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.effinger"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism Behind Bars: An Inside-Out Poetry Workshop</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-04-10">April 17, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>04.17.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Romanticism Behind Bars: An Inside-Out Poetry Workshop
                    <note place="foot" resp="author"> Thanks to Simone Davis, Randell Duguid,Shoshana Pollack, Peter Stuart, the
                        Walls to Bridges Collective, the incarcerated women of GVI who participated
                        in the workshop, and my students of English 3444E. Thanks to Teresa Hubel
                        and the English Department at Huron University, Catharine Dishke Hondzel and
                        the RBC Foundation and the Willie May &amp; William H. Lumpkin
                        Community-Based Learning Grant for financial support that made this workshop
                        possible.</note></head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Elizabeth Effinger</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of New Brunswick</affiliation>
                </byline>
          
            <quote>“The pedagogy of community-based learning, when done with great care and integrity,
                has the power to turn things inside-out and upside-down for those engaged in it. It
                provokes one to think differently about the world, and consider one’s relationship
                to the world in a new way” — Lori Pompa, “Drawing Forth,” 24</quote>
                
            <quote>“The ability to read critically the messages that society, politics, and culture
                bombards us with is, more than ever, needed training in a society in which the
                manipulation of minds and hearts is increasingly what running the world is all
                about” — Peter Brooks, <hi rend="italic">The Humanities and Public Life</hi>, 2</quote>
                
            <p>For years, I have walked my dog along a winding, picturesque trail that hugs a quiet
                section of the Grand River in Kitchener, Ontario (Canada). Along this trail two
                institutions enter into view: the city’s wastewater treatment facility, and Canada’s
                newest and largest federal women’s prison, the Grand Valley Institution for Women
                (GVI). While Canadians might remember this prison as the place that housed convicted
                serial killer Karla Holmolka, the GVI has been increasingly garnering attention for
                its internal troubles, such as the case of Ashley Smith, an inmate who in 2007 took
                her own life while under watch of multiple correctional officers — a story that
                received national media coverage — and the 2016 death of Terry Baker, another
                incarcerated woman at the GVI.</p>
                
            <p>On these walks, I have often thought about Foucault’s remarks on heterotopic spaces,
                for surely it is symbolic that the site selected for the new prison was near the
                waste facility.<note place="foot" resp="author"> On the
                        concept of “heterotopia” see Michel Foucault, “Of Other Spaces,”<hi
                            rend="italic">Diacritics</hi> 16 (Spring 1986): 22-27.</note> But
                it was on one particular summer stroll, while I was thinking about Romantic poetry,
                that I found myself wondering about the other insidious proximities that marked our
                spaces. Standing on the trail, looking at the prison that was jarringly framed
                through both the green canopy of the forest and the dull grey barbed wire and
                chain-link fence, what came into focus was the uneasy silence in which these two
                radically different spaces co-existed. Questions pressed me: Where were the
                continuities between our spaces? In what ways were we all — perhaps with the
                exception of my dog, now splashing about in the river — suffering from what Blake
                famously called our “mind-forg’d manacles” (Erdman 27)? Could the incarcerated women
                see the woods? What did nature mean to them? What place, if any, did nature have in
                prison? Did they look at the woods or perhaps even the walking trail as Coleridge
                might have in “This Lime-Tree Bower My Prison”? What place, if any, did poetry have
                in their lives while in prison? These questions stuck with me. That moment became
                the germ behind a community-based experiential learning assignment that I developed
                for an undergraduate Nineteenth-Century British Literature course, a year-long,
                third-year survey class for English majors. In what follows, I describe the
                planning, development, and execution of the assignment before turning to a
                consideration of how community-based learning (CBL) initiatives, such as this one,
                activate the potential of three growing, but currently separate, sympathetic
                discourses within Romantic scholarship: the public humanities, the discourse of
                care, and the prison narrative.<note place="foot" resp="author"> On discourses of care, see Sara Guyer,<hi rend="italic">Romanticism
                            After Auschwitz </hi>(2007), and Brittany Pladek, “‘Soothing Thoughts’:
                        Romantic Palliative Care and the Poetics of Relief,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >European Romantic Review </hi>23.3 (2012): 403-413. On Romantic
                        incarceration see, for example, John Bugg, <hi rend="italic">Five Long
                            Winters: The Trials of British Romanticism</hi> (2014); Judith Thompson,
                            <hi rend="italic">John Thelwall in the Wordsworth Circle: The Silenced
                            Partner </hi>(2012); and, extending into the longer nineteenth century,
                        Jason Haslam, <hi rend="italic">Fitting Sentences: Identity in Nineteenth
                            and Twentieth-Century Prison Narratives</hi> (2005). See my note 15 on
                        Romanticism and the public humanities.</note> As a pedagogy that
                connects the classroom and the community, while recognizing them as mutually
                informing bodies aimed at making a positive difference, CBL offers community
                partners access to a greater, engaged audience committed to social and community
                awareness and action, and offers students and scholars of Romanticism an expanded
                sense of how our field can make a positive difference in building communities when
                we turn our work inside out. </p>
                
            <p>In February 2016, I facilitated a one-day poetry workshop, held in a classroom at the
                GVI. Modelled, in part, on the Walls to Bridges program (W2B), a Canadian program
                rooted in the pedagogic principles of the U.S. Inside-Out Prison Exchange Program,
                the project involved bringing together incarcerated (or “inside”) students and
                thirteen university (“outside”) students from my Nineteenth-Century British
                Literature course at Huron University (London, Ontario) in order to create a brief
                but meaningful exchange between these different student bodies. In fact, one of the
                challenges in designing this activity was thinking about the outcomes for not only
                my own students, but the incarcerated students, too.</p>
                
            <p>I learned through my research and early discussions with the education director of
                the GVI and the staff of the Walls to Bridges program that this workshop would be
                meaningful for the inside students because education programming enhances prisoner
                wellbeing, including their mental health and personal growth (Davis <hi
                    rend="italic">et al</hi> 2013; Duguid and Pawson 1998; Lockwood <hi
                    rend="italic">et al </hi>2012; Sokoloff and Schenck-Fontaine 2017, Vacca 2004).
                Moreover, the benefits to their wellbeing extend beyond the prison walls, as
                exchanges between inside and outside students expose both groups to a multiplicity
                of perspectives and help challenge preconceptions. Through these thoughtful
                exchanges, the outside students may come to rethink their positions on crime and the
                prison-industrial complex. Education initiatives also contribute to the health of
                the prison system; it gains new learning opportunities for its inmates, who benefit
                from creative expression and collective scholarly discussion, which allows them to
                experience their voices as meaningfully engaged with non-incarcerated voices.
                Finally, in practical ways, educational activities may positively impact plans for
                release and reintegration, as participation demonstrates the inside students’
                ability to self-regulate, collaborate, and work both independently and with a
                diverse group of others. Participation in education programming, including workshops
                like this one, may thus support future job possibilities or entry into higher
                education programs (Tewksbury and Stengel 2006). With a clear sense, then, of how
                this workshop could contribute to the public good, we began.</p>
                
            <p>The outside students were mostly third- and fourth-year English majors in their early
                twenties. Few had ever participated in community-based learning projects, and none
                had ever visited a prison or jail or had conversations with incarcerated peoples. As
                in-class discussions prior to our workshop revealed, their understandings and
                expectations of prison were largely shaped by media representations, including
                popular tele-series like <hi rend="italic">Orange is the New Black</hi>. Conversely,
                the inside students were drawn from the medium- and maximum-security units of the
                prison and ranged in ages from early twenties to thirties. They had spent varying
                durations of time (some in months, others in years) in both provincial and federal
                prisons from across the country for sentences, including life-sentences, pertaining
                to drugs, violence, and murder. They had varying degrees of education among them;
                some were working on obtaining their high-school diploma, others were taking
                university courses either in-person through W2B or online through other
                institutions, and one woman already had an undergraduate degree with plans towards
                graduate-level work. Mostly, their experiences with university courses were rooted
                in the social sciences, unlike the literature-based background of the outside
                students. However, what might be the most pragmatic difference between these inside
                and outside participants was the (in)accessibility to the internet. While outside
                students readily make use of the internet – a quick trip to Google or Wikipedia – as
                a way to help decipher a text, no such an opportunity exists for incarcerated
                peoples in Canadian provincial and federal prisons. This meant that the close
                readings that the incarcerated women shared with the class during the workshop were
                entirely their own – a fact not lost on the outside students, many of whom admitted
                on the bus ride back to campus that they felt deeply humbled by the insightful
                observations and comments made by the inmates. More on that bus ride later.</p>
                
            <p>While the prison workshop itself was brief, preparations were months in the making
                and essential to its success. Photocopies of the poems to be discussed were shared
                with the inside students prior to the workshop. Both inside and outside students
                read, in advance, the same selection of Romantic poems that treat the prison as
                experience or metaphor. As I explained in some introductory remarks before we
                launched into a discussion of the texts, many Romantic writers were intensely
                concerned with questions of freedom, authority, social injustices, resistance and
                revolution. <hi rend="italic">Liberté, égalité, fraternité!</hi> While some writers
                themselves spent time behind bars or had brushes with the (in)justice system (cf.
                Thelwall, Blake, Helen Maria Williams, the Lambs, De Quincey, Shelley), others were
                drawn to the imaginative space of the prison as a way of exploring various states of
                confinement (cf. Godwin, Wollstonecraft, Byron, Coleridge).<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                    In the future,I imagine teaching an entire course on
                    Romantic imprisonment.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>While sitting in a circle (a formation designed to bring all students face-to-face
                with one another), we completed creative writing exercises, critically discussed the
                texts at hand, and shared our reflective responses to the work with one another. The
                very act of sharing responses with the group was intended to help mark the emergence
                of a reflective space, emphasizing the role that literature can play in the creation
                of community. A more detailed description of the assignment follows in the
                subsequent sections.</p>
                
            <p>In the planning-stage of the project, I consulted with both community and campus
                partners: the prison’s Education Director and the program coordinators from the
                Walls to Bridges Collective (W2BC), which is a think tank based in Wilfrid Laurier
                University’s Faculty of Social Work that since 2011 has offered university-based
                programming at the GVI.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Walls
                        to Bridges understands itself as creating “collaborative and innovative
                        learning communities within correctional settings.” For more information
                        visit their website:<ref target="http://wallstobridges.ca">Walls to Bridges</ref></note>
                Emailing with the W2BC was essential to first determine if there was interest among
                the incarcerated women for such a collaboration. I secured funding from the RBC
                Foundation and Willie May &amp; William H. Lumpkin Community-Based Learning Grant,
                which covered the cost of transportation to and from the prison and refreshments for
                the event. Teresa Hubel, then Chair of Huron University’s English Department,
                generously supplied workshop materials for the incarcerated students, which the
                women were able to keep. Finally, all workshop participants from the university were
                required to complete a background check a few months prior to the visit before being
                granted permission to participate. Like all visitors at the GVI, our class was
                subject to a security screening, much like in an airport. Photo IDs were scrutinized
                and hands were swabbed for drugs (a major security concern).</p>
                
            <p>While it was a mandatory assignment for the outside students, it was strictly
                voluntary for those on the inside. Many of the inside students had prior experience
                in a classroom setting with university students, while others simply had a general
                interest in poetry and creative writing. For the outside students, this assignment
                consisted of three parts: (1) attendance and participation at the GVI; (2)
                participation in a post-workshop discussion back at the university; and (3) a
                formal, written reflection on the workshop to submitted at the end of term, as part
                of the final exam. The final assignment sheet can be found below in “Appendix A.”
                This assignment was designed to be an opportunity to include CBL opportunities for
                students within the parameters of a traditional literature survey course. This was
                not a specialized course exploring the campus-community connection, nor was it
                focused on Romantic prison writings – although, of course, this projectwould be at
                home in such courses. Instead, my goal was to design a CBL-component in the
                traditional literature survey course, as a way of exploring how individual projects
                can make connections between the classroom and the community. After all, this is
                part of the challenge many instructors perceive in making course material relevant
                to students beyond the classroom and in other areas of their lives. </p>
                
            <p>In the prison classroom, students sat in a circle, in keeping with the circle
                pedagogy central to both Canada’s W2B program and the US Inside-Out program. Within
                the circle, each student is equal and has a shared responsibility in the life of the
                class, while the instructor serves as group facilitator and shares, like everyone
                else, in the learning process.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a more detailed rationale of the use of circle pedagogy in Inside-Out,
                        see Lori Pompa’s “Drawing Forth, Finding Voice, Making Change: Inside-Out
                        Learning as Transformative Pedagogy.”</note> However, outside the
                circle, my role in the outside classroom was more formal; I delivered a
                lecture-discussion on the history of incarceration and penal reform throughout the
                eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, and assigned selections from Foucault’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Discipline and Punish</hi>, Bentham’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Panopticon</hi>, and Elizabeth Fry’s <hi rend="italic">Observations in
                    Visiting, Superintendence and Government of Female Prisoners</hi>.<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Later in the course, we also read
                        Dickens’s<hi rend="italic">A Visit to Newgate</hi> and selections from
                    Wilde’s <hi rend="italic">De Profundis</hi>. </note> This helped establish a
                general movement away from prisons as disorderly places in the eighteenth century
                toward orderly and strictly regulated places by the mid-nineteenth century. Such
                knowledge would further enhance our visit to a twenty-first century prison. </p>
                
            <p>I also prepared my students by lecturing on the politics of incarceration and the
                role of prison-based educational programming in Canada. For the outside students,
                whose exposure to incarceration was virtually non-existent, it was important to
                stress that incarceration in Canada differs from that in the United States (where
                most of the media representations of prisons are based). In Canada, there is what
                Simone Weil Davis calls “the blistering and tragic scale of criminalization and
                overincarceration of Indigenous people,” a group which alone makes up 23% of
                Canada’s prison population, though in some provinces Indigenous peoples make up
                between 90-98% of the population in jails and prisons (Davis, “Beyond ‘Replication’”
                259-60). In Canadian federal prisons, educational programs are understood to
                “facilitate inmates’ reintegration by increasing educational skill levels through
                the provision of accredited programs.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                        Commissioner’s Directive<ref
                            target="http://www.csc-scc.gc.ca/acts-and-regulations/720-cd-eng.shtml#s2g">csc-scc.org</ref>
                        </note> While Adult Basic Education (grades 1 to 12) is Correctional
                Service Canada’s educational priority, additional education programs are available,
                including Additional Language Programs, Adapted Education Programs, and General
                Educational Development. Prisoners have access to post-secondary education programs,
                in most cases through paper-based correspondence with an accredited university,
                college or CEGEP, and normally pay the costs themselves, although the institution
                may cover some or all of the cost of education.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                     Canadian inmates do not pay the cost of postsecondary education if
                        there is a federal or provincial arrangement to provide these programs
                        within the institution, or if the Institutional Head of the prison finds
                        that these criteria are met: 1) the educational costs are within the budget
                        limits; 2) the inmate meets the criteria set out by the Ministry of
                        Education; 3) the program is a priority in the inmate’s Correctional Plan;
                        and 4)the program is from a recognized and accredited post-secondary
                        institution.See sections 28 and 29 of the Commissioner’s Directive: <ref
                            target="http://www.csc-scc.gc.ca/acts-and-regulations/720-cd-eng.shtml#s2g">csc-scc.org</ref>
                        </note> However, the mid-1990s in both the US and Canada saw
                government cutbacks and program closures to postsecondary educational opportunities
                for incarcerated peoples.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Since the
                    mid-1990s, federal and state prisoners have been denied access to Pell grants,
                    which provide funding for post-secondary education. In 2015, under the Obama
                    Administration, the Department of Education launched the Second Chance Pell
                    pilot program, which sees the return of financial assistance for incarcerated
                    individuals pursuing higher education. In Canada, government cutbacks in the
                    mid-1990s closed the University of Victoria (later Simon Fraser University)
                    prison postsecondary education program in British Columbia. For a history of the
                    this program in Canada, see Stephen Duguid’s <hi rend="italic">Can Prisons
                        Work?, </hi>chapter 5.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>While there are differences between the Canadian W2B program and the American
                Inside-Out models, what is common to both is the semi-anonymous space of the
                incarcerated classroom:<note place="foot" resp="author"> On
                        the differences between Walls to Bridges and Inside-Out, see Simone Weil
                        Davis’s essay, “Beyond ‘Replication’.”</note> students use only first
                names and are prohibited from communicating outside of the course or workshop. “It
                is important,” notes Lori Pompa, founder and director of Inside-Out, “that outside
                participants are not studying their incarcerated classmates; they are not serving in
                a counselling or teaching or advising capacity” toward the incarcerated students,
                nor are they privy to the details or circumstances surrounding their incarceration
                (“Breaking Down the Walls” 257).</p>
                
            <p>The three-hour workshop at the GVI consisted of two clusters of activities. First, we
                performed a number of short creative writing ice-breaker exercises that were linked
                to the readings and topics at hand. For example, one activity was to collectively
                write a story through a spoken word-chain (where one person says a word, and the
                next person says the first word that comes into their mind as quickly as possible) —
                an exercise designed to create group cohesion through sharing, but also to show
                language and storytelling as spaces of freedom. Students were encouraged to say any
                word that came to mind — a task that proved to be very challenging. Another activity
                was timed writing, which involved students writing for three minutes without
                stopping (then two minutes, then one minute), each time beginning with a single word
                as their inspiration or writing prompt. Inside and outside students took turns
                selecting the words. One word in particular, “window,” produced many moving creative
                reflections from the students, even a short poem. After each exercise ended,
                students were encouraged to share their writing out loud with the group. The
                incarcerated women were consistently the first volunteering to share, and their
                contributions were enthusiastic, reflective, self-expressive, and respectful.</p>
                
            <p>The second activity was an informal discussion of a few short poems from the Romantic
                period, a period that, as John Bugg notes, saw the rise and reform of prisons
                throughout Europe, and that subsequently gave birth to the genre of prison
                literature (50). One week prior to the workshop, all inside and outside students
                received a handout with the texts to be discussed. These poems, which were selected
                by my class, included Anna Barbauld’s “The Mouse’s Petition” (1773), William Blake’s
                “London” (1794), John Thelwall’s “The Cell” (1795), Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s “This
                Lime-Tree Bower My Prison” (1797), and Dorothy Wordsworth’s “Thoughts on My
                Sick-Bed” (1832). These poems treated the prison as an experience or a metaphor,
                drawing on themes of enclosure, confinement, and solitude in various senses
                (intellectual, emotional, political, as well as physical). While some of these texts
                treated these conditions or states in positive terms, as necessary conditions for
                artistic, creative expression, others framed them as oppressive architectures of
                power and obstacles to change. </p>
                
            <p>Students collectively shared their personal responses to these texts and made
                intertextual connections between them. We all shared a laugh when one inside student
                commented on how “whiny” Coleridge sounded as he complained about his lime-tree
                bower. He wouldn’t have lasted, quipped another inside student, a single day in the
                    GVI.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Although it didn’t come up
                        during that discussion, in retrospect I think this would have been an
                        opportune moment to discuss the intersection of race, class, and privilege,
                        and the distances that exist between the lived carceral experience and the
                        prison as metaphor. Future iterations of this project might tease out the
                        connections between the horrors of slavery and incarceration and include
                        selections from Olaudah Equiano’s<hi rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative
                            of the Life of Olaudah Equiano </hi>and Mary Prince’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >The History of Mary Prince, A West Indian Slave, Related by
                            Herself</hi>.</note> Conversation gravitated toward the major common
                threads within these poems, such as the positive influence of nature and the
                importance of the imagination. The incarcerated students described their own
                strained relationships with the natural world. A number of women spoke candidly
                about their combined efforts to save food to feed the squirrels and rabbits that
                breach the prison fences. Indeed, one inside woman, who admitted to being envious of
                animals’ freedom to cross the barbed-wire fence, reminded me of the Poet in
                Shelley’s <hi rend="italic">Alastor</hi> who laments the beauty and freedom of the
                swan flying overhead while he remains mired in the “wide and melancholy waste”
                (273). Another incarcerated woman spoke of her attempt to save and germinate apple
                seeds in her cell as a way of bringing beauty and life into an inhospitable
                environment (they were removed by the prison guards during a raid). Beyond
                reflections on nature, another incarcerated student shared how one of the poems we
                read, Dorothy Wordsworth’s “Thoughts on My Sick-Bed,” spoke to her own feelings of
                loneliness as well as the freedom afforded by her memories. </p>
                
            <p>At the conclusion of the workshop, inside students admitted that while they were not
                frequent readers of poetry (preferring mostly self-help books), they had enjoyed the
                poems and they might seek out poetry in the future.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> Since then, I was invited back to
                        facilitate poetry workshops at the GVI. I co-directed a subsequent project,
                            titled<hi rend="italic">Erasing Frankenstein</hi>, a collaborative
                        poetic adaptation of Shelley’s <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi> created
                        by incarcerated and non-incarcerated individuals from the Walls to Bridges
                        Collective at the GVI and university students at UNB. For more, visit
                        www.erasingfrankenstein.org. </note> Outside students participated in a
                debriefing of the workshop in the class following the event. Back in the university
                classroom, outside students were asked to evaluate themselves, specifically their
                engagement and performance within the experience, and to share their insights and
                observations with the class. Numerous outside students described how the space of
                the incarcerated classroom quickly felt familiar, and how jarring it was to be
                reminded at various points, such as when an alarm went off, that they were inside a
                prison. Some outside students confessed to feeling somewhat shadowed by the depth
                and intensity of the inside students’ comments and readings of the poems. One
                outside student shared that she felt emotionally overwhelmed by their stories. One
                student later wrote on course evaluations that this experience was the highlight of
                their entire undergraduate education.</p>
                
            <p>I suspected this post-workshop debriefing would produce these kinds of responses, for
                what was a very energetic, boisterous bus ride from the university to the prison
                was, on the hour-long drive back, a very quiet ride. When asked about why they were
                so quiet, my students said that they were processing the experience. Some said they
                were frustrated that the experience was so short and had wanted more time to talk
                with the incarcerated women. One student shared that she was holding back tears at
                multiple points throughout the workshop, upset over the inside women’s lack of
                freedom. Many students expressed feeling guilty over being able to leave the prison
                with the knowledge that their new classmates could not. All outside students agreed
                that their expectations changed. </p>
                
            <p>My goal in designing this experiential activity was to recast Romantic poetry and
                inject it with new life and new lives, by bringing this poetry into meaningful
                connection with a greater public beyond the parameters of the traditional university
                classroom. Could there be a way to reduce not only the historical distance between
                our present and the Romantic past, but also the more challenging distance between
                the discourse and experience of incarceration? At its heart, this was a project
                about collapsing distances. If Romantic poetry about incarceration seemed doubly
                removed, discussing it in a prison classroom with currently incarcerated individuals
                helped make this poetry more accessible. For instance, the incarcerated women shared
                that in important ways their current conditions were not those facing Romantic
                prisoners. Their cells were not as Thelwall describes his in “The Cell,” with its
                “damp foul floor, the ragged wall / And shattered window, grated high” (5-6).<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> For a photographic tour of the Grand
                        Valley Institution for Women, including images of administrative
                        segregation, see <ref
                            target="http://kitchener.ctvnews.ca/in-pictures/inside-the-grand-valley-prison-for-women-1.3602398">Kitchener</ref>
                        </note> And yet, for as physically different as Romantic and
                present-day prisons are, the incarcerated women were quick to connect with the
                poem’s “Patriot” (2), who within the “noxious gloom” (1) is still able to “smile”
                (4) because of his memories, as he “Looks inward to his heart and sees / The objects
                that must ever please” (13-14). While outside students immediately read the poem’s
                “Patriot” as a political prisoner, having learned about the French Revolution in the
                early weeks of our course, one incarcerated woman thoughtfully offered a different
                reading of the word “patriot,” as someone who fights for what they believe in. The
                challenge of incarceration, she explained, is to remain a patriot, that is, to stay
                committed to those things worth fighting for, such as freedom, without losing hope.
                Many of the women spoke about the importance of returning to their memories as a
                critical way of managing their mental health and personal wellbeing while serving
                their sentences.</p>
                
            <p>During the workshop, I asked the group to think about what today’s equivalent of “The
                Cell” might be, in light of these historical differences. The incarcerated women
                insisted that if written today, Thelwall’s poem would refer to the biggest problems
                of the prison industrial complex: overcrowding, interpersonal violence, lack of
                supports for mental health, and administrative segregation (otherwise known as
                solitary confinement). This discussion in particular emphasized the continuity
                between these historical moments; deplorable conditions and methods persist albeit
                in different forms. For those of us from the outside, the discussions that followed
                from this poem made us aware of a different kind of insidious dampness behind the
                exterior walls of a modern penal institution with its manicured landscaping,
                well-maintained parking lot, and friendly correctional officers’ faces.</p>
                
            <p>Admittedly, this workshop was a mere toe-dip into the deep waters of inside-out
                learning, but it gave me a sense of what a more sustained engagement could
                accomplish. The project has also opened doors for undergraduate students: one
                outside student who actively participated in the workshop accepted a meaningful
                summer research assistantship at Huron University where she worked to develop future
                community-based learning (CBL) opportunities. In September 2016, she travelled on
                behalf of the university to Norway to research potential international
                CBL-partnerships.</p>
                
            <p>Beyond this one individual student success story, the hope and biggest payoff of this
                kind of learning is to trigger, as Pompa puts it, “a new way of seeing the world, in
                which everyone involved shares an opportunity to work through their stereotypes and
                myths” (257), and to which I would add <hi rend="italic">and recognizes the
                    importance of the humanities in building bridges across institutions and
                    communities</hi>. The transformative pedagogical work of W2B and Inside-Out, and
                the linkages they create between the university and the prison, raise larger
                questions and new perspectives through which to cross-examine each institutional
                body. Is there a way to see their various crises as interlinked? For example, at a
                time when prisons are increasingly faced with growing populations, and humanities
                programs and classrooms the inverse trend, how might these two bodies in “crisis”
                speak <hi rend="italic">positively</hi> to one another? <note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> I emphasize<hi rend="italic"
                            >positively</hi>, for there are already unhealthy relationships between
                        higher education and prisons, such as the financial investments of American
                        universities with the Corrections Corporation of America (CCA) and GEO
                        Group, two major private prison operators in the United States. In 2015, <hi
                            rend="italic">CNN</hi> reported that as the result of a successful
                        student-activist campaign, Columbia University became the first university
                        in the United States to announce its divestiture from these private prison
                        companies (Chan).</note> Indeed, prisons and universities might benefit
                from a more sustained thinking about the impact of humanities programming in the
                reduction of recidivism and in thoughtfully informing policies and processes around
                segregation and reintegration. After all, the number of complaints from incarcerated
                women at the GVI has dramatically increased (139%) within the last three years.
                Canada’s federal Correctional Investigator, Howard Sapers, received 344 complaints
                from the GVI in 2015-2016, a number that comprises nearly 41 percent of complaints
                from federally incarcerated women in all of Canada.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> Catherine Thompson, “Complaints
                        skyrocket at Grand Valley women’s prison”<hi rend="italic">Waterloo Region
                            Record </hi>Nov. 4, 2016. <ref
                            target="http://www.therecord.com/news-story/6948432-complaints-skyrocket-at-grand-valley-women-s-prison/">The Record</ref>
                        </note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Romanticists are increasingly thinking through the relationship between classrooms
                and communities, and with good reason.<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                    To name just a few scholars doing this work, see Julie
                        Ellison, Founding Director of<hi rend="italic">Imagining America: Artists
                            and Scholars in Public Life</hi>, and co-author of “Scholarship in
                        Public: Knowledge Creation and Tenure Policy in the Engaged University”;
                        Joshua Lambier, Program Director of The Public Humanities at Western; and
                        Sara Guyer, who developed “Public Romanticism and the Public Humanities,” a
                        graduate seminar that she describes as a first-step toward a full-scale
                        graduate certificate in the Public Humanities.</note> The payoff of
                community-based learning, such as that modelled in the W2B, Inside-Out and public
                humanities movements, is contributing to the public good, and to expand the range
                and impact of academic discussions beyond the parameters of the campus classroom.
                Yet one critique levelled against community-based learning is precisely on the
                grounds of this paternalistic drive to be helpful to the community Other (Mitchell
                2008). Intentionally by design, this workshop was not curative; it was not aimed at
                healing individuals or the incarcerated community. In keeping with the spirit of W2B
                and Inside-Out, the workshop was “<hi rend="italic">not</hi> about helping,
                researching, or mentoring incarcerated students; the pedagogical foundation is
                collaborative learning in which all students are equal carriers of knowledge”
                (Pollack “Building Bridges” 504). This, however, is not to deny the palliative
                experiences of this kind of learning, facilitated by our conversations of Romantic
                poetry. Indeed, as Nyki Kish notes, in reference to her experience of taking a W2B
                course while locked up in the GVI’s maximum security unit, there is “a healing
                quality to the circle setting” (Freitas, McAuley and Kish 308). In the class
                circles, Kish continues:
                
            <quote>there was no hierarchy and there were not the power struggles that dominated my
                experience with both guards and other imprisoned women in max. In class circles I
                felt safe to think, and share, and interact, and especially as our class read texts
                and poetry relevant to oppression, criminalization and issues of imprisonment, I
                began to find something I had lost in the trauma of experiencing the penal system:
                my voice. (308)</quote>
                
            Helping incarcerated peoples to find their voices is often cited as a desired outcome
                of prison writing programs. Lisa Rhodes, reflecting on her time spent mentoring
                prisoners through Pen America’s Prison Writing Mentorship, sees writing as “the
                catharsis to help them [prisoners] through their struggles” (164). North of the
                border, Sylvie Frigon describes the goal of the creative writing prison workshops
                developed by the Ontario Francophone Authors Association as providing “les
                voies/voix de la fiction” (129;<hi rend="italic">the paths/voice of fiction</hi>) to
                inmates in Québec prisons by publishing their texts on the outside. Writing is
                frequently framed as offering prisoners both a space for self-expression and a
                vehicle for reconnection to both the outside world and the self. Indeed, research
                specifically supports the impact of arts and writing programs on prisoners’ lives.
                In 2014, Larry Brewster studied projects modeled after the Arts-In-Corrections (AIC)
                program in four California state prisons and measured changes in attitude and
                behavior of inmates participating in a 12-week arts program (poetry, writing,
                theatre, visual arts). There was a positive correlation between participation in the
                arts programming and improved time management, social competence, achievement
                motivation, intellectual flexibility, emotional control and self-confidence, among
                others. The study also found a reduction in disciplinary reports and a greater
                participation in other academic programming. Thus, we can speak of education’s
                palliative work in the prison, and also more specifically of the arts.</p>
                
            <p>What was interesting to learn, however, was that this experience was positive not
                only for the inside students but those outside as well, and this largely rested on
                how this learning happened. As students told me during our post-workshop discussion,
                they thought it was the larger experience of sitting in a circle, collaboratively
                working with new classmates from such different lived realities as them, listening
                to first-hand experiences of incarceration, and having intense discussions over the
                shared content that made it so meaningful. For me, their answers raised some more
                questions: what role, then, did these particular poems play in creating this
                experience? What if it had been a different genre?<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                    I would go on to explore this question in a subsequent collaboration
                    also at the GVI, <hi rend="italic">Erasing Frankenstein</hi>, in which we
                    discussed Mary Shelley’s 1818 novel.</note> And how did the fact that it was a
                one-time, intense but fleeting experience shape students’ impressions? What was the
                relationship here between the workshop’s content and form?</p>
                
            <p>I suspect that the fact that the poems were about incarceration helped shift the
                perceived authority in the space of the prison classroom away from the outside
                students toward the inside students. In giving the incarcerated women the lead in
                our discussions, in having the outside students listen to their responses to the
                historical differences and continuities of the incarcerated experience from the
                Romantic period to the present day, everyone in the room was learning with and from
                one another. More than anything, Romantic poetry ultimately served as the conduit
                for more profound learning outcomes: first, through these conversations, the outside
                students confronted their preconceptions about prisoners as dangerous, uneducated,
                inarticulate, and uninterested in poetry; and second, the outside students gained
                literary insights from the prisoners, as “the potential objects of knowledge in
                those jail classrooms (e.g. prisoners) become subjects of literary study” (Wiltse
                21). In coming to recognize how they learned about the Romantics with and from the
                prisoners in these intellectual discussions about literature (rather than the other
                way around), I am pleased to think that my students experienced a positive
                disruption to their preconceptions about their sense of privilege and the flow of
                knowledge in their encounters with groups and communities beyond the campus. Thus, I
                came away from the experience thinking in broader ways about how formal or
                structural changes to pedagogy can shape our relationship to the content in profound
                ways. In this sense, the experience of teaching Romantic poetry in the prison
                classroom contributed to my own pedagogical wellbeing; it opened me up to thinking
                about new spaces and configurations for teaching within the humanities.</p>
                
            <p>Increasingly the mission of the humanities is an outward-looking one: a key objective
                of public humanities initiatives is “to cultivate a renewed spirit of citizenship
                and engagement through arts and humanities research and collaboration,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> This is a key objective of
                        the Public Humanities at Western project.</note> an objective deeply
                rooted in the Romantic ideals of <hi rend="italic">Bildung</hi>. Similarly, the
                revaluation of Schiller’s concept of aesthetic education is at the heart of Gayatri
                Chakravorty Spivak’s hope for the socially engaged humanities. We, who practice and
                study within the humanities, need to become, as Peter Brooks puts it in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Humanities and the Public Life</hi>, “less modest, and to
                stake a claim to the public importance of our task” (2). Tellingly, Brooks turns to
                a Romantic poet to sharpen his point: “Shelley was not entirely wrong to insist that
                poets are the unacknowledged legislators of mankind: Cultural change carries
                everything in its wake” (2). Community-based learning projects, whether on a micro-
                or macro-scale, have the potential to transform and reinvigorate all those involved:
                faculty, students, community partners, research, activism, poetry and its publics. </p>
                
            <p>This workshop attempted to create an academic and experiential learning opportunity
                that would foster a greater kind of civically engaged wellbeing. As Shoshana
                Pollack, coordinator of the national W2B program argues, workshops and courses that
                cultivate an exchange between inside and outside learners help to “dispel
                stereotypes, create a sense of connection and community across perceived
                differences, and cultivate a drive for social action, both within the criminal
                justice system and in the wider community” (517). There is a place for the enmeshed
                academic and experiential study of Romanticism, and it can contribute to the
                enhanced personal development of all co-learners, inside and out.</p>
                
                <p><hi rend="bold">APPENDIX A</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Assignment: Final Reflection on Prison Poetry Workshop</hi></p>
                <p>Format: typed, double-spaced (approx. 2000 words)
                Weight: 15% 
                Due: at the start of the final exam. 
               This term we participated in a new community-based learning (CBL) project. Its aim
                    was the creation of a brief but meaningful exchange between different bodies of
                    students: the “inside” students (the inmates of the Grand Valley Institution for
                    Women) and the “outside” students (Huron University students). Modelled, in part, on
                    the Walls to Bridges Program (a Canadian program rooted in the pedagogic principles
                    of the U.S. Inside-Out Prison Exchange Program), this project involved a one-day
                    visit to the GVI, and a collaborative classroom dialogue between Inside-Out
                    students. </p>
                
               <p> You are being evaluated in three ways, two of which you have already completed: (1)
                    participation during the inside-out visit; (2) participation in an in-class
                    discussion following the visit; and (3) a written, reflective response to the visit,
                    to be submitted as part of the final exam. As with the other two parts of this
                    project, successful students will be attentive, reflective, thoughtful, and
                    critically engaged with their own experience with this CBL workshop.</p>
                
                <p><hi rend="bold">The Task</hi></p>
                <p>This final reflection requires you to reflect on the prison poetry workshop at the
                    GVI at greater length and detail on your thoughts, impressions, and to make critical
                    connections between your experience and course material. You will be evaluated based
                    on the professionalism, thoroughness, and demonstrated effort and engagement of your
                    answers.</p>
                
                <p>Please answer the following questions in your final reflection. While you do not have
                    to answer these questions in order, your reflection must address them all.</p>
                
                <div type="paratext">
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>Briefly describe the event.</item>
                    <item>What were your expectations of this workshop? Did they change after the
                        workshop?</item>
                    <item>What did you hope to gain by participating in it?</item>
                    <item>What is the one thing that you were most interested in learning during the
                        workshop?</item>
                    <item>Before this experience, what kinds of experience did you have in the areas of
                        (a) community-based learning, or (b) prison-outreach?</item>
                    <item>What is your definition of experiential learning?</item>
                    <item>How did the community partners (the GVI, the inside students) enhance student
                        learning?</item>
                    <item>What is your impression of experiential learning?</item>
                    <item>What were some of the challenges that you encountered?</item>
                    <item>What was your favourite part of most meaningful part of the workshop?
                        Why?</item>
                    <item>What was your least favourite part? Why?</item>
                    <item>Describe your level of engagement at all stages of this project. Briefly
                        describe the opportunities you had to play an active role in the formation of
                        the project. What was your participation like during the workshop and in our
                        follow-up class discussion?</item>
                    <item>Describe your feelings about participating in this workshop. What were your
                        feelings going into this? Why do you think you felt that way? Try your best to
                        give a detailed self-analysis of your feelings before and after the
                        workshop.</item>
                    <item>What are some ways that this CBL project, and the larger CBL program at Huron,
                        could be improved?</item>
                    <item>How do you see this workshop connecting with the coursework? What specific
                        texts or readings resonated with this project? (hint: make connections)</item>
                    <item>What were some of the critical issues, concepts, or topics that we examined
                        during the workshop?</item>
                    <item>In your opinion, how might community-based learning projects, such as ours,
                        cause improvements within our communities?</item>
                </list>
             </div>
            </div>
                
            <div type="citation">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                
            <bibl>Brewster, Larry. “The Impact of Prison Arts Programs on Inmate Attitudes and
                Behaviours: A Quantitative Evaluation” <hi rend="italic">Justice Policy Journal
                </hi>11.2 (2014): 1-28.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Brooks, Peter. “Introduction.” <hi rend="italic">The Humanities and the Public Life.
                </hi>Ed. Peter Brooks with Hilary Jewett. New York: Fordham University Press, 2014.
                1-14.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Bugg, John. <hi rend="italic">Five Long Winters: The Trials of British
                    Romanticism</hi>. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2014.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Chan, Wilfred. “Columbia becomes first U.S. university to divest from prisons.” <hi
                    rend="italic">CNN. </hi>24 June 2015. Web. 3 Sep. 2016.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Davis, Simone Weil. “Beyond ‘Replication’: Inside-Out in Canada” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Turning Teaching Inside Out: A Pedagogy of Transformation for Community-Based
                    Education</hi>. Ed. Simone Weil Davis and Barbara Sherr Roswell. Basingstoke:
                Palgrave, 2013. 257-265. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Duguid, Stephen. <hi rend="italic">Can Prisons Work? The Prisoner as Object and
                    Subject in Modern Corrections</hi>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 2000.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Duguid, Stephen and Ray Pawson. “Education, change and transformation: The prison
                experience” <hi rend="italic">Evaluation Review</hi> 22.4 (1998): 470–495.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Ellison, Julie and Timothy Eatman. “Scholarship in Public: Knowledge Creation and
                Tenure Policy in the Engaged University.” Syracuse, NY: Imagining America, 2008. PDF
                file.</bibl
                >
            <bibl>Erdman, David. <hi rend="italic">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>.
                Rev. ed. New York: Random House, 1988. Print.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Foucault, Michel. “Of Other Spaces,” <hi rend="italic">Diacritics</hi> 16 (Spring
                1986): 22-27.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Freitas, Monica, Bonnie McAuley and Nyki Kish. “Experiencing the inside-out program
                in a maximum-security prison.” In Criminalizing women: Gender and (in)justice in
                neo-liberal times.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Frigon, Sylvie. “Rencontres littéraires en prison ou comment voyager de l’ombre à la
                lumière” <hi rend="italic">Justice et santé mentale </hi>48.1 (2015): 123-141. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Guyer, Sara. “Public Romanticism and the Public Humanities: A Graduate Seminar” <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Circles Pedagogies</hi>. November 2013. 2 Sep. 2016. <ref
                    target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/pedagogies/contest/2013.guyer">umd.edu</ref></bibl>
                
            <bibl>—. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism After Auschwitz</hi>. Stanford: Stanford University
                Press, 2007.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Lockwood, Susan, John M. Nally, Taiping Ho, and Katie Knutson, “The effect of
                correctional education on post release employment and recidivism: A 5-year follow-up
                study in the state of Indiana” <hi rend="italic">Crime &amp; Delinquency</hi> 58.3
                (2012): 380–396. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Mitchell, Tania. “Traditional vs. critical service-learning: Engaging the literature
                to differentiate two models.” <hi rend="italic">Michigan Journal of Community
                    Service Learning</hi> (Spring 2008): 50–65.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Pladek, Brittany. “‘Soothing Thoughts’: Romantic Palliative Care and the Poetics of
                Relief” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review </hi>23.3 (2012): 403-413.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Pollack, Shoshana. “Building Bridges: Experiential and Integrative Learning in a
                Canadian Women’s Prison” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Teaching in Social Work
                </hi>36.5 (2016): 503-518.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Pompa, Lori. “Breaking Down the Walls: Inside-Outside Learning and the Pedagogy of
                Transformation” in <hi rend="italic">Challenging the Prison-Industrial Complex:
                    Activism, Arts, and Educational Alternatives</hi>. Ed. Stephen J. Hartnett.
                2011. 253-272. Print.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>—. “Drawing Forth, Finding Voice, Making Change: Inside-Out Learning as
                Transformative Pedagogy” in <hi rend="italic">Turning Teaching Inside Out: A
                    Pedagogy of Transformation for Community-Based Education</hi>. Ed. Simone Weil
                Davis and Barbara Sherr Roswell. Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2013. 14-25.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Rhodes, Lisa. “Poetry and Prison Writing Program: A Mentor’s Narrative Report” <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal of Poetry Therapy</hi> 15.3 (2002): 163-168.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Sokoloff, Natalie and Anika Schenck-Fontaine. “College programs in prison and upon
                reentry for men and women: a literature review” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary
                    Justice Review </hi>20.1 (2017): 95-114.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty. <hi rend="italic">An Aesthetic Education in the Era of
                    Globalization</hi>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2012.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Tewksbury, Richard and Kenneth M. Stengel. “Assessing correctional education
                programs: The students’ perspective” <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Correctional
                    Education</hi> 57.1 (2006): 13–25. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Thompson, Catherine. “Complaints skyrocket at Grand Valley women’s prison” <hi
                    rend="italic">Waterloo Region Record </hi>Nov. 4, 2016. <ref
                    target="http://www.therecord.com/news-story/6948432-complaints-skyrocket-at-grand-valley-women-s-prison/">The Record</ref>
                </bibl>
                
            <bibl>Thompson, Judith. <hi rend="italic">John Thelwall in the Wordsworth Circle: The
                    Silenced Partner</hi>. New York: Palgrave, 2012.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Vacca, James. “Educated Prisoners Are Less Likely to Return to Prison” <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal of Correctional Education</hi> 55.4 (2004): 297-305.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Wiltse, Ed. “Doing Time in College: Student-Prisoner Reading Groups and the Object(s)
                of Literary Study.” <hi rend="italic">Critical Survey</hi> 23.3 (2011): 6-22.</bibl>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
